<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?properties open_access?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1367-4803</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1367-4811</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">10121331</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37018142</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btad176</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">btad176</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Applications Note</subject>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading">
          <subject>Structural Bioinformatics</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01060</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>SmoothT—a server constructing low-energy pathways from conformational ensembles for interactive visualization and enhanced sampling</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6719-2997</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Staritzbichler</surname>
          <given-names>René</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Institute of Medical Physics and Biophysics, University of Leipzig</institution>, Leipzig 04107, <country country="DE">Germany</country></aff>
        <xref rid="btad176-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
        <!--rene.staritzbichler@medizin.uni-leipzig.de-->
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0521-322X</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Ristic</surname>
          <given-names>Nikola</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Institute of Medical Physics and Biophysics, University of Leipzig</institution>, Leipzig 04107, <country country="DE">Germany</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Stapke</surname>
          <given-names>Tülin</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Institute of Medical Physics and Biophysics, University of Leipzig</institution>, Leipzig 04107, <country country="DE">Germany</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0063-1104</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Hildebrand</surname>
          <given-names>Peter W</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Institute of Medical Physics and Biophysics, University of Leipzig</institution>, Leipzig 04107, <country country="DE">Germany</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>Institute of Medical Physics and Biophysics, Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin, Corporate Member of Freie Universität Berlin und Humboldt- Universität zu Berlin</institution>, Berlin 10117, <country country="DE">Germany</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>Berlin Institute of Health at Charité-Universitätsmedizin</institution>, Berlin 10178, <country country="DE">Germany</country></aff>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name>
          <surname>Valencia</surname>
          <given-names>Alfonso</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Associate Editor</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="btad176-cor1">Corresponding author. Institute of Medical Physics and Biophysics, University of Leipzig, Leipzig 04107, Germany. E-mail: <email>rene.staritzbichler@medizin.uni-leipzig.de</email></corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <month>4</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2023-04-05">
      <day>05</day>
      <month>4</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>05</day>
      <month>4</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>39</volume>
    <issue>4</issue>
    <elocation-id>btad176</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>20</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>21</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>10</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="corrected-typeset">
        <day>21</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2023. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xlink:href="btad176.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <sec id="s1">
        <title>Motivation</title>
        <p>The SmoothT software and webservice offers the construction of pathways from an ensemble of conformations. The user provides an archive of molecule conformations in Protein Databank (PDB) format, from which a starting and a final conformation need to be selected. The individual PDB files need to contain an energy value or score, estimating the quality of the respective confirmation. Additionally, the user has to provide a root-mean-square deviation (RMSD) cut-off, below which conformations are considered neighboring. From this, SmoothT constructs a graph that connects similar conformations.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2">
        <title>Results</title>
        <p>SmoothT returns the energetically most favorable pathway within in this graph. This pathway is directly displayed as interactive animation using the NGL viewer. Simultaneously, the energy along the pathway is plotted, highlighting the conformation that is currently displayed in the 3D window.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3">
        <title>Availability and implementation</title>
        <p>SmoothT is available as webservice at: <ext-link xlink:href="http://proteinformatics.org/smoothT" ext-link-type="uri">http://proteinformatics.org/smoothT</ext-link>. Examples, a tutorial, and FAQs can be found there. Ensembles up to 2 GB (compressed) can be uploaded. Results will be stored for 5 days. The server is completely free and requires no registration. The C++ source code is available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/starbeachlab/smoothT" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/starbeachlab/smoothT</ext-link>.</p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100001659</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>421152132</award-id>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="2"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec>
    <title>1 Introduction</title>
    <p>Biological processes commonly involve transitions between distinct molecular states, which in most cases are related to conformational changes. Examples of such pairs of states are bound versus unbound, unfolded versus folded, and inactive versus active. Driving force of molecular processes is generally the aim of these systems to reach a minimum in free energy. The correct path between starting and final state is expected to be the one with the lowest energy barrier. Determining the most realistic path means searching through the energy landscape for the one with the lowest energy (<xref rid="btad176-B6" ref-type="bibr">Smidstrup et al. 2014</xref>).</p>
    <p>Mapping complete energy landscapes of macro-molecules will certainly remain unattainable in the near future due to their immense complexity. The most common modeling techniques for macro-molecules are molecular dynamics (MD) and Monte Carlo (MC). While in general MD calculates the time-evolution of the system, following Newton’s classical equation of motion, MC approaches create random samples following a given distribution, typically the Boltzmann distribution. Hence, MC algorithms are successfully applied whenever the size or complexity of the search space prohibits both a systematic scan or MD, since MD would simply spend too much time sampling local minima of the free-energy landscape—although methods exist to enhance the sampling rate of MD, e.g. umbrella sampling (<xref rid="btad176-B7" ref-type="bibr">Torrie and Valleau 1977</xref>) or meta-dynamics (<xref rid="btad176-B2" ref-type="bibr">Laio and Parrinello 2002</xref>).</p>
    <p>SmoothT, on the other hand, is constructing pathways from previously computed ensembles of macro-molecular conformations. It therefore allows to combine results from different techniques and provides an efficient way to create starting points for enhanced sampling techniques with little initial assumption about the pathway. It should be noted, however, that other methods generally aim to recover transition pathways by taking the sampling itself into account, yielding pathways as they would have occurred according to the underlying physical model (<xref rid="btad176-B3" ref-type="bibr">Metzner et al. 2009</xref>; <xref rid="btad176-B5" ref-type="bibr">Schütte et al. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="btad176-B1" ref-type="bibr">Bowman et al. 2014</xref>), thus providing conformational and kinetic information about the pathway.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>2 Materials and methods</title>
    <p>The path determination in SmoothT is performed in two phases. First, a graph is constructed containing all putative pathways. Second, the most favorable pathway is selected. The graph is constructed by calculating the similarity between conformations. Conformations that are below the user-defined RMSD cut-off are connected by an edge. The RMSD is calculated without superimposition. Nodes contain the conformation with the associated energy. The energies are shifted by the lowest energy found in the graph (see the method section on the server for illustrations). The most favorable pathway is determined in a dynamic programming approach, in which for each node it is decided locally which of its connected nodes leads to the assembly of the best sub-path. The selection follows two criteria. The first is the energy barrier, the maximum energy along the path. The second is the area under the RMSD-energy curve. The integral over the energy, shifted by the minimum energy, will favor first short pathways and for pathways of similar length, it will favor those with an overall lower energy. The actual pathway is constructed by a back-propagation. The server displays both the trajectory using the NGL viewer (<xref rid="btad176-B4" ref-type="bibr">Rose and Hildebrand 2015</xref>) as well as an energy diagram, highlighting the energy of the snapshot currently displayed in the NGL window (see <xref rid="btad176-F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>3 Examples</title>
    <p>One example of usage would take snapshots from several independent MD simulations to connect them into a simple representation of the simulated transition. Another example would use an ensemble of Monte Carlo docking poses as input and connect them into a simple estimation of the transition from the unbound to bound state. The output pathways themselves can serve as starting point of simulations, e.g. in an enhanced sampling approach. In this way, SmoothT provides a natural link between the global sampling of MC methods and the local sampling of MD simulations. SmoothT has no restrictions on the types and number of molecules that can be used.</p>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack id="ack1">
    <title>Acknowledgments</title>
    <p>We would like to extend our thanks to Guillermo Pérez-Hernández for useful discussions about transition state theory and contributions to the text.</p>
  </ack>
  <sec>
    <title>Funding</title>
    <p>This work was supported by Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG, German Research Foundation) through CRC 1423 [421152132; sub-project Z04] as well as through the Open Access Publishing Fund of Leipzig University within the DFG program Open Access Publication Funding.</p>
    <p>Conflict of interest: None declared.</p>
    <fig position="float" id="btad176-F1">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>The user provides the conformational ensemble, the starting and ending conformation, the RMSD threshold, and an identifier for the energy values in the PDB files. SmoothT then constructs a graph, connecting similar conformations in a backtrace. SmoothT extracts the most favorable pathway according to two energy-related criteria. The server displays an animation of the transition and an energy plot (right box). The big dot in the plot indicates the energy of the current snapshot</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="btad176f1" position="float"/>
    </fig>
  </sec>
  <ref-list id="ref1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="btad176-B1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pande</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Noé</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name></person-group> (eds). <source>An Introduction to Markov State Models and their Application to Long Timescale Molecular Simulation</source>. Dordrecht: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>, <year>2014</year>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad176-B2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Laio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parrinello</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Escaping free-energy minima</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2002</year>;<volume>99</volume>:<fpage>12562</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12271136</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad176-B3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Metzner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schütte</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vanden-Eijnden</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Transition path theory for Markov jump processes</article-title>. <source>Multiscale Model Simul</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>1192</fpage>–<lpage>219</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad176-B4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hildebrand</surname><given-names>PW.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>NGL viewer: a web application for molecular visualization</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>W576</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25925569</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad176-B5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Schütte</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Noé</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Markov state models based on milestoning</article-title>. <source>J Chem Phys</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>134</volume>:<fpage>204105</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21639422</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad176-B6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Smidstrup</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stokbro</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Improved initial guess for minimum energy path calculations</article-title>. <source>J Chem Phys</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>140</volume>:<fpage>214106</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24907989</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad176-B7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Torrie</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Valleau</surname><given-names>JP.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Nonphysical sampling distributions in Monte Carlo free-energy estimation: umbrella sampling</article-title>. <source>J Comput Phys</source><year>1977</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
