<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>BMC Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1471-2105</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">10386769</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">5420</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-023-05420-y</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Software</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>ROGUE: an R Shiny app for RNA sequencing analysis and biomarker discovery</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1087-9840</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Farrel</surname>
          <given-names>Alvin</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>farrela@chop.edu</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Li</surname>
          <given-names>Peng</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Veenbergen</surname>
          <given-names>Sharon</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Patel</surname>
          <given-names>Khushbu</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Maris</surname>
          <given-names>John M.</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <name>
          <surname>Leonard</surname>
          <given-names>Warren J.</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>wjl@helix.nih.gov</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.94365.3d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2297 5165</institution-id><institution>Laboratory of Molecular Immunology, National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, </institution><institution>National Institutes of Health, </institution></institution-wrap>Bethesda, MD USA </aff>
      <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.94365.3d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2297 5165</institution-id><institution>Immunology Center, National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, </institution><institution>National Institutes of Health, </institution></institution-wrap>Bethesda, MD USA </aff>
      <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.239552.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0680 8770</institution-id><institution>Division of Oncology and Center for Childhood Cancer Research, </institution><institution>Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia, </institution></institution-wrap>Philadelphia, PA USA </aff>
      <aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.239552.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0680 8770</institution-id><institution>Department of Biomedical and Health Informatics, </institution><institution>Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia, </institution></institution-wrap>Philadelphia, PA USA </aff>
      <aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5645.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">000000040459992X</institution-id><institution>Laboratory of Pediatric Gastroenterology, </institution><institution>Erasmus University Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Rotterdam, The Netherlands </aff>
      <aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.25879.31</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8972</institution-id><institution>Perelman School of Medicine at the University of Pennsylvania, </institution></institution-wrap>Philadelphia, PA USA </aff>
      <aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5645.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">000000040459992X</institution-id><institution>Present Address: Laboratory of Medical Immunology, Department of Immunology, </institution><institution>Erasmus University Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Rotterdam, The Netherlands </aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>29</day>
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>29</day>
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>24</volume>
    <elocation-id>303</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>13</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2020</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>18</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© This is a U.S. Government work and not under copyright protection in the US; foreign copyright protection may apply 2023</copyright-statement>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract id="Abs1">
      <sec>
        <title>Background</title>
        <p id="Par1">The growing power and ever decreasing cost of RNA sequencing (RNA-Seq) technologies have resulted in an explosion of RNA-Seq data production. Comparing gene expression values within RNA-Seq datasets is relatively easy for many interdisciplinary biomedical researchers; however, user-friendly software applications increase the ability of biologists to efficiently explore available datasets.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Results</title>
        <p id="Par2">Here, we describe ROGUE (RNA-Seq Ontology Graphic User Environment, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://marisshiny.research.chop.edu/ROGUE/">https://marisshiny.research.chop.edu/ROGUE/</ext-link>), a user-friendly R Shiny application that allows a biologist to perform differentially expressed gene analysis, gene ontology and pathway enrichment analysis, potential biomarker identification, and advanced statistical analyses. We use ROGUE to identify potential biomarkers and show unique enriched pathways between various immune cells.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Conclusions</title>
        <p id="Par3">User-friendly tools for the analysis of next generation sequencing data, such as ROGUE, will allow biologists to efficiently explore their datasets, discover expression patterns, and advance their research by allowing them to develop and test hypotheses.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Supplementary Information</title>
        <p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12859-023-05420-y.</p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
      <title>Keywords</title>
      <kwd>R Shiny</kwd>
      <kwd>RNA-Seq</kwd>
      <kwd>Differential expression</kwd>
      <kwd>Biomarkers</kwd>
      <kwd>GSEA</kwd>
      <kwd>Gene ontology</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group>
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000002</institution-id>
            <institution>the Division of Intramural Research, National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, NIH, and National Institutes of Health</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>R35 CA220500</award-id>
        <award-id>P01 CA217959</award-id>
        <award-id>U54 CA232568</award-id>
        <principal-award-recipient>
          <name>
            <surname>Maris</surname>
            <given-names>John M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </principal-award-recipient>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
        <meta-value>© BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2023</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec id="Sec1">
    <title>Background</title>
    <p id="Par30">RNA sequencing (RNA-Seq) has become an extremely powerful tool for understanding biological pathways and molecular mechanisms. Technological advancements, both wet-lab and computational, have transformed RNA-Seq into a more accessible tool, giving biomedical researchers access to a less biased view of RNA biology and transcriptomics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. The growing power and ever decreasing cost of RNA-Seq technologies have resulted in a marked increase in RNA-Seq dataset production.</p>
    <p id="Par31">The explosion of computational algorithms and pipelines in the last decade has given researchers the ability to perform rigorous analyses and explore RNA-Seq data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Differential expression analysis (DEA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], which is the most common analysis performed on RNA-Seq, is used to estimate steady-state mRNA levels. There are multiple bioinformatics pipelines and packages used to perform DEA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], including edgeR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], DESeq[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], and limma-voom [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Different combinations of the various algorithms to analyze sequence reads and perform DEA can affect the biological conclusions drawn from the data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Researchers must carefully select the optimal combination of tools based on their specific biological questions and the available computational resources to perform deep dives and thorough exploration of their RNA-Seq data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p>
    <p id="Par32">DEA is often combined with gene ontology (GO) analysis, pathway analysis, and clustering algorithms to characterize data and elucidate the processes and dynamics involved in transcription [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. These studies give new insights into gene regulatory networks and expression. Gene enrichment analysis is a standard GO approach to evaluate upregulated pathways and processes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Dimensionality reduction methods, such as multidimensional scaling (MDS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>], principal component analysis (PCA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], and t-distributed stochastic neighbor embedding (t-SNE) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], are used to identify RNA-Seq libraries with similar gene expression profiles. Moreover, while many other sophisticated RNA-Seq technologies exist, such as isoform analyses, single-cell RNA-Seq, and spatially resolved RNA-Seq methods, bulk RNA-Seq remains a powerful tool that continues to shape our understanding of biology.</p>
    <p id="Par33">The availability of RNA sequencing datasets is becoming more common due to increased support of open data by academicians and requirements by scientific journals and funding agencies to make publication-affiliated datasets publicly available. This has gifted the scientific community with an extensive repository of datasets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] derived from cell lines, animal models, and patient-derived samples of a wide variety of tissues and diseases. Researchers can explore these datasets of interest to generate or test hypotheses. However, even standard DEA and GO analyses often requires a bioinformatician or a computationally savvy biologist.</p>
    <p id="Par34">User-friendly tools for RNA-Seq analyses will allow biomedical scientists with limited programming experience to explore these datasets. Here we present <underline>R</underline>NA-Seq <underline>O</underline>ntology <underline>G</underline>raphic <underline>U</underline>ser <underline>E</underline>nvironment (ROGUE), an R Shiny application that allows biologists to perform differentially expressed gene analysis, gene ontology and pathway enrichment analysis, potential biomarker identification, and advanced statistical analyses. We demonstrate the capability of ROGUE by exploring the basic differences between CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, and natural killer (NK) cells. Furthermore, we show how ROGUE can be used to identify biomarkers and differentially enriched pathways present in similar immune cells in different diseases.</p>
    <p id="Par35">We propose that ROGUE will allow scientists to explore their datasets and also compare their findings with publicly available datasets, increasing the potential of data-driven biomedical discovery.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec2">
    <title>Methods</title>
    <sec id="Sec3">
      <title>Workflow</title>
      <p id="Par36">ROGUE is an R Shiny web app with a graphic user interface (GUI) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A) that takes expression data as input such as raw read counts, length-normalized counts, expression units including fragments per kilobase of transcript per million mapped reads (FPKM), reads per kilobase of transcript per million mapped reads (RPKM), and transcripts per million (TPM). Users can generate their own RNA-Seq matrix or download publicly available RNA-Seq expression data from databases such as gene expression omnibus (GEO) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], ArrayExpress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], The genotype tissue expression (GTEx) Project [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], and the cancer genome atlas (TCGA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. An online manual is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://marisshiny.research.chop.edu/ROGUE/Instructions.pdf">https://marisshiny.research.chop.edu/ROGUE/Instructions.pdf</ext-link>. When the input is raw read counts or length-normalized counts quantified by packages such as HT-seq [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] or RSEM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], ROGUE generates RPKM tables and can perform DEA using edgeR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] or DESeq2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] which are two of the state-of-the-art R packages for DEA analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] and has been shown to outperform other methods in various applications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. ROGUE also allows users to perform more advanced analyses such as biomarker discovery based on gene expression, dimensionality reduction, gene set enrichment analysis, and gene ontology analysis (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p><bold>A</bold> ROGUE R Shiny app graphic user interface. <bold>B</bold> ROGUE workflow. ROGUE takes raw read counts, normalized counts, or quantified expression values (RPKM, FPKM, TPM) as input. The user can quickly look at the clustering of all samples based on the expression values of all genes, perform differential expression analysis, and compare genes between samples or groups. ROGUE also includes statistical tools for gene set enrichment analysis (GSEA), gene ontology (GO) analysis, biomarker discovery, and dimensionality reduction by t-SNE, PCA, or UMAP</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2023_5420_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
      <p id="Par37">Gene expression comparison between samples and groups can be visualized with heatmaps, bar plots, and boxplots. Users can also use ROGUE to predict possible biomarkers by ranking genes with maximized fold change and minimized coefficients of variation in gene expression between groups of samples. The Welch’s t-test and the Wilcoxon Rank Sum Test can also be used to rank genes by their difference in expression distribution between the groups using the Biomarker Discovery Tool.</p>
      <p id="Par38">Gene set enrichment analysis (GSEA) is a computational method that determines whether a pre-ranked (i.e., log fold change) gene list shows statistically significant, concordant differences between two biological states (e.g., CD4<sup>+</sup> vs. CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells). GSEA between individual samples or groups can be performed using the Fast Gene Set Enrichment Analysis (fgsea) R package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>] with data imported from the Molecular Signatures Database (MSigDB) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Alternatively, gene ontology analysis on a list of differentially expressed genes can be performed using the Gene Ontology Resource [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], which is imported into ROGUE. Furthermore, ROGUE can determine differentially expressed gene sets using the Gene Ontology Resource. This resource uses the Wilcoxon rank sum test to determine if the expression of all genes within a biological process or molecular function are statistically different between samples or groups.</p>
      <p id="Par39">Dimensionality reduction methods can be applied to the datasets and visualized using 2-dimensional and 3-dimensional plots. ROGUE performs PCA using the ‘prcomp’ R function, t-SNE using the ‘Rtsne’ R package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], and Uniform Manifold Approximation and Projection (UMAP) method for dimensionality reduction using the ‘uwot’ R package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>].</p>
      <p id="Par40">The source code for ROGUE is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/afarrel/ROGUE">https://github.com/afarrel/ROGUE</ext-link>. All packages and implementation of the tools are described at this repository.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4">
      <title>Datasets</title>
      <p id="Par41">We performed basic analyses on datasets GSE60424 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], GSE102317 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], and GSE40350 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>] and GSE101470 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>] from the GEO Database to illustrate the basic features of ROGUE. Human CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, NK cells, neutrophils, and monocytes from healthy subjects and subjects diagnosed with type 1 diabetes, amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, sepsis, and multiple sclerosis were retrieved from GSE60424. RNA-Seq data from mouse CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells and NK cells were retrieved from GSE102317, GSE40350, and GSE101470, respectively, for additional analyses. Dataset GSE102317 contains RNA-Seq data from CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells treated with IL-2 and IL-21 for 0 (control), 2, 4, and 24 h. Dataset GSE40350 contains CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells treated with IL-2 and IL-15 for 0 (control), 4, and 24 h. Dataset GSE101470 includes RNA-Seq from mature CD11b<sup>−</sup>/CD27<sup>−</sup>, CD11b<sup>−</sup>/CD27<sup>+</sup>, CD11b<sup>+</sup>/CD27<sup>+</sup>, and CD11b<sup>+</sup>/CD27<sup>low</sup> NK cells as well as <italic>Stat5</italic> double knock-in mice with N-terminal mutations in STAT5A and STAT5B that prevent STAT5 tetramerization but not dimerization.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec5">
    <title>Results and discussion</title>
    <sec id="Sec6">
      <title>Workflow</title>
      <p id="Par42">We demonstrate the capability of ROGUE by exploring some basic differences between CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, and natural killer (NK) cells in datasets downloaded from the GEO Database. First, we performed DEA using edgeR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] and compared the expression of genes of interest between cell types. We then performed GSEA, GO analysis, and biomarker discovery based on gene expression to understand functional differences between the cells and discover possible biomarkers. We used ROGUE to perform dimensionality reduction by t-SNE to evaluate if the transcriptome of these cells were distinct enough to cluster each sample by cell type. Finally, we searched for differentially expressed gene sets from the GO Resource to evaluate changes in pathways pre and post-interferon beta (IFNβ) treatment in immune cells from patients with multiple sclerosis (MS).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec7">
      <title>Basic DEA and GO analysis</title>
      <p id="Par43">To illustrate the basic features of ROGUE, we first performed DEA on CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells versus CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells from healthy humans in dataset GSE60424 using edgeR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] and generated a volcano plot showing the differentially expressed genes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A). We next performed GSEA using the ‘fgsea’ R package to identify enriched gene signatures from the differentially expressed genes between CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells and CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells from healthy humans (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B, C, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). For this illustration, we expect to see gene sets with enhanced expression in experiments with stimulated CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells or with lower expression in CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells to be enriched in our CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells RNA-Seq libraries and lower in our CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell libraries. Interestingly, the most enriched gene set for CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells when compared to CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells was a set (GSE45739) of genes downregulated in CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells with <italic>Nras</italic> knockout (KO) mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B). While CD4<sup>+</sup> thymocyte differentiation is not affected in <italic>Nras</italic> KO mice, CD8<sup>+</sup> thymocyte differentiation has been shown to be significantly reduced [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Not surprisingly, the most enriched gene set for CD4<sup>+</sup> human T cells, was a set (GSE22886) of genes downregulated in naïve CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells when compared to CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>C). A heatmap was used to display the distinct expression patterns of the differentially expressed genes between CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells from the four healthy donors in the dataset (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>D). Basic GO analysis of genes upregulated in CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells showed enrichment in genes related to immune effector process, immune response, and leukocyte activation (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>E). We next used the gene ontology comparison tool to evaluate which type of T cell expresses more genes related to the T cell receptor (TCR) complex. This analysis interestingly revealed that the TCR complex was more enriched in the CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells as they expressed more genes at greater RPKM than the CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>F).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Basic analysis of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells versus CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells in healthy individuals. <bold>A</bold> Volcano plot showing differentially expressed genes. <bold>B</bold> GSEA showing the most enriched gene set when CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells were compared to CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells. <bold>C</bold> GSEA shows that the gene set downregulated in naive CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells when compared to naive CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells followed the same pattern in the current dataset. <bold>D</bold> Heatmap showing top differentially expressed genes between CD8<sup>+</sup> and CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells. <bold>E</bold> Gene ontologies of genes upregulated in CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells. <bold>F</bold> Distribution of expressed genes related to the T cell receptor complex</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2023_5420_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec8">
      <title>Biomarker discovery</title>
      <p id="Par44">Biomarker discovery is essential in biomedical and pharmaceutical research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Although mRNA is not always translated into protein, one can infer potential biomarkers from RNA-Seq data. ROGUE uses an optional combination of the coefficient of variation (CV), Wilcoxon-ranked sum test, or t-test for biomarker discovery between RNA-Seq library groups. ROGUE was used to identify potential biomarkers between CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, and NK cells using the Biomarker Discovery tool (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A), and a subset of these potential biomarkers was compared across the various cell types using a heatmap (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B). The expression values of the potential biomarkers were used to perform t-SNE on all the RNA-Seq libraries. A 2-dimensional plot of the t-SNE results shows that RNA-Seq libraries from CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, and NK cells from healthy controls clustered reasonably well based on the potential biomarkers discovered (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>C). Clusters were not as distinct when t-SNE was performed on T and NK cell libraries from both healthy controls and patients in 2 dimensions (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>D), but the clusters in a 3-dimensional plot generated by t-SNE were more homogeneous (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>E). We evaluated the occurrence of these biomarkers in mouse immune cells and observed that only a few of the biomarkers can be used across all datasets in both species (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: A–B). As expected, CD4 and CTLA4 were identified as potential biomarkers for differentiating CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells from CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells and NK cells across both datasets while CD8A and CD8B were identified as potential biomarkers for CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells. Gene expression of the potential human NK cell biomarkers were enriched in mouse NK cells that expressed CD27 (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: C–D). t-SNE was performed on the mouse datasets using the gene expressions of the potential biomarkers. The enrichment of the potential human NK cell biomarkers in mouse CD27<sup>+</sup> NK cells was reflected in the t-SNE plot as they formed a distinct cluster from the other NK cells (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: E). It is worth noting that even though the mouse immune cells cluster well using the biomarkers ascertained from the human immune cells, it is possible that the immune cells cluster well due to a batch effect instead of gene expression signature (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: F).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Biomarker Discovery among CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, and NK cells. <bold>A</bold> The Biomarker tool shows genes with high expression in one cell type and very low expression in the other cell types, suggesting that they may be potential biomarkers. <bold>B</bold> Heatmap showing relative expression values of the potential biomarkers’ gene expression for CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cell, and NK cell groups. <bold>C</bold> 2-dimensional t-SNE plot of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, and NK cells from healthy controls using the identified potential biomarkers. <bold>D</bold> 2-dimensional t-SNE plot of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, and NK cells from both healthy and diseased groups using the identified potential biomarkers. <bold>E</bold> 3-dimensional t-SNE plot using the identified potential biomarkers emphasizes separation between clusters</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2023_5420_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec9">
      <title>Comparison of biological pathways after treating multiple sclerosis patients with IFNβ</title>
      <p id="Par45">Dataset GSE60424 contains RNA-Seq data from CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, NK cells, neutrophils, and monocytes of MS patients before and after IFNβ treatment. MS is an inflammatory demyelinating disease of the central nervous system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. IFNβ treatment is a safe and reasonably effective treatment for MS patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>] due to its anti-inflammatory and immunomodulatory effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. While this is a widely-used treatment, the precise mechanism is unknown. To identify potential hypotheses of the mechanism downstream of IFNβ treatment, we used ROGUE to identify differentially expressed biological processes in CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, and NK cells isolated from patients pre- or post-treatment with IFNβ. CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells showed upregulation of the MDA-5 signaling pathway, among other biological processes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>). CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells and NK cells showed upregulation of 2′–5′-oligoadenylate synthetase activity (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>B, C). Given that the MDA-5 signaling pathway and 2′–5′-oligoadenylate synthetase activity are both involved in interferon signaling in innate immunity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>], and both pathways were upregulated in CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, and NK cells (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: A), we examined the differentially expressed biological processes in neutrophils and monocytes. As expected, we observed an increase in pathways related to interferon production, protein secretion, as well as positive regulation of MDA-5 pathway (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>D and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: B). This led us to examine the expression of genes related to MDA-5 and 2′–5′-oligoadenylate synthetase in all five cell types pre- and post-treatment, as this might give insights into the underlying mechanism. Furthermore, there is at least one report that polymorphisms in MDA-5 (IFIH1) are associated with MS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>], although another report states that this association does not exist in a specific French population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. Nevertheless, the MDA-5 signaling pathway and 2′–5′-oligoadenylate synthetase activity were upregulated in all five cell types (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>E). We then confirmed that both MDA-5 and RIG-I (DDX58) are upregulated in MS patients’ immune cells following treatment with IFNβ, as they are involved in the induction of IRF7 expression and constitutively-expressed IRF3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>] (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: C). A well-defined mechanism of interferon-stimulated gene (ISG) expression is that IRF3 and IRF7 regulate the expression of type 1 interferons, which then induce ISGs through JAK-STAT signaling, including OAS1A and OAS1B [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. However, IFNα and IFNβ mRNAs are not expressed, which suggests that administered IFNβ rather than endogenously produced IFNβ induces ISGs through the JAK-STAT pathway. This model is consistent with our data, as ISGs were upregulated in all five cell types after IFNβ-treatment with significantly greater expression of MDA-5, RIG-1 and ISGs observed in neutrophils (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>E and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: C). Given that 2′–5′-oligoadenylate synthetase can induce apoptosis in tumors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>], perhaps this alternative role of 2′–5′-oligoadenylate synthetase also occurs in immune cells, giving it a pro-inflammatory role as well as an anti-inflammatory role by promoting apoptosis and regulating cell growth and proliferation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. Furthermore, the disproportionate upregulation of genes with pro-apoptotic and antiproliferative roles in neutrophils supports Hasselbalch and Søndergaard’s report of a higher neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio, which is a marker of systemic inflammation, before treatment with IFNβ when compared to controls by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. Moreover, Pierson et al. demonstrated that depleting neutrophils in the MS animal model reduces the progression of the disease and Naegel et al. showed evidence that the increase in neutrophils in relapsing–remitting MS is likely due to decreased apoptosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. If this potential pro-apoptotic anti-inflammatory role of 2′–5′-oligoadenylate synthetase exists, it could be the mechanism by which IFNβ treatment positively impacts MS patients. In addition to 2′–5′-oligoadenylate synthetase activity, IFNβ may be involved in another pathway that explains the MDA-5/RIG-1 upregulation. Shimoni et al. suggested that IFNβ can bind cell surface receptors and promote the induction of RIG-1 as part of a positive feedback loop [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. Wang et al. further showed that RIG-1 and MDA5 signaling induces tumor necrosis factor (TNF) in macrophages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>], and TNF has been shown to have anti-inflammatory effects in MS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. The anti-inflammatory effects of TNF coupled with the pro-apoptotic role of 2′–5′-oligoadenylate synthetase may be part of the downstream mechanism contributing to the positive response induced by IFNβ in MS patients.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Using differentially expressed pathways to generate and/or explore hypotheses. <bold>A</bold> Distribution of MDA-5 signaling pathway in untreated (red) and IFNβ-treated (blue) CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells showing an upregulation of genes related to MDA-5 signaling. <bold>B</bold>, <bold>C</bold> Distribution of 2′–5′-oligoadenylate synthetase activity in untreated (red) and IFNβ-treated (blue) CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells (<bold>B</bold>) and NK cells (<bold>C</bold>) showing an upregulation of genes 2′–5′-oligoadenylate synthetase activity. <bold>D</bold> Boxplots showing pathways that may be differentially regulated in neutrophils with multiple genes consistently upregulated or downregulated post-IFNβ treatment. <bold>E</bold> Bar plot showing upregulated MDA-5 (IFIH1), RIG-I (DDX58), and genes related to 2′–5′-oligoadenylate synthetase in IFNβ-treated monocytes, neutrophils, CD4 + T cells, CD8 + T cells, and NK cells</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2023_5420_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec10">
    <title>Conclusion</title>
    <p id="Par46">ROGUE is designed to be a user-friendly R Shiny application that allows users to perform basic tasks with available RNA-Seq data such as differentially expressed gene analysis and gene ontology analysis. While other freely available web tools and portals have been developed to allow researchers to address discrete questions based on molecular and genomic datasets without the need for strong computational skills [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>], ROGUE allows deeper dataset exploration, allowing users to compare gene expression and gene set enrichments between samples and groups. For example, users can explore similarities of expression profiles using the dimensionality reduction methods such as t-SNE, PCA, UMAP, and MDS and search for potential biomarkers between groups of RNA-Seq libraries, to our knowledge making it the only currently available tool to allow this range of dataset analysis (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>). Furthermore, users have the option to download their session and continue their analysis at a later time. Users can also restore a session if the web application gets disconnected from the server. In addition to the case study presented here, we successfully tested ROGUE on ten diverse human and mouse case studies downloaded from Expression Atlas to illustrate the various applications and robustness (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>). It is worth noting that ROGUE is an R Shiny application thus allowing the inclusion of many statistical and graphical functions by the R community as well as the ability to be implemented on both local and web servers; however, like all R Shiny applications there are limitations. One of these limitations is that R Shiny applications that are implemented on web servers may perform slowly and sometimes disconnect from the server resulting in a subsequent crash when processing large datasets or performing computationally intensive functions. For this reason, we recommend downloading the local version of ROGUE from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/afarrel/ROGUE">https://github.com/afarrel/ROGUE</ext-link> when processing large datasets. Here, we show that a user can explore RNA-Seq data obtained from public databases and use ROGUE to analyze that data to generate or support new or existing hypotheses. ROGUE provides non-R programmers access to many statistical and graphical R packages for RNA-Seq analyses through a GUI so they can analyze their data and create figures. Ideally, tools like ROGUE will allow more biomedical researchers to take advantage of genomic data available and help expedite needed bioinformatics analyses. ROGUE is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://marisshiny.research.chop.edu/ROGUE/">https://marisshiny.research.chop.edu/ROGUE/</ext-link>.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec900">
    <title>Availability and requirements</title>
    <p id="Par47">Project Name: ROGUE.</p>
    <p id="Par48">Project Home Page: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://marisshiny.research.chop.edu/ROGUE/">https://marisshiny.research.chop.edu/ROGUE/</ext-link>.</p>
    <p id="Par49">Github: https://github.com/afarrel/ROGUE.</p>
    <p id="Par50">Operating System: Platform independent.</p>
    <p id="Par51">Programming language: R.</p>
    <p id="Par52">Other requirements: R environment and included packages. Tested on R version 3.6.</p>
    <p id="Par53">Any restrictions to use by non-academics: none.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Information</title>
    <sec id="Sec11">
      <p>
        <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1">
          <media xlink:href="12859_2023_5420_MOESM1_ESM.pdf">
            <caption>
              <p><bold>Additional file 1: </bold>GSEA analysis of healthy human CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells vs CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells.</p>
            </caption>
          </media>
        </supplementary-material>
        <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2">
          <media xlink:href="12859_2023_5420_MOESM2_ESM.pdf">
            <caption>
              <p><bold>Additional file 2:</bold> Evaluating biomarkers found in human CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, and NK cells in mouse immune cells from different datasets.</p>
            </caption>
          </media>
        </supplementary-material>
        <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3">
          <media xlink:href="12859_2023_5420_MOESM3_ESM.pdf">
            <caption>
              <p><bold>Additional file 3:</bold> Distribution of gene expression profiles in the differentially expressed pathways.</p>
            </caption>
          </media>
        </supplementary-material>
        <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4">
          <media xlink:href="12859_2023_5420_MOESM4_ESM.pdf">
            <caption>
              <p><bold>Additional file 4:</bold> Evaluation of MD5A-signaling, RIG-1 signaling, and 2'-5'-oligoadenylate synthetase pre- and post-IFNβ treatment.</p>
            </caption>
          </media>
        </supplementary-material>
        <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5">
          <media xlink:href="12859_2023_5420_MOESM5_ESM.xlsx">
            <caption>
              <p><bold>Additional file 5:</bold> Available Rshiny RNAseq analysis tools.</p>
            </caption>
          </media>
        </supplementary-material>
        <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6">
          <media xlink:href="12859_2023_5420_MOESM6_ESM.docx">
            <caption>
              <p><bold>Additional file 6:</bold> List of case studies.</p>
            </caption>
          </media>
        </supplementary-material>
      </p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <glossary>
    <title>Abbreviations</title>
    <def-list>
      <def-item>
        <term>CV</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par4">Coefficient of variation</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>DEA</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par5">Differential expression analysis</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>FGSEA</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par6">Fast gene set enrichment analysis</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>FPKM</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par7">Fragments per kilobase of transcript per million mapped reads</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>GEO</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par8">Gene expression omnibus</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>GO</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par9">Gene ontology</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>GSEA</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par10">Gene set enrichment analysis</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>GTEx</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par11">The genotype tissue expression</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>GUI</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par12">Graphic user interface</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>IFNα</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par13">Interferon alpha</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>IFNβ</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par14">Interferon beta</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>ISG</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par15">Interferon-stimulated gene</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>MDS</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par16">Multidimensional scaling</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>MSigDB</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par17">Molecular signatures database</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>MS</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par18">Multiple sclerosis</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>NK</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par19">Natural killer</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>PCA</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par20">Principal component analysis</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>RNA-Seq</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par21">RNA sequencing</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>ROGUE</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par22">RNA-Seq ontology graphic user environment</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>RPKM</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par23">Reads per kilobase of transcript per million mapped reads</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>TCGA</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par24">The cancer genome atlas</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>TCR</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par25">T cell receptor</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>TNF</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par26">Tumor necrosis factor</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>TPM</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par27">Transcripts per million</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>t-SNE</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par28">T-distributed stochastic neighbor embedding</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>UMAP</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par29">Uniform manifold approximation and projection</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
    </def-list>
  </glossary>
  <fn-group>
    <fn>
      <p>
        <bold>Publisher's Note</bold>
      </p>
      <p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
    </fn>
  </fn-group>
  <ack>
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <p>We thank Jian-Xin Lin for discussions and suggestions in reviewing the application and the manuscript. We are grateful to Grace Coggins and Laura Scolaro for using this application in their research and suggesting changes to increase usability.</p>
  </ack>
  <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
    <title>Author contributions</title>
    <p>Conceptualization, AF; Methodology, AF, PL, and SV; Software, AF, PL and KP; Formal Analysis, AF; Funding Acquisition, WJL and JMM; Writing, AF, PL, SV, JMM and WJL; Supervision, AF and WJL. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
  </notes>
  <notes notes-type="funding-information">
    <title>Funding</title>
    <p>This work was supported by the Division of Intramural Research, National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, NIH, and NIH grants R35 CA220500, P01 CA217959 and U54 CA232568 (JMM).</p>
  </notes>
  <notes notes-type="data-availability">
    <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
    <p>RNA sequencing expression data from human immune cells: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE60424">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE60424</ext-link>. RNA sequencing expression data from mouse immune cells: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE102317">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE102317</ext-link>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE40350">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE40350</ext-link>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE101470">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE101470</ext-link></p>
  </notes>
  <notes>
    <title>Declarations</title>
    <notes id="FPar1">
      <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
      <p id="Par54">Not applicable.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes id="FPar2">
      <title>Consent for publication</title>
      <p id="Par55">Not applicable.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p id="Par56">The authors declare that they have no competing interest.</p>
    </notes>
  </notes>
  <ref-list id="Bib1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="CR1">
      <label>1.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Garalde</surname>
            <given-names>DR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Snell</surname>
            <given-names>EA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jachimowicz</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sipos</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lloyd</surname>
            <given-names>JH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bruce</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Highly parallel direct RNA sequencing on an array of nanopores</article-title>
        <source>Nat Methods</source>
        <year>2018</year>
        <volume>15</volume>
        <fpage>201</fpage>
        <lpage>206</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.4577</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 29334379?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29334379</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR2">
      <label>2.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Smith</surname>
            <given-names>AM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jain</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mulroney</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Garalde</surname>
            <given-names>DR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Akeson</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Reading canonical and modified nucleobases in 16S ribosomal RNA using nanopore native RNA sequencing</article-title>
        <source>PLoS ONE</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>14</volume>
        <fpage>e0216709</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0216709</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 31095620?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31095620</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR3">
      <label>3.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Byrne</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Beaudin</surname>
            <given-names>AE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Olsen</surname>
            <given-names>HE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jain</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cole</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Palmer</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Nanopore long-read RNAseq reveals widespread transcriptional variation among the surface receptors of individual B cells</article-title>
        <source>Nat Commun</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <fpage>16027</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms16027</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 28722025?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28722025</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR4">
      <label>4.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Trapnell</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Williams</surname>
            <given-names>BA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pertea</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mortazavi</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kwan</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>van Baren</surname>
            <given-names>MJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Transcript assembly and quantification by RNA-Seq reveals unannotated transcripts and isoform switching during cell differentiation</article-title>
        <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>28</volume>
        <fpage>511</fpage>
        <lpage>515</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.1621</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 20436464?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20436464</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR5">
      <label>5.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pertea</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pertea</surname>
            <given-names>GM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Leek</surname>
            <given-names>JT</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Salzberg</surname>
            <given-names>SL</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Transcript-level expression analysis of RNA-seq experiments with HISAT</article-title>
        <source>StringTie and Ballgown Nat Protoc</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <fpage>1650</fpage>
        <lpage>1667</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2016.095</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 27560171?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27560171</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR6">
      <label>6.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bray</surname>
            <given-names>NL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pimentel</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Melsted</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pachter</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Near-optimal probabilistic RNA-seq quantification</article-title>
        <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>34</volume>
        <fpage>525</fpage>
        <lpage>527</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.3519</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 27043002?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27043002</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR7">
      <label>7.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sahraeian</surname>
            <given-names>SME</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mohiyuddin</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sebra</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tilgner</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Afshar</surname>
            <given-names>PT</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Au</surname>
            <given-names>KF</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Gaining comprehensive biological insight into the transcriptome by performing a broad-spectrum RNA-seq analysis</article-title>
        <source>Nat Commun</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <fpage>59</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-017-00050-4</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 28680106?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28680106</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR8">
      <label>8.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dewey</surname>
            <given-names>CN</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>RSEM: accurate transcript quantification from RNA-Seq data with or without a reference genome</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinform</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <fpage>323</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-12-323</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR9">
      <label>9.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Trapnell</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Roberts</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Goff</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pertea</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kelley</surname>
            <given-names>DR</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Differential gene and transcript expression analysis of RNA-seq experiments with TopHat and Cufflinks</article-title>
        <source>Nat Protoc</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <fpage>562</fpage>
        <lpage>578</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2012.016</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 22383036?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22383036</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR10">
      <label>10.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Robinson</surname>
            <given-names>MD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McCarthy</surname>
            <given-names>DJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Smyth</surname>
            <given-names>GK</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>edgeR: a bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data</article-title>
        <source>Bioinform Oxf Engl</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>26</volume>
        <fpage>139</fpage>
        <lpage>140</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR11">
      <label>11.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Love</surname>
            <given-names>MI</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huber</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Anders</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA-seq data with DESeq2</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>15</volume>
        <fpage>550</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-014-0550-8</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25516281?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25516281</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR12">
      <label>12.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Law</surname>
            <given-names>CW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shi</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Smyth</surname>
            <given-names>GK</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>voom: precision weights unlock linear model analysis tools for RNA-seq read counts</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>15</volume>
        <fpage>R29</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2014-15-2-r29</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24485249?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24485249</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR13">
      <label>13.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Costa-Silva</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Domingues</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lopes</surname>
            <given-names>FM</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>RNA-Seq differential expression analysis: An extended review and a software tool</article-title>
        <source>PLoS ONE</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <fpage>e0190152</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0190152</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 29267363?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29267363</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR14">
      <label>14.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Conesa</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Madrigal</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tarazona</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gomez-Cabrero</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cervera</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McPherson</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A survey of best practices for RNA-seq data analysis</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>17</volume>
        <fpage>13</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-016-0881-8</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 26813401?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26813401</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR15">
      <label>15.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Seyednasrollah</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Laiho</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Elo</surname>
            <given-names>LL</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Comparison of software packages for detecting differential expression in RNA-seq studies</article-title>
        <source>Brief Bioinform</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>16</volume>
        <fpage>59</fpage>
        <lpage>70</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bib/bbt086</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24300110?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24300110</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR16">
      <label>16.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Williams</surname>
            <given-names>CR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Baccarella</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Parrish</surname>
            <given-names>JZ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>CC</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Empirical assessment of analysis workflows for differential expression analysis of human samples using RNA-Seq</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinform</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>18</volume>
        <fpage>38</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-016-1457-z</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR17">
      <label>17.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ashburner</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ball</surname>
            <given-names>CA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Blake</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Botstein</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Butler</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cherry</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Gene ontology: tool for the unification of biology. The Gene Ontology Consortium</article-title>
        <source>Nat Genet</source>
        <year>2000</year>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <fpage>25</fpage>
        <lpage>29</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/75556</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 10802651?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10802651</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR18">
      <label>18.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Subramanian</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tamayo</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mootha</surname>
            <given-names>VK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mukherjee</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ebert</surname>
            <given-names>BL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gillette</surname>
            <given-names>MA</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Gene set enrichment analysis: a knowledge-based approach for interpreting genome-wide expression profiles</article-title>
        <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
        <year>2005</year>
        <volume>102</volume>
        <fpage>15545</fpage>
        <lpage>15550</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0506580102</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 16199517?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16199517</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR19">
      <label>19.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mi</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Muruganujan</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ebert</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Thomas</surname>
            <given-names>PD</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>PANTHER version 14: more genomes, a new PANTHER GO-slim and improvements in enrichment analysis tools</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>47</volume>
        <fpage>D419</fpage>
        <lpage>D426</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gky1038</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 30407594?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30407594</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR20">
      <label>20.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Carbon</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ireland</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mungall</surname>
            <given-names>CJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shu</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Marshall</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lewis</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>AmiGO: online access to ontology and annotation data</article-title>
        <source>Bioinforma Oxf Engl</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <fpage>288</fpage>
        <lpage>289</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btn615</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR21">
      <label>21.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Loraine</surname>
            <given-names>AE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Blakley</surname>
            <given-names>IC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jagadeesan</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Harper</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Miller</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Firon</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Analysis and visualization of RNA-Seq expression data using RStudio, bioconductor, and integrated genome browser</article-title>
        <source>Methods Mol Biol Clifton NJ</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>1284</volume>
        <fpage>481</fpage>
        <lpage>501</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4939-2444-8_24</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR22">
      <label>22.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jolliffe</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <person-group person-group-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Lovric</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Principal component analysis</article-title>
        <source>International encyclopedia of statistical science</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>
        <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
        <fpage>1094</fpage>
        <lpage>1096</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR23">
      <label>23.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jolliffe I. Principal component analysis. In: Wiley StatsRef: Statistics Reference Online. American Cancer Society; 2014. 10.1002/9781118445112.stat06472.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR24">
      <label>24.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>van der Maaten</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hinton</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Visualizing data using t-SNE</article-title>
        <source>J Mach Learn Res</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <fpage>2579</fpage>
        <lpage>2605</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR25">
      <label>25.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Edgar</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Domrachev</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lash</surname>
            <given-names>AE</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Gene Expression Omnibus: NCBI gene expression and hybridization array data repository</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
        <year>2002</year>
        <volume>30</volume>
        <fpage>207</fpage>
        <lpage>210</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/30.1.207</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 11752295?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11752295</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR26">
      <label>26.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Athar</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Füllgrabe</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>George</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Iqbal</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huerta</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ali</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>ArrayExpress update—from bulk to single-cell expression data</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>47</volume>
        <fpage>D711</fpage>
        <lpage>D715</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gky964</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 30357387?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30357387</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR27">
      <label>27.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Carithers</surname>
            <given-names>LJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ardlie</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Barcus</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Branton</surname>
            <given-names>PA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Britton</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Buia</surname>
            <given-names>SA</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A novel approach to high-quality postmortem tissue procurement: the GTEx project</article-title>
        <source>Biopreserv Biobank</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>13</volume>
        <fpage>311</fpage>
        <lpage>319</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/bio.2015.0032</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 26484571?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26484571</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR28">
      <label>28.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">The Cancer Genome Atlas Research Network, Weinstein JN, Collisson EA, Mills GB, Shaw KRM, Ozenberger BA, et al. The Cancer Genome Atlas Pan-Cancer analysis project. Nat Genet. 2013;45:1113–20.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR29">
      <label>29.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Anders</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pyl</surname>
            <given-names>PT</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huber</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>HTSeq—a Python framework to work with high-throughput sequencing data</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>31</volume>
        <fpage>166</fpage>
        <lpage>169</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu638</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25260700?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25260700</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR30">
      <label>30.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Schurch</surname>
            <given-names>NJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schofield</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gierliński</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cole</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sherstnev</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Singh</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>How many biological replicates are needed in an RNA-seq experiment and which differential expression tool should you use?</article-title>
        <source>RNA N Y N</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>22</volume>
        <fpage>839</fpage>
        <lpage>851</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1261/rna.053959.115</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR31">
      <label>31.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Assefa</surname>
            <given-names>AT</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>De Paepe</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Everaert</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mestdagh</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Thas</surname>
            <given-names>O</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vandesompele</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Differential gene expression analysis tools exhibit substandard performance for long non-coding RNA-sequencing data</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol</source>
        <year>2018</year>
        <volume>19</volume>
        <fpage>96</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-018-1466-5</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 30041657?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30041657</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR32">
      <label>32.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Korotkevich G, Sukhov V, Budin N, Shpak B, Artyomov MN, Sergushichev A. Fast gene set enrichment analysis. bioRxiv. 2021; 060012.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR33">
      <label>33.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liberzon</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Subramanian</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pinchback</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Thorvaldsdóttir</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tamayo</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mesirov</surname>
            <given-names>JP</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Molecular signatures database (MSigDB) 3.0</article-title>
        <source>Bioinform Oxf Engl</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>27</volume>
        <fpage>1739</fpage>
        <lpage>1740</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr260</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR34">
      <label>34.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <collab>Gene Ontology Consortium</collab>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The Gene Ontology resource: enriching a GOld mine</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <year>2021</year>
        <volume>49</volume>
        <fpage>D325</fpage>
        <lpage>D334</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkaa1113</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33290552</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR35">
      <label>35.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Krijthe JH. Rtsne: T-Distributed stochastic neighbor embedding using Barnes–Hut implementation. 2015. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/jkrijthe/Rtsne">https://github.com/jkrijthe/Rtsne</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR36">
      <label>36.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Melville J. uwot: the uniform manifold approximation and projection (UMAP) method for dimensionality reduction. 2020. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=uwot">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=uwot</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR37">
      <label>37.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">McInnes L, Healy J, Melville J. UMAP: uniform manifold approximation and projection for dimension reduction. 2020.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR38">
      <label>38.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Becht</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McInnes</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Healy</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dutertre</surname>
            <given-names>C-A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kwok</surname>
            <given-names>IWH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ng</surname>
            <given-names>LG</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Dimensionality reduction for visualizing single-cell data using UMAP</article-title>
        <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
        <year>2018</year>
        <volume>37</volume>
        <fpage>38</fpage>
        <lpage>44</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.4314</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR39">
      <label>39.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Linsley</surname>
            <given-names>PS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Speake</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Whalen</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chaussabel</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Copy number loss of the interferon gene cluster in melanomas is linked to reduced T cell infiltrate and poor patient prognosis</article-title>
        <source>PLoS ONE</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <fpage>e109760</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0109760</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25314013?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25314013</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR40">
      <label>40.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mitra</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Spolski</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Oh</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liao</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tang</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>STAT5-mediated chromatin interactions in superenhancers activate IL-2 highly inducible genes: Functional dissection of the Il2ra gene locus</article-title>
        <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>114</volume>
        <fpage>12111</fpage>
        <lpage>12119</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1714019114</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 29078395?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29078395</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR41">
      <label>41.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>J-X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Du</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kazemian</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gebregiorgis</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Spolski</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Critical functions for STAT5 tetramers in the maturation and survival of natural killer cells</article-title>
        <source>Nat Commun</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <fpage>1320</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-017-01477-5</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 29105654?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29105654</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR42">
      <label>42.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ring</surname>
            <given-names>AM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>J-X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Feng</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mitra</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rickert</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bowman</surname>
            <given-names>GR</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Mechanistic and structural insight into the functional dichotomy between IL-2 and IL-15</article-title>
        <source>Nat Immunol</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>13</volume>
        <fpage>1187</fpage>
        <lpage>1195</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni.2449</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 23104097?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23104097</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR43">
      <label>43.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pérez de Castro</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Diaz</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Malumbres</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hernández</surname>
            <given-names>M-I</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jagirdar</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jiménez</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Mice deficient for N-ras: impaired antiviral immune response and T-cell function</article-title>
        <source>Cancer Res</source>
        <year>2003</year>
        <volume>63</volume>
        <fpage>1615</fpage>
        <lpage>1622</lpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 12670913?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12670913</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR44">
      <label>44.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liotta</surname>
            <given-names>LA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ferrari</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Petricoin</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Clinical proteomics: written in blood</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <year>2003</year>
        <volume>425</volume>
        <fpage>905</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/425905a</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 14586448?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14586448</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR45">
      <label>45.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Goossens</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nakagawa</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hoshida</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Cancer biomarker discovery and validation</article-title>
        <source>Transl Cancer Res</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <fpage>256</fpage>
        <lpage>269</lpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 26213686?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26213686</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR46">
      <label>46.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Norouzinia</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chaleshi</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Alizadeh</surname>
            <given-names>AHM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zali</surname>
            <given-names>MR</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Biomarkers in inflammatory bowel diseases: insight into diagnosis, prognosis and treatment</article-title>
        <source>Gastroenterol Hepatol Bed Bench</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <fpage>155</fpage>
        <lpage>167</lpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 29118930?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29118930</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR47">
      <label>47.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wootla</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Eriguchi</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rodriguez</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Is multiple sclerosis an autoimmune disease?</article-title>
        <source>Autoimmune Dis</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>2012</volume>
        <fpage>969657</fpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 22666554?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22666554</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR48">
      <label>48.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jacobs</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Brownscheidle</surname>
            <given-names>CM</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Appropriate use of interferon beta-1a in multiple sclerosis</article-title>
        <source>BioDrugs</source>
        <year>1999</year>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <fpage>155</fpage>
        <lpage>163</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/00063030-199911030-00002</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 18031126?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18031126</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR49">
      <label>49.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Clerico</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Contessa</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Durelli</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Interferon-β1a for the treatment of multiple sclerosis</article-title>
        <source>Expert Opin Biol Ther</source>
        <year>2007</year>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <fpage>535</fpage>
        <lpage>542</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1517/14712598.7.4.535</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 17373904?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17373904</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR50">
      <label>50.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bertolotto</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gilli</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Interferon-beta responders and non-responders. A biological approach</article-title>
        <source>Neurol Sci Off J Ital Neurol Soc Ital Soc Clin Neurophysiol</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>29</volume>
        <issue>Suppl 2</issue>
        <fpage>S216</fpage>
        <lpage>217</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR51">
      <label>51.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Freedman</surname>
            <given-names>MS</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Long-term follow-up of clinical trials of multiple sclerosis therapies</article-title>
        <source>Neurology</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>76</volume>
        <issue>Supplement 1</issue>
        <fpage>S26</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0b013e318205051d</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 21205679?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21205679</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR52">
      <label>52.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kasper</surname>
            <given-names>LH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Reder</surname>
            <given-names>AT</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Immunomodulatory activity of interferon-beta</article-title>
        <source>Ann Clin Transl Neurol</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>1</volume>
        <fpage>622</fpage>
        <lpage>631</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/acn3.84</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25356432?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25356432</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR53">
      <label>53.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dhib-Jalbut</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Marks</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Interferon-β mechanisms of action in multiple sclerosis</article-title>
        <source>Neurology</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>74</volume>
        <issue>Supplement 1</issue>
        <fpage>S17</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0b013e3181c97d99</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 20038758?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20038758</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR54">
      <label>54.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Loo</surname>
            <given-names>Y-M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gale</surname>
            <given-names>MJ</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Immune signaling by RIG-I-like receptors</article-title>
        <source>Immunity</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>34</volume>
        <fpage>680</fpage>
        <lpage>692</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2011.05.003</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 21616437?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21616437</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR55">
      <label>55.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Qiu</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tang</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Long non-coding RNAs: regulators of viral infection and the interferon antiviral response</article-title>
        <source>Front Microbiol</source>
        <year>2018</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <fpage>1621</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.01621</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 30072977?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30072977</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR56">
      <label>56.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pulit-Penaloza</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Scherbik</surname>
            <given-names>SV</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Brinton</surname>
            <given-names>MA</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Type 1 IFN-independent activation of a subset of interferon stimulated genes in West Nile virus Eg101-infected mouse cells</article-title>
        <source>Virology</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>425</volume>
        <fpage>82</fpage>
        <lpage>94</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virol.2012.01.006</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 22305622?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22305622</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR57">
      <label>57.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Choi</surname>
            <given-names>UY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kang</surname>
            <given-names>J-S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hwang</surname>
            <given-names>YS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Y-J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Oligoadenylate synthase-like (OASL) proteins: dual functions and associations with diseases</article-title>
        <source>Exp Mol Med</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>47</volume>
        <fpage>e144</fpage>
        <lpage>e144</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/emm.2014.110</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25744296?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25744296</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR58">
      <label>58.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Martínez</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Santiago</surname>
            <given-names>JL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cénit</surname>
            <given-names>MC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>de Las</surname>
            <given-names>HV</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>de la Calle</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fernández-Arquero</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>IFIH1-GCA-KCNH7 locus: influence on multiple sclerosis risk</article-title>
        <source>Eur J Hum Genet EJHG</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>16</volume>
        <fpage>861</fpage>
        <lpage>864</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ejhg.2008.16</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 18285833?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18285833</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR59">
      <label>59.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Couturier</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gourraud</surname>
            <given-names>P-A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cournu-Rebeix</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gout</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bucciarelli</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Edan</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>IFIH1-GCA-KCNH7 locus is not associated with genetic susceptibility to multiple sclerosis in French patients</article-title>
        <source>Eur J Hum Genet EJHG</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>17</volume>
        <fpage>844</fpage>
        <lpage>847</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ejhg.2008.259</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 19156166?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19156166</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR60">
      <label>60.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Malathi</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dong</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gale</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
            <suffix>Jr</suffix>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Silverman</surname>
            <given-names>RH</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Small self-RNA generated by RNase L amplifies antiviral innate immunity</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <year>2007</year>
        <volume>448</volume>
        <fpage>816</fpage>
        <lpage>819</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature06042</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 17653195?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17653195</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR61">
      <label>61.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mullan</surname>
            <given-names>PB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hosey</surname>
            <given-names>AM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Buckley</surname>
            <given-names>NE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Quinn</surname>
            <given-names>JE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kennedy</surname>
            <given-names>RD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Johnston</surname>
            <given-names>PG</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The 2,5 oligoadenylate synthetase/RNaseL pathway is a novel effector of BRCA1- and interferon-γ-mediated apoptosis</article-title>
        <source>Oncogene</source>
        <year>2005</year>
        <volume>24</volume>
        <fpage>5492</fpage>
        <lpage>5501</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.onc.1208698</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 15940267?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15940267</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR62">
      <label>62.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hasselbalch</surname>
            <given-names>IC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Søndergaard</surname>
            <given-names>HB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Koch-Henriksen</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Olsson</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ullum</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sellebjerg</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio is associated with multiple sclerosis</article-title>
        <source>Mult Scler J Exp Transl Clin</source>
        <year>2018</year>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <fpage>2055217318813183</fpage>
        <lpage>2055217318813183</lpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 30515298?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30515298</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR63">
      <label>63.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pierson</surname>
            <given-names>ER</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wagner</surname>
            <given-names>CA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Goverman</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The contribution of neutrophils to CNS autoimmunity</article-title>
        <source>Clin Immunol Orlando Fla</source>
        <year>2018</year>
        <volume>189</volume>
        <fpage>23</fpage>
        <lpage>28</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clim.2016.06.017</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR64">
      <label>64.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Naegele</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tillack</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Reinhardt</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schippling</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Martin</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sospedra</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Neutrophils in multiple sclerosis are characterized by a primed phenotype</article-title>
        <source>J Neuroimmunol</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>242</volume>
        <fpage>60</fpage>
        <lpage>71</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jneuroim.2011.11.009</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 22169406?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22169406</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR65">
      <label>65.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shimoni</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nudelman</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hayot</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sealfon</surname>
            <given-names>SC</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Multi-scale stochastic simulation of diffusion-coupled agents and its application to cell culture simulation</article-title>
        <source>PLoS ONE</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <fpage>e29298</fpage>
        <lpage>e29298</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029298</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 22216238?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22216238</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR66">
      <label>66.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gao</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Barrett</surname>
            <given-names>JW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shao</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bartee</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mohamed</surname>
            <given-names>MR</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>RIG-I mediates the co-induction of tumor necrosis factor and type I interferon elicited by myxoma virus in primary human macrophages</article-title>
        <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <fpage>e1000099</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000099</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 18617992?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18617992</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR67">
      <label>67.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Marino</surname>
            <given-names>MW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wong</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Grail</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dunn</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bettadapura</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>TNF is a potent anti-inflammatory cytokine in autoimmune-mediated demyelination</article-title>
        <source>Nat Med</source>
        <year>1998</year>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <fpage>78</fpage>
        <lpage>83</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm0198-078</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 9427610?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9427610</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR68">
      <label>68.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sundararajan</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Knoll</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hombach</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Becker</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schultze</surname>
            <given-names>JL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ulas</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Shiny-Seq: advanced guided transcriptome analysis</article-title>
        <source>BMC Res Notes</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <fpage>432</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13104-019-4471-1</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 31319888?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31319888</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR69">
      <label>69.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Su</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shimizu</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kadota</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>TCC-GUI: a Shiny-based application for differential expression analysis of RNA-Seq count data</article-title>
        <source>BMC Res Notes</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <fpage>133</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13104-019-4179-2</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 30867032?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30867032</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>BMC Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1471-2105</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">10386769</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">5420</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-023-05420-y</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Software</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>ROGUE: an R Shiny app for RNA sequencing analysis and biomarker discovery</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1087-9840</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Farrel</surname>
          <given-names>Alvin</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>farrela@chop.edu</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Li</surname>
          <given-names>Peng</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Veenbergen</surname>
          <given-names>Sharon</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Patel</surname>
          <given-names>Khushbu</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Maris</surname>
          <given-names>John M.</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <name>
          <surname>Leonard</surname>
          <given-names>Warren J.</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>wjl@helix.nih.gov</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.94365.3d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2297 5165</institution-id><institution>Laboratory of Molecular Immunology, National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, </institution><institution>National Institutes of Health, </institution></institution-wrap>Bethesda, MD USA </aff>
      <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.94365.3d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2297 5165</institution-id><institution>Immunology Center, National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, </institution><institution>National Institutes of Health, </institution></institution-wrap>Bethesda, MD USA </aff>
      <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.239552.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0680 8770</institution-id><institution>Division of Oncology and Center for Childhood Cancer Research, </institution><institution>Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia, </institution></institution-wrap>Philadelphia, PA USA </aff>
      <aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.239552.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0680 8770</institution-id><institution>Department of Biomedical and Health Informatics, </institution><institution>Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia, </institution></institution-wrap>Philadelphia, PA USA </aff>
      <aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5645.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">000000040459992X</institution-id><institution>Laboratory of Pediatric Gastroenterology, </institution><institution>Erasmus University Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Rotterdam, The Netherlands </aff>
      <aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.25879.31</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8972</institution-id><institution>Perelman School of Medicine at the University of Pennsylvania, </institution></institution-wrap>Philadelphia, PA USA </aff>
      <aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5645.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">000000040459992X</institution-id><institution>Present Address: Laboratory of Medical Immunology, Department of Immunology, </institution><institution>Erasmus University Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Rotterdam, The Netherlands </aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>29</day>
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>29</day>
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>24</volume>
    <elocation-id>303</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>13</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2020</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>18</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© This is a U.S. Government work and not under copyright protection in the US; foreign copyright protection may apply 2023</copyright-statement>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract id="Abs1">
      <sec>
        <title>Background</title>
        <p id="Par1">The growing power and ever decreasing cost of RNA sequencing (RNA-Seq) technologies have resulted in an explosion of RNA-Seq data production. Comparing gene expression values within RNA-Seq datasets is relatively easy for many interdisciplinary biomedical researchers; however, user-friendly software applications increase the ability of biologists to efficiently explore available datasets.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Results</title>
        <p id="Par2">Here, we describe ROGUE (RNA-Seq Ontology Graphic User Environment, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://marisshiny.research.chop.edu/ROGUE/">https://marisshiny.research.chop.edu/ROGUE/</ext-link>), a user-friendly R Shiny application that allows a biologist to perform differentially expressed gene analysis, gene ontology and pathway enrichment analysis, potential biomarker identification, and advanced statistical analyses. We use ROGUE to identify potential biomarkers and show unique enriched pathways between various immune cells.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Conclusions</title>
        <p id="Par3">User-friendly tools for the analysis of next generation sequencing data, such as ROGUE, will allow biologists to efficiently explore their datasets, discover expression patterns, and advance their research by allowing them to develop and test hypotheses.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Supplementary Information</title>
        <p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12859-023-05420-y.</p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
      <title>Keywords</title>
      <kwd>R Shiny</kwd>
      <kwd>RNA-Seq</kwd>
      <kwd>Differential expression</kwd>
      <kwd>Biomarkers</kwd>
      <kwd>GSEA</kwd>
      <kwd>Gene ontology</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group>
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000002</institution-id>
            <institution>the Division of Intramural Research, National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, NIH, and National Institutes of Health</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>R35 CA220500</award-id>
        <award-id>P01 CA217959</award-id>
        <award-id>U54 CA232568</award-id>
        <principal-award-recipient>
          <name>
            <surname>Maris</surname>
            <given-names>John M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </principal-award-recipient>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
        <meta-value>© BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2023</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec id="Sec1">
    <title>Background</title>
    <p id="Par30">RNA sequencing (RNA-Seq) has become an extremely powerful tool for understanding biological pathways and molecular mechanisms. Technological advancements, both wet-lab and computational, have transformed RNA-Seq into a more accessible tool, giving biomedical researchers access to a less biased view of RNA biology and transcriptomics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. The growing power and ever decreasing cost of RNA-Seq technologies have resulted in a marked increase in RNA-Seq dataset production.</p>
    <p id="Par31">The explosion of computational algorithms and pipelines in the last decade has given researchers the ability to perform rigorous analyses and explore RNA-Seq data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Differential expression analysis (DEA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], which is the most common analysis performed on RNA-Seq, is used to estimate steady-state mRNA levels. There are multiple bioinformatics pipelines and packages used to perform DEA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], including edgeR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], DESeq[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], and limma-voom [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Different combinations of the various algorithms to analyze sequence reads and perform DEA can affect the biological conclusions drawn from the data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Researchers must carefully select the optimal combination of tools based on their specific biological questions and the available computational resources to perform deep dives and thorough exploration of their RNA-Seq data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p>
    <p id="Par32">DEA is often combined with gene ontology (GO) analysis, pathway analysis, and clustering algorithms to characterize data and elucidate the processes and dynamics involved in transcription [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. These studies give new insights into gene regulatory networks and expression. Gene enrichment analysis is a standard GO approach to evaluate upregulated pathways and processes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Dimensionality reduction methods, such as multidimensional scaling (MDS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>], principal component analysis (PCA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], and t-distributed stochastic neighbor embedding (t-SNE) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], are used to identify RNA-Seq libraries with similar gene expression profiles. Moreover, while many other sophisticated RNA-Seq technologies exist, such as isoform analyses, single-cell RNA-Seq, and spatially resolved RNA-Seq methods, bulk RNA-Seq remains a powerful tool that continues to shape our understanding of biology.</p>
    <p id="Par33">The availability of RNA sequencing datasets is becoming more common due to increased support of open data by academicians and requirements by scientific journals and funding agencies to make publication-affiliated datasets publicly available. This has gifted the scientific community with an extensive repository of datasets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] derived from cell lines, animal models, and patient-derived samples of a wide variety of tissues and diseases. Researchers can explore these datasets of interest to generate or test hypotheses. However, even standard DEA and GO analyses often requires a bioinformatician or a computationally savvy biologist.</p>
    <p id="Par34">User-friendly tools for RNA-Seq analyses will allow biomedical scientists with limited programming experience to explore these datasets. Here we present <underline>R</underline>NA-Seq <underline>O</underline>ntology <underline>G</underline>raphic <underline>U</underline>ser <underline>E</underline>nvironment (ROGUE), an R Shiny application that allows biologists to perform differentially expressed gene analysis, gene ontology and pathway enrichment analysis, potential biomarker identification, and advanced statistical analyses. We demonstrate the capability of ROGUE by exploring the basic differences between CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, and natural killer (NK) cells. Furthermore, we show how ROGUE can be used to identify biomarkers and differentially enriched pathways present in similar immune cells in different diseases.</p>
    <p id="Par35">We propose that ROGUE will allow scientists to explore their datasets and also compare their findings with publicly available datasets, increasing the potential of data-driven biomedical discovery.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec2">
    <title>Methods</title>
    <sec id="Sec3">
      <title>Workflow</title>
      <p id="Par36">ROGUE is an R Shiny web app with a graphic user interface (GUI) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A) that takes expression data as input such as raw read counts, length-normalized counts, expression units including fragments per kilobase of transcript per million mapped reads (FPKM), reads per kilobase of transcript per million mapped reads (RPKM), and transcripts per million (TPM). Users can generate their own RNA-Seq matrix or download publicly available RNA-Seq expression data from databases such as gene expression omnibus (GEO) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], ArrayExpress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], The genotype tissue expression (GTEx) Project [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], and the cancer genome atlas (TCGA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. An online manual is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://marisshiny.research.chop.edu/ROGUE/Instructions.pdf">https://marisshiny.research.chop.edu/ROGUE/Instructions.pdf</ext-link>. When the input is raw read counts or length-normalized counts quantified by packages such as HT-seq [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] or RSEM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], ROGUE generates RPKM tables and can perform DEA using edgeR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] or DESeq2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] which are two of the state-of-the-art R packages for DEA analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] and has been shown to outperform other methods in various applications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. ROGUE also allows users to perform more advanced analyses such as biomarker discovery based on gene expression, dimensionality reduction, gene set enrichment analysis, and gene ontology analysis (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p><bold>A</bold> ROGUE R Shiny app graphic user interface. <bold>B</bold> ROGUE workflow. ROGUE takes raw read counts, normalized counts, or quantified expression values (RPKM, FPKM, TPM) as input. The user can quickly look at the clustering of all samples based on the expression values of all genes, perform differential expression analysis, and compare genes between samples or groups. ROGUE also includes statistical tools for gene set enrichment analysis (GSEA), gene ontology (GO) analysis, biomarker discovery, and dimensionality reduction by t-SNE, PCA, or UMAP</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2023_5420_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
      <p id="Par37">Gene expression comparison between samples and groups can be visualized with heatmaps, bar plots, and boxplots. Users can also use ROGUE to predict possible biomarkers by ranking genes with maximized fold change and minimized coefficients of variation in gene expression between groups of samples. The Welch’s t-test and the Wilcoxon Rank Sum Test can also be used to rank genes by their difference in expression distribution between the groups using the Biomarker Discovery Tool.</p>
      <p id="Par38">Gene set enrichment analysis (GSEA) is a computational method that determines whether a pre-ranked (i.e., log fold change) gene list shows statistically significant, concordant differences between two biological states (e.g., CD4<sup>+</sup> vs. CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells). GSEA between individual samples or groups can be performed using the Fast Gene Set Enrichment Analysis (fgsea) R package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>] with data imported from the Molecular Signatures Database (MSigDB) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Alternatively, gene ontology analysis on a list of differentially expressed genes can be performed using the Gene Ontology Resource [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], which is imported into ROGUE. Furthermore, ROGUE can determine differentially expressed gene sets using the Gene Ontology Resource. This resource uses the Wilcoxon rank sum test to determine if the expression of all genes within a biological process or molecular function are statistically different between samples or groups.</p>
      <p id="Par39">Dimensionality reduction methods can be applied to the datasets and visualized using 2-dimensional and 3-dimensional plots. ROGUE performs PCA using the ‘prcomp’ R function, t-SNE using the ‘Rtsne’ R package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], and Uniform Manifold Approximation and Projection (UMAP) method for dimensionality reduction using the ‘uwot’ R package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>].</p>
      <p id="Par40">The source code for ROGUE is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/afarrel/ROGUE">https://github.com/afarrel/ROGUE</ext-link>. All packages and implementation of the tools are described at this repository.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4">
      <title>Datasets</title>
      <p id="Par41">We performed basic analyses on datasets GSE60424 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], GSE102317 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], and GSE40350 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>] and GSE101470 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>] from the GEO Database to illustrate the basic features of ROGUE. Human CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, NK cells, neutrophils, and monocytes from healthy subjects and subjects diagnosed with type 1 diabetes, amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, sepsis, and multiple sclerosis were retrieved from GSE60424. RNA-Seq data from mouse CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells and NK cells were retrieved from GSE102317, GSE40350, and GSE101470, respectively, for additional analyses. Dataset GSE102317 contains RNA-Seq data from CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells treated with IL-2 and IL-21 for 0 (control), 2, 4, and 24 h. Dataset GSE40350 contains CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells treated with IL-2 and IL-15 for 0 (control), 4, and 24 h. Dataset GSE101470 includes RNA-Seq from mature CD11b<sup>−</sup>/CD27<sup>−</sup>, CD11b<sup>−</sup>/CD27<sup>+</sup>, CD11b<sup>+</sup>/CD27<sup>+</sup>, and CD11b<sup>+</sup>/CD27<sup>low</sup> NK cells as well as <italic>Stat5</italic> double knock-in mice with N-terminal mutations in STAT5A and STAT5B that prevent STAT5 tetramerization but not dimerization.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec5">
    <title>Results and discussion</title>
    <sec id="Sec6">
      <title>Workflow</title>
      <p id="Par42">We demonstrate the capability of ROGUE by exploring some basic differences between CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, and natural killer (NK) cells in datasets downloaded from the GEO Database. First, we performed DEA using edgeR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] and compared the expression of genes of interest between cell types. We then performed GSEA, GO analysis, and biomarker discovery based on gene expression to understand functional differences between the cells and discover possible biomarkers. We used ROGUE to perform dimensionality reduction by t-SNE to evaluate if the transcriptome of these cells were distinct enough to cluster each sample by cell type. Finally, we searched for differentially expressed gene sets from the GO Resource to evaluate changes in pathways pre and post-interferon beta (IFNβ) treatment in immune cells from patients with multiple sclerosis (MS).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec7">
      <title>Basic DEA and GO analysis</title>
      <p id="Par43">To illustrate the basic features of ROGUE, we first performed DEA on CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells versus CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells from healthy humans in dataset GSE60424 using edgeR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] and generated a volcano plot showing the differentially expressed genes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A). We next performed GSEA using the ‘fgsea’ R package to identify enriched gene signatures from the differentially expressed genes between CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells and CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells from healthy humans (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B, C, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). For this illustration, we expect to see gene sets with enhanced expression in experiments with stimulated CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells or with lower expression in CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells to be enriched in our CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells RNA-Seq libraries and lower in our CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell libraries. Interestingly, the most enriched gene set for CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells when compared to CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells was a set (GSE45739) of genes downregulated in CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells with <italic>Nras</italic> knockout (KO) mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B). While CD4<sup>+</sup> thymocyte differentiation is not affected in <italic>Nras</italic> KO mice, CD8<sup>+</sup> thymocyte differentiation has been shown to be significantly reduced [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Not surprisingly, the most enriched gene set for CD4<sup>+</sup> human T cells, was a set (GSE22886) of genes downregulated in naïve CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells when compared to CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>C). A heatmap was used to display the distinct expression patterns of the differentially expressed genes between CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells from the four healthy donors in the dataset (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>D). Basic GO analysis of genes upregulated in CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells showed enrichment in genes related to immune effector process, immune response, and leukocyte activation (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>E). We next used the gene ontology comparison tool to evaluate which type of T cell expresses more genes related to the T cell receptor (TCR) complex. This analysis interestingly revealed that the TCR complex was more enriched in the CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells as they expressed more genes at greater RPKM than the CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>F).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Basic analysis of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells versus CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells in healthy individuals. <bold>A</bold> Volcano plot showing differentially expressed genes. <bold>B</bold> GSEA showing the most enriched gene set when CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells were compared to CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells. <bold>C</bold> GSEA shows that the gene set downregulated in naive CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells when compared to naive CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells followed the same pattern in the current dataset. <bold>D</bold> Heatmap showing top differentially expressed genes between CD8<sup>+</sup> and CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells. <bold>E</bold> Gene ontologies of genes upregulated in CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells. <bold>F</bold> Distribution of expressed genes related to the T cell receptor complex</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2023_5420_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec8">
      <title>Biomarker discovery</title>
      <p id="Par44">Biomarker discovery is essential in biomedical and pharmaceutical research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Although mRNA is not always translated into protein, one can infer potential biomarkers from RNA-Seq data. ROGUE uses an optional combination of the coefficient of variation (CV), Wilcoxon-ranked sum test, or t-test for biomarker discovery between RNA-Seq library groups. ROGUE was used to identify potential biomarkers between CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, and NK cells using the Biomarker Discovery tool (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A), and a subset of these potential biomarkers was compared across the various cell types using a heatmap (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B). The expression values of the potential biomarkers were used to perform t-SNE on all the RNA-Seq libraries. A 2-dimensional plot of the t-SNE results shows that RNA-Seq libraries from CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, and NK cells from healthy controls clustered reasonably well based on the potential biomarkers discovered (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>C). Clusters were not as distinct when t-SNE was performed on T and NK cell libraries from both healthy controls and patients in 2 dimensions (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>D), but the clusters in a 3-dimensional plot generated by t-SNE were more homogeneous (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>E). We evaluated the occurrence of these biomarkers in mouse immune cells and observed that only a few of the biomarkers can be used across all datasets in both species (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: A–B). As expected, CD4 and CTLA4 were identified as potential biomarkers for differentiating CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells from CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells and NK cells across both datasets while CD8A and CD8B were identified as potential biomarkers for CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells. Gene expression of the potential human NK cell biomarkers were enriched in mouse NK cells that expressed CD27 (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: C–D). t-SNE was performed on the mouse datasets using the gene expressions of the potential biomarkers. The enrichment of the potential human NK cell biomarkers in mouse CD27<sup>+</sup> NK cells was reflected in the t-SNE plot as they formed a distinct cluster from the other NK cells (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: E). It is worth noting that even though the mouse immune cells cluster well using the biomarkers ascertained from the human immune cells, it is possible that the immune cells cluster well due to a batch effect instead of gene expression signature (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: F).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Biomarker Discovery among CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, and NK cells. <bold>A</bold> The Biomarker tool shows genes with high expression in one cell type and very low expression in the other cell types, suggesting that they may be potential biomarkers. <bold>B</bold> Heatmap showing relative expression values of the potential biomarkers’ gene expression for CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cell, and NK cell groups. <bold>C</bold> 2-dimensional t-SNE plot of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, and NK cells from healthy controls using the identified potential biomarkers. <bold>D</bold> 2-dimensional t-SNE plot of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, and NK cells from both healthy and diseased groups using the identified potential biomarkers. <bold>E</bold> 3-dimensional t-SNE plot using the identified potential biomarkers emphasizes separation between clusters</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2023_5420_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec9">
      <title>Comparison of biological pathways after treating multiple sclerosis patients with IFNβ</title>
      <p id="Par45">Dataset GSE60424 contains RNA-Seq data from CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, NK cells, neutrophils, and monocytes of MS patients before and after IFNβ treatment. MS is an inflammatory demyelinating disease of the central nervous system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. IFNβ treatment is a safe and reasonably effective treatment for MS patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>] due to its anti-inflammatory and immunomodulatory effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. While this is a widely-used treatment, the precise mechanism is unknown. To identify potential hypotheses of the mechanism downstream of IFNβ treatment, we used ROGUE to identify differentially expressed biological processes in CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, and NK cells isolated from patients pre- or post-treatment with IFNβ. CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells showed upregulation of the MDA-5 signaling pathway, among other biological processes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>). CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells and NK cells showed upregulation of 2′–5′-oligoadenylate synthetase activity (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>B, C). Given that the MDA-5 signaling pathway and 2′–5′-oligoadenylate synthetase activity are both involved in interferon signaling in innate immunity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>], and both pathways were upregulated in CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, and NK cells (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: A), we examined the differentially expressed biological processes in neutrophils and monocytes. As expected, we observed an increase in pathways related to interferon production, protein secretion, as well as positive regulation of MDA-5 pathway (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>D and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: B). This led us to examine the expression of genes related to MDA-5 and 2′–5′-oligoadenylate synthetase in all five cell types pre- and post-treatment, as this might give insights into the underlying mechanism. Furthermore, there is at least one report that polymorphisms in MDA-5 (IFIH1) are associated with MS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>], although another report states that this association does not exist in a specific French population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. Nevertheless, the MDA-5 signaling pathway and 2′–5′-oligoadenylate synthetase activity were upregulated in all five cell types (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>E). We then confirmed that both MDA-5 and RIG-I (DDX58) are upregulated in MS patients’ immune cells following treatment with IFNβ, as they are involved in the induction of IRF7 expression and constitutively-expressed IRF3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>] (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: C). A well-defined mechanism of interferon-stimulated gene (ISG) expression is that IRF3 and IRF7 regulate the expression of type 1 interferons, which then induce ISGs through JAK-STAT signaling, including OAS1A and OAS1B [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. However, IFNα and IFNβ mRNAs are not expressed, which suggests that administered IFNβ rather than endogenously produced IFNβ induces ISGs through the JAK-STAT pathway. This model is consistent with our data, as ISGs were upregulated in all five cell types after IFNβ-treatment with significantly greater expression of MDA-5, RIG-1 and ISGs observed in neutrophils (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>E and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: C). Given that 2′–5′-oligoadenylate synthetase can induce apoptosis in tumors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>], perhaps this alternative role of 2′–5′-oligoadenylate synthetase also occurs in immune cells, giving it a pro-inflammatory role as well as an anti-inflammatory role by promoting apoptosis and regulating cell growth and proliferation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. Furthermore, the disproportionate upregulation of genes with pro-apoptotic and antiproliferative roles in neutrophils supports Hasselbalch and Søndergaard’s report of a higher neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio, which is a marker of systemic inflammation, before treatment with IFNβ when compared to controls by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. Moreover, Pierson et al. demonstrated that depleting neutrophils in the MS animal model reduces the progression of the disease and Naegel et al. showed evidence that the increase in neutrophils in relapsing–remitting MS is likely due to decreased apoptosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. If this potential pro-apoptotic anti-inflammatory role of 2′–5′-oligoadenylate synthetase exists, it could be the mechanism by which IFNβ treatment positively impacts MS patients. In addition to 2′–5′-oligoadenylate synthetase activity, IFNβ may be involved in another pathway that explains the MDA-5/RIG-1 upregulation. Shimoni et al. suggested that IFNβ can bind cell surface receptors and promote the induction of RIG-1 as part of a positive feedback loop [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. Wang et al. further showed that RIG-1 and MDA5 signaling induces tumor necrosis factor (TNF) in macrophages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>], and TNF has been shown to have anti-inflammatory effects in MS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. The anti-inflammatory effects of TNF coupled with the pro-apoptotic role of 2′–5′-oligoadenylate synthetase may be part of the downstream mechanism contributing to the positive response induced by IFNβ in MS patients.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Using differentially expressed pathways to generate and/or explore hypotheses. <bold>A</bold> Distribution of MDA-5 signaling pathway in untreated (red) and IFNβ-treated (blue) CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells showing an upregulation of genes related to MDA-5 signaling. <bold>B</bold>, <bold>C</bold> Distribution of 2′–5′-oligoadenylate synthetase activity in untreated (red) and IFNβ-treated (blue) CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells (<bold>B</bold>) and NK cells (<bold>C</bold>) showing an upregulation of genes 2′–5′-oligoadenylate synthetase activity. <bold>D</bold> Boxplots showing pathways that may be differentially regulated in neutrophils with multiple genes consistently upregulated or downregulated post-IFNβ treatment. <bold>E</bold> Bar plot showing upregulated MDA-5 (IFIH1), RIG-I (DDX58), and genes related to 2′–5′-oligoadenylate synthetase in IFNβ-treated monocytes, neutrophils, CD4 + T cells, CD8 + T cells, and NK cells</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2023_5420_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec10">
    <title>Conclusion</title>
    <p id="Par46">ROGUE is designed to be a user-friendly R Shiny application that allows users to perform basic tasks with available RNA-Seq data such as differentially expressed gene analysis and gene ontology analysis. While other freely available web tools and portals have been developed to allow researchers to address discrete questions based on molecular and genomic datasets without the need for strong computational skills [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>], ROGUE allows deeper dataset exploration, allowing users to compare gene expression and gene set enrichments between samples and groups. For example, users can explore similarities of expression profiles using the dimensionality reduction methods such as t-SNE, PCA, UMAP, and MDS and search for potential biomarkers between groups of RNA-Seq libraries, to our knowledge making it the only currently available tool to allow this range of dataset analysis (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>). Furthermore, users have the option to download their session and continue their analysis at a later time. Users can also restore a session if the web application gets disconnected from the server. In addition to the case study presented here, we successfully tested ROGUE on ten diverse human and mouse case studies downloaded from Expression Atlas to illustrate the various applications and robustness (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>). It is worth noting that ROGUE is an R Shiny application thus allowing the inclusion of many statistical and graphical functions by the R community as well as the ability to be implemented on both local and web servers; however, like all R Shiny applications there are limitations. One of these limitations is that R Shiny applications that are implemented on web servers may perform slowly and sometimes disconnect from the server resulting in a subsequent crash when processing large datasets or performing computationally intensive functions. For this reason, we recommend downloading the local version of ROGUE from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/afarrel/ROGUE">https://github.com/afarrel/ROGUE</ext-link> when processing large datasets. Here, we show that a user can explore RNA-Seq data obtained from public databases and use ROGUE to analyze that data to generate or support new or existing hypotheses. ROGUE provides non-R programmers access to many statistical and graphical R packages for RNA-Seq analyses through a GUI so they can analyze their data and create figures. Ideally, tools like ROGUE will allow more biomedical researchers to take advantage of genomic data available and help expedite needed bioinformatics analyses. ROGUE is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://marisshiny.research.chop.edu/ROGUE/">https://marisshiny.research.chop.edu/ROGUE/</ext-link>.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec900">
    <title>Availability and requirements</title>
    <p id="Par47">Project Name: ROGUE.</p>
    <p id="Par48">Project Home Page: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://marisshiny.research.chop.edu/ROGUE/">https://marisshiny.research.chop.edu/ROGUE/</ext-link>.</p>
    <p id="Par49">Github: https://github.com/afarrel/ROGUE.</p>
    <p id="Par50">Operating System: Platform independent.</p>
    <p id="Par51">Programming language: R.</p>
    <p id="Par52">Other requirements: R environment and included packages. Tested on R version 3.6.</p>
    <p id="Par53">Any restrictions to use by non-academics: none.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Information</title>
    <sec id="Sec11">
      <p>
        <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1">
          <media xlink:href="12859_2023_5420_MOESM1_ESM.pdf">
            <caption>
              <p><bold>Additional file 1: </bold>GSEA analysis of healthy human CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells vs CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells.</p>
            </caption>
          </media>
        </supplementary-material>
        <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2">
          <media xlink:href="12859_2023_5420_MOESM2_ESM.pdf">
            <caption>
              <p><bold>Additional file 2:</bold> Evaluating biomarkers found in human CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, and NK cells in mouse immune cells from different datasets.</p>
            </caption>
          </media>
        </supplementary-material>
        <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3">
          <media xlink:href="12859_2023_5420_MOESM3_ESM.pdf">
            <caption>
              <p><bold>Additional file 3:</bold> Distribution of gene expression profiles in the differentially expressed pathways.</p>
            </caption>
          </media>
        </supplementary-material>
        <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4">
          <media xlink:href="12859_2023_5420_MOESM4_ESM.pdf">
            <caption>
              <p><bold>Additional file 4:</bold> Evaluation of MD5A-signaling, RIG-1 signaling, and 2'-5'-oligoadenylate synthetase pre- and post-IFNβ treatment.</p>
            </caption>
          </media>
        </supplementary-material>
        <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5">
          <media xlink:href="12859_2023_5420_MOESM5_ESM.xlsx">
            <caption>
              <p><bold>Additional file 5:</bold> Available Rshiny RNAseq analysis tools.</p>
            </caption>
          </media>
        </supplementary-material>
        <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6">
          <media xlink:href="12859_2023_5420_MOESM6_ESM.docx">
            <caption>
              <p><bold>Additional file 6:</bold> List of case studies.</p>
            </caption>
          </media>
        </supplementary-material>
      </p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <glossary>
    <title>Abbreviations</title>
    <def-list>
      <def-item>
        <term>CV</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par4">Coefficient of variation</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>DEA</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par5">Differential expression analysis</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>FGSEA</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par6">Fast gene set enrichment analysis</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>FPKM</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par7">Fragments per kilobase of transcript per million mapped reads</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>GEO</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par8">Gene expression omnibus</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>GO</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par9">Gene ontology</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>GSEA</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par10">Gene set enrichment analysis</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>GTEx</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par11">The genotype tissue expression</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>GUI</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par12">Graphic user interface</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>IFNα</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par13">Interferon alpha</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>IFNβ</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par14">Interferon beta</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>ISG</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par15">Interferon-stimulated gene</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>MDS</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par16">Multidimensional scaling</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>MSigDB</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par17">Molecular signatures database</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>MS</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par18">Multiple sclerosis</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>NK</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par19">Natural killer</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>PCA</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par20">Principal component analysis</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>RNA-Seq</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par21">RNA sequencing</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>ROGUE</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par22">RNA-Seq ontology graphic user environment</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>RPKM</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par23">Reads per kilobase of transcript per million mapped reads</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>TCGA</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par24">The cancer genome atlas</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>TCR</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par25">T cell receptor</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>TNF</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par26">Tumor necrosis factor</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>TPM</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par27">Transcripts per million</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>t-SNE</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par28">T-distributed stochastic neighbor embedding</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>UMAP</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par29">Uniform manifold approximation and projection</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
    </def-list>
  </glossary>
  <fn-group>
    <fn>
      <p>
        <bold>Publisher's Note</bold>
      </p>
      <p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
    </fn>
  </fn-group>
  <ack>
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <p>We thank Jian-Xin Lin for discussions and suggestions in reviewing the application and the manuscript. We are grateful to Grace Coggins and Laura Scolaro for using this application in their research and suggesting changes to increase usability.</p>
  </ack>
  <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
    <title>Author contributions</title>
    <p>Conceptualization, AF; Methodology, AF, PL, and SV; Software, AF, PL and KP; Formal Analysis, AF; Funding Acquisition, WJL and JMM; Writing, AF, PL, SV, JMM and WJL; Supervision, AF and WJL. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
  </notes>
  <notes notes-type="funding-information">
    <title>Funding</title>
    <p>This work was supported by the Division of Intramural Research, National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, NIH, and NIH grants R35 CA220500, P01 CA217959 and U54 CA232568 (JMM).</p>
  </notes>
  <notes notes-type="data-availability">
    <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
    <p>RNA sequencing expression data from human immune cells: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE60424">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE60424</ext-link>. RNA sequencing expression data from mouse immune cells: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE102317">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE102317</ext-link>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE40350">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE40350</ext-link>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE101470">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE101470</ext-link></p>
  </notes>
  <notes>
    <title>Declarations</title>
    <notes id="FPar1">
      <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
      <p id="Par54">Not applicable.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes id="FPar2">
      <title>Consent for publication</title>
      <p id="Par55">Not applicable.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p id="Par56">The authors declare that they have no competing interest.</p>
    </notes>
  </notes>
  <ref-list id="Bib1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="CR1">
      <label>1.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Garalde</surname>
            <given-names>DR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Snell</surname>
            <given-names>EA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jachimowicz</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sipos</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lloyd</surname>
            <given-names>JH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bruce</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Highly parallel direct RNA sequencing on an array of nanopores</article-title>
        <source>Nat Methods</source>
        <year>2018</year>
        <volume>15</volume>
        <fpage>201</fpage>
        <lpage>206</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.4577</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 29334379?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29334379</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR2">
      <label>2.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Smith</surname>
            <given-names>AM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jain</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mulroney</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Garalde</surname>
            <given-names>DR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Akeson</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Reading canonical and modified nucleobases in 16S ribosomal RNA using nanopore native RNA sequencing</article-title>
        <source>PLoS ONE</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>14</volume>
        <fpage>e0216709</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0216709</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 31095620?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31095620</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR3">
      <label>3.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Byrne</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Beaudin</surname>
            <given-names>AE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Olsen</surname>
            <given-names>HE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jain</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cole</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Palmer</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Nanopore long-read RNAseq reveals widespread transcriptional variation among the surface receptors of individual B cells</article-title>
        <source>Nat Commun</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <fpage>16027</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms16027</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 28722025?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28722025</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR4">
      <label>4.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Trapnell</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Williams</surname>
            <given-names>BA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pertea</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mortazavi</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kwan</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>van Baren</surname>
            <given-names>MJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Transcript assembly and quantification by RNA-Seq reveals unannotated transcripts and isoform switching during cell differentiation</article-title>
        <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>28</volume>
        <fpage>511</fpage>
        <lpage>515</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.1621</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 20436464?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20436464</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR5">
      <label>5.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pertea</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pertea</surname>
            <given-names>GM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Leek</surname>
            <given-names>JT</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Salzberg</surname>
            <given-names>SL</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Transcript-level expression analysis of RNA-seq experiments with HISAT</article-title>
        <source>StringTie and Ballgown Nat Protoc</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <fpage>1650</fpage>
        <lpage>1667</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2016.095</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 27560171?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27560171</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR6">
      <label>6.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bray</surname>
            <given-names>NL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pimentel</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Melsted</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pachter</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Near-optimal probabilistic RNA-seq quantification</article-title>
        <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>34</volume>
        <fpage>525</fpage>
        <lpage>527</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.3519</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 27043002?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27043002</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR7">
      <label>7.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sahraeian</surname>
            <given-names>SME</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mohiyuddin</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sebra</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tilgner</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Afshar</surname>
            <given-names>PT</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Au</surname>
            <given-names>KF</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Gaining comprehensive biological insight into the transcriptome by performing a broad-spectrum RNA-seq analysis</article-title>
        <source>Nat Commun</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <fpage>59</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-017-00050-4</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 28680106?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28680106</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR8">
      <label>8.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dewey</surname>
            <given-names>CN</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>RSEM: accurate transcript quantification from RNA-Seq data with or without a reference genome</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinform</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <fpage>323</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-12-323</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR9">
      <label>9.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Trapnell</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Roberts</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Goff</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pertea</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kelley</surname>
            <given-names>DR</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Differential gene and transcript expression analysis of RNA-seq experiments with TopHat and Cufflinks</article-title>
        <source>Nat Protoc</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <fpage>562</fpage>
        <lpage>578</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2012.016</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 22383036?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22383036</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR10">
      <label>10.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Robinson</surname>
            <given-names>MD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McCarthy</surname>
            <given-names>DJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Smyth</surname>
            <given-names>GK</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>edgeR: a bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data</article-title>
        <source>Bioinform Oxf Engl</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>26</volume>
        <fpage>139</fpage>
        <lpage>140</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR11">
      <label>11.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Love</surname>
            <given-names>MI</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huber</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Anders</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA-seq data with DESeq2</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>15</volume>
        <fpage>550</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-014-0550-8</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25516281?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25516281</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR12">
      <label>12.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Law</surname>
            <given-names>CW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shi</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Smyth</surname>
            <given-names>GK</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>voom: precision weights unlock linear model analysis tools for RNA-seq read counts</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>15</volume>
        <fpage>R29</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2014-15-2-r29</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24485249?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24485249</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR13">
      <label>13.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Costa-Silva</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Domingues</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lopes</surname>
            <given-names>FM</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>RNA-Seq differential expression analysis: An extended review and a software tool</article-title>
        <source>PLoS ONE</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <fpage>e0190152</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0190152</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 29267363?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29267363</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR14">
      <label>14.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Conesa</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Madrigal</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tarazona</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gomez-Cabrero</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cervera</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McPherson</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A survey of best practices for RNA-seq data analysis</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>17</volume>
        <fpage>13</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-016-0881-8</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 26813401?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26813401</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR15">
      <label>15.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Seyednasrollah</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Laiho</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Elo</surname>
            <given-names>LL</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Comparison of software packages for detecting differential expression in RNA-seq studies</article-title>
        <source>Brief Bioinform</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>16</volume>
        <fpage>59</fpage>
        <lpage>70</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bib/bbt086</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24300110?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24300110</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR16">
      <label>16.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Williams</surname>
            <given-names>CR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Baccarella</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Parrish</surname>
            <given-names>JZ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>CC</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Empirical assessment of analysis workflows for differential expression analysis of human samples using RNA-Seq</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinform</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>18</volume>
        <fpage>38</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-016-1457-z</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR17">
      <label>17.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ashburner</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ball</surname>
            <given-names>CA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Blake</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Botstein</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Butler</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cherry</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Gene ontology: tool for the unification of biology. The Gene Ontology Consortium</article-title>
        <source>Nat Genet</source>
        <year>2000</year>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <fpage>25</fpage>
        <lpage>29</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/75556</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 10802651?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10802651</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR18">
      <label>18.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Subramanian</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tamayo</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mootha</surname>
            <given-names>VK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mukherjee</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ebert</surname>
            <given-names>BL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gillette</surname>
            <given-names>MA</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Gene set enrichment analysis: a knowledge-based approach for interpreting genome-wide expression profiles</article-title>
        <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
        <year>2005</year>
        <volume>102</volume>
        <fpage>15545</fpage>
        <lpage>15550</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0506580102</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 16199517?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16199517</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR19">
      <label>19.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mi</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Muruganujan</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ebert</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Thomas</surname>
            <given-names>PD</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>PANTHER version 14: more genomes, a new PANTHER GO-slim and improvements in enrichment analysis tools</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>47</volume>
        <fpage>D419</fpage>
        <lpage>D426</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gky1038</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 30407594?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30407594</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR20">
      <label>20.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Carbon</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ireland</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mungall</surname>
            <given-names>CJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shu</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Marshall</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lewis</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>AmiGO: online access to ontology and annotation data</article-title>
        <source>Bioinforma Oxf Engl</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <fpage>288</fpage>
        <lpage>289</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btn615</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR21">
      <label>21.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Loraine</surname>
            <given-names>AE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Blakley</surname>
            <given-names>IC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jagadeesan</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Harper</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Miller</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Firon</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Analysis and visualization of RNA-Seq expression data using RStudio, bioconductor, and integrated genome browser</article-title>
        <source>Methods Mol Biol Clifton NJ</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>1284</volume>
        <fpage>481</fpage>
        <lpage>501</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4939-2444-8_24</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR22">
      <label>22.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jolliffe</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <person-group person-group-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Lovric</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Principal component analysis</article-title>
        <source>International encyclopedia of statistical science</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>
        <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
        <fpage>1094</fpage>
        <lpage>1096</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR23">
      <label>23.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jolliffe I. Principal component analysis. In: Wiley StatsRef: Statistics Reference Online. American Cancer Society; 2014. 10.1002/9781118445112.stat06472.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR24">
      <label>24.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>van der Maaten</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hinton</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Visualizing data using t-SNE</article-title>
        <source>J Mach Learn Res</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <fpage>2579</fpage>
        <lpage>2605</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR25">
      <label>25.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Edgar</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Domrachev</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lash</surname>
            <given-names>AE</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Gene Expression Omnibus: NCBI gene expression and hybridization array data repository</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
        <year>2002</year>
        <volume>30</volume>
        <fpage>207</fpage>
        <lpage>210</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/30.1.207</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 11752295?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11752295</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR26">
      <label>26.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Athar</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Füllgrabe</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>George</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Iqbal</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huerta</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ali</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>ArrayExpress update—from bulk to single-cell expression data</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>47</volume>
        <fpage>D711</fpage>
        <lpage>D715</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gky964</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 30357387?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30357387</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR27">
      <label>27.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Carithers</surname>
            <given-names>LJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ardlie</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Barcus</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Branton</surname>
            <given-names>PA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Britton</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Buia</surname>
            <given-names>SA</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A novel approach to high-quality postmortem tissue procurement: the GTEx project</article-title>
        <source>Biopreserv Biobank</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>13</volume>
        <fpage>311</fpage>
        <lpage>319</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/bio.2015.0032</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 26484571?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26484571</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR28">
      <label>28.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">The Cancer Genome Atlas Research Network, Weinstein JN, Collisson EA, Mills GB, Shaw KRM, Ozenberger BA, et al. The Cancer Genome Atlas Pan-Cancer analysis project. Nat Genet. 2013;45:1113–20.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR29">
      <label>29.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Anders</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pyl</surname>
            <given-names>PT</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huber</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>HTSeq—a Python framework to work with high-throughput sequencing data</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>31</volume>
        <fpage>166</fpage>
        <lpage>169</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu638</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25260700?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25260700</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR30">
      <label>30.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Schurch</surname>
            <given-names>NJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schofield</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gierliński</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cole</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sherstnev</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Singh</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>How many biological replicates are needed in an RNA-seq experiment and which differential expression tool should you use?</article-title>
        <source>RNA N Y N</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>22</volume>
        <fpage>839</fpage>
        <lpage>851</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1261/rna.053959.115</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR31">
      <label>31.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Assefa</surname>
            <given-names>AT</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>De Paepe</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Everaert</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mestdagh</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Thas</surname>
            <given-names>O</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vandesompele</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Differential gene expression analysis tools exhibit substandard performance for long non-coding RNA-sequencing data</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol</source>
        <year>2018</year>
        <volume>19</volume>
        <fpage>96</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-018-1466-5</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 30041657?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30041657</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR32">
      <label>32.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Korotkevich G, Sukhov V, Budin N, Shpak B, Artyomov MN, Sergushichev A. Fast gene set enrichment analysis. bioRxiv. 2021; 060012.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR33">
      <label>33.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liberzon</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Subramanian</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pinchback</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Thorvaldsdóttir</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tamayo</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mesirov</surname>
            <given-names>JP</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Molecular signatures database (MSigDB) 3.0</article-title>
        <source>Bioinform Oxf Engl</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>27</volume>
        <fpage>1739</fpage>
        <lpage>1740</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr260</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR34">
      <label>34.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <collab>Gene Ontology Consortium</collab>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The Gene Ontology resource: enriching a GOld mine</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <year>2021</year>
        <volume>49</volume>
        <fpage>D325</fpage>
        <lpage>D334</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkaa1113</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33290552</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR35">
      <label>35.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Krijthe JH. Rtsne: T-Distributed stochastic neighbor embedding using Barnes–Hut implementation. 2015. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/jkrijthe/Rtsne">https://github.com/jkrijthe/Rtsne</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR36">
      <label>36.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Melville J. uwot: the uniform manifold approximation and projection (UMAP) method for dimensionality reduction. 2020. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=uwot">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=uwot</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR37">
      <label>37.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">McInnes L, Healy J, Melville J. UMAP: uniform manifold approximation and projection for dimension reduction. 2020.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR38">
      <label>38.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Becht</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McInnes</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Healy</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dutertre</surname>
            <given-names>C-A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kwok</surname>
            <given-names>IWH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ng</surname>
            <given-names>LG</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Dimensionality reduction for visualizing single-cell data using UMAP</article-title>
        <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
        <year>2018</year>
        <volume>37</volume>
        <fpage>38</fpage>
        <lpage>44</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.4314</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR39">
      <label>39.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Linsley</surname>
            <given-names>PS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Speake</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Whalen</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chaussabel</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Copy number loss of the interferon gene cluster in melanomas is linked to reduced T cell infiltrate and poor patient prognosis</article-title>
        <source>PLoS ONE</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <fpage>e109760</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0109760</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25314013?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25314013</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR40">
      <label>40.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mitra</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Spolski</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Oh</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liao</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tang</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>STAT5-mediated chromatin interactions in superenhancers activate IL-2 highly inducible genes: Functional dissection of the Il2ra gene locus</article-title>
        <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>114</volume>
        <fpage>12111</fpage>
        <lpage>12119</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1714019114</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 29078395?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29078395</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR41">
      <label>41.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>J-X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Du</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kazemian</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gebregiorgis</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Spolski</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Critical functions for STAT5 tetramers in the maturation and survival of natural killer cells</article-title>
        <source>Nat Commun</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <fpage>1320</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-017-01477-5</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 29105654?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29105654</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR42">
      <label>42.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ring</surname>
            <given-names>AM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>J-X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Feng</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mitra</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rickert</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bowman</surname>
            <given-names>GR</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Mechanistic and structural insight into the functional dichotomy between IL-2 and IL-15</article-title>
        <source>Nat Immunol</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>13</volume>
        <fpage>1187</fpage>
        <lpage>1195</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni.2449</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 23104097?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23104097</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR43">
      <label>43.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pérez de Castro</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Diaz</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Malumbres</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hernández</surname>
            <given-names>M-I</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jagirdar</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jiménez</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Mice deficient for N-ras: impaired antiviral immune response and T-cell function</article-title>
        <source>Cancer Res</source>
        <year>2003</year>
        <volume>63</volume>
        <fpage>1615</fpage>
        <lpage>1622</lpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 12670913?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12670913</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR44">
      <label>44.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liotta</surname>
            <given-names>LA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ferrari</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Petricoin</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Clinical proteomics: written in blood</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <year>2003</year>
        <volume>425</volume>
        <fpage>905</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/425905a</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 14586448?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14586448</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR45">
      <label>45.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Goossens</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nakagawa</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hoshida</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Cancer biomarker discovery and validation</article-title>
        <source>Transl Cancer Res</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <fpage>256</fpage>
        <lpage>269</lpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 26213686?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26213686</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR46">
      <label>46.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Norouzinia</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chaleshi</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Alizadeh</surname>
            <given-names>AHM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zali</surname>
            <given-names>MR</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Biomarkers in inflammatory bowel diseases: insight into diagnosis, prognosis and treatment</article-title>
        <source>Gastroenterol Hepatol Bed Bench</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <fpage>155</fpage>
        <lpage>167</lpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 29118930?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29118930</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR47">
      <label>47.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wootla</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Eriguchi</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rodriguez</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Is multiple sclerosis an autoimmune disease?</article-title>
        <source>Autoimmune Dis</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>2012</volume>
        <fpage>969657</fpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 22666554?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22666554</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR48">
      <label>48.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jacobs</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Brownscheidle</surname>
            <given-names>CM</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Appropriate use of interferon beta-1a in multiple sclerosis</article-title>
        <source>BioDrugs</source>
        <year>1999</year>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <fpage>155</fpage>
        <lpage>163</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/00063030-199911030-00002</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 18031126?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18031126</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR49">
      <label>49.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Clerico</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Contessa</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Durelli</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Interferon-β1a for the treatment of multiple sclerosis</article-title>
        <source>Expert Opin Biol Ther</source>
        <year>2007</year>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <fpage>535</fpage>
        <lpage>542</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1517/14712598.7.4.535</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 17373904?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17373904</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR50">
      <label>50.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bertolotto</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gilli</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Interferon-beta responders and non-responders. A biological approach</article-title>
        <source>Neurol Sci Off J Ital Neurol Soc Ital Soc Clin Neurophysiol</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>29</volume>
        <issue>Suppl 2</issue>
        <fpage>S216</fpage>
        <lpage>217</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR51">
      <label>51.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Freedman</surname>
            <given-names>MS</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Long-term follow-up of clinical trials of multiple sclerosis therapies</article-title>
        <source>Neurology</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>76</volume>
        <issue>Supplement 1</issue>
        <fpage>S26</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0b013e318205051d</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 21205679?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21205679</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR52">
      <label>52.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kasper</surname>
            <given-names>LH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Reder</surname>
            <given-names>AT</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Immunomodulatory activity of interferon-beta</article-title>
        <source>Ann Clin Transl Neurol</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>1</volume>
        <fpage>622</fpage>
        <lpage>631</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/acn3.84</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25356432?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25356432</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR53">
      <label>53.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dhib-Jalbut</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Marks</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Interferon-β mechanisms of action in multiple sclerosis</article-title>
        <source>Neurology</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>74</volume>
        <issue>Supplement 1</issue>
        <fpage>S17</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0b013e3181c97d99</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 20038758?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20038758</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR54">
      <label>54.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Loo</surname>
            <given-names>Y-M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gale</surname>
            <given-names>MJ</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Immune signaling by RIG-I-like receptors</article-title>
        <source>Immunity</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>34</volume>
        <fpage>680</fpage>
        <lpage>692</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2011.05.003</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 21616437?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21616437</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR55">
      <label>55.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Qiu</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tang</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Long non-coding RNAs: regulators of viral infection and the interferon antiviral response</article-title>
        <source>Front Microbiol</source>
        <year>2018</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <fpage>1621</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.01621</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 30072977?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30072977</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR56">
      <label>56.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pulit-Penaloza</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Scherbik</surname>
            <given-names>SV</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Brinton</surname>
            <given-names>MA</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Type 1 IFN-independent activation of a subset of interferon stimulated genes in West Nile virus Eg101-infected mouse cells</article-title>
        <source>Virology</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>425</volume>
        <fpage>82</fpage>
        <lpage>94</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virol.2012.01.006</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 22305622?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22305622</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR57">
      <label>57.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Choi</surname>
            <given-names>UY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kang</surname>
            <given-names>J-S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hwang</surname>
            <given-names>YS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Y-J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Oligoadenylate synthase-like (OASL) proteins: dual functions and associations with diseases</article-title>
        <source>Exp Mol Med</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>47</volume>
        <fpage>e144</fpage>
        <lpage>e144</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/emm.2014.110</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25744296?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25744296</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR58">
      <label>58.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Martínez</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Santiago</surname>
            <given-names>JL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cénit</surname>
            <given-names>MC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>de Las</surname>
            <given-names>HV</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>de la Calle</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fernández-Arquero</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>IFIH1-GCA-KCNH7 locus: influence on multiple sclerosis risk</article-title>
        <source>Eur J Hum Genet EJHG</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>16</volume>
        <fpage>861</fpage>
        <lpage>864</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ejhg.2008.16</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 18285833?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18285833</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR59">
      <label>59.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Couturier</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gourraud</surname>
            <given-names>P-A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cournu-Rebeix</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gout</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bucciarelli</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Edan</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>IFIH1-GCA-KCNH7 locus is not associated with genetic susceptibility to multiple sclerosis in French patients</article-title>
        <source>Eur J Hum Genet EJHG</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>17</volume>
        <fpage>844</fpage>
        <lpage>847</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ejhg.2008.259</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 19156166?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19156166</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR60">
      <label>60.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Malathi</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dong</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gale</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
            <suffix>Jr</suffix>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Silverman</surname>
            <given-names>RH</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Small self-RNA generated by RNase L amplifies antiviral innate immunity</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <year>2007</year>
        <volume>448</volume>
        <fpage>816</fpage>
        <lpage>819</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature06042</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 17653195?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17653195</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR61">
      <label>61.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mullan</surname>
            <given-names>PB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hosey</surname>
            <given-names>AM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Buckley</surname>
            <given-names>NE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Quinn</surname>
            <given-names>JE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kennedy</surname>
            <given-names>RD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Johnston</surname>
            <given-names>PG</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The 2,5 oligoadenylate synthetase/RNaseL pathway is a novel effector of BRCA1- and interferon-γ-mediated apoptosis</article-title>
        <source>Oncogene</source>
        <year>2005</year>
        <volume>24</volume>
        <fpage>5492</fpage>
        <lpage>5501</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.onc.1208698</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 15940267?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15940267</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR62">
      <label>62.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hasselbalch</surname>
            <given-names>IC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Søndergaard</surname>
            <given-names>HB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Koch-Henriksen</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Olsson</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ullum</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sellebjerg</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio is associated with multiple sclerosis</article-title>
        <source>Mult Scler J Exp Transl Clin</source>
        <year>2018</year>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <fpage>2055217318813183</fpage>
        <lpage>2055217318813183</lpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 30515298?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30515298</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR63">
      <label>63.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pierson</surname>
            <given-names>ER</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wagner</surname>
            <given-names>CA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Goverman</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The contribution of neutrophils to CNS autoimmunity</article-title>
        <source>Clin Immunol Orlando Fla</source>
        <year>2018</year>
        <volume>189</volume>
        <fpage>23</fpage>
        <lpage>28</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clim.2016.06.017</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR64">
      <label>64.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Naegele</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tillack</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Reinhardt</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schippling</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Martin</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sospedra</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Neutrophils in multiple sclerosis are characterized by a primed phenotype</article-title>
        <source>J Neuroimmunol</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>242</volume>
        <fpage>60</fpage>
        <lpage>71</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jneuroim.2011.11.009</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 22169406?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22169406</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR65">
      <label>65.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shimoni</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nudelman</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hayot</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sealfon</surname>
            <given-names>SC</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Multi-scale stochastic simulation of diffusion-coupled agents and its application to cell culture simulation</article-title>
        <source>PLoS ONE</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <fpage>e29298</fpage>
        <lpage>e29298</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029298</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 22216238?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22216238</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR66">
      <label>66.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gao</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Barrett</surname>
            <given-names>JW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shao</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bartee</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mohamed</surname>
            <given-names>MR</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>RIG-I mediates the co-induction of tumor necrosis factor and type I interferon elicited by myxoma virus in primary human macrophages</article-title>
        <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <fpage>e1000099</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000099</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 18617992?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18617992</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR67">
      <label>67.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Marino</surname>
            <given-names>MW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wong</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Grail</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dunn</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bettadapura</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>TNF is a potent anti-inflammatory cytokine in autoimmune-mediated demyelination</article-title>
        <source>Nat Med</source>
        <year>1998</year>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <fpage>78</fpage>
        <lpage>83</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm0198-078</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 9427610?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9427610</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR68">
      <label>68.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sundararajan</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Knoll</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hombach</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Becker</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schultze</surname>
            <given-names>JL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ulas</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Shiny-Seq: advanced guided transcriptome analysis</article-title>
        <source>BMC Res Notes</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <fpage>432</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13104-019-4471-1</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 31319888?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31319888</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR69">
      <label>69.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Su</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shimizu</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kadota</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>TCC-GUI: a Shiny-based application for differential expression analysis of RNA-Seq count data</article-title>
        <source>BMC Res Notes</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <fpage>133</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13104-019-4179-2</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 30867032?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30867032</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
