<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.2 20060430//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 2.2?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
<front>
  <?epub May-8-2007?>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">nar</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">1933230</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17488836</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm305</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Articles</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>NTMG (N-terminal Truncated Mutants Generator for cDNA): an automatic multiplex PCR assays design for generating various N-terminal truncated cDNA mutants</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Chen</surname>
          <given-names>Yung-Fu</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">
          <sup>1</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Chen</surname>
          <given-names>Rung-Ching</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">
          <sup>2</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Tseng</surname>
          <given-names>Lin-Yu</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">
          <sup>3</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Lin</surname>
          <given-names>Elong</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">
          <sup>4</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Chan</surname>
          <given-names>Yung-Kuan</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">
          <sup>5</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Pan</surname>
          <given-names>Ren-Hao</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">
          <sup>3</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <aff id="AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Health Services Management, China Medical University, Taichung, Taiwan, ROC, <sup>2</sup>Department of Information Management, Chaoyang University of Technology, Taichung, Taiwan, ROC, <sup>3</sup>Department of Computer Science, National Chung Hsing University, Taichung, Taiwan, ROC, <sup>4</sup>Department of Food Science, Central Taiwan University of Science and Technology, Taichung, Taiwan, ROC and <sup>5</sup>Department of Management Information System, National Chung Hsing University, Taichung, Taiwan, ROC</aff>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. <phone>+886-4-22874020</phone><fax>+886-4-22853869</fax><email>lytseng@cs.nchu.edu.tw</email></corresp>
      <fn>
        <p>The authors wish it to be known that the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors</p>
      </fn>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2007</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>8</day>
      <month>5</month>
      <year>2007</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>8</day>
      <month>5</month>
      <year>2007</year>
    </pub-date>
    <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
						epub date downloaded from Highwire. -->
    <volume>35</volume>
    <issue>Web Server issue</issue>
    <fpage>W66</fpage>
    <lpage>W70</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>31</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>3</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© 2007 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2007</copyright-year>
      <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">
        <license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract>
      <p>The sequential deletion method is generally used to locate the functional domain of a protein. With this method, in order to find the various N-terminal truncated mutants, researchers have to investigate the ATG-like codons, to design various multiplex polymerase chain reaction (PCR) forward primers and to do several PCR experiments. This web server (N-terminal Truncated Mutants Generator for cDNA) will automatically generate groups of forward PCR primers and the corresponding reverse PCR primers that can be used in a single batch of a multiplex PCR experiment to extract the various N-terminal truncated mutants. This saves much time and money for those who use the sequential deletion method in their research. This server is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://oblab.cs.nchu.edu.tw:8080/WebSDL/">http://oblab.cs.nchu.edu.tw:8080/WebSDL/</ext-link>.</p>
    </abstract>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec>
    <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
    <p>The sequential deletion method and other biological and biochemical experiments are generally used to locate the functional domain of a protein. For example, a previous study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>) used the sequential deletion method accompanied by manual PCR primers design to generate the N-terminal truncated mutants of different lengths (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>), which in turn were used in further biological experiments to decipher the functional domain of the 5S RNA-protein complex (5S rRNP). The 5S rRNP is believed to be formed by a co-translation event leading to the binding of the 5S rRNA to the nascent ribosomal protein L5. The formation of 5S rRNP complex facilitates the nuclear entry of the protein L5. Lin <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>) used an in vitro translation system to investigate how and when 5S rRNA triggers the formation of the eukaryotic 5S rRNP. The L5 and truncated L5 mutant mRNAs were prepared on a large scale for their investigation and a great amount of time was needed to manually modify the in-frame pattern of ATG start codon for conventional PCR and truncated mutant translation experiments.
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>The illustration of the produced N-terminal truncated mutants.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm305f1"/></fig></p>
    <p>In order to save time and money needed in the traditional sequential deletion method, this web-based application system NTMG is proposed to automatically do the multiplex PCR assays design in order to generate the various N-terminal truncated mutants. Given a protein cDNA sequence, the NTMG will first find those ATG-like codons that are suitable to act as the starting positions of truncated mutants. Then, the NTMG will design the forward primers for all possible truncated mutants. Finally, with all these primers, the NTMG will choose those primers that can be divided into the least number of groups such that each group constitutes a multiplex PCR assay.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>SYSTEM</title>
    <p>In this section, we describe the input to the NTMG, the methodology of the NTMG and the output of the NTMG. Since the primer design and the multiplex PCR primer design are two important parts of the NTMG, some factors concerning the primer design such as the primer length and the melting temperature are input as parameters.</p>
    <p>There are also some factors that may affect the multiplex PCR amplification with multiple primers in the same tube (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). These factors include the cross-dimerization, the melting temperature, the products co-existence and others. All these factors are also input as parameters. Each input parameter has a default value but users may change that value. We first introduce the input parameters in the following subsection.</p>
    <sec>
      <title>Input Parameters</title>
      <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> gives the input screen of the NTMG. On the top of the screen, the cDNA sequence, the start codon address and the stop codon address are input. Then comes four classes of parameters:
<list list-type="roman-lower"><list-item><p>Primer Criteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4 B5 B6 B7">4–7</xref>)</p><p>These include the forward primer length (default 20–30 bp), the reverse primer length (default 14–28 bp) and the GC content (default 40-60%).</p></list-item><list-item><p>Temperature Criteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8 B9 B10">8–10</xref>)</p><p>These include melting temperature (default 51–60°C), the melting temperature range for each group (default 5°C), the molar concentration of monovalent cation (default 50 mmol/l), the molar concentration of Mg<sup>2+</sup> (default 1.25 mmol/l) and the dNTPs concentration (default 0.02 mmol/l).</p></list-item><list-item><p>Complementary Criteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10 B11 B12">10–12</xref>)</p><p>These include the terminal repeated sequence (default 3 bp), the intra self-complementary sequence (default 3 bp), the specificity (default 65%), the cross-dimer distance (default 10 bp), the cross-dimer – total similarity (default 50%) and the cross-dimer – terminal similarity (default 3 bp).</p></list-item><list-item><p>Grouping Criteria</p><p>These include the product length difference (default 80 bp) and the maximum number of primers in each group (default 16).</p></list-item></list>
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>The input screen of the NTMG.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm305f2"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Methodology</title>
      <p>The flowchart of the NTMG is depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>.
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>The flowchart of the NTMG.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm305f3"/></fig></p>
      <p>First, a cDNA sequence is input, then the NTMG searches the sequence with in-frame criterion in order to find all the ATG-like codons. An ATG-like codon is a XTG, an AXG or an ATX with X representing A, T, C or G. For each ATG-like codon, the NTMG generates candidate primers using the sliding window. The NTMG also modifies the ATG-like codon into the ATG codon in each candidate primer. Hence, each candidate primer contains the ATG start codon with in-frame criterion that can translate correctly to truncated mutants.</p>
      <p>After that, the NTMG applies the primary criteria and the secondary criteria to check if the candidate primers satisfy all the criteria. Those candidate primers that pass the criteria checking are then divided into classes according to the melting temperature. Each class contains primers whose melting temperatures are within the same range (default 5°C). So the primers chosen from the same class may be used in the same PCR experiment. For candidate primers in the same class, the NTMG does the cross-dimer check and the co-existence check and builds the cross-dimer matrix and the co-existence matrix. These two matrices are then ANDed to produce a new matrix which acts as an adjacency matrix of a graph. Previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>) proposed the transformation of minimizing the number of primers into the finding of the maximum clique in a graph. Next, each class is further divided into subclasses according to the positions of the ATG-like codons. The proposed genetic algorithm is then applied for each class in order to choose a set of primers, one from each subclass and the objective is to divide these primers into as few groups as possible such that each group of primers can be put in a tube in the PCR experiment. That is, the genetic algorithm tries to find a good multiplex PCR assay design. A heuristic maximum clique algorithm is proposed to calculate the fitness of a chromosome in the genetic algorithm. This heuristic algorithm tries to find the maximum clique in the graph previously mentioned and the maximum clique corresponds to the minimum number of grouping. Finally, the NTMG finds the corresponding reverse primer and outputs the results.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Environment</title>
      <p>The NTMG is written in Java using Java 2 Platform standard Edition 5.0 Development Kit (J2SDK) and employs the java server page (JSP) on the Apache Tomcat Server (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tomcat.apache.org/">http://tomcat.apache.org/</ext-link>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Output</title>
      <p>The NTMG outputs the number of primer groups, the number of forward primers, the number of reverse primers and the primers in each group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref> shows a solution report).
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>The output solution of the NTMG.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm305f4"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>CONCLUSION AND FUTURE WORK</title>
    <p>A web-based application system called the NTMG is provided for researches who need to apply the sequential deletion method to locate the functional domain of a protein. After input the cDNA sequence, the NTMG automatically generates groups of primers. Each group of primers can be put in a tube and all tubes can be accommodated in a single batch of the multiplex PCR amplification under the same condition. Thus, time and money can be saved. We conducted a wet laboratory experiment on the multiplex PCR assay design proposed by the NTMG on input HL5 cDNA. The NTMG found 48 forward primers and one reverse primer and it divided them into 8 groups. In the wet PCR experiment, 44 PCR products had been found and the success rate is 91.7% (see Supplementary Data). Hence, the NTMG is of practical use to researchers who need to apply the sequential deletion method.</p>
    <p>As a future work, we plan to develop the more general multiplex PCR assay design. Given a set of PCR experiment requirements, we plan to develop a system that can automatically find the primers and try to divide the primers into as few groups as possible such that the primers in each group can be put in a tube and all tubes can be accommodated in a single batch of the multiplex PCR experiment.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title>
    <p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online.</p>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack>
    <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
    <p>This study was supported in part by China Medical University under grand CMU95-184. This study was also partially supported by the National Science Council of R.O.C. under the contract NSC 95-2221-E-005-078. Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for this article was provided by National Chung Hsing University, ROC.</p>
    <p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p>
  </ack>
  <ref-list>
    <title>REFERENCES</title>
    <ref id="B1">
      <label>1</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>SW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The participation of 5S rRNA in the co-translational formation of eukaryotic 5S ribonucleoprotein complex</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
        <year>2001</year>
        <volume>29</volume>
        <fpage>2510</fpage>
        <lpage>2516</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11410658</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B2">
      <label>2</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Edwards</surname>
            <given-names>MC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gibbs</surname>
            <given-names>RA</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Multiplex PCR: advantages, development, and applications</article-title>
        <source>PCR Methods Appl</source>
        <year>1994</year>
        <volume>3</volume>
        <fpage>65</fpage>
        <lpage>75</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B3">
      <label>3</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bourque</surname>
            <given-names>SN</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Valero</surname>
            <given-names>JR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mercier</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lavoie</surname>
            <given-names>MC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Levesque</surname>
            <given-names>RC</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Multiplex polymerase chain reaction for detection and differentiation of the microbial insecticide Bacillus thuringiensis</article-title>
        <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol</source>
        <year>1993</year>
        <volume>59</volume>
        <fpage>523</fpage>
        <lpage>527</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8434916</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B4">
      <label>4</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kampke</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kieninger</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mecklenburg</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Efficient primer design algorithms</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2000</year>
        <volume>17</volume>
        <fpage>214</fpage>
        <lpage>225</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11294787</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B5">
      <label>5</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>JS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>CC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shiue</surname>
            <given-names>YL</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Primer design using genetic algorithm</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2004</year>
        <volume>20</volume>
        <fpage>1710</fpage>
        <lpage>1717</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14988099</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B6">
      <label>6</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lowe</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sharefkin</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>SQ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dieffenbach</surname>
            <given-names>CW</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A computer program for selection of oligonucleotide primers for polymerase chain reactions</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
        <year>1990</year>
        <volume>18</volume>
        <fpage>1757</fpage>
        <lpage>1761</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1692404</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B7">
      <label>7</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kupfer</surname>
            <given-names>KC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Davies</surname>
            <given-names>CJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Burbee</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Evans</surname>
            <given-names>LA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Garner</surname>
            <given-names>HR</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>PRIMO: a primer design program that applies base quality statistics for automated large-scale DNA sequencing</article-title>
        <source>Genomics</source>
        <year>1997</year>
        <volume>40</volume>
        <fpage>476</fpage>
        <lpage>485</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9073516</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B8">
      <label>8</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Innis</surname>
            <given-names>MA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gelfand</surname>
            <given-names>DH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sninsky</surname>
            <given-names>JJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>White</surname>
            <given-names>TJ</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <source>PCR Protocols: A Guide to Methods and Applications</source>
        <year>1990</year>
        <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
        <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B9">
      <label>9</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>von Ahsen</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wittwer</surname>
            <given-names>CT</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schutz</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Oligonucleotide melting temperature under PCR conditions: nearest-neighbor corrections for Mg2+, deoxynucleotide triphosphate, and dimethyl sulfoxide concentrations with comparison to alternative empirical formulas</article-title>
        <source>Clin. Chem</source>
        <year>2001</year>
        <volume>47</volume>
        <fpage>1956</fpage>
        <lpage>1961</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11673362</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B10">
      <label>10</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>SH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>CY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cho</surname>
            <given-names>CS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lo</surname>
            <given-names>CZ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hsiung</surname>
            <given-names>CA</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Primer Design Assistant (PDA): a web-based primer design tool</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
        <year>2003</year>
        <volume>31</volume>
        <fpage>3751</fpage>
        <lpage>3754</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12824410</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B11">
      <label>11</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Haas</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vingron</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Poustka</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wiemann</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Primer design for large scale sequencing</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
        <year>1998</year>
        <volume>26</volume>
        <fpage>3006</fpage>
        <lpage>3012</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9611248</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B12">
      <label>12</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kwok</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kellogg</surname>
            <given-names>DE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McKinney</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Spasic</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Goda</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Levenson</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sninsky</surname>
            <given-names>JJ</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Effects of primer-template mismatches on the polymerase chain reaction: Human Immunodeficiency Virus 1 model studies</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
        <year>1990</year>
        <volume>18</volume>
        <fpage>999</fpage>
        <lpage>1005</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2179874</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B13">
      <label>13</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ouyang</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kaplan</surname>
            <given-names>PD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Libchaber</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>DNA solution of the maximal clique problem</article-title>
        <source>Science</source>
        <year>1997</year>
        <volume>278</volume>
        <fpage>446</fpage>
        <lpage>449</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9334300</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B14">
      <label>14</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Linhart</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shamir</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The degenerate primer design problem: theory and applications</article-title>
        <source>J. Comput. Biol</source>
        <year>2005</year>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <fpage>431</fpage>
        <lpage>456</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15882141</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
