<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?properties open_access?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">gbe</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Genome Biology and Evolution</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1759-6653</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>US</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">10581538</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37793175</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evad177</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">evad177</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Letter</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01130</subject>
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01140</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>IRplus: An Augmented Tool to Detect Inverted Repeats in Plastid Genomes</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Díez Menéndez</surname>
          <given-names>Carmen</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Escuela Politécnica Superior, Universidad Autónoma de Madrid</institution>, <addr-line>Madrid</addr-line>, <country country="ES">Spain</country></aff>
        <xref rid="evad177-FM1" ref-type="author-notes"/>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <name>
          <surname>Poczai</surname>
          <given-names>Peter</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Botany Unit, Finnish Museum of Natural History, University of Helsinki</institution>, <addr-line>Helsinki</addr-line>, <country country="FI">Finland</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>Museomics Research Group, Helsinki Institute of Life Science (HiLIFE), University of Helsinki</institution>, <addr-line>Helsinki</addr-line>, <country country="FI">Finland</country></aff>
        <xref rid="evad177-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
        <!--peter.poczai@helsinki.fi-->
        <xref rid="evad177-FM1" ref-type="author-notes"/>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Williams</surname>
          <given-names>Bernardo</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Department of Computer Science, University of Helsinki</institution>, <addr-line>Helsinki</addr-line>, <country country="FI">Finland</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Myllys</surname>
          <given-names>Leena</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Botany Unit, Finnish Museum of Natural History, University of Helsinki</institution>, <addr-line>Helsinki</addr-line>, <country country="FI">Finland</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6317-3860</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Amiryousefi</surname>
          <given-names>Ali</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Systems Oncology Research Program, Faculty of Medicine, University of Helsinki</institution>, <addr-line>Helsinki</addr-line>, <country country="FI">Finland</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>Ludwig Center at Harvard and Laboratory of Systems Pharmacology, Harvard Medical School</institution>, <addr-line>Boston, Massachusetts</addr-line>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
        <xref rid="evad177-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
        <!--ali.amiryousefi@helsinki.fi-->
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name>
          <surname>Piganeau</surname>
          <given-names>Gwenael</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Associate Editor</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <fn id="evad177-FM1">
        <p>Carmen Díez Menéndez and Peter Poczai contributed equally to this work.</p>
      </fn>
      <corresp id="evad177-cor1">Corresponding authors: E-mails: <email>ali.amiryousefi@helsinki.fi</email>; <email>peter.poczai@helsinki.fi</email>.</corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <month>10</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2023-10-04">
      <day>04</day>
      <month>10</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>04</day>
      <month>10</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>15</volume>
    <issue>10</issue>
    <elocation-id>evad177</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="corrected-typeset">
        <day>17</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2023. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xlink:href="evad177.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <p>High-throughput sequencing methods have increased the accessibility of plastid genomes, which are crucial for clarifying phylogenetic relationships. Current large sequencing efforts require software tools for routine display of their distinctive quadripartite structure, which is denoted by four junction sites. By concentrating on these junctions and their close vicinity, IRscope has emerged as the standard tool for detection of this structure and creating simplified comparative graphical maps of plastid genomes. Here, we provide an augmented version (IRplus) that encompasses a novel set of functions such as integrated error detection, flexible color schemes, and an upgraded method to detect inverted repeats in genomic sequences. Spanning across the plant tree of life, IRplus allows the quick visualization of various sets of plastid genomes and features, next to smooth interoperability with other widely used annotation file formats and platforms. The IRplus can be accessed at <ext-link xlink:href="https://irscope.shinyapps.io/IRplus/" ext-link-type="uri">https://irscope.shinyapps.io/IRplus/</ext-link>, and source codes are freely available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/AmiryousefiLab/IRplus" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/AmiryousefiLab/IRplus</ext-link>.</p>
    </abstract>
    <kwd-group>
      <kwd>chloroplasts</kwd>
      <kwd>comparative genomics</kwd>
      <kwd>molecular evolution</kwd>
      <kwd>genome structure</kwd>
      <kwd>plastid genome</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Academy of Finland</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100002341</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>323711</award-id>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Finnish Cultural Foundation</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100003125</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Eötvös Research Grant</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="6"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <boxed-text id="evad177-box1" position="float">
    <caption>
      <title>Significance</title>
    </caption>
    <p>The expansion and contraction of inverted repeats and bordering regions is principally responsible for the size variation of plastid genomes and conveys significant evolutionary signals. As shown by multiple relevant studies, plastid genome structure analysis has led to novel insights into this organelle's biology aided by individually created IR maps. To further supports this process, IRplus, the upgraded version of its predecessor enables for adaptive identification and scaled visualization of the genetic structure of plastid genomes in vicinity of their junction sites.</p>
  </boxed-text>
  <sec sec-type="intro" id="evad177-s0">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <p>Plastids found in photosynthetic organisms are endosymbiotic organelles with their own genomes (plastome). Although the origin and timing of the primary endosymbiosis is debated (<xref rid="evad177-B13" ref-type="bibr">Irisarri et al. 2021</xref>; <xref rid="evad177-B6" ref-type="bibr">de Vries and de Vries 2022</xref>), this event stands as an important turning point in the evolution of eukaryotic life. It is presumed that ∼1.9 billion years ago in the Paleoproterozoic, a cyanobiont (a symbiotic cyanobacterium) initiated a symbiogenetic event with a heterotrophic eukaryotic host leading to the formation of primary plastids in the monophyletic supergroup called Archaeplastida (or Plantae sensu lato), which includes land plants, glaucophytes, and red and green algae (see <xref rid="evad177-B29" ref-type="bibr">Sánchez-Baracaldo et al. 2017</xref>; <xref rid="evad177-B32" ref-type="bibr">Strassert et al. 2021</xref>). The endosymbiosis occurred repeatedly, and plastid-bearing lineages spread across the eukaryotic tree of life (<xref rid="evad177-B30" ref-type="bibr">Sibbald and Archibald 2020</xref>). Plastids were lost and reduced several times among photosynthetic lineages; they moved horizontally on the phylogenetic tree and can be obtained through kleptoplasty by heterotrophic organisms such as <italic toggle="yes">Elysia</italic> sea slugs (<xref rid="evad177-B12" ref-type="bibr">Havurinne and Tyystjärvi 2020</xref>).</p>
    <p>The explosive increase in complete plastid genome sequences due to high-throughput sequencing technologies (HTS) challenged the traditional static view of plastid DNA (ptDNA) (<xref rid="evad177-B9" ref-type="bibr">Gonçalves et al. 2020</xref>; <xref rid="evad177-B7" ref-type="bibr">Doyle 2022</xref>). It was also revealed that plastid genomes of several green plant lineages underwent significant structural changes and gene or intron losses and demonstrated rate heterogeneity in protein-coding sequences (<xref rid="evad177-B36" ref-type="bibr">Wicke et al. 2011</xref>, <xref rid="evad177-B26" ref-type="bibr">Ruhlman and Jansen 2018</xref>; <xref rid="evad177-B10" ref-type="bibr">Gonçalves et al. 2019</xref>). This rather dynamic nature of plastid genomes is responsible for heritable variation both within and between populations through heteroplasmy driven by recombination separate from biparental inheritance paradigms (<xref rid="evad177-B38" ref-type="bibr">Woloszynska 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evad177-B21" ref-type="bibr">Mower and Vickrey 2018</xref>; <xref rid="evad177-B9" ref-type="bibr">Gonçalves et al. 2020</xref>).</p>
    <p>Despite such complex mechanisms, plastid genomes maintain a quadripartite structure across all major green plant lineages, which consists of a large and small single copy (LSC and SSC) region separated by two identical copies of inverted repeats (IRs) creating four separate junction sites (JS) (<xref rid="evad177-B11" ref-type="bibr">Goulding et al. 1996</xref>). The junctions connecting the IRs with the LSC are called JLA (IRa/LSC) and JLB (IRb/LSC), whereas the endpoints meeting the SSC are labeled as JSA (SSC/IRa) and JSB (IRb/SSC). Although the LSC and SSC regions appear in an inverted orientation and equimolar state due to “flip-flopping” (<xref rid="evad177-B27" ref-type="bibr">Ruhlman et al. 2017</xref>), the two IRs share the same sequence because of their important function in genome stability (<xref rid="evad177-B23" ref-type="bibr">Palmer and Thompson 1982</xref>) and replication initiation (<xref rid="evad177-B37" ref-type="bibr">Wolfe et al. 1987</xref>). However, the presence of IRs is not essential for chloroplast functionality (<xref rid="evad177-B21" ref-type="bibr">Mower and Vickrey 2018</xref>); IR-lacking genomes accumulate a set of novel repeats around the endpoint of the JS (e.g., inverted repeat-lacking clade of legumes (<xref rid="evad177-B28" ref-type="bibr">Sabir et al. 2014</xref>)), which generate further structural diversity through repeat-mediated recombination (<xref rid="evad177-B26" ref-type="bibr">Ruhlman and Jansen 2018</xref>; <xref rid="evad177-B9" ref-type="bibr">Gonçalves et al. 2020</xref>). Moreover, the IR structure is dynamic, and the quadripartite plastome organization can be regained after ancestral loss in some seed plant lineages (<xref rid="evad177-B14" ref-type="bibr">Jost et al. 2022</xref>). The two copies also undergo frequent intramolecular recombination, which produces isomeric forms resulting in expansion and contraction of the JS. These identical sequences are then maintained through the continuous operation of gene conversion driven by recombination-dependent replication (RDR) and not through “flip-flop” recombination as previously thought (<xref rid="evad177-B17" ref-type="bibr">Kolodner and Tewari 1979</xref>; <xref rid="evad177-B39" ref-type="bibr">Zampini et al. 2017</xref>). Thus, nucleotide substitution is 3-fold lower in the IRs than, for example, in the SSC region (<xref rid="evad177-B37" ref-type="bibr">Wolfe et al. 1987</xref>; <xref rid="evad177-B41" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al. 2016</xref>). The fascinating consequence of this copy-dependent repair mechanism is the phenomenon known as rate heterotachy (<xref rid="evad177-B19" ref-type="bibr">Lockhart et al. 2006</xref>; <xref rid="evad177-B1" ref-type="bibr">Abdullah et al. 2020</xref>). Theoretically, genes that moved from the IR to the LSC or SSC should experience a rate acceleration corresponding to their new position, whereas genes that moved from the LSC or SSC to the IR should undergo a deceleration similar to that of other IR genes, known as the IR rate effect. Recent studies provided strong evidence for the existence of this phenomena (<xref rid="evad177-B41" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al. 2016</xref>), although some exceptions do exist (<xref rid="evad177-B35" ref-type="bibr">Weng et al. 2017</xref>). This suggests that there are differences in both the rate and type of mutations throughout the plastid genome. <xref rid="evad177-B24" ref-type="bibr">Robbins and Kelly (2023)</xref> have recently shown that the evolutionary rate of a plastid gene is contingent upon its positional proximity to the IR within the plastid genome. They found that angiosperm plastid genes that are situated farther away from the IR boundaries have exhibited a greater capacity to explore a wider range of sequence space on which natural selection can act. As a result, the location of a gene and the overall structure of the plastid genome have limited the capacity for adaptive modifications in the chloroplast.</p>
    <p>Nonidentical IR sequences escaping homogenization are rare; expansion and contraction create further genome rearrangements that resemble large inversions (<xref rid="evad177-B16" ref-type="bibr">Knox 2014</xref>). For example, if genes from one end of the SSC are moved to the IR through an expansion and then duplicated in both copies during a contraction, this will look like a large inversion has occurred across most of the SSC, with the new IR boundary as one endpoint. Such structural diversity is rare among most land plants, and the phylogenetic distribution of lineage-specific JS changes shows a conservative evolutionary trajectory. In contrast to angiosperms and nonvascular land plants, streptophytic green algae (<xref rid="evad177-B34" ref-type="bibr">Turmel et al. 2017</xref>), lycophytes (<xref rid="evad177-B31" ref-type="bibr">Smith 2009</xref>), ferns (<xref rid="evad177-B25" ref-type="bibr">Robinson et al. 2018</xref>), and gymnosperms (<xref rid="evad177-B5" ref-type="bibr">Chaw et al. 2018</xref>) exhibit remarkable structural variation. Despite the explosive growth of whole-genome sequences, many branches of the Archaeplastida phylogenetic tree remain unclear. Results from species that have not previously been explored may reveal fascinating structural variation, highlighting the need to continue investigating the evolutionary dynamics of plastid genomes.</p>
    <p>The essence of this exploration is based on comparative genomics through direct comparison of large-scale genetic material of different organisms between each other to gain a better understanding of species evolution and gene functions among plastid genomic regions. Detection of IR expansion/contraction and the correct identification of IRs and possible sequence errors are crucial for the study of structural diversity in plastid genomes (<xref rid="evad177-B2" ref-type="bibr">Amiryousefi et al 2018a</xref>). In recent years, IRscope (<xref rid="evad177-B3" ref-type="bibr">Amiryousefi et al. 2018b</xref>) became a widely applied tool to explore the evolutionary dynamics of IRs and to depict JS changes. Here, with the incorporation of a novel set of functions, we present an augmented version of this software (IRplus) that significantly facilitates the detection of the IR regions and deeper comparative analysis of more diverse plastid genomes.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="evad177-s1">
    <title>Program Description</title>
    <p>We provide downloadable source codes in an open-access format by expanding the functionality of the program beyond what we presented previously. The entire R source code, including all libraries and dependencies, is deposited at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/AmiryousefiLab/IRplus" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/AmiryousefiLab/IRplus</ext-link>. The online interactive version of the code is also accessible through <ext-link xlink:href="https://irscope.shinyapps.io/IRplus/" ext-link-type="uri">https://irscope.shinyapps.io/IRplus/</ext-link>. For enhanced clarity and more control on the program's utility, the updated code functions are formatted and organized in separate files, which require the installation of the RStudio package. All functions have been wrapped together in an R repository, allowing users to download and change the program according to their needs. In general, the main three updates of IRplus are the 1) enhanced ability to detect inverted repeats in the presence of minimal mismatches between these regions among a wider range of species; 2) updated coloring themes, which allow a more versatile depiction of the outputs; and 3) overall finetuning of the existing functions and their parameters based on our experience and user's feedbacks.</p>
    <sec id="evad177-s1.1">
      <title>Novel Inverted Repeat Detection</title>
      <p>By default, built-in methods for automated IR recognition in currently available software (e.g., <xref rid="evad177-B20" ref-type="bibr">Lohse et al. 2013</xref>) operate under the assumption that all IR sequences are identical and single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNP) can terminate IR detection (<xref rid="evad177-B40" ref-type="bibr">Zheng et al. 2020</xref>). Nonidentical IR sequences may arise from sequencing errors or from mutations escaping copy correction mechanisms. Recently, we developed a novel method to detect mismatches in IR regions (<xref rid="evad177-B40" ref-type="bibr">Zheng et al. 2020</xref>), and we adopted this algorithm in IRplus, resulting in a faster and more versatile IR detection. In brief, IRplus extracts corresponding genome sequences from the uploaded files and initiates subgenome formation and then maps reverse complement sequences by adjusting the start and endpoints of the IR regions. The optimum radius is determined by an internal function setting its parameters based on the positions of the genes in relation to the various junctions. Therefore, if the first neighboring gene to the JS is located <italic toggle="yes">x</italic> bp away, that distance will be used as the radius for that particular species and junction. Afterward, the program will repeat the process for the subsequent species with this learned parameter. If this value does not contain any gene marked in the sequence, a new longer distance is determined where the first neighboring gene of that species is detected and then recursively carried over to the previous species. This allows the scalable representation of genes present in the vicinity of the JS in a comparative manner between species under study. In the next step, the whole IR regions are shifted in a sliding window to detect mismatches among them. Finally, the differences between the IRs are highlighted if their sequences are nonidentical. If insertions, SNPs, and deletions are present among IRs, they will be marked with green, orange, and red dots, respectively. If mismatches are located near the JS, they are shown in the specific place where they occur. Otherwise, a text with the number of mismatches of each kind will appear in the middle of the resulting plot (<xref rid="evad177-F1" ref-type="fig">fig. 1</xref> and <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Data S1, Supplementary Material</xref> online).</p>
      <fig position="float" id="evad177-F1" fig-type="figure">
        <label><sc>Fig.</sc> 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Plot representing the JS across various groups of plants. To the left of each track, the plot shows the length of each plastid genome (bp), whereas JS are indicated above the tracks. Genes in the vicinity of the JS in forward (5′–3′) orientation on the positive strand (+) appear above the tracks, whereas genes in reverse (3′–5′) on the negative strand (−) are shown below the bars. The size (bp) of each quadripartite segment of the plastid genome is shown in the bars. Artificial changes were made in the sequences of <italic toggle="yes">Alteris fauriei</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Solanum lycopersicum</italic> as depicted in the plot. Other examples are based on plastid genome sequences retrieved directly from the NCBI by IRplus. In case of nonidentical IRs, errors are summarized in the center of the bars. The first number marks the total number of SNPs found in the IRs, whereas numbers after the slash indicate the presence of indels. Insertions are marked with plus (+), whereas deletions are marked with negative (−) signs.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="evad177f1" position="float"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec id="evad177-s1.2">
      <title>Versatile Coloring Schemes</title>
      <p>We outfitted IRplus with a new interactive interface and output themes that provide a considerably easier control and seamless regulation of the output. An option to analyze up to 20 species was added. The user interface changes dynamically according to the chosen number, and a validator section was added to track the number of species included in the analysis. IRplus first attempts to use external libraries, such as Biostrings (<xref rid="evad177-B22" ref-type="bibr">Pagés et al. 2022</xref>), coRdon (<xref rid="evad177-B8" ref-type="bibr">Elek et al. 2022</xref>), and genbankr (<xref rid="evad177-B4" ref-type="bibr">Becker and Lawrence 2022</xref>) to read compatible GenBank (.gb) files. If this is not possible, IRplus uses its own generic functions to extract necessary information regarding the structure of the genomes. One of the major changes in the updated version of the program is its compatibility with files exported from the popular software Geneious Prime (<xref rid="evad177-B15" ref-type="bibr">Kearse et al. 2012</xref>).</p>
      <p>Given the increasing quantity of deposited plastid genomes, it is important to have drawing tools with flexible coloring schemes that can render visual representations of genomes in a user-specified manner (<xref rid="evad177-B40" ref-type="bibr">Zheng et al. 2020</xref>). We outfitted IRplus with tools and coloring schemes to provide a foundation for more accurate IR expansion/contraction data display. It allows for sequential, divergent, and qualitative schemes that are readily comprehensible, including those with color vision deficiency. Users can choose from different predefined themes (e.g., cherry tree, sea, and sunset) to create visual representations of IR JS and corresponding genes. The resulting plots can be customized using random coloring options. A sample plot with only two species is also shown in the same tab, ensuring comparison of various plotting themes. The updated version of the program allows downloading of results in various file formats (e.g., pdf, png, jpeg, bmp, and tiff), thus simplifying downstream image processing.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="evad177-s1.3">
      <title>Updated Features</title>
      <p>Several bugs were fixed to extract species names from different file types. Following submission, the software will start a search for IR regions in the input files. The interactive timing meter provides insight into the calculation work and output variation, and the real-time interactive coloring theme may be utilized to simply generate the required output. Note that the species chosen will result in the identification of a consensus radius for each junction point of the to-be-plotted genes. This implies that the algorithm may not produce optimal results if the input files do not reflect closely related species. When this occurs, the application will alert the user so that the evolutionary distance of the underlying input species can be reduced. Note that the input files may consist of handwritten annotations, GenBank accession numbers, or associated GB files of chloroplast genomes. If no IR is found for some of the species, to avoid errors, the user is advised to run the program again without those species. It is important to note that IRplus is only a plotting tool and does not correct apparent annotation errors of plastid genomes present in the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI), for example, unexpected truncation of genes, misannotated exon–intron boundaries, or shifted replication of origin (<xref rid="evad177-B33" ref-type="bibr">Tillich et al. 2017</xref>; <xref rid="evad177-B2" ref-type="bibr">Amiryousefi et al. 2018a</xref>).</p>
      <p>In the Frequently Asked Question (FAQ) section, a new tab is added which is directly connected with GitHub issues section. Based on our experience, this may serve as an interactive forum where users can report bugs or ask relevant questions. Our experience showed number of issues with the use of IRscope in last years communicated to us by the users. These issues ranging from misidentification of the IR regions (due to aberrant dissimilarity of the IRs) to misplaced features of the genome on the resulting plots were addressed in the updated IRplus. Thanks to its improved detection method, also the scope of the input species is expanded considerably to encompass all IR-containing plastid genomes (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">supplementary Table S1, Supplementary Material</xref> online). IRplus was also improved in handling of the SSC reversion function as in a number of reported cases, IRscope failed to conserve the genomic structure at IR JS. Low memory space and its consequential disconnection from servers in IRscope was also bypassed by deploying IRplus on considerably enhanced machines leading to continuous analysis of up to 20 species at once.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="evad177-s2">
    <title>Conclusions</title>
    <p>IRplus is the update of the widely appreciated online IR detection and mapping software (IRscope) which is created to represent a more accurate genetic architecture of IR JS in plastid genomes. Due to its novel algorithm, IRplus determines the correct location of IRs despite the mismatches introduced in de novo plastid genomes due to sequencing and assembly error. Although the quality of the input files is still of paramount importance, IRplus offers an adaptive capability to partially overcome this issue in existence of the minimal anomalies in the genome sequences. Also, this freeware exhibits a high level of compatibility to annotation and assembly outputs of major tools in this space, such as Geneious and DOGMA. In addition to its many coloring schemes, IRplus allows a versatile interactive adjustment of the output. The free availability of the software’s source code provides yet an additional level of flexibility that allows more expert R users to adopt their results as necessary.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
      <label>evad177_Supplementary_Data</label>
      <media xlink:href="evad177_supplementary_data.zip">
        <caption>
          <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
        </caption>
      </media>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack id="ack1">
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <p>We thank the open-access support of Helsinki University Library. We thank the support of the Academy of Finland (no. 323711) grant awarded to L.M., Finnish Cultural Foundation grant to A.A., and the Eötvös Research Grant to P.P. The authors thank Derek Ho for assistance in editing the manuscript.</p>
  </ack>
  <sec id="evad177-s3">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <p><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary data</xref> are available at <italic toggle="yes">Genome Biology and Evolution</italic> online.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="evad177-s4">
    <title>Author Contributions</title>
    <p>All authors of the manuscript have read and agreed to its content and are accountable for all aspects of the accuracy and integrity of the manuscript in accordance with the ICMJE criteria. The study was conceived by A.A. and P.P. Supervised by A.A, the program was developed by C.D.M., revised by B.W., and tested by P.P. and A.A. Funding was gathered by L.M., who administered the project and supervised the work together with A.A. Resulting data and visualization features were interpreted by all authors. P.P. and A.A. wrote the manuscript which was read and revised by all authors.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="evad177-s5">
    <title>Data Availability</title>
    <p>The code described in the article is publicly available on GitHub at the repository (<ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/AmiryousefiLab/IRplus" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/AmiryousefiLab/IRplus</ext-link>, last accessed July 19, 2023). The documentation for the software can be accessed in the program's website (<ext-link xlink:href="https://irscope.shinyapps.io/IRplus/" ext-link-type="uri">https://irscope.shinyapps.io/IRplus/</ext-link>, last accessed July 19, 2023).</p>
  </sec>
  <ref-list id="ref1">
    <title>Literature Cited</title>
    <ref id="evad177-B1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="given-only"><given-names>Abdullah</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><year>2020</year>. <article-title>Complete chloroplast genomes of <italic toggle="yes">Anthurium huixtlense</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Pothos scandens</italic> (Pothoideae, Araceae): unique inverted repeat expansion and contraction affect rate evolution</article-title>. <source>J Mol Evol</source>. <volume>88</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>562</fpage>–<lpage>574</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32642873</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Amiryousefi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hyvönen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poczai</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2018a</year>. <article-title>The chloroplast genome structure of bittersweet (<italic toggle="yes">Solanum dulcamara</italic>): plastid genome structure evolution in Solanaceae</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>13</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<comment>e0196069</comment>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Amiryousefi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hyvönen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poczai</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2018b</year>. <article-title>IRscope: an online program to visualize the junction sites of chloroplast genomes</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>34</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>3030</fpage>–<lpage>3031</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29659705</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year><article-title>.</article-title><comment><italic toggle="yes">genbankr: parsing GenBank files into semantically useful objects</italic>. R package version 1.26.0.</comment></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chaw</surname><given-names>S-M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C-S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sudianto</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2018</year>. <part-title>Evolution of gymnosperm plastid genomes</part-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Chaw</surname><given-names>S-M</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></string-name></person-group>, editors. <source>Advances in botanical research, plastid genome evolution</source>. <volume>Vol. 85</volume>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge (MA)</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>. p. <fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>222</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>de Vries</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Vries</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. <article-title>Evolutionary genomic insights into cyanobacterial symbioses in plants</article-title>. <source>Quant Plant Biol</source>. <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>e16</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37077989</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. <article-title>Defining coalescent genes: theory meets practice in organelle phylogenomics</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source>. <volume>71</volume>:<fpage>476</fpage>–<lpage>489</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34191012</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B8">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Elek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuzman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vlahovicek</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. <comment><italic toggle="yes">coRdon: codon usage analysis and prediction of gene expressivity</italic>. R package version 1.16.0,</comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/BioinfoHR/coRdon" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/BioinfoHR/coRdon</ext-link></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B9">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gonçalves</surname><given-names>DJP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruhlman</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mandel</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year>. <article-title>Under the rug: abandoning persistent misconceptions that obfuscate organelle evolution</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source>. <volume>151</volume>:<fpage>106903</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32628998</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B10">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gonçalves</surname><given-names>DJP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2019</year>. <article-title>Incongruence between gene trees and species trees and phylogenetic signal variation in plastid genes</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source>. <volume>138</volume>:<fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>232</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31146023</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B11">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Goulding</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olmstead</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morden</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>1996</year>. <article-title>Ebb and flow of the chloroplast inverted repeat</article-title>. <source>Mol Gen Genet</source>. <volume>252</volume>:<fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>206</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8804393</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B12">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Havurinne</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tyystjärvi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year>. <article-title>Photosynthetic sea slugs induce protective changes to the light reactions of the chloroplasts they steal from algae</article-title>. <source>eLife</source><volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e57389</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33077025</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B13">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Irisarri</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Strassert</surname><given-names>JFH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burki</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year>. <article-title>Phylogenomic insights into the origin of primary plastids</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source>. <volume>71</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>120</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33988690</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B14">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jost</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><year>2022</year>. <article-title>Structural plastome evolution in holoparasitic Hydnoraceae with special focus on inverted and direct repeats</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol Evol</source>. <volume>14</volume>:<comment>evac077</comment>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B15">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kearse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><year>2012</year>. <article-title>Geneious Basic: an integrated and extendable desktop software platform for the organization and analysis of sequence data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>28</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1647</fpage>–<lpage>1649</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22543367</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B16">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Knox</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2014</year>. <article-title>The dynamic history of plastid genomes in the Campanulaceae sensu lato unique among angiosperms</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Aci USA</source>. <volume>111</volume>(<issue>30</issue>):<fpage>11097</fpage>–<lpage>11102</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B17">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kolodner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tewari</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>1979</year>. <article-title>Inverted repeats in chloroplast DNA from higher plants</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Aci USA</source>. <volume>76</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B19">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lockhart</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><year>2006</year>. <article-title>Heterotachy and tree building: a case study with plastids and eubacteria</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16151191</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B20">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drechsel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kahlau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2013</year>. <article-title>OrganellarGenomeDRAW – a suite of tools for generating physical maps of plastid and mitochondrial genomes and visualizing expression data sets</article-title>. <source>Nucl Acids Res</source>. <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>W575</fpage>–<lpage>W581</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23609545</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B21">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mower</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vickrey</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2018</year>. <part-title>Structural diversity among plastid genomes of land plants</part-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Chaw</surname><given-names>S-M</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></string-name></person-group>, editors. <source>Advances in botanical research, plastid genome Evolution</source>. <volume>Vol. 85</volume>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge (MA)</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>. p. <fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>292</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B22">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pagès</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aboyoun</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gentleman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>DebRoy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. <comment><italic toggle="yes">Biostrings: efficient manipulation of biological strings</italic>. R package version 2.66.0,</comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://bioconductor.org/packages/Biostrings" ext-link-type="uri">https://bioconductor.org/packages/Biostrings</ext-link></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B23">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>1982</year>. <article-title>Chloroplast DNA rearrangements are more frequent when a large inverted repeat sequence is lost</article-title>. <source>Cell</source><volume>29</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>537</fpage>–<lpage>550</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6288261</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B24">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>EHJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2023</year>. <article-title>The evolutionary constraints on angiosperm chloroplast adaptation</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol Evol</source>. <volume>15</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<comment>evad101</comment>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B25">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><year>2018</year>. <article-title>Mobile elements shape plastome evolution in ferns</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol Evol</source>. <volume>10</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2558</fpage>–<lpage>2571</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30165616</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B26">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ruhlman</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2018</year>. <part-title>Aberration of analogy? The atypical plastomes of Geraniaceae</part-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Chaw</surname><given-names>S-M</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></string-name></person-group>, editors. <source>Advances in botanical research, plastid genome Evolution</source>. <volume>Vol. 85</volume>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge (MA)</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>. p. <fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B27">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ruhlman</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blazier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sabir</surname><given-names>JSM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>Recombination dependent replication and gene conversion homogenize sequences and diversify plastid genome structure</article-title>. <source>Am J Bot</source>. <volume>104</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>559</fpage>–<lpage>572</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28400415</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B28">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sabir</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><year>2014</year>. <article-title>Evolutionary and biotechnology implications of plastid genome variation in the inverted-repeat-lacking clade of legumes</article-title>. <source>Plant Biotech J</source>. <volume>12</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>743</fpage>–<lpage>754</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B29">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sánchez-Baracaldo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raven</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pisani</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knoll</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>Early photosynthetic eukaryotes inhabited low-salinity habitats’</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Aci USA</source>. <volume>114</volume>(<issue>37</issue>):<fpage>E7737</fpage>–<lpage>E7745</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B30">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sibbald</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Archibald</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year>. <article-title>Genomic insights into plastid evolution</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol Evol</source>. <volume>12</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>978</fpage>–<lpage>990</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32402068</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B31">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <article-title>Unparalleled GC content in the plastid DNA of Selaginella</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>. <volume>71</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>627</fpage>–<lpage>639</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19774466</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B32">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Strassert</surname><given-names>JFH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Irisarri</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burki</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year>. <article-title>A molecular timescale for eukaryote evolution with implications for the origin of red algal-derived plastids</article-title>. <source>Nat Comm</source>. <volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1879</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B33">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tillich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><year>2017</year>. <article-title>GeSeq – versatile and accurate annotation of organelle genomes</article-title>. <source>Nucl Acids Res</source>. <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>W6</fpage>–<lpage>W11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28486635</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B34">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Turmel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Otis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lemieux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>Divergent copies of the large inverted repeat in the chloroplast genomes of ulvophycean green algae</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>994</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28428552</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B35">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruhlman</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>Expansion of inverted repeat does not decrease substitution rates in <italic toggle="yes">Pelargonium</italic> plastid genomes</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <volume>214</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>842</fpage>–<lpage>851</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27991660</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B36">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wicke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schneeweiss</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>DePamphilis</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quandt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2011</year>. <article-title>The evolution of the plastid chromosome in land plants: gene content, gene order, gene function</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>. <volume>76</volume>(<issue>3–5</issue>):<fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>297</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21424877</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B37">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>1987</year>. <article-title>Rates of nucleotide substitution vary greatly among plant mitochondrial, chloroplast, and nuclear DNAs</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Aci USA</source>. <volume>84</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>9054</fpage>–<lpage>9058</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B38">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Woloszynska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2010</year>. <article-title>Heteroplasmy and stoichiometric complexity of plant mitochondrial genomes – though this be madness, yet there's method in’t</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source>. <volume>61</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>657</fpage>–<lpage>671</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19995826</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B39">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zampini</surname><given-names>É</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Truche</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lepage</surname><given-names>É</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tremblay-Belzile</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brisson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2017</year>. <part-title>Plastid genome stability and repair</part-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X-Q</given-names></string-name></person-group>, editors. <source>Somatic genome variation in animals, plants, and microorganisms</source>. <publisher-loc>Hoboken, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd</publisher-name>. p. <fpage>119</fpage>–<lpage>163</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B40">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poczai</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hyvönen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amiryousefi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year>. <article-title>Chloroplot: an online program for the versatile plotting of organelle genomes</article-title>. <source>Fronti Genet</source>. <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>576124</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B41">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mower</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2016</year>. <article-title>Evolutionary dynamics of the plastid inverted repeat: the effects of expansion, contraction, and loss on substitution rates</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <volume>209</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1747</fpage>–<lpage>1756</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26574731</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?properties open_access?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">gbe</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Genome Biology and Evolution</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1759-6653</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>US</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">10581538</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37793175</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evad177</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">evad177</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Letter</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01130</subject>
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01140</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>IRplus: An Augmented Tool to Detect Inverted Repeats in Plastid Genomes</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Díez Menéndez</surname>
          <given-names>Carmen</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Escuela Politécnica Superior, Universidad Autónoma de Madrid</institution>, <addr-line>Madrid</addr-line>, <country country="ES">Spain</country></aff>
        <xref rid="evad177-FM1" ref-type="author-notes"/>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <name>
          <surname>Poczai</surname>
          <given-names>Peter</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Botany Unit, Finnish Museum of Natural History, University of Helsinki</institution>, <addr-line>Helsinki</addr-line>, <country country="FI">Finland</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>Museomics Research Group, Helsinki Institute of Life Science (HiLIFE), University of Helsinki</institution>, <addr-line>Helsinki</addr-line>, <country country="FI">Finland</country></aff>
        <xref rid="evad177-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
        <!--peter.poczai@helsinki.fi-->
        <xref rid="evad177-FM1" ref-type="author-notes"/>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Williams</surname>
          <given-names>Bernardo</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Department of Computer Science, University of Helsinki</institution>, <addr-line>Helsinki</addr-line>, <country country="FI">Finland</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Myllys</surname>
          <given-names>Leena</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Botany Unit, Finnish Museum of Natural History, University of Helsinki</institution>, <addr-line>Helsinki</addr-line>, <country country="FI">Finland</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6317-3860</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Amiryousefi</surname>
          <given-names>Ali</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Systems Oncology Research Program, Faculty of Medicine, University of Helsinki</institution>, <addr-line>Helsinki</addr-line>, <country country="FI">Finland</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>Ludwig Center at Harvard and Laboratory of Systems Pharmacology, Harvard Medical School</institution>, <addr-line>Boston, Massachusetts</addr-line>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
        <xref rid="evad177-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
        <!--ali.amiryousefi@helsinki.fi-->
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name>
          <surname>Piganeau</surname>
          <given-names>Gwenael</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Associate Editor</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <fn id="evad177-FM1">
        <p>Carmen Díez Menéndez and Peter Poczai contributed equally to this work.</p>
      </fn>
      <corresp id="evad177-cor1">Corresponding authors: E-mails: <email>ali.amiryousefi@helsinki.fi</email>; <email>peter.poczai@helsinki.fi</email>.</corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <month>10</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2023-10-04">
      <day>04</day>
      <month>10</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>04</day>
      <month>10</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>15</volume>
    <issue>10</issue>
    <elocation-id>evad177</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="corrected-typeset">
        <day>17</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2023. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xlink:href="evad177.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <p>High-throughput sequencing methods have increased the accessibility of plastid genomes, which are crucial for clarifying phylogenetic relationships. Current large sequencing efforts require software tools for routine display of their distinctive quadripartite structure, which is denoted by four junction sites. By concentrating on these junctions and their close vicinity, IRscope has emerged as the standard tool for detection of this structure and creating simplified comparative graphical maps of plastid genomes. Here, we provide an augmented version (IRplus) that encompasses a novel set of functions such as integrated error detection, flexible color schemes, and an upgraded method to detect inverted repeats in genomic sequences. Spanning across the plant tree of life, IRplus allows the quick visualization of various sets of plastid genomes and features, next to smooth interoperability with other widely used annotation file formats and platforms. The IRplus can be accessed at <ext-link xlink:href="https://irscope.shinyapps.io/IRplus/" ext-link-type="uri">https://irscope.shinyapps.io/IRplus/</ext-link>, and source codes are freely available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/AmiryousefiLab/IRplus" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/AmiryousefiLab/IRplus</ext-link>.</p>
    </abstract>
    <kwd-group>
      <kwd>chloroplasts</kwd>
      <kwd>comparative genomics</kwd>
      <kwd>molecular evolution</kwd>
      <kwd>genome structure</kwd>
      <kwd>plastid genome</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Academy of Finland</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100002341</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>323711</award-id>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Finnish Cultural Foundation</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100003125</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Eötvös Research Grant</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="6"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <boxed-text id="evad177-box1" position="float">
    <caption>
      <title>Significance</title>
    </caption>
    <p>The expansion and contraction of inverted repeats and bordering regions is principally responsible for the size variation of plastid genomes and conveys significant evolutionary signals. As shown by multiple relevant studies, plastid genome structure analysis has led to novel insights into this organelle's biology aided by individually created IR maps. To further supports this process, IRplus, the upgraded version of its predecessor enables for adaptive identification and scaled visualization of the genetic structure of plastid genomes in vicinity of their junction sites.</p>
  </boxed-text>
  <sec sec-type="intro" id="evad177-s0">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <p>Plastids found in photosynthetic organisms are endosymbiotic organelles with their own genomes (plastome). Although the origin and timing of the primary endosymbiosis is debated (<xref rid="evad177-B13" ref-type="bibr">Irisarri et al. 2021</xref>; <xref rid="evad177-B6" ref-type="bibr">de Vries and de Vries 2022</xref>), this event stands as an important turning point in the evolution of eukaryotic life. It is presumed that ∼1.9 billion years ago in the Paleoproterozoic, a cyanobiont (a symbiotic cyanobacterium) initiated a symbiogenetic event with a heterotrophic eukaryotic host leading to the formation of primary plastids in the monophyletic supergroup called Archaeplastida (or Plantae sensu lato), which includes land plants, glaucophytes, and red and green algae (see <xref rid="evad177-B29" ref-type="bibr">Sánchez-Baracaldo et al. 2017</xref>; <xref rid="evad177-B32" ref-type="bibr">Strassert et al. 2021</xref>). The endosymbiosis occurred repeatedly, and plastid-bearing lineages spread across the eukaryotic tree of life (<xref rid="evad177-B30" ref-type="bibr">Sibbald and Archibald 2020</xref>). Plastids were lost and reduced several times among photosynthetic lineages; they moved horizontally on the phylogenetic tree and can be obtained through kleptoplasty by heterotrophic organisms such as <italic toggle="yes">Elysia</italic> sea slugs (<xref rid="evad177-B12" ref-type="bibr">Havurinne and Tyystjärvi 2020</xref>).</p>
    <p>The explosive increase in complete plastid genome sequences due to high-throughput sequencing technologies (HTS) challenged the traditional static view of plastid DNA (ptDNA) (<xref rid="evad177-B9" ref-type="bibr">Gonçalves et al. 2020</xref>; <xref rid="evad177-B7" ref-type="bibr">Doyle 2022</xref>). It was also revealed that plastid genomes of several green plant lineages underwent significant structural changes and gene or intron losses and demonstrated rate heterogeneity in protein-coding sequences (<xref rid="evad177-B36" ref-type="bibr">Wicke et al. 2011</xref>, <xref rid="evad177-B26" ref-type="bibr">Ruhlman and Jansen 2018</xref>; <xref rid="evad177-B10" ref-type="bibr">Gonçalves et al. 2019</xref>). This rather dynamic nature of plastid genomes is responsible for heritable variation both within and between populations through heteroplasmy driven by recombination separate from biparental inheritance paradigms (<xref rid="evad177-B38" ref-type="bibr">Woloszynska 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evad177-B21" ref-type="bibr">Mower and Vickrey 2018</xref>; <xref rid="evad177-B9" ref-type="bibr">Gonçalves et al. 2020</xref>).</p>
    <p>Despite such complex mechanisms, plastid genomes maintain a quadripartite structure across all major green plant lineages, which consists of a large and small single copy (LSC and SSC) region separated by two identical copies of inverted repeats (IRs) creating four separate junction sites (JS) (<xref rid="evad177-B11" ref-type="bibr">Goulding et al. 1996</xref>). The junctions connecting the IRs with the LSC are called JLA (IRa/LSC) and JLB (IRb/LSC), whereas the endpoints meeting the SSC are labeled as JSA (SSC/IRa) and JSB (IRb/SSC). Although the LSC and SSC regions appear in an inverted orientation and equimolar state due to “flip-flopping” (<xref rid="evad177-B27" ref-type="bibr">Ruhlman et al. 2017</xref>), the two IRs share the same sequence because of their important function in genome stability (<xref rid="evad177-B23" ref-type="bibr">Palmer and Thompson 1982</xref>) and replication initiation (<xref rid="evad177-B37" ref-type="bibr">Wolfe et al. 1987</xref>). However, the presence of IRs is not essential for chloroplast functionality (<xref rid="evad177-B21" ref-type="bibr">Mower and Vickrey 2018</xref>); IR-lacking genomes accumulate a set of novel repeats around the endpoint of the JS (e.g., inverted repeat-lacking clade of legumes (<xref rid="evad177-B28" ref-type="bibr">Sabir et al. 2014</xref>)), which generate further structural diversity through repeat-mediated recombination (<xref rid="evad177-B26" ref-type="bibr">Ruhlman and Jansen 2018</xref>; <xref rid="evad177-B9" ref-type="bibr">Gonçalves et al. 2020</xref>). Moreover, the IR structure is dynamic, and the quadripartite plastome organization can be regained after ancestral loss in some seed plant lineages (<xref rid="evad177-B14" ref-type="bibr">Jost et al. 2022</xref>). The two copies also undergo frequent intramolecular recombination, which produces isomeric forms resulting in expansion and contraction of the JS. These identical sequences are then maintained through the continuous operation of gene conversion driven by recombination-dependent replication (RDR) and not through “flip-flop” recombination as previously thought (<xref rid="evad177-B17" ref-type="bibr">Kolodner and Tewari 1979</xref>; <xref rid="evad177-B39" ref-type="bibr">Zampini et al. 2017</xref>). Thus, nucleotide substitution is 3-fold lower in the IRs than, for example, in the SSC region (<xref rid="evad177-B37" ref-type="bibr">Wolfe et al. 1987</xref>; <xref rid="evad177-B41" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al. 2016</xref>). The fascinating consequence of this copy-dependent repair mechanism is the phenomenon known as rate heterotachy (<xref rid="evad177-B19" ref-type="bibr">Lockhart et al. 2006</xref>; <xref rid="evad177-B1" ref-type="bibr">Abdullah et al. 2020</xref>). Theoretically, genes that moved from the IR to the LSC or SSC should experience a rate acceleration corresponding to their new position, whereas genes that moved from the LSC or SSC to the IR should undergo a deceleration similar to that of other IR genes, known as the IR rate effect. Recent studies provided strong evidence for the existence of this phenomena (<xref rid="evad177-B41" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al. 2016</xref>), although some exceptions do exist (<xref rid="evad177-B35" ref-type="bibr">Weng et al. 2017</xref>). This suggests that there are differences in both the rate and type of mutations throughout the plastid genome. <xref rid="evad177-B24" ref-type="bibr">Robbins and Kelly (2023)</xref> have recently shown that the evolutionary rate of a plastid gene is contingent upon its positional proximity to the IR within the plastid genome. They found that angiosperm plastid genes that are situated farther away from the IR boundaries have exhibited a greater capacity to explore a wider range of sequence space on which natural selection can act. As a result, the location of a gene and the overall structure of the plastid genome have limited the capacity for adaptive modifications in the chloroplast.</p>
    <p>Nonidentical IR sequences escaping homogenization are rare; expansion and contraction create further genome rearrangements that resemble large inversions (<xref rid="evad177-B16" ref-type="bibr">Knox 2014</xref>). For example, if genes from one end of the SSC are moved to the IR through an expansion and then duplicated in both copies during a contraction, this will look like a large inversion has occurred across most of the SSC, with the new IR boundary as one endpoint. Such structural diversity is rare among most land plants, and the phylogenetic distribution of lineage-specific JS changes shows a conservative evolutionary trajectory. In contrast to angiosperms and nonvascular land plants, streptophytic green algae (<xref rid="evad177-B34" ref-type="bibr">Turmel et al. 2017</xref>), lycophytes (<xref rid="evad177-B31" ref-type="bibr">Smith 2009</xref>), ferns (<xref rid="evad177-B25" ref-type="bibr">Robinson et al. 2018</xref>), and gymnosperms (<xref rid="evad177-B5" ref-type="bibr">Chaw et al. 2018</xref>) exhibit remarkable structural variation. Despite the explosive growth of whole-genome sequences, many branches of the Archaeplastida phylogenetic tree remain unclear. Results from species that have not previously been explored may reveal fascinating structural variation, highlighting the need to continue investigating the evolutionary dynamics of plastid genomes.</p>
    <p>The essence of this exploration is based on comparative genomics through direct comparison of large-scale genetic material of different organisms between each other to gain a better understanding of species evolution and gene functions among plastid genomic regions. Detection of IR expansion/contraction and the correct identification of IRs and possible sequence errors are crucial for the study of structural diversity in plastid genomes (<xref rid="evad177-B2" ref-type="bibr">Amiryousefi et al 2018a</xref>). In recent years, IRscope (<xref rid="evad177-B3" ref-type="bibr">Amiryousefi et al. 2018b</xref>) became a widely applied tool to explore the evolutionary dynamics of IRs and to depict JS changes. Here, with the incorporation of a novel set of functions, we present an augmented version of this software (IRplus) that significantly facilitates the detection of the IR regions and deeper comparative analysis of more diverse plastid genomes.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="evad177-s1">
    <title>Program Description</title>
    <p>We provide downloadable source codes in an open-access format by expanding the functionality of the program beyond what we presented previously. The entire R source code, including all libraries and dependencies, is deposited at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/AmiryousefiLab/IRplus" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/AmiryousefiLab/IRplus</ext-link>. The online interactive version of the code is also accessible through <ext-link xlink:href="https://irscope.shinyapps.io/IRplus/" ext-link-type="uri">https://irscope.shinyapps.io/IRplus/</ext-link>. For enhanced clarity and more control on the program's utility, the updated code functions are formatted and organized in separate files, which require the installation of the RStudio package. All functions have been wrapped together in an R repository, allowing users to download and change the program according to their needs. In general, the main three updates of IRplus are the 1) enhanced ability to detect inverted repeats in the presence of minimal mismatches between these regions among a wider range of species; 2) updated coloring themes, which allow a more versatile depiction of the outputs; and 3) overall finetuning of the existing functions and their parameters based on our experience and user's feedbacks.</p>
    <sec id="evad177-s1.1">
      <title>Novel Inverted Repeat Detection</title>
      <p>By default, built-in methods for automated IR recognition in currently available software (e.g., <xref rid="evad177-B20" ref-type="bibr">Lohse et al. 2013</xref>) operate under the assumption that all IR sequences are identical and single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNP) can terminate IR detection (<xref rid="evad177-B40" ref-type="bibr">Zheng et al. 2020</xref>). Nonidentical IR sequences may arise from sequencing errors or from mutations escaping copy correction mechanisms. Recently, we developed a novel method to detect mismatches in IR regions (<xref rid="evad177-B40" ref-type="bibr">Zheng et al. 2020</xref>), and we adopted this algorithm in IRplus, resulting in a faster and more versatile IR detection. In brief, IRplus extracts corresponding genome sequences from the uploaded files and initiates subgenome formation and then maps reverse complement sequences by adjusting the start and endpoints of the IR regions. The optimum radius is determined by an internal function setting its parameters based on the positions of the genes in relation to the various junctions. Therefore, if the first neighboring gene to the JS is located <italic toggle="yes">x</italic> bp away, that distance will be used as the radius for that particular species and junction. Afterward, the program will repeat the process for the subsequent species with this learned parameter. If this value does not contain any gene marked in the sequence, a new longer distance is determined where the first neighboring gene of that species is detected and then recursively carried over to the previous species. This allows the scalable representation of genes present in the vicinity of the JS in a comparative manner between species under study. In the next step, the whole IR regions are shifted in a sliding window to detect mismatches among them. Finally, the differences between the IRs are highlighted if their sequences are nonidentical. If insertions, SNPs, and deletions are present among IRs, they will be marked with green, orange, and red dots, respectively. If mismatches are located near the JS, they are shown in the specific place where they occur. Otherwise, a text with the number of mismatches of each kind will appear in the middle of the resulting plot (<xref rid="evad177-F1" ref-type="fig">fig. 1</xref> and <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Data S1, Supplementary Material</xref> online).</p>
      <fig position="float" id="evad177-F1" fig-type="figure">
        <label><sc>Fig.</sc> 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Plot representing the JS across various groups of plants. To the left of each track, the plot shows the length of each plastid genome (bp), whereas JS are indicated above the tracks. Genes in the vicinity of the JS in forward (5′–3′) orientation on the positive strand (+) appear above the tracks, whereas genes in reverse (3′–5′) on the negative strand (−) are shown below the bars. The size (bp) of each quadripartite segment of the plastid genome is shown in the bars. Artificial changes were made in the sequences of <italic toggle="yes">Alteris fauriei</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Solanum lycopersicum</italic> as depicted in the plot. Other examples are based on plastid genome sequences retrieved directly from the NCBI by IRplus. In case of nonidentical IRs, errors are summarized in the center of the bars. The first number marks the total number of SNPs found in the IRs, whereas numbers after the slash indicate the presence of indels. Insertions are marked with plus (+), whereas deletions are marked with negative (−) signs.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="evad177f1" position="float"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec id="evad177-s1.2">
      <title>Versatile Coloring Schemes</title>
      <p>We outfitted IRplus with a new interactive interface and output themes that provide a considerably easier control and seamless regulation of the output. An option to analyze up to 20 species was added. The user interface changes dynamically according to the chosen number, and a validator section was added to track the number of species included in the analysis. IRplus first attempts to use external libraries, such as Biostrings (<xref rid="evad177-B22" ref-type="bibr">Pagés et al. 2022</xref>), coRdon (<xref rid="evad177-B8" ref-type="bibr">Elek et al. 2022</xref>), and genbankr (<xref rid="evad177-B4" ref-type="bibr">Becker and Lawrence 2022</xref>) to read compatible GenBank (.gb) files. If this is not possible, IRplus uses its own generic functions to extract necessary information regarding the structure of the genomes. One of the major changes in the updated version of the program is its compatibility with files exported from the popular software Geneious Prime (<xref rid="evad177-B15" ref-type="bibr">Kearse et al. 2012</xref>).</p>
      <p>Given the increasing quantity of deposited plastid genomes, it is important to have drawing tools with flexible coloring schemes that can render visual representations of genomes in a user-specified manner (<xref rid="evad177-B40" ref-type="bibr">Zheng et al. 2020</xref>). We outfitted IRplus with tools and coloring schemes to provide a foundation for more accurate IR expansion/contraction data display. It allows for sequential, divergent, and qualitative schemes that are readily comprehensible, including those with color vision deficiency. Users can choose from different predefined themes (e.g., cherry tree, sea, and sunset) to create visual representations of IR JS and corresponding genes. The resulting plots can be customized using random coloring options. A sample plot with only two species is also shown in the same tab, ensuring comparison of various plotting themes. The updated version of the program allows downloading of results in various file formats (e.g., pdf, png, jpeg, bmp, and tiff), thus simplifying downstream image processing.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="evad177-s1.3">
      <title>Updated Features</title>
      <p>Several bugs were fixed to extract species names from different file types. Following submission, the software will start a search for IR regions in the input files. The interactive timing meter provides insight into the calculation work and output variation, and the real-time interactive coloring theme may be utilized to simply generate the required output. Note that the species chosen will result in the identification of a consensus radius for each junction point of the to-be-plotted genes. This implies that the algorithm may not produce optimal results if the input files do not reflect closely related species. When this occurs, the application will alert the user so that the evolutionary distance of the underlying input species can be reduced. Note that the input files may consist of handwritten annotations, GenBank accession numbers, or associated GB files of chloroplast genomes. If no IR is found for some of the species, to avoid errors, the user is advised to run the program again without those species. It is important to note that IRplus is only a plotting tool and does not correct apparent annotation errors of plastid genomes present in the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI), for example, unexpected truncation of genes, misannotated exon–intron boundaries, or shifted replication of origin (<xref rid="evad177-B33" ref-type="bibr">Tillich et al. 2017</xref>; <xref rid="evad177-B2" ref-type="bibr">Amiryousefi et al. 2018a</xref>).</p>
      <p>In the Frequently Asked Question (FAQ) section, a new tab is added which is directly connected with GitHub issues section. Based on our experience, this may serve as an interactive forum where users can report bugs or ask relevant questions. Our experience showed number of issues with the use of IRscope in last years communicated to us by the users. These issues ranging from misidentification of the IR regions (due to aberrant dissimilarity of the IRs) to misplaced features of the genome on the resulting plots were addressed in the updated IRplus. Thanks to its improved detection method, also the scope of the input species is expanded considerably to encompass all IR-containing plastid genomes (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">supplementary Table S1, Supplementary Material</xref> online). IRplus was also improved in handling of the SSC reversion function as in a number of reported cases, IRscope failed to conserve the genomic structure at IR JS. Low memory space and its consequential disconnection from servers in IRscope was also bypassed by deploying IRplus on considerably enhanced machines leading to continuous analysis of up to 20 species at once.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="evad177-s2">
    <title>Conclusions</title>
    <p>IRplus is the update of the widely appreciated online IR detection and mapping software (IRscope) which is created to represent a more accurate genetic architecture of IR JS in plastid genomes. Due to its novel algorithm, IRplus determines the correct location of IRs despite the mismatches introduced in de novo plastid genomes due to sequencing and assembly error. Although the quality of the input files is still of paramount importance, IRplus offers an adaptive capability to partially overcome this issue in existence of the minimal anomalies in the genome sequences. Also, this freeware exhibits a high level of compatibility to annotation and assembly outputs of major tools in this space, such as Geneious and DOGMA. In addition to its many coloring schemes, IRplus allows a versatile interactive adjustment of the output. The free availability of the software’s source code provides yet an additional level of flexibility that allows more expert R users to adopt their results as necessary.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
      <label>evad177_Supplementary_Data</label>
      <media xlink:href="evad177_supplementary_data.zip">
        <caption>
          <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
        </caption>
      </media>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack id="ack1">
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <p>We thank the open-access support of Helsinki University Library. We thank the support of the Academy of Finland (no. 323711) grant awarded to L.M., Finnish Cultural Foundation grant to A.A., and the Eötvös Research Grant to P.P. The authors thank Derek Ho for assistance in editing the manuscript.</p>
  </ack>
  <sec id="evad177-s3">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <p><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary data</xref> are available at <italic toggle="yes">Genome Biology and Evolution</italic> online.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="evad177-s4">
    <title>Author Contributions</title>
    <p>All authors of the manuscript have read and agreed to its content and are accountable for all aspects of the accuracy and integrity of the manuscript in accordance with the ICMJE criteria. The study was conceived by A.A. and P.P. Supervised by A.A, the program was developed by C.D.M., revised by B.W., and tested by P.P. and A.A. Funding was gathered by L.M., who administered the project and supervised the work together with A.A. Resulting data and visualization features were interpreted by all authors. P.P. and A.A. wrote the manuscript which was read and revised by all authors.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="evad177-s5">
    <title>Data Availability</title>
    <p>The code described in the article is publicly available on GitHub at the repository (<ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/AmiryousefiLab/IRplus" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/AmiryousefiLab/IRplus</ext-link>, last accessed July 19, 2023). The documentation for the software can be accessed in the program's website (<ext-link xlink:href="https://irscope.shinyapps.io/IRplus/" ext-link-type="uri">https://irscope.shinyapps.io/IRplus/</ext-link>, last accessed July 19, 2023).</p>
  </sec>
  <ref-list id="ref1">
    <title>Literature Cited</title>
    <ref id="evad177-B1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="given-only"><given-names>Abdullah</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><year>2020</year>. <article-title>Complete chloroplast genomes of <italic toggle="yes">Anthurium huixtlense</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Pothos scandens</italic> (Pothoideae, Araceae): unique inverted repeat expansion and contraction affect rate evolution</article-title>. <source>J Mol Evol</source>. <volume>88</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>562</fpage>–<lpage>574</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32642873</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Amiryousefi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hyvönen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poczai</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2018a</year>. <article-title>The chloroplast genome structure of bittersweet (<italic toggle="yes">Solanum dulcamara</italic>): plastid genome structure evolution in Solanaceae</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>13</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<comment>e0196069</comment>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Amiryousefi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hyvönen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poczai</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2018b</year>. <article-title>IRscope: an online program to visualize the junction sites of chloroplast genomes</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>34</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>3030</fpage>–<lpage>3031</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29659705</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year><article-title>.</article-title><comment><italic toggle="yes">genbankr: parsing GenBank files into semantically useful objects</italic>. R package version 1.26.0.</comment></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chaw</surname><given-names>S-M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C-S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sudianto</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2018</year>. <part-title>Evolution of gymnosperm plastid genomes</part-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Chaw</surname><given-names>S-M</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></string-name></person-group>, editors. <source>Advances in botanical research, plastid genome evolution</source>. <volume>Vol. 85</volume>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge (MA)</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>. p. <fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>222</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>de Vries</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Vries</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. <article-title>Evolutionary genomic insights into cyanobacterial symbioses in plants</article-title>. <source>Quant Plant Biol</source>. <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>e16</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37077989</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. <article-title>Defining coalescent genes: theory meets practice in organelle phylogenomics</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source>. <volume>71</volume>:<fpage>476</fpage>–<lpage>489</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34191012</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B8">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Elek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuzman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vlahovicek</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. <comment><italic toggle="yes">coRdon: codon usage analysis and prediction of gene expressivity</italic>. R package version 1.16.0,</comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/BioinfoHR/coRdon" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/BioinfoHR/coRdon</ext-link></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B9">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gonçalves</surname><given-names>DJP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruhlman</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mandel</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year>. <article-title>Under the rug: abandoning persistent misconceptions that obfuscate organelle evolution</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source>. <volume>151</volume>:<fpage>106903</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32628998</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B10">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gonçalves</surname><given-names>DJP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2019</year>. <article-title>Incongruence between gene trees and species trees and phylogenetic signal variation in plastid genes</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source>. <volume>138</volume>:<fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>232</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31146023</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B11">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Goulding</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olmstead</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morden</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>1996</year>. <article-title>Ebb and flow of the chloroplast inverted repeat</article-title>. <source>Mol Gen Genet</source>. <volume>252</volume>:<fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>206</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8804393</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B12">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Havurinne</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tyystjärvi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year>. <article-title>Photosynthetic sea slugs induce protective changes to the light reactions of the chloroplasts they steal from algae</article-title>. <source>eLife</source><volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e57389</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33077025</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B13">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Irisarri</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Strassert</surname><given-names>JFH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burki</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year>. <article-title>Phylogenomic insights into the origin of primary plastids</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source>. <volume>71</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>120</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33988690</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B14">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jost</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><year>2022</year>. <article-title>Structural plastome evolution in holoparasitic Hydnoraceae with special focus on inverted and direct repeats</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol Evol</source>. <volume>14</volume>:<comment>evac077</comment>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B15">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kearse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><year>2012</year>. <article-title>Geneious Basic: an integrated and extendable desktop software platform for the organization and analysis of sequence data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>28</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1647</fpage>–<lpage>1649</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22543367</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B16">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Knox</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2014</year>. <article-title>The dynamic history of plastid genomes in the Campanulaceae sensu lato unique among angiosperms</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Aci USA</source>. <volume>111</volume>(<issue>30</issue>):<fpage>11097</fpage>–<lpage>11102</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B17">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kolodner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tewari</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>1979</year>. <article-title>Inverted repeats in chloroplast DNA from higher plants</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Aci USA</source>. <volume>76</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B19">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lockhart</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><year>2006</year>. <article-title>Heterotachy and tree building: a case study with plastids and eubacteria</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16151191</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B20">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drechsel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kahlau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2013</year>. <article-title>OrganellarGenomeDRAW – a suite of tools for generating physical maps of plastid and mitochondrial genomes and visualizing expression data sets</article-title>. <source>Nucl Acids Res</source>. <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>W575</fpage>–<lpage>W581</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23609545</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B21">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mower</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vickrey</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2018</year>. <part-title>Structural diversity among plastid genomes of land plants</part-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Chaw</surname><given-names>S-M</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></string-name></person-group>, editors. <source>Advances in botanical research, plastid genome Evolution</source>. <volume>Vol. 85</volume>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge (MA)</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>. p. <fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>292</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B22">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pagès</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aboyoun</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gentleman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>DebRoy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. <comment><italic toggle="yes">Biostrings: efficient manipulation of biological strings</italic>. R package version 2.66.0,</comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://bioconductor.org/packages/Biostrings" ext-link-type="uri">https://bioconductor.org/packages/Biostrings</ext-link></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B23">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>1982</year>. <article-title>Chloroplast DNA rearrangements are more frequent when a large inverted repeat sequence is lost</article-title>. <source>Cell</source><volume>29</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>537</fpage>–<lpage>550</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6288261</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B24">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>EHJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2023</year>. <article-title>The evolutionary constraints on angiosperm chloroplast adaptation</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol Evol</source>. <volume>15</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<comment>evad101</comment>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B25">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><year>2018</year>. <article-title>Mobile elements shape plastome evolution in ferns</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol Evol</source>. <volume>10</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2558</fpage>–<lpage>2571</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30165616</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B26">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ruhlman</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2018</year>. <part-title>Aberration of analogy? The atypical plastomes of Geraniaceae</part-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Chaw</surname><given-names>S-M</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></string-name></person-group>, editors. <source>Advances in botanical research, plastid genome Evolution</source>. <volume>Vol. 85</volume>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge (MA)</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>. p. <fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B27">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ruhlman</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blazier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sabir</surname><given-names>JSM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>Recombination dependent replication and gene conversion homogenize sequences and diversify plastid genome structure</article-title>. <source>Am J Bot</source>. <volume>104</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>559</fpage>–<lpage>572</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28400415</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B28">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sabir</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><year>2014</year>. <article-title>Evolutionary and biotechnology implications of plastid genome variation in the inverted-repeat-lacking clade of legumes</article-title>. <source>Plant Biotech J</source>. <volume>12</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>743</fpage>–<lpage>754</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B29">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sánchez-Baracaldo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raven</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pisani</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knoll</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>Early photosynthetic eukaryotes inhabited low-salinity habitats’</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Aci USA</source>. <volume>114</volume>(<issue>37</issue>):<fpage>E7737</fpage>–<lpage>E7745</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B30">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sibbald</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Archibald</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year>. <article-title>Genomic insights into plastid evolution</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol Evol</source>. <volume>12</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>978</fpage>–<lpage>990</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32402068</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B31">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <article-title>Unparalleled GC content in the plastid DNA of Selaginella</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>. <volume>71</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>627</fpage>–<lpage>639</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19774466</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B32">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Strassert</surname><given-names>JFH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Irisarri</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burki</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year>. <article-title>A molecular timescale for eukaryote evolution with implications for the origin of red algal-derived plastids</article-title>. <source>Nat Comm</source>. <volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1879</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B33">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tillich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><year>2017</year>. <article-title>GeSeq – versatile and accurate annotation of organelle genomes</article-title>. <source>Nucl Acids Res</source>. <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>W6</fpage>–<lpage>W11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28486635</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B34">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Turmel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Otis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lemieux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>Divergent copies of the large inverted repeat in the chloroplast genomes of ulvophycean green algae</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>994</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28428552</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B35">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruhlman</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>Expansion of inverted repeat does not decrease substitution rates in <italic toggle="yes">Pelargonium</italic> plastid genomes</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <volume>214</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>842</fpage>–<lpage>851</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27991660</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B36">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wicke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schneeweiss</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>DePamphilis</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quandt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2011</year>. <article-title>The evolution of the plastid chromosome in land plants: gene content, gene order, gene function</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>. <volume>76</volume>(<issue>3–5</issue>):<fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>297</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21424877</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B37">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>1987</year>. <article-title>Rates of nucleotide substitution vary greatly among plant mitochondrial, chloroplast, and nuclear DNAs</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Aci USA</source>. <volume>84</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>9054</fpage>–<lpage>9058</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B38">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Woloszynska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2010</year>. <article-title>Heteroplasmy and stoichiometric complexity of plant mitochondrial genomes – though this be madness, yet there's method in’t</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source>. <volume>61</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>657</fpage>–<lpage>671</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19995826</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B39">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zampini</surname><given-names>É</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Truche</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lepage</surname><given-names>É</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tremblay-Belzile</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brisson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2017</year>. <part-title>Plastid genome stability and repair</part-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X-Q</given-names></string-name></person-group>, editors. <source>Somatic genome variation in animals, plants, and microorganisms</source>. <publisher-loc>Hoboken, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd</publisher-name>. p. <fpage>119</fpage>–<lpage>163</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B40">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poczai</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hyvönen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amiryousefi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year>. <article-title>Chloroplot: an online program for the versatile plotting of organelle genomes</article-title>. <source>Fronti Genet</source>. <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>576124</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evad177-B41">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mower</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2016</year>. <article-title>Evolutionary dynamics of the plastid inverted repeat: the effects of expansion, contraction, and loss on substitution rates</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <volume>209</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1747</fpage>–<lpage>1756</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26574731</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
