<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?properties open_access?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1367-4803</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1367-4811</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">10172036</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37099718</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btad288</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">btad288</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Applications Note</subject>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading">
          <subject>Genetics and Population Analysis</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01060</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>twas_sim, a Python-based tool for simulation and power analysis of transcriptome-wide association analysis</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9670-3939</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Wang</surname>
          <given-names>Xinran</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Department of Population and Public Health Sciences, Keck School of Medicine, University of Southern California</institution>, Los Angeles, CA 90033, <country country="US">United States</country></aff>
        <xref rid="btad288-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
        <!--xwang505@usc.edu-->
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Lu</surname>
          <given-names>Zeyun</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Department of Population and Public Health Sciences, Keck School of Medicine, University of Southern California</institution>, Los Angeles, CA 90033, <country country="US">United States</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Bhattacharya</surname>
          <given-names>Arjun</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Department of Pathology and Laboratory Medicine, David Geffen School of Medicine, University of California, Los Angeles</institution>, Los Angeles, CA 90095, <country country="US">United States</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>Institute of Quantitative and Computational Biosciences, David Geffen School of Medicine, University of California, Los Angeles</institution>, Los Angeles, CA 90095, <country country="US">United States</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Pasaniuc</surname>
          <given-names>Bogdan</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Department of Pathology and Laboratory Medicine, David Geffen School of Medicine, University of California, Los Angeles</institution>, Los Angeles, CA 90095, <country country="US">United States</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>Department of Human Genetics, David Geffen School of Medicine, University of California, Los Angeles</institution>, Los Angeles, CA 90095, <country country="US">United States</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>Department of Computational Medicine, David Geffen School of Medicine, University of California, Los Angeles</institution>, Los Angeles, CA 90095, <country country="US">United States</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9352-5927</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Mancuso</surname>
          <given-names>Nicholas</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Department of Population and Public Health Sciences, Keck School of Medicine, University of Southern California</institution>, Los Angeles, CA 90033, <country country="US">United States</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>Department of Quantitative and Computational Biology, University of Southern California</institution>, Los Angeles, CA 90097, <country country="US">United States</country></aff>
        <xref rid="btad288-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
        <!--nmancuso@usc.edu-->
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name>
          <surname>Schwartz</surname>
          <given-names>Russell</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Associate Editor</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="btad288-cor1">Corresponding authors. Department of Population and Public Health Sciences, Keck School of Medicine, University of Southern California, Los Angeles, CA, USA. E-mail: <email>xwang505@usc.edu</email> (X.W.); <email>nmancuso@usc.edu</email> (N.M.)</corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <month>5</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2023-04-26">
      <day>26</day>
      <month>4</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>26</day>
      <month>4</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>39</volume>
    <issue>5</issue>
    <elocation-id>btad288</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>18</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>06</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="editorial-decision">
        <day>13</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>13</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="corrected-typeset">
        <day>10</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2023. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xlink:href="btad288.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <sec id="s1">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <p>Genome-wide association studies (GWASs) have identified numerous genetic variants associated with complex disease risk; however, most of these associations are non-coding, complicating identifying their proximal target gene. Transcriptome-wide association studies (TWASs) have been proposed to mitigate this gap by integrating expression quantitative trait loci (eQTL) data with GWAS data. Numerous methodological advancements have been made for TWAS, yet each approach requires <italic toggle="yes">ad hoc</italic> simulations to demonstrate feasibility. Here, we present <monospace>twas_sim</monospace>, a computationally scalable and easily extendable tool for simplified performance evaluation and power analysis for TWAS methods.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2">
        <title>Availability and implementation</title>
        <p>Software and documentation are available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/mancusolab/twas_sim" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/mancusolab/twas_sim</ext-link>.</p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>NIH</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100000002</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>R01HG012133</award-id>
        <award-id>R01GM140287</award-id>
        <award-id>R01CA258808</award-id>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="3"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec>
    <title>1 Introduction</title>
    <p>Genome-wide association studies (GWASs) have identified numerous genetic variants associated with complex traits and diseases (<xref rid="btad288-B18" ref-type="bibr">Visscher et al. 2017</xref>). However, most associated variants fall within non-coding regions, which makes identifying the target gene challenging (<xref rid="btad288-B6" ref-type="bibr">Hindorff et al. 2009</xref>; <xref rid="btad288-B3" ref-type="bibr">Edwards et al. 2013</xref>). Furthermore, functional evidence suggests that most GWAS hits are involved in regulatory processes (<xref rid="btad288-B10" ref-type="bibr">Maurano et al. 2012</xref>; <xref rid="btad288-B17" ref-type="bibr">Vierstra et al. 2020</xref>), which implies that causal variants regulate the expression of nearby genes. Transcriptome-wide association studies (TWASs) have been proposed to address this limitation by integrating expression quantitative trait loci (eQTL) data with GWAS data to identify functionally informed gene-level associations (<xref rid="btad288-B4" ref-type="bibr">Gamazon et al. 2015</xref>; <xref rid="btad288-B5" ref-type="bibr">Gusev et al. 2016</xref>). A growing ecosystem of methods have been developed around TWAS, each relying on different statistical assumptions (<xref rid="btad288-B9" ref-type="bibr">Mancuso et al. 2019</xref>; <xref rid="btad288-B11" ref-type="bibr">Nagpal et al. 2019</xref>; <xref rid="btad288-B2" ref-type="bibr">Bhattacharya et al. 2021</xref>; <xref rid="btad288-B7" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al. 2021</xref>; <xref rid="btad288-B15" ref-type="bibr">Tang et al. 2021</xref>; <xref rid="btad288-B8" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al. 2022</xref>; <xref rid="btad288-B12" ref-type="bibr">Parrish et al. 2022</xref>). Prior methodological work evaluated performance through a combination of <italic toggle="yes">ad hoc</italic> simulations and real data analysis. However, validating and assessing model performance requires researchers to implement custom simulations, which duplicates effort and can result in subtle differences in how baselines are defined.</p>
    <p>To address this, we developed <monospace>twas_sim</monospace>, a computationally scalable and easily extendable tool for downstream TWAS method evaluation and comparison (e.g., statistical power, false positive rate, etc.). It leverages real genetic data to capture typical linkage disequilibrium (LD) patterns and can simulate gene expression levels and complex traits under a variety of feasible genetic architectures. Importantly, it is capable of dynamically loading custom code (e.g., Python, R, and Julia) to evaluate independently developed TWAS methods. It is freely available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/mancusolab/twas_sim" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/mancusolab/twas_sim</ext-link>.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>2 Implementation</title>
    <p><monospace>twas_sim</monospace> is a python-based tool that uses real genotype data to generate TWAS test statistics by simulating complex traits as a function of latent expression levels, fitting eQTL weights in independent reference data, and performing genome- and predicted transcriptome-association testing on the simulated complex trait (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S1</xref>). <monospace>twas_sim</monospace> accepts optional arguments to vary eQTL/GWAS sample sizes, genetic architectures (e.g., <inline-formula id="IE1"><mml:math id="IM1" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IE2"><mml:math id="IM2" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula>, and sparsity of eQTL effects), horizontal pleiotropy through linkage, and reference genotype datasets for each step in the pipeline (e.g., GWAS, eQTL reference, and TWAS testing). For details on parameters and options, see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Tables S1</xref> and <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref> and <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Note</xref>.</p>
    <p><monospace>twas_sim</monospace> supports simulating GWAS summary data through two possible modes. Standard mode simulates genotypes for GWAS individuals using multivariate normal approximations parameterized by LD at the genomic region, simulates phenotypes under a fixed eQTL and trait architecture, and finally performs marginal regression at each approximate SNP to obtain GWAS summary statistics. When GWAS sample size, <inline-formula id="IE3"><mml:math id="IM3" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">GWAS</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, is large, this process requires large amounts of memory (i.e., <inline-formula id="IE4"><mml:math id="IM4" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">GWAS</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula id="IE5"><mml:math id="IM5" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the number of genetic variants. As a workaround, <monospace>twas_sim</monospace> supports fast mode, which simulates GWAS summary statistics directly using the multivariate normal distribution parameterized by LD (<xref rid="btad288-B13" ref-type="bibr">Pasaniuc and Price 2017</xref>). By making distributional assumptions of the underlying summary statistics, this setting bypasses the need for individual-level genotype data and requires memory only proportional to <inline-formula id="IE6"><mml:math id="IM6" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>, which can vastly reduce the memory footprint and vastly speed up simulation times (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Note</xref>). Importantly, to model LD misspecification, <monospace>twas_sim</monospace> supports the option to use different LD reference panels across GWAS and eQTL simulations in addition to TWAS testing. To predict gene expression levels into GWAS data, <monospace>twas_sim</monospace> supports internally fitting least absolute shrinkage and selection operator (LASSO), elastic net and genomic best linear unbiased prediction (GBLUP) linear prediction models from simulated reference gene expression data; in addition, it also allows users to use true eQTL effect sizes for TWAS calculation instead of regularization method (<xref rid="btad288-B14" ref-type="bibr">Searle et al. 1992</xref>; <xref rid="btad288-B16" ref-type="bibr">Tibshirani 1996</xref>; <xref rid="btad288-B21" ref-type="bibr">Zou and Hastie 2005</xref>). The dynamic import feature enables <monospace>twas_sim</monospace> to include external prediction tools easily. It requires only that users define a simple Python interface with a function named “fit” (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Note</xref> and <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Algorithms S1</xref> and <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref>). To illustrate the simplicity of our dynamic import approach, we have provided two example scripts in the repository to perform Ordinary Least Square (OLS) regression using sklearn and the Sum of Single Effects (SuSiE) sparse regression from susieR (<xref rid="btad288-B20" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al. 2020</xref>).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>3 Application</title>
    <p>To illustrate the utility of <monospace>twas_sim</monospace>, we performed simulations using genetic data from 1000Genomes (<xref rid="btad288-B1" ref-type="bibr">1000 Genomes Project Consortium 2015</xref>) across a variety of gene expression and complex trait architectures, and genotype reference panels (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Note</xref>). First, we investigated unbiasedness under null simulations (i.e., <italic toggle="yes">α</italic> = 0) under three metrics: Kolmogorov–Smirnov test on TWAS <italic toggle="yes">Z</italic>-scores, family-wise error rate (FWER) on TWAS <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value, and inflation (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Note</xref>). We found TWAS test statistics computed using Elastic Net are largely consistent with the null (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.26) and observed similar patterns for other linear models (see <xref rid="btad288-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>). Focusing on Elastic Net prediction models, we observed similar results under various eQTL architectures, eQTL/GWAS sample sizes, and simulation modes (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S3</xref>). Next, we evaluated FWER with found calibrated results across prediction models, eQTL architecture, eQTL/GWAS sample sizes, and simulation modes (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S2</xref>). Similarly, we found no inflation across all settings (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S3</xref>). Together, these results suggest that TWAS test statistics are robust to model assumptions.</p>
    <fig position="float" id="btad288-F1">
      <label>Figure 1.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>TWAS simulation results. (A) QQ plot for TWAS <italic toggle="yes">χ</italic><sup>2</sup> under the null hypothesis. Each point reflects the <italic toggle="yes">χ</italic><sup>2</sup> statistic under null simulations based on different predictive models. (B) TWAS power analysis. Each point reflects the proportion of simulations where the null was rejected at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 2.27<italic toggle="yes">E</italic>–06. <italic toggle="yes">X</italic>-axis reflects the proportion of trait variability explained by gene expression (C) Memory usage by simulation mode. Height of bars reflects the average memory usage for fast/standard simulation modes. All error bars reflect 95% confidence interval.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="btad288f1" position="float"/>
    </fig>
    <p>Next, we evaluated the power of each prediction model when a causal relationship between eQTL and complex trait exists (i.e., <italic toggle="yes">α</italic> ≠ 0). We observed Elastic Net (power = 0.66) outperformed GBLUP (power = 0.64), LASSO (power = 0.62), and SuSiE (power = 0.44; see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figs S4 and S5</xref>). We assessed power under various simulation settings and observed power increased with increasing <inline-formula id="IE7"><mml:math id="IM7" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula>, GWAS and eQTL sample sizes, eQTL and sparsity of eQTL architectures (see <xref rid="btad288-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>; <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figs S4</xref> and <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S5</xref>).</p>
    <p>To assess the degree to which LD misspecification affects TWAS test statistics, we performed simulations splitting 1000G EUR individuals into two subsets (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 244, 245). The first subset was used to simulate GWAS test statistics, whereas the second was used for eQTL simulation and downstream TWAS testing. Under the null, we found TWAS test statistics computed using the same reference panel (<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>=<italic toggle="yes"> 0</italic>.26) and the misspecified reference panel (<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>=<italic toggle="yes"> 0</italic>.57) were largely consistent (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S3</xref>), with similar estimates inflation (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.049) and moderately reduced FWER (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.005). In simulations under a causal model, we observed LD misspecification reduced power significantly compared with the correctly specified model (<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>=<italic toggle="yes"> </italic>2.2<italic toggle="yes">E</italic>–16; see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S6A–L</xref>).</p>
    <p>To highlight the scalability of <monospace>twas_sim</monospace> to extremely large GWAS sample sizes, we evaluated its performance under standard and fast simulation modes. We found fast mode required 6× and 36× less memory and 8× and 41× less CPU time compared with standard mode, for GWAS sample sizes of 100K and 500K, respectively (see <xref rid="btad288-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1C</xref> and <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S7</xref>).</p>
    <p>Lastly, to assess how horizontal pleiotropy through linkage (i.e., genes whose eQTLs are in LD with eQTLs for a causal gene) inflates TWAS test statistics, we simulated GWAS effect sizes independently from eQTLs and performed TWAS testing. Overall, we found that while TWAS test statistics at tagging genes were not as large as those computed using the causal gene (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S8A</xref>), we observed significantly inflated test statistics resulting in an elevated FWER (<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>= 0.02), which is consistent with previous works (<xref rid="btad288-B9" ref-type="bibr">Mancuso et al. 2019</xref>; <xref rid="btad288-B19" ref-type="bibr">Wainberg et al. 2019</xref>; <xref rid="btad288-B8" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al. 2022</xref>) emphasizing the need for joint testing of multiple nearby genes or statistical fine-mapping (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Note</xref> and <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S8B</xref>).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>4 Conclusion</title>
    <p>Here, we present <monospace>twas_sim</monospace>, a flexible and scalable computational simulation tool of TWAS test statistics. It simulates expression levels and complex traits under a variety of feasible genetic architectures. Simulation results are easily interpretable for downstream model evaluation. The simulator currently supports fitting LASSO, Elastic Net, and GBLUP prediction models to predict gene expression into GWAS. It is easily extendable with dynamic import function to include additional linear models to accommodate TWAS methods.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
      <label>btad288_Supplementary_Data</label>
      <media xlink:href="btad288_supplementary_data.docx">
        <caption>
          <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
        </caption>
      </media>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack id="ack1">
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <p>The authors thank members of Mancuso and Pasaniuc labs for helpful feedback. They also thank users who have submitted helpful feature requests and bug reports in previous implementations.</p>
  </ack>
  <sec>
    <title>Supplementary data</title>
    <p><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary data</xref> are available at <italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic> online.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
    <title>Conflict of interest</title>
    <p>None declared.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>Funding</title>
    <p>This work was supported by NIH [R01HG012133, R01GM140287, and R01CA258808].</p>
  </sec>
  <ref-list id="ref1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="btad288-B1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>1000 Genomes Project Consortium</collab>. <article-title>A global reference for human genetic variation</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>526</volume>:<fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26432245</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad288-B2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>MOSTWAS: multi-omic strategies for transcriptome-wide association studies</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>e1009398</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33684137</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad288-B3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beesley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>French</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Beyond GWASs: illuminating the dark road from association to function</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>93</volume>:<fpage>779</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24210251</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad288-B4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gamazon</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>; <collab>GTEx Consortium</collab>. <article-title>A gene-based association method for mapping traits using reference transcriptome data</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>1091</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26258848</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad288-B5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gusev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Integrative approaches for large-scale transcriptome-wide association studies</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>245</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26854917</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad288-B6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hindorff</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sethupathy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Junkins</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Potential etiologic and functional implications of genome-wide association loci for human diseases and traits</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>106</volume>:<fpage>9362</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19474294</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad288-B7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Multi-trait transcriptome-wide association studies with probabilistic Mendelian randomization</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>108</volume>:<fpage>240</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33434493</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad288-B8">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gopalan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Multi-ancestry fine-mapping improves precision to identify causal genes in transcriptome-wide association studies</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>109</volume>:<fpage>1388</fpage>–<lpage>404</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35931050</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad288-B9">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mancuso</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Freund</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Probabilistic fine-mapping of transcriptome-wide association studies</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>675</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30926970</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad288-B10">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Maurano</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Humbert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rynes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Systematic localization of common disease-associated variation in regulatory DNA</article-title>. <source>Science</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>337</volume>:<fpage>1190</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22955828</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad288-B11">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nagpal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>TIGAR: an improved Bayesian tool for transcriptomic data imputation enhances gene mapping of complex traits</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>258</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31230719</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad288-B12">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Parrish</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>TIGAR-V2: efficient TWAS tool with nonparametric Bayesian eQTL weights of 49 tissue types from GTEx V8</article-title>. <source>HGG Adv</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>100068</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35047855</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad288-B13">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pasaniuc</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>AL.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Dissecting the genetics of complex traits using summary association statistics</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27840428</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad288-B14">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Searle</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Casella</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCulloch</surname><given-names>CE.</given-names></string-name></person-group> Prediction of Random Variables. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Searle</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></string-name></person-group> (ed.), <source>Variance Components</source>. <publisher-loc>Nashville, TN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons 1992</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad288-B15">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buchman</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Jager</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Novel variance-component TWAS method for studying complex human diseases with applications to Alzheimer’s dementia</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>e1009482</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33798195</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad288-B16">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tibshirani</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Regression shrinkage and selection via the lasso</article-title>. <source>J R Stat Soc</source><year>1996</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad288-B17">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lazar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sandstrom</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Global reference mapping of human transcription factor footprints</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>583</volume>:<fpage>729</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32728250</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad288-B18">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Visscher</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wray</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>10 years of GWAS discovery: biology, function, and translation</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28686856</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad288-B19">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wainberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sinnott-Armstrong</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mancuso</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Opportunities and challenges for transcriptome-wide association studies</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>592</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30926968</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad288-B20">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carbonetto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>A simple new approach to variable selection in regression, with application to genetic fine mapping</article-title>. <source>J R Stat Soc Series B Stat Methodol</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>82</volume>:<fpage>1273</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad288-B21">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hastie</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Regularization and variable selection via the elastic net</article-title>. <source>J R Stat Soc Ser B Stat Methodol</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>301</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
