<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?properties open_access?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">NAR Genom Bioinform</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">NAR Genom Bioinform</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nargab</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>NAR Genomics and Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">2631-9268</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">10034587</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nargab/lqad030</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">lqad030</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI00030</subject>
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI00980</subject>
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01060</subject>
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01140</subject>
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01180</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Methods Article</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>DiSiR: fast and robust method to identify ligand–receptor interactions at subunit level from single-cell RNA-sequencing data</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1785-0234</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Vahid</surname>
          <given-names>Milad R</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Sanofi R&amp;D Data and Data Science, Artificial Intelligence &amp; Deep Analytics</institution>, Omics Data Science, 450 Water Street, <addr-line>Cambridge</addr-line>, MA <addr-line>02142</addr-line>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Kurlovs</surname>
          <given-names>Andre H</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Sanofi R&amp;D, Precision Medicine and Computational Biology</institution>, 350 Water Street, <addr-line>Cambridge</addr-line>, MA <addr-line>02142</addr-line>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Andreani</surname>
          <given-names>Tommaso</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Sanofi R&amp;D Data and Data Science, Artificial Intelligence &amp; Deep Analytics, Omics Data Science</institution>, Frankfurt am Main <addr-line>65926</addr-line>, <country country="DE">Germany</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Augé</surname>
          <given-names>Franck</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Sanofi R&amp;D Data and Data Science, Artificial Intelligence &amp; Deep Analytics, Omics Data Science</institution>, 1, Av Pierre Brossolette <addr-line>91385</addr-line>, Chilly-Mazarin, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Olfati-Saber</surname>
          <given-names>Reza</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Sanofi R&amp;D Data and Data Science, Artificial Intelligence &amp; Deep Analytics</institution>, Omics Data Science, 450 Water Street, <addr-line>Cambridge</addr-line>, MA <addr-line>02142</addr-line>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>de Rinaldis</surname>
          <given-names>Emanuele</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Sanofi R&amp;D, Precision Medicine and Computational Biology</institution>, 350 Water Street, <addr-line>Cambridge</addr-line>, MA <addr-line>02142</addr-line>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <name>
          <surname>Rapaport</surname>
          <given-names>Franck</given-names>
        </name>
        <!--franck.rapaport@sanofi.com-->
        <aff><institution>Sanofi R&amp;D Data and Data Science, Artificial Intelligence &amp; Deep Analytics</institution>, Omics Data Science, 450 Water Street, <addr-line>Cambridge</addr-line>, MA <addr-line>02142</addr-line>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>Sanofi R&amp;D, Precision Medicine and Computational Biology</institution>, 350 Water Street, <addr-line>Cambridge</addr-line>, MA <addr-line>02142</addr-line>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
        <xref rid="COR1" ref-type="corresp"/>
        <xref rid="FN1" ref-type="author-notes"/>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <name>
          <surname>Savova</surname>
          <given-names>Virginia</given-names>
        </name>
        <!--virginia.savova@sanofi.com-->
        <aff><institution>Sanofi R&amp;D, Precision Medicine and Computational Biology</institution>, 350 Water Street, <addr-line>Cambridge</addr-line>, MA <addr-line>02142</addr-line>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
        <xref rid="COR2" ref-type="corresp"/>
        <xref rid="FN1" ref-type="author-notes"/>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="COR1">To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 617 685 5118; Email: <email>franck.rapaport@sanofi.com</email></corresp>
      <corresp id="COR2">Correspondence may also be addressed to Virginia Savova. Email: <email>virginia.savova@sanofi.com</email></corresp>
      <fn id="FN1">
        <p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p>
      </fn>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <month>3</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2023-03-23">
      <day>23</day>
      <month>3</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>23</day>
      <month>3</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>5</volume>
    <issue>1</issue>
    <elocation-id>lqad030</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>17</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>29</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>09</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2023. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of NAR Genomics and Bioinformatics.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact <email>journals.permissions@oup.com</email></license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xlink:href="lqad030.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <p>Most cell–cell interactions and crosstalks are mediated by ligand–receptor interactions. The advent of single-cell RNA-sequencing (scRNA-seq) techniques has enabled characterizing tissue heterogeneity at single-cell level. In the past few years, several methods have been developed to study ligand–receptor interactions at cell type level using scRNA-seq data. However, there is still no easy way to query the activity of a specific user-defined signaling pathway in a targeted way or to map the interactions of the same subunit with different ligands as part of different receptor complexes. Here, we present DiSiR, a fast and easy-to-use permutation-based software framework to investigate how individual cells are interacting with each other by analyzing signaling pathways of multi-subunit ligand-activated receptors from scRNA-seq data, not only for available curated databases of ligand–receptor interactions, but also for interactions that are not listed in these databases. We show that, when utilized to infer ligand–receptor interactions from both simulated and real datasets, DiSiR outperforms other well-known permutation-based methods, e.g. CellPhoneDB and ICELLNET. Finally, to demonstrate DiSiR’s utility in exploring data and generating biologically relevant hypotheses, we apply it to COVID lung and rheumatoid arthritis (RA) synovium scRNA-seq datasets and highlight potential differences between inflammatory pathways at cell type level for control versus disease samples.</p>
    </abstract>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Sanofi</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100004339</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="11"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec sec-type="intro" id="SEC1">
    <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
    <p>Ligand-receptor interactions are crucial for the development and normal function of multicellular organisms. It comes as no surprise that drugs commonly produce their therapeutic effects by binding to specific receptors located on specific types of cells. Therefore, dissecting signaling pathways at cell type level is vital to further understand how multicellular organisms function, and to aid in deciphering drugs’ mechanisms of action and engineering future pharmaceuticals.</p>
    <p>The emergence of single-cell RNA-sequencing (scRNA-seq) technologies has made it possible to study cellular composition across tissues, including relatively more heterogeneous regions, such as cancers. Most available single-cell data analysis methods focus on the prediction of cell type labels and cellular differentiation trajectories (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1–3</xref>). However, it is now possible to measure the gene expressions of ligands and receptors in different cell types and systematically decode intercellular communication networks and their alterations in different diseases.</p>
    <p>Over the past recent years, many computational tools have been developed to study ligand–receptor (LR) interactions at cell type level using scRNA-seq data. Armingol <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) have categorized available computational tools, based on their underlying mathematical/statistical models, into the following main categories: (i) differential combination (or differentially expressed genes)-based methods (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5–8</xref>), (ii) expression permutation-based methods (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9–11</xref>), (iii) graph (or network)-based methods (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12–15</xref>) and (iv) array (or tensor)-based methods (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>).</p>
    <p>A well-known example of the first class is PyMINEr (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), which constructs a graph network wherein a connection between two genes indicates that their expressions are significantly correlated, and then integrates the graph structure with cell type enrichment analyses to identify cell type-specific expression patterns. SingleCellSignalR (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) is an example of the methods which belong to the second class. The authors compiled the contents of existing LR databases such as FANTOM5 (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>), HPRD (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), HPMR (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>), the IUPHAR/BPS Guide to Pharmacology (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>), and UniProtKB/Swissprot (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) into a novel database, referred to as LRdb. They then estimated the validity of each potential LR pair in LRdb by computing a score based on their gene expressions in the respective cell types. Efremova <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> adapted approaches of the second class to accommodate LR complexes with multi-subunits and introduced CellPhoneDB (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>) as a powerful tool to identify cellular communications in scRNA-seq data. ICELLNET (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>) is another example of methods from the second class that accounts for multiple LR subunits and is based on a score calculated as the geometric mean of ligand and receptor expressions. In NicheNet (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), which can be classified as a graph-based method (third class), LR links between interacting cells are obtained based on a score calculated by comparing gene expression data with the ligand-signaling network using the Personalized PageRank algorithm (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). As an important effort to use linear algebraic and tensor-based approaches to better understand cell signaling networks, Tsuyuzaki <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> have recently introduced scTensor which is based on non-negative tensor decomposition (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). In this method, in contrast to conventional methods, cell–cell interactions (CCIs) are regarded as hypergraphs between graphs made of cell types (nodes) and LR pairs (edges) and are represented as tensors as opposed to two-dimensional matrices.</p>
    <p>What all these methods have in common is that they are not designed to focus on specific custom LR interactions, especially when both ligands and receptors contain multiple subunits, and instead interrogate all the interactions that are listed in their built-in database. In this paper, we present a fast and easy-to-use computational method, referred to as DiSiR (DiSiR: <underline>Di</underline>mer <underline>Si</underline>gnal <underline>R</underline>eceptor Analysis), which builds upon the framework from existing expression permutation-based methods such as CellPhoneDB that also address this capacity. In contrast to CellPhoneDB, which uses an average expression of ligand–receptor pairs for its upstream statistical analysis, here, in DiSiR, we consider the product of ligand and receptor expressions in our analysis. Our method accepts user-defined LR input, including readily available curated LR databases, and has been specifically optimized to analyze complex pathways involving multi-subunit receptor complexes with multi-subunit ligands, or hypothetical interactions. Unlike other methods which emphasize the overall number of interactions across cell types, we have focused on visualizing which cell types interact directionally. In this manuscript, we evaluate the performance of DiSiR using a ‘gold-standard’ LR interaction database (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Zhou <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> analyzed these interactions in scRNA-seq data from melanoma patients and generated a corresponding cell–cell communication network (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). We use this network as the expected results to benchmark the performance of DiSiR against well-known available permutation-based methods CellPhoneDB (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) and ICELLNET (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). We also extend our benchmarking analysis by simulating several ground truth datasets using a simulation scheme proposed in (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="SEC2">
    <title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title>
    <sec id="SEC2-1">
      <title>Overview of the method</title>
      <p>DiSiR is designed to enable identifying single multi-subunit ligand–receptor interactions at cell type level through the following algorithm (Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>):</p>
      <list list-type="bullet">
        <list-item>
          <p>Assume the subunits of ligand <italic toggle="yes">L</italic> and receptor <italic toggle="yes">R</italic> are denoted by <inline-formula><tex-math id="M0001" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${L_1},\ {L_2},\ \cdots ,\ {L_N}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><tex-math id="M0001a" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${R_1},\ {R_2},\ \cdots ,\ {R_M}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, respectively. We refer to the cells of cell types <italic toggle="yes">A</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B</italic> as clusters <italic toggle="yes">A</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>For each <inline-formula><tex-math id="M0002" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${L_i}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>–<inline-formula><tex-math id="M0003" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${R_j}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> subunit interaction, where <inline-formula><tex-math id="M0004" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$K{\rm{\: }}\{ {( {{L_i},\ {R_j}} )} \} \in \{ {( {{L_n},\ {R_m}} )|n\ = \ 1, \cdots ,N,\ m\ = \ 1, \cdots ,M} \}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> denotes a set of all ligand–receptor subunit pairs listed in the input interactions list, calculate ‘clusters A and B average expressions’ by calculating the average expressions of <inline-formula><tex-math id="M0005" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${L_i}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><tex-math id="M0006" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${R_j}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> over all the cells within clusters <italic toggle="yes">A</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>, respectively. If a ligand or receptor subunit is not expressed in at least one of the resulting average expressions, then it will be removed from the input interactions for the cell type <italic toggle="yes">A–</italic>cell type <italic toggle="yes">B</italic> communication, i.e. it will not be included in the rest of the analysis.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>Generate <inline-formula><tex-math id="M0007" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$k$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> sets of ‘shuffled clusters <inline-formula><tex-math id="M0008" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$A\text{'}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><tex-math id="M0009" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$B\text{'}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> average expressions’ by randomly permuting the cluster assignment of all cells and re-calculating the average expressions of <inline-formula><tex-math id="M00010" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${L_i}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><tex-math id="M00011" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${R_j}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> over all the cells belonging to the new random clusters <inline-formula><tex-math id="M00012" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$A\text{'}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><tex-math id="M00013" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$B\text{'}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> (the default value for <inline-formula><tex-math id="M00014" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$k$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> is 1000).</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>The <inline-formula><tex-math id="M00015" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${L_i}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>–<inline-formula><tex-math id="M00016" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${R_j}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> subunit interaction is considered by DiSiR as a significant interaction if the product of clusters A and B average expressions is significantly higher than the products of shuffled clusters <inline-formula><tex-math id="M00017" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$A\text{'}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><tex-math id="M00018" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$B\text{'}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> average expressions according to a two-sided non-parametric permutation test (results with a <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value &lt; 0.05 are considered significant).</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>DiSiR identifies a L–R interaction between cell types <italic toggle="yes">A</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B</italic> as significant if<inline-formula><tex-math id="M00019" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${\rm{\ }}{L_i}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>–<inline-formula><tex-math id="M00020" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${R_j}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> subunit interactions are significant for all subunit combinations listed in the input interactions list.</p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
      <fig position="float" id="F1">
        <label>Figure 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Schematic overview and illustration of the ease-of-use of DiSiR framework. (<bold>A</bold>) DiSiR uses as input 1) a single-cell gene expression matrix, 2) cell type annotations, and 3) a list of putative ligand–receptor interactions at subunit level. DiSiR then characterizes the ligand ‘L’–receptor ‘R’ interaction between cell types ‘A’ and ‘B’ based on the products of expressions of ‘L’ subunits by cell type ‘A’ and expressions of ‘R’ subunits by cell type ‘B’. This interaction is identified by DiSiR as a significant interaction if these products are significantly higher than random shuffling results for all ‘L–R’ subunit combinations. (<bold>B</bold>) Diagram that shows the workflow of data processing, filtering, and visualization of the obtained results in DiSiR. Weak interactions are filtered out if the fraction of cells expressing the ligand (or receptor) within its corresponding cell type is less than a threshold <inline-formula><tex-math id="M00021" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$Th$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>. DiSiR also provides an interactive graph-based representation module and heatmap/bubble plots to show the resulting interactions for complex signaling pathways at different level.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="lqad030fig1" position="float"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2-2">
      <title>Single-cell data sets and data pre-preprocessing steps</title>
      <p>We tested DiSiR on a couple of pathways in two publicly available single-cell datasets. We obtained lung COVID-19 single-cell transcriptomic data from GEO145926 (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) and the AMP consortium's Phase 1 rheumatoid arthritis (RA) data from <ext-link xlink:href="https://immunogenomics.io/ampra/" ext-link-type="uri">https://immunogenomics.io/ampra/</ext-link> (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). We subsequently filtered the data based on empirically customized standard procedures. We only kept cells for further analysis if they had at least 1000 genes and at most 20% of the genes were mitochondrial (COVID), or if they had at least 200 genes and at most 10% of the genes were mitochondrial (AMP RA Phase 1). We then normalized total barcode counts in each of the two datasets so that each cell had the same total normalized read count. Afterwards, we used SPRING (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>), a web-based software tool to visualize high dimensional transcriptomic data, with 60 (COVID) and 30 principal components (AMP RA Phase 1). We then annotated the cells with SignacX version 2.2.0 (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>)– a neural network-based cell annotation tool that uses expression data and is also aided by the edges from the SPRING plot. Finally, we transferred the resulting annotated expression data into log2 space for DiSiR analysis.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2-3">
      <title>Filtering approach</title>
      <p>DiSiR uses a filtering approach to discard weak interactions that might be associated with noise by thresholding the fraction of cells expressing each ligand/receptor subunit within its corresponding cell type. The user can visualize this metric for combinations of signaling pathway components and cell types using a bubble plot in which the size of each circle is associated with the corresponding fraction and the color of each circle is related to the max-normalized average expression of each LR subunit within its corresponding cell type (e.g. see Figure <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2B</xref>). A LR interaction between two cell types is then retained if this score is higher than a certain threshold level <inline-formula><tex-math id="M00022" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$0 \le Th \le 1$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> for all ligand/receptor subunits. We provide an analysis framework using sensitivity scores, across all possible threshold values, to determine the optimal value for <inline-formula><tex-math id="M00023" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$Th$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> (see the ‘Results and discussion’ section). Users also have the freedom to be more stringent on the value of <italic toggle="yes">Th</italic> in order to focus on stronger interactions. By default, <italic toggle="yes">Th</italic> is set to 0 (see justification in the validation and benchmarking section).</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F2">
        <label>Figure 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Analysis of Calprotectin signaling pathways at cell type level from RA synovium scRNA-seq data. (<bold>A</bold>) SPRING representation of RA synovium scRNA-seq data (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) and the corresponding cell type labels assigned to each cell. (<bold>B</bold>) Bubble plot illustrating max-normalized average expressions of the calprotectin signaling pathway components including ligand subunits, <italic toggle="yes">S100A8</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S100A9</italic>, and the <italic toggle="yes">TLR4</italic> receptor, per cell type (color of the circles), and fraction of cells expressing them within its corresponding cell type (size of the circles; adjusted by the total number of cells expressing the respective gene). (<bold>C</bold>) Left panel is the heatmap depicting all putative cell–cell communications of the <italic toggle="yes">S100A8|TLR4 + S100A9|TLR4</italic> pathway (when both interactions are presented). The colormap shows the strength of interaction between the cell types. The middle and right panels show the chord diagram and graph representation of significant <italic toggle="yes">S100A8|TLR4 + S100A9|TLR4</italic> interactions between different cell types identified by DiSiR, respectively.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="lqad030fig2" position="float"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2-4">
      <title>Graph and heatmap plot representation</title>
      <p>We propose three visualizations for the output cell–cell interactions: graph representation, heatmap plots, and chord diagrams. Graph representation is a directed graph in which each node is a cell type present in the input data set and each edge corresponds to an LR interaction between two cell types, from ligand-expressing cells to receptor-expressing cells. We use self-loops on the corresponding node to denote ligand and receptor present in the same cell type. We use the ‘visNetwork version 2.1.0’ package in R version 4.0.0 with an interactive environment. Heatmap plots illustrate all interactions (including above threshold interactions) between different cell types listed in rows and columns of the heatmaps. The thickness of links in graph representation and the color intensity in heatmap representation are associated with the strength of interactions between cell types. Finally, we use ‘circlize version 0.4.15’ package to generate chord diagrams for circular visualization of the output interactions (see Figure <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2C</xref> for the examples of these different plots). Single-cell clustering plots were also visualized using SPRING and Harmony (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) version 0.1.0 (for the COVID data).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2-5">
      <title>Ligand-receptor interaction strength</title>
      <p>DiSiR identifies significant interactions based on the product of the expressions of ligand and receptor subunits. The L-–R interaction strength is defined as</p>
      <disp-formula id="M1">
        <label>(1)</label>
        <tex-math id="M00024" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\begin{equation*}Interaction\_Strength_{LR}{\rm{\:}}\frac{1}{{\left| K \right|}}\mathop \sum \limits_{\left( {{L_i},{R_j}} \right) \in K} {e_{{L_i}\ }}{e_{{R_j}\ }},\end{equation*}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
      </disp-formula>
      <p>where <inline-formula><tex-math id="M00025" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${e_{{L_1}\ }},\ {e_{{L_2}\ }},\ \cdots ,\ {e_{{L_N}\ }}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>and <inline-formula><tex-math id="M00026" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${e_{{R_1}\ }},\ {e_{{R_2}\ }},\ \cdots ,\ {e_{{R_M}\ }}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, denote log<sub>2</sub> expressions of ligand L and receptor R subunits expressed by cell types <italic toggle="yes">A</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>, respectively, <inline-formula><tex-math id="M00027" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$K\ = \ \{ {( {{L_i},\ {R_j}} )} \}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> is a set of all ligand–receptor subunit pairs listed in the input interactions list, and <inline-formula><tex-math id="M00028" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$| K |$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> is the number of elements of <inline-formula><tex-math id="M00029" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$K$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2-6">
      <title>Performance evaluation scores</title>
      <p>We compare the identified LR interactions with a ‘gold-standard’ LR interaction database at cell type level (see the ‘Validation and benchmarking analysis of DiSiR across different methods’ section). For each cell type, we categorize the identified interactions which are included in the expected interactions as true positives and the ones that are absent from the expected interactions as false positives. The expected interactions that are not matched with any identified interaction are referred to as false negatives. Finally, the interactions that are neither identified by the method nor listed in the expected interactions are true negatives. Denoting the number of true positives by TP, the number of true negatives by TN, the number of false negatives by FN, and the number of false positives by FP, we define the precision (<inline-formula><tex-math id="M00030" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$Pr$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>) and sensitivity (<inline-formula><tex-math id="M00031" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$Sn$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>) measures as</p>
      <disp-formula id="M2">
        <label>(2)</label>
        <tex-math id="M00032" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\begin{equation*}Pr\ = \frac{{TP}}{{TP + FP}}\ \ Sn\ = \frac{{TP}}{{TP + FN}}\ \end{equation*}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
      </disp-formula>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="results" id="SEC3">
    <title>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</title>
    <p>DiSiR uses a single-cell gene expression matrix, cell type annotations, and a list of putative ligand–receptor interactions at subunit level as input (Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). DiSiR identifies the ligand ‘L’–receptor ‘R’ interaction between cell types ‘<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>’ and ‘<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>’ based on the products of log-normalized expressions of ‘L’ subunits by cell type ‘A’ and log-normalized expressions of ‘R’ subunits by cell type ‘<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>’. This interaction is considered by DiSiR as significant if these products are significantly higher than the result of random shuffling of cell type labels for all ‘L–R’ subunit combinations. DiSiR can also optionally filter out interactions between cell types with low fractions or total numbers of cells expressing the LR subunits (see ‘Materials and Methods’ section).</p>
    <sec id="SEC3-1">
      <title>Analysis of individual multi-subunit ligand–receptor interactions at cell type level</title>
      <p>We have applied DiSiR on a Rheumatoid Arthritis (RA) scRNA-seq dataset (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) to analyze the <italic toggle="yes">S100A8/A9</italic> (calprotectin) signaling pathway (Figure <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S1</xref>). The SPRING (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) plot of the RA synovium revealed a total of 8990 cells (Figure <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2A</xref>; see Materials and Methods for details). Of those cells, all but 691 were annotated by SignacX (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). As a test-case, we explored the calprotectin-toll-like-receptor 4 (<italic toggle="yes">CLP/TLR4</italic>) pathway, in which the proteins encoded by <italic toggle="yes">S100A8</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S100A9</italic> combine into a dimer and bind <italic toggle="yes">TLR4</italic>. This pathway is a known biomarker of RA (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>) that is currently absent from most available LR databases, including the CellPhoneDB database. This result serves as proof of concept that DiSiR is capable of quickly interrogating a pathway, as well as shedding additional light on the biology of this interaction. Indeed, the higher weights of the links connecting macrophages (Figure <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2C</xref>) suggest that macrophages are the primary signaling cells, signaling mainly to themselves and to monocytes. Note that we use the following notation in the interaction graph: there is a link <italic toggle="yes">L1 | R1 + L2 | R2</italic> between two nodes <italic toggle="yes">C1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">C2</italic>, if cell types <italic toggle="yes">C1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">C2</italic> communicate with each other through the ligand L–receptor R interactions, where <italic toggle="yes">L1, L2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">R1, R2</italic> are subunits of L and R, respectively. In addition, we observe signals in cells that are not part of the immune system (annotated as ‘Fibroblasts’ and ‘NonImmune’ by SignacX). These findings are consistent with the existing paradigm that <italic toggle="yes">CLP</italic> is released by phagocytes and binds <italic toggle="yes">TLR4</italic> on other phagocytic cells as well as on non-immune cells (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>); it also contains the resolution and the granularity that is more specific to the AMP RA Phase1 dataset and that can help narrow down the exact mechanism of <italic toggle="yes">CLP</italic> signaling in RA.</p>
      <p>In addition to <italic toggle="yes">CLP</italic>, we also tested DiSiR on the classical <italic toggle="yes">IL6</italic> signaling pathway that requires both <italic toggle="yes">IL6ST</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">IL6R</italic> receptor subunits (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>). As with <italic toggle="yes">CLP</italic>, the <italic toggle="yes">IL6</italic> pathway is also elevated in RA. DiSiR predicts that, in RA synovium, <italic toggle="yes">IL6</italic> is primarily secreted by B-cells, which is consistently with a recent review of the role of <italic toggle="yes">IL6</italic> in RA (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>), while CD4 + T-cells constitute the main receiving immune cell type. The role of <italic toggle="yes">IL6</italic> signaling to CD4+ T-cells has already attracted researchers’ attention (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). However, another immune cell type associated with <italic toggle="yes">IL6</italic> secretion in the review—macrophages—were not found as major secretors of <italic toggle="yes">IL6</italic> in the AMP RA dataset, and we did not independently observe a high level of expression of <italic toggle="yes">IL6</italic> in the macrophages (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S2B</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC3-2">
      <title>Application of DiSiR to analyze and visualize complex immunoinflammatory signaling pathways in COVID-19 scRNA-seq data</title>
      <p>As another application, we wanted to focus on the differences in cell–cell communications in more complex inflammatory signaling pathways for disease versus control samples. For this purpose, we have applied DiSiR on a lung scRNA-seq dataset to analyze the <italic toggle="yes">IL6/IL11</italic> (Figure <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) and <italic toggle="yes">IL1RAP</italic> (Figure <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) signaling pathways for COVID-19 versus healthy samples (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). As a member of <italic toggle="yes">IL6</italic> family cytokines, <italic toggle="yes">IL11</italic> competes with <italic toggle="yes">IL6</italic> for its joint receptor subunit <italic toggle="yes">IL6ST</italic>. More specifically, <italic toggle="yes">IL11</italic> binds to another receptor subunit <italic toggle="yes">IL11R</italic> and forms a complex with <italic toggle="yes">IL6ST</italic>, which activates the downstream signaling through the activation of <italic toggle="yes">STAT3</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">ERK</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">PI3K</italic> pathways (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Our results find a potential enrichment in LR interactions between monocytes and macrophages as well as between monocytes and T cells (CD4+, CD8+ and Tregs) in COVID patients compared to healthy controls (Figure <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S3</xref>), which is consistent with previous results for severe COVID (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>).</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F3">
        <label>Figure 3.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Study of <italic toggle="yes">IL6/IL11</italic> signaling pathways for COVID-19 versus healthy control samples using DiSiR from lung scRNA-seq data. (<bold>A</bold>) SPRING representation of lung scRNA-seq data and its corresponding cell types. (<bold>B</bold>) Heatmap plot and (<bold>C</bold>) chord diagrams illustrating the difference between cell–cell communications identified by DiSiR for the <italic toggle="yes">IL6/IL11</italic> signaling pathway, i.e. <italic toggle="yes">IL6|IL6R + IL6|IL6ST</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">IL11|IL116A + IL11|IL6ST</italic>, between COVID-19 versus control samples in lung scRNA-seq data, using the default threshold level (<italic toggle="yes">Th</italic>= 0). As can be seen, no significant <italic toggle="yes">IL11|IL116A + IL11|IL6ST</italic> interaction is identified by DiSiR across healthy samples.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="lqad030fig3" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <fig position="float" id="F4">
        <label>Figure 4.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Study and illustrations of complex multi-subunits <italic toggle="yes">IL1RAP</italic> signaling pathways for COVID versus control samples using DiSiR from lung scRNA-seq data. (<bold>A</bold>) Heatmap plot illustrating the differences between cell–cell communications identified by DiSiR for the <italic toggle="yes">IL1RAP</italic> signaling pathway between COVID-19 and control samples in lung scRNA-seq data. The colormap shows the strength of interaction between the cell types. Chord diagram representation of significant ligand–receptor interactions, involved in the <italic toggle="yes">IL1RAP</italic> signaling pathway, e.g<italic toggle="yes">. IL1A|IL1RAP + IL1A|IL1R1, IL1B|IL1RAP + IL1B|IL1R1, IL1RN|IL1RAP + IL1RN|IL1RL1, IL33|IL1RAP + IL33|IL1RL1, IL36B|IL1RAP + IL36B|IL1RL2, IL36G|IL1RAP + IL36G|IL1RL2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">IL36RN|IL1RAP + IL36RN|IL1RL2</italic>, between different cell types identified by DiSiR for (<bold>B</bold>) healthy versus (<bold>C</bold>) COVID samples using the default threshold level (<italic toggle="yes">Th</italic>= 0).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="lqad030fig4" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>We also analyzed the <italic toggle="yes">IL1RAP</italic> pathway, which is involved in three signaling cascades that affect many <italic toggle="yes">IL1</italic> family cytokines, such as <italic toggle="yes">IL1A</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">IL1B</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">IL33</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">IL36</italic>, in different diseases (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). They then form seven multi-subunit pairs. It has been shown that <italic toggle="yes">IL1RAP</italic> and the majority of the components involved in its signaling pathway are differentially expressed between the airways of COVID-19 patients and SARS-CoV-2 negative patients according to nasopharyngeal swabs data (q-value for <italic toggle="yes">IL1RAP</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">IL1A</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">IL1B</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">IL36A</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">IL36B</italic> are <inline-formula><tex-math id="M00033" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$1.97 \times {10^{ - 10}}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, 0.00185, 0.015, 0.05 and 0.023, respectively) (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). We have applied DiSiR to the COVID-19 data to study the <italic toggle="yes">IL1RAP</italic> signaling pathway at cell type level. We found an enrichment of LR interactions between ligand-expressing monocytes/macrophages and neutrophils, and receptor-expressing monocytes/macrophages, epithelial and regulatory T cells (T-regs) in COVID-19 (Figure <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC3-3">
      <title>Validation and benchmarking analysis of DiSiR across different methods</title>
      <p>To evaluate the performance of DiSiR, we first used a published LR interaction database (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). This database is a part of FANTOM5 and includes ∼2500 LR pairs over 144 primary cell types, which represents a large-scale map of cell-to-cell communication in human. Zhou <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) investigated these interactions in the transcriptomes of ∼4000 single cells isolated from melanoma patients (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>), including both malignant tumor cells and stromal and immune cells. By manually comparing the LR pair expression patterns among seven major cell types present in this data (melanoma cells, T cells, B cells, macrophages, NK cells, cancer-associated fibroblasts (CAF), and endothelial cells), the authors were able to build a cell–cell communication map indicating which cell types interacts with each other based on specific LR links (Figure <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S4</xref>). We use this melanoma disease map (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) as the expected results and benchmark the performance of DiSiR against well-known available permutation-based methods CellPhoneDB and ICELLNET, which are comparable to DiSiR in terms of required input, underlying approach, and output results (we have used the same melanoma dataset (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>) as Zhou <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) in our benchmarking analysis).</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F5">
        <label>Figure 5.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Melanoma disease network. (<bold>A</bold>) Chord diagram representation of cell–cell interaction network between cancer cells and different cell types identified by DiSiR. (<bold>B</bold>) Cell-cell interaction network between cancer and non-cancer cells in the melanoma dataset extracted in (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) using the same melanoma scRNA-seq data (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>) as part (A).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="lqad030fig5" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>We compute recall (sensitivity) and precision measures (see the ‘Performance evaluation scores’ in Materials and Methods for more details) associated with the identification of LR interactions at cell type level, between cancer cells and the other cell types, across different threshold values for all methods. We want to emphasize that the same LR database has been used to search over for all the methods used in the paper, e.g. DiSiR, CellPhoneDB, and ICELLNET. The obtained results show that DiSiR outperforms the other methods in terms of sensitivity across different threshold values ranging from 0 and 1 (Figure <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> and Supplementary Table S1). DiSiR also displays a better precision compared to the other related methods for lower threshold values, where enough interactions have been identified for all the methods (for instance, at <italic toggle="yes">Th</italic> = 0, DiSiR, CellPhoneDB and ICELLNET identify 89, 135 and 161 interactions, respectively). For some of the higher threshold values, CellPhoneDB has a better precision score than DiSiR. However, CellPhoneDB only identifies a very low number of LR interactions at these threshold values. For example, at <italic toggle="yes">Th</italic> = 0.2, the number of identified interactions by CellPhoneDB is only equal to 10 (DiSiR has identified 72 interactions in this case) and this number is reduced to zero by further increasing the threshold value (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S1</xref> for more details).</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F6">
        <label>Figure 6.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Technical assessment of DiSiR using a gold-standard melanoma cellular network. Sensitivity and precision scores, shown in (<bold>A</bold>) boxplot and (<bold>B</bold>) tabular forms, across different threshold (fraction of cells expressing the relevant genes) values for DiSiR versus CellPhoneDB and ICELLNET (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S1</xref> for the whole results).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="lqad030fig6" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>To further evaluate the precision and sensitivity of DiSiR, we have applied DiSiR and CellphoneDB to the RA dataset and calculated sensitivity and precision scores using the reconstructed IL6 signaling network in RA disease, provided in Figure 1D of (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>), as the expected results. We have calculated these scores at different threshold values, restricting our analysis to thresholds for which we could still capture a signal. We have repeated similar analyses on the COVID-19 dataset, using the monocyte-immune cell interaction network in COVID disease provided in Figure 3 of a recent publication (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) as expected results and focusing on the IL6 signaling pathway. As can be seen in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S5</xref>, DiSiR’s sensitivity scores are significantly better than CellPhoneDB’s for almost all threshold values for both datasets. Since the expected IL6 pathway networks in both RA and COVID are relatively sparse, DiSiR’s and CellPhoneDB’s results are both enriched in false positive, leading to relatively poor precision scores for both methods. As shown in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S5B</xref>, for the COVID data, DiSiR continues to outperform CellPhoneDB significantly in terms of precision as well.</p>
      <p>As we prioritize sensitivity, we have decided to set the optimal threshold obtained in this case (<inline-formula><tex-math id="M00034" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$Th\ = \ 0$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>) as default, with the option for the user to choose their own threshold. This low optimal threshold value suggests that DiSiR performs well even when there are fewer cells expressing the ligands/receptors of interest. We used this default value to analyze other scRNA-seq data sets in this paper, e.g. the RA and COVID-19 lung scRNA-seq data.</p>
      <p>We have also generated several ‘simulated expected results’ using a simulation scheme adapted from (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). We have designed three scenarios to evaluate the performance of DiSiR compared to the other permutation-based approaches, e.g. CellPhoneDB and ICELLNET. Each scenario has six simulated datasets and every dataset consists of 16672 genes and 11 cell clusters, i.e. cell types. The expression levels were generated from normal distributions, where the parameters of means and standard deviations for each gene in each cell cluster were derived from real single-cell RNA-seq datasets (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). In each dataset, there are 100 randomly selected ligand–receptor pairs between randomly selected cell types that are ‘highly upregulated’ or ‘moderately upregulated’ in different scenarios as below:</p>
      <list list-type="bullet">
        <list-item>
          <p>Scenario 1: Both randomly selected ligands and receptors are ‘highly upregulated’.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>Scenario 2: The selected ligands and receptors are ‘highly upregulated’ and ‘moderately upregulated’, respectively.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>Scenario 3: The selected ligands and receptors are ‘moderately upregulated’ and ‘highly upregulated’, respectively.</p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
      <p>In order to simulate the ‘high upregulation’, a constant expression level <inline-formula><tex-math id="M00035" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${e_h} \ge 0$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> was added to the normalized expressions of the selected genes within each cluster (see the supplementary notes of (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>) for more detail about the normalization step). Whereas, to simulate the ‘moderate upregulation’, a randomly sampled expression level <inline-formula><tex-math id="M00036" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${e_l}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, evenly sampled from <inline-formula><tex-math id="M00037" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$[ {0,{e_h}} ]$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, was added to the normalized expression of each selected gene within each cluster. The different datasets in each scenario then differ by this added expression level <inline-formula><tex-math id="M00038" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${e_h}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, which ranges from 0 to 5. Denoting the mean of normalized expressions of all genes across all cell types by <inline-formula><tex-math id="M00039" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${e_m}\sim 2.5$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, these six values are:</p>
      <disp-formula>
        <tex-math id="M00040" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\begin{equation*}{e_h} = \left( {0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5} \right) = \left( {0, 0.4, 0.8, 1.2, 1.6, 2} \right){e_m}.\end{equation*}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
      </disp-formula>
      <p>In <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S6</xref>, for each scenario, we have compared the expression levels of selected ligands/receptors with the rest of the genes across different datasets.</p>
      <p>To benchmark the performance of DiSiR against CellPhoneDB and ICELLNET using the simulated data, we have defined the following accuracy score:</p>
      <disp-formula>
        <tex-math id="M00041" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\begin{eqnarray*} &amp;&amp; Accuracy\ score =\nonumber\\ &amp;&amp; \frac{{\# \ of\ identified\ interactions\ that\ are\ upregulated\ in\ the\ simulated\ dataset\ }}{{\# \ of\ all\ upregulated\ interaction\ in\ the\ simulated\ dataset}} \end{eqnarray*}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
      </disp-formula>
      <p>As can been in Figure <xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>, DiSiR continues to outperform the other methods for all the simulated datasets in different scenarios.</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F7">
        <label>Figure 7.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Technical assessment of DiSiR on the simulated datasets. (<bold>A</bold>) Simulation settings in three scenarios (each scenario has six different datasets). Accuracy scores are shown across different datasets simulated using a range of added expression levels <inline-formula><tex-math id="M00042" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$( {{e_h}} ),$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> expressed in terms of a factor of the mean of normalized expressions <inline-formula><tex-math id="M00043" notation="LaTeX">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$({e_m})$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, in (<bold>B</bold>) scenario 1, (<bold>C</bold>) scenario 2 and (<bold>D</bold>) scenario 3 for DiSiR, ICELLNET and CellphoneDB.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="lqad030fig7" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>We have compared the running time of DiSiR and CellPhoneDB (searching over its entire database) applied to the AMP RA Phase 1 data on our system (2.4 GHz 8-Core Intel Core i9 processor 16GB RAM 2667 MHz DDR4). The execution time of about one minute for DiSiR, versus ∼55 minutes for CellPhoneDB, suggests that DiSiR is an easy and time-efficient method to study single interactions between individual components of complex pathways.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="SEC4">
    <title>CONCLUSION</title>
    <p>In summary, DiSiR is a novel easy-to-use software framework that enables the analysis of complex multi-subunit ligand–multi-subunit receptor interactions from scRNA-seq data, even for the interactions (or genes) that are not listed in available databases. We have applied our method on two COVID and RA scRNA-seq data and highlighted potential differences between inflammatory pathways at cell type level for control versus disease samples.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="SEC5">
    <title>DATA AVAILABILITY</title>
    <p>All expression transcriptomic data used in this study are publicly available (see the ‘Single-cell data sets and data pre-preprocessing steps’ section). All simulated expression data and the corresponding codes for generating them are available from GitHub at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/miladrafiee/disir_package" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/miladrafiee/disir_package</ext-link> and from Zenodo at <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7706658" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7706658</ext-link>. Disir_package v1.0.0 was used to generate the results in this work and is freely available for academic research use at the above GitHub page as well.</p>
    <p>A user-friendly internet-based tool for DiSiR is publicly available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://disir-scrna.streamlitapp.com" ext-link-type="uri">https://disir-scrna.streamlitapp.com</ext-link>, which works with the example input file formats provided in the GitHub page.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
      <label>lqad030_Supplemental_File</label>
      <media xlink:href="lqad030_supplemental_file.pdf">
        <caption>
          <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
        </caption>
      </media>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack id="ACK1">
    <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
    <p>We would like to thank Richa Hanamsagar for insightful discussions.</p>
  </ack>
  <sec id="SEC6">
    <title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title>
    <p><ext-link xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/nargab/article-lookup/doi/10.1093/nargab/lqad030#supplementary-data" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Data</ext-link> are available at NARGAB Online.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="SEC7">
    <title>FUNDING</title>
    <p>Sanofi.</p>
    <p><italic toggle="yes">Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p>
  </sec>
  <ref-list id="REF1">
    <title>REFERENCES</title>
    <ref id="B1">
      <label>1.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guerrero-Juarez</surname><given-names>C.F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuan</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Myung</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Plikus</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Inference and analysis of cell–cell communication using CellChat</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2021</year>; <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1088</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33597522</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B2">
      <label>2.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hafemeister</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Papalexi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mauck</surname><given-names>W.M.</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stoeckius</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smibert</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Satija</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive Integration of Single-Cell Data</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>2019</year>; <volume>177</volume>:<fpage>1888</fpage>–<lpage>1902</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31178118</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B3">
      <label>3.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>La Manno</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Soldatov</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zeisel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hochgerner</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petukhov</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lidschreiber</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kastriti</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lönnerberg</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Furlan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>RNA velocity of single cells</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2018</year>; <volume>560</volume>:<fpage>494</fpage>–<lpage>498</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30089906</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B4">
      <label>4.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Armingol</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Officer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harismendy</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>N.E.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Deciphering cell–cell interactions and communication from gene expression</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Genet.</source><year>2021</year>; <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33168968</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B5">
      <label>5.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cillo</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kurten</surname><given-names>C.H.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tabib</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Onkar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duvvuri</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Soose</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Immune landscape of viral- and carcinogen-driven head and neck cancer</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>. <year>2020</year>; <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>183</fpage>–<lpage>199</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31924475</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B6">
      <label>6.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ajani</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Futreal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>iTALK: an R package to characterize and illustrate intercellular communication</article-title>. <year>2019</year>; <comment>bioRxiv doi:</comment><comment>04 January 2019, preprint: not peer reviewed</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/507871</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B7">
      <label>7.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tyler</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rotti</surname><given-names>P.G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Flamme-Wiese</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mullins</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Norris</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>PyMINEr Finds Gene and Autocrine-Paracrine Networks from Human Islet scRNA-Seq</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep.</source><year>2019</year>; <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>1951</fpage>–<lpage>1964</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30759402</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B8">
      <label>8.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Slowikowski</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fonseka</surname><given-names>C.Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tabechian</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>L.B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salomon-Escoto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Defining inflammatory cell states in rheumatoid arthritis joint synovial tissues by integrating single-cell transcriptomics and mass cytometry</article-title>. <source>Nat. Immunol.</source><year>2019</year>; <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>928</fpage>–<lpage>942</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31061532</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B9">
      <label>9.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cabello-Aguilar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alame</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kon-Sun-Tack</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fau</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lacroix</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Colinge</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>SingleCellSignalR: inference of intercellular networks from single-cell transcriptomics</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2020</year>; <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>e55</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32196115</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B10">
      <label>10.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Noël</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Massenet-Regad</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carmi-Levy</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cappuccio</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grandclaudon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trichot</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kieffer</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mechta-Grigoriou</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Soumelis</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Dissection of intercellular communication using the transcriptome-based framework ICELLNET</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2021</year>; <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1089</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33597528</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B11">
      <label>11.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dries</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Giotto: a toolbox for integrative analysis and visualization of spatial expression data</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2021</year>; <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>78</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33685491</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B12">
      <label>12.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Browaeys</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saelens</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saeys</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>NicheNet: modeling intercellular communication by linking ligands to target genes</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>. <year>2020</year>; <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>162</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31819264</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B13">
      <label>13.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Durrans</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Narula</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rafii</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elemento</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Transcriptome analysis of individual stromal cell populations identifies stroma-tumor crosstalk in mouse lung cancer model</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep.</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1187</fpage>–<lpage>1201</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25704820</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B14">
      <label>14.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Inferring spatial and signaling relationships between cells from single cell transcriptomic data</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2020</year>; <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>2084</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32350282</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B15">
      <label>15.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Karikomi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>MacLean</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Cell lineage and communication network inference via optimization for single-cell transcriptomics</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2019</year>; <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>e66</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30923815</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B16">
      <label>16.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tsuyuzaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nikaido</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Uncovering hypergraphs of cell–cell interaction from single cell RNA-sequencing data</article-title>. <year>2019</year>; <comment>bioRxiv doi:</comment><comment>04 March 2019, preprint: not peer reviewed</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/566182</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B17">
      <label>17.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ramilowski</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harshbarger</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kloppmann</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lizio</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Satagopam</surname><given-names>V.P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kawaji</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carninci</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rost</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>A draft network of ligand–receptor-mediated multicellular signalling in human</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>7866</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26198319</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B18">
      <label>18.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>T.K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kandasamy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Human Protein Reference Database and Human Proteinpedia as discovery tools for systems biology</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol. Biol.</source><year>2009</year>; <volume>577</volume>:<fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19718509</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B19">
      <label>19.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ben-Shlomo</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu Hsu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rauch</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kowalski</surname><given-names>H.W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hsueh</surname><given-names>A.J</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Signaling receptome: a genomic and evolutionary perspective of plasma membrane receptors involved in signal transduction</article-title>. <source>Sci. STKE</source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>2003</volume>:<fpage>RE9</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12815191</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B20">
      <label>20.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Harding</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sharman</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Faccenda</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Southan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pawson</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ireland</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>A.J.G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bruce</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>S.P.H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Anderton</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>The IUPHAR/BPS Guide to PHARMACOLOGY in 2018: updates and expansion to encompass the new guide to IMMUNOPHARMACOLOGY</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2018</year>; <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>D1091</fpage>–<lpage>D1106</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29149325</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B21">
      <label>21.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Apweiler</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bairoch</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Natale</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>W.C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boeckmann</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferro</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gasteiger</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>The Universal Protein Resource (UniProt): an expanding universe of protein information</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2006</year>; <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>D187</fpage>–<lpage>D191</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16381842</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B22">
      <label>22.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Efremova</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vento-Tormo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Teichmann</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vento-Tormo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>CellPhoneDB: inferring cell–cell communication from combined expression of multi-subunit ligand–receptor complexes</article-title>. <source>Nat. Protoc.</source><year>2020</year>; <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1484</fpage>–<lpage>1506</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32103204</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B23">
      <label>23.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Vento-Tormo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Efremova</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Botting</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Turco</surname><given-names>M.Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vento-Tormo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>K.B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stephenson</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Polanski</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goncalves</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Single-cell reconstruction of the early maternal-fetal interface in humans</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2018</year>; <volume>563</volume>:<fpage>347</fpage>–<lpage>353</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30429548</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B24">
      <label>24.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Motwani</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Winograd</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>The PageRank citation ranking: bringing order to the web</article-title>. <year>1999</year>; <publisher-name>Stanford InfoLab</publisher-name><comment>Technical Report</comment>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B25">
      <label>25.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J.X.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taramelli</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pedrini</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knijnenburg</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Extracting intercellular signaling network of cancer tissues using ligand–receptor expression patterns from whole-tumor and single-cell transcriptomes</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep.</source><year>2017</year>; <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>8815</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28821810</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B26">
      <label>26.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>C.Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shyr</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Dysregulated Ligand-receptor interactions from single cell transcriptomics</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2022</year>; <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>3216</fpage>–<lpage>3221</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35482476</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B27">
      <label>27.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Single-cell landscape of bronchoalveolar immune cells in patients with COVID-19</article-title>. <source>Nat. Med.</source><year>2020</year>; <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>842</fpage>–<lpage>844</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32398875</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B28">
      <label>28.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Weinreb</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wolock</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>SPRING: a kinetic interface for visualizing high dimensional single-cell expression data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2018</year>; <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>1246</fpage>–<lpage>1248</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29228172</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B29">
      <label>29.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chamberlain</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hanamsagar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nestle</surname><given-names>F.O.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Rinaldis</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Savova</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Cell type classification and discovery across diseases, technologies and tissues reveals conserved gene signatures and enables standardized single-cell readouts</article-title>. <year>2021</year>; <comment>bioRxiv doi:</comment><comment>08 February 2021, preprint: not peer reviewed</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2021.02.01.429207</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B30">
      <label>30.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Korsunsky</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Millard</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Slowikowski</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baglaenko</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Loh</surname><given-names>P.R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raychaudhuri</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Fast, sensitive and accurate integration of single-cell data with Harmony</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>. <year>2019</year>; <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1289</fpage>–<lpage>1296</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31740819</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B31">
      <label>31.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Aghdashi</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seyedmardani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghasemi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khodamoradi</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of serum calprotectin level and disease activity in patients with rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>Curr. Rheumatol. Rev.</source><year>2019</year>; <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>316</fpage>–<lpage>320</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30666913</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B32">
      <label>32.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>The role of calprotectin in rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>J. Transl. Int. Med.</source><year>2019</year>; <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>126</fpage>–<lpage>131</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32010597</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B33">
      <label>33.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F.P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.X.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.X.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>B cells in rheumatoid arthritis:pathogenic mechanisms and treatment prospects</article-title>. <source>Front. Immunol.</source><year>2021</year>; <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>750753</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34650569</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B34">
      <label>34.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dienz</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rincon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>The effects of IL-6 on CD4 T cell responses</article-title>. <source>Clin. Immunol.</source><year>2009</year>; <volume>130</volume>:<fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18845487</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B35">
      <label>35.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Johnstone</surname><given-names>C.N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chand</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Putoczki</surname><given-names>T.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Emerging roles for IL-11 signaling in cancer development and progression: focus on breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Cytokine Growth Factor Rev.</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>489</fpage>–<lpage>498</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26209885</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B36">
      <label>36.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Single-cell analysis of two severe COVID-19 patients reveals a monocyte-associated and tocilizumab-responding cytokine storm</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2020</year>; <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>3924</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32764665</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B37">
      <label>37.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Højen</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>M.L.V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McKee</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wade</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Azam</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lunding</surname><given-names>L.P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Graaf</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Swartzwelter</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wegmann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tolstrup</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>IL-1R3 blockade broadly attenuates the functions of six members of the IL-1 family, revealing their contribution to models of disease</article-title>. <source>Nat. Immunol.</source><year>2019</year>; <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1138</fpage>–<lpage>1149</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31427775</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B38">
      <label>38.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mozsary</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meydan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Foox</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosiene</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shaiber</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Danko</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Afshinnekoo</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>MacKay</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sedlazeck</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Shotgun transcriptome, spatial omics, and isothermal profiling of SARS-CoV-2 infection reveals unique host responses, viral diversification, and drug interactions</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2021</year>; <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1660</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33712587</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B39">
      <label>39.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tirosh</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Izar</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Prakadan</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wadsworth</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names><suffix>2nd</suffix></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Treacy</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trombetta</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rotem</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rodman</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lian</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Dissecting the multicellular ecosystem of metastatic melanoma by single-cell RNA-seq</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2016</year>; <volume>352</volume>:<fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27124452</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B40">
      <label>40.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Biesemann</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Margerie</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Asbrand</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rehberg</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Additive efficacy of a bispecific anti-TNF/IL-6 nanobody compound in translational models of rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>Sci. Transl. Med.</source><year>2023</year>; <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>eabq4419</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36724239</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
