<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?origin publisher?>
<?FILEmeta_JBC104810 xml ?>
<?FILEmain xml ?>
<?FILEmain pdf ?>
<?FILEgr1 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr2 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr3 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr4 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr5 jpg ?>
<?FILEfx1 jpg ?>
<?FILEmmc1 docx ?>
<?FILEmmc2 jpg ?>
<?FILEmmc2 mp4 ?>
<?FILEmmc3 jpg ?>
<?FILEmmc3 mp4 ?>
<?FILEmmc4 jpg ?>
<?FILEmmc4 mp4 ?>
<?FILEmmc5 jpg ?>
<?FILEmmc5 mp4 ?>
<?properties open_access?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Biol Chem</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Biol Chem</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9258</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1083-351X</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">10267603</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S0021-9258(23)01838-0</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbc.2023.104810</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">104810</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Research Article</subject>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Editors' Pick</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>A web-based integrative transcriptome analysis, RNAseqChef, uncovers the cell/tissue type-dependent action of sulforaphane</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1">
        <name>
          <surname>Etoh</surname>
          <given-names>Kan</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2">
        <name>
          <surname>Nakao</surname>
          <given-names>Mitsuyoshi</given-names>
        </name>
        <email>mnakao@gpo.kumamoto-u.ac.jp</email>
        <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="aff1">Department of Medical Cell Biology, Institute of Molecular Embryology and Genetics, Kumamoto University, Kumamoto, Japan</aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>For correspondence: Mitsuyoshi Nakao <email>mnakao@gpo.kumamoto-u.ac.jp</email></corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>11</day>
      <month>5</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <month>6</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>11</day>
      <month>5</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>299</volume>
    <issue>6</issue>
    <elocation-id>104810</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>27</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© 2023 The Authors</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract id="abs0010">
      <p>RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) is a powerful technique for understanding cellular state and dynamics. However, comprehensive transcriptomic characterization of multiple RNA-seq datasets is laborious without bioinformatics training and skills. To remove the barriers to sequence data analysis in the research community, we have developed “RNAseqChef” (<underline>RNA</underline>-<underline>seq</underline> data <underline>c</underline>ontroller <underline>h</underline>ighlighting <underline>e</underline>xpression <underline>f</underline>eatures), a web-based platform of systematic transcriptome analysis that can automatically detect, integrate, and visualize differentially expressed genes and their biological functions. To validate its versatile performance, we examined the pharmacological action of sulforaphane (SFN), a natural isothiocyanate, on various types of cells and mouse tissues using multiple datasets <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic>. Notably, SFN treatment upregulated the ATF6-mediated unfolded protein response in the liver and the NRF2-mediated antioxidant response in the skeletal muscle of diet-induced obese mice. In contrast, the commonly downregulated pathways included collagen synthesis and circadian rhythms in the tissues tested. On the server of RNAseqChef, we simply evaluated and visualized all analyzing data and discovered the NRF2-independent action of SFN. Collectively, RNAseqChef provides an easy-to-use open resource that identifies context-dependent transcriptomic features and standardizes data assessment.</p>
    </abstract>
    <kwd-group id="kwrds0010">
      <title>Keywords</title>
      <kwd>RNAseqChef</kwd>
      <kwd>open resource</kwd>
      <kwd>transcriptomics</kwd>
      <kwd>sulforaphane</kwd>
      <kwd>NRF2 (<italic>NFE2L2</italic>)</kwd>
      <kwd>antioxidant response</kwd>
      <kwd>ATF6</kwd>
      <kwd>unfolded protein response</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
  </article-meta>
  <def-list>
    <title>Abbreviations</title>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0055">BAT</term>
      <def>
        <p>brown adipose tissue</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0065">DEG</term>
      <def>
        <p>differentially expressed gene</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0075">eWAT</term>
      <def>
        <p>epididymal white adipose tissue</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0085">GEO</term>
      <def>
        <p>Gene Expression Omnibus</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0095">HFD</term>
      <def>
        <p>high-fat diet</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0105">iWAT</term>
      <def>
        <p>inguinal WAT</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0115">NRF2</term>
      <def>
        <p>nucleus factor-E2-related factor 2</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0125">PCA</term>
      <def>
        <p>Principal component analysis</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0135">RNA-seq</term>
      <def>
        <p>RNA sequencing</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0145">ROS</term>
      <def>
        <p>reactive oxygen species</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0155">SFN</term>
      <def>
        <p>Sulforaphane</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0165">TF</term>
      <def>
        <p>transcription factor</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0175">UMAP</term>
      <def>
        <p>Uniform manifold approximation and projection</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0185">UPR</term>
      <def>
        <p>unfolded protein response</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
  </def-list>
  <notes>
    <p id="misc0010">Reviewed by members of the JBC Editorial Board. Edited by Brian Strahl</p>
  </notes>
</front>
<body>
  <p id="p0010">RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) is a core technology used for comprehensive gene expression analyses (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). RNA-seq datasets are deposited in public databases such as the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) so that researchers can freely utilize the available data (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Currently, more than 100,000 datasets derived from cell lines and tissues of various species are available for re-analyses, which are useful resources for those with a general interest in the life science field. However, a series of data investigations, including differentially expressed gene (DEG) analysis, data integration, clustering, functional analysis, and visualization, are considerably laborious for most researchers and scientists not specializing in bioinformatics.</p>
  <p id="p0015">Sulforaphane (SFN) is a natural isothiocyanate generated by cruciferous vegetables such as broccoli. SFN is known to interact with the active cysteine residues of KEAP1 (Kelch-like ECH-associated protein 1), resulting in the activation of nucleus factor-E2-related factor 2, NRF2 (<italic>NFE2L2</italic>), which is the master transcription factor for redox homeostasis (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). SFN treatment has anti-obesity and antidiabetic effects through NRF2 activation in multiple models, such as diet-induced obese mice and rodents (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Indeed, SFN-induced activation of NRF2 has been shown to ameliorate oxidative and endoplasmic reticulum (ER) stress, which causes excessive adipogenesis, lipid accumulation, inflammation, and fibrosis (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). However, recent studies have shown the cytotoxic effect of SFN in cancer cells <italic>via</italic> mitochondrial damage and apoptosis induction (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Although it is plausible that SFN actions depend on cellular status, little is known about the context-dependent effects of SFN. Furthermore, the NRF2-independent actions of SFN remain poorly understood.</p>
  <p id="p0020">Upon RNA-seq analysis of multiple datasets, numerous workflows are required for the user’s demands. However, existing web platforms are adjusted for the analysis of “single dataset” (controls <italic>versus</italic> subjects) but not “multiple datasets” ([controls <italic>versus</italic> subjects] × n). In this study, we developed RNAseqChef (an RNA-seq data controller highlighting expression features), a web-based systematic analysis of multiple RNA-seq datasets. Using this platform, we performed integrative transcriptome analysis of SFN-treated cultured cells and model mice. We found that SFN-induced ATF6-mediated unfolded protein response (UPR) without NRF2 activation, and that SFN-induced UPR occurred in the liver, but not in other metabolic tissues, in diet-induced obese mice. We also found that SFN treatment downregulated the expression of collagen and circadian rhythm-associated genes involved in fibrosis and lipid metabolism, respectively. Thus, SFN-induced transcriptomic changes depended on the cell/tissue type. RNAseqChef platform evaluates molecular features without special bioinformatic skills in biological and medical research fields and allows integration, simplification, user-centered, and standardization of data assessment.</p>
  <sec id="sec1">
    <title>Results</title>
    <sec id="sec1.1">
      <title>Design of RNAseqChef</title>
      <p id="p0025">RNAseqChef (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://imeg-ku.shinyapps.io/RNAseqChef/" id="intref0010">https://imeg-ku.shinyapps.io/RNAseqChef/</ext-link>) is a user-centered web-based application for the systematic integrative analysis of RNA-seq data (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figs. 1</xref><italic>A</italic> and <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">S1</xref>; <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Movie S1</xref>). The user’s graphical interface of RNAseqChef comprises “Menu”, “Settings”, “Output” and “Tab” panels, which do not require any special bioinformatics skills to navigate (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S2</xref>). In contrast to the existing web platforms (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>), users can analyze not only a single dataset but also integrate and evaluate multiple datasets (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref><italic>B</italic>). To establish the versatility of RNAseqChef, we divided its core functions into six sections, which enabled us to handle various types of input files (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref><italic>A</italic>). RNAseqChef consists of the following 2 units: DEG Analysis Unit (“Pair-wise”, “3 conditions DEG” and “Multi DEG”) and Integrative Analysis Unit (“Venn diagram”, “Normalized count analysis” and “Enrichment viewer”). The DEG Analysis Unit was optimized for the analysis of a single dataset to automatically perform DEG detection, pathway analysis, and data visualization by uploading the raw count data. “Pair-wise DEG” was adjusted for pair-wise comparison analysis, and “3 conditions DEG” was enhanced for multiple comparison analysis of three groups using EBSeq (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). “Multi DEG” was optimized for the analysis of time-series experiments using the DESeq2 likelihood ratio test (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). To increase the throughput for the pairwise analysis of multiple datasets and subsequent integrative analysis, we created the batch-mode in “Pair-wise DEG”, which sequentially performs DEG analysis of all uploaded files, and then outputs the following results: clustering plot, MA-plot, DEG result, lists of both upregulated and downregulated DEGs, and normalized count data. The results files obtained from the DEG Analysis Unit can be used as input files for the Integrative Analysis Unit, which makes it easy to perform a flexible analysis on demand (<italic>e.g.</italic>, <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref><italic>A</italic> and <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Movie S2</xref>). “Venn diagram” was optimized for Venn diagram and subsequent analysis (heatmap and pathway analysis). “Normalized count analysis” was adjusted for clustering analysis of normalized count data, and “Enrichment viewer” was optimized for functional pathway and promoter motif analysis. In addition, the pathway databases that are used for enrichment analysis in RNAseqChef can be referred to from the “MSigDB” (Molecular Signatures Database) and “DoRothEA regulon” in the “More” section of RNAseqChef.<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Overview of RNAseqChef (RNA-seq data controller highlighting gene expression feature).</bold><italic>A</italic>, RNAseqChef is a web-based platform of systematic transcriptome analysis and can automatically detect, integrate, and visualize the DEGs and their biological functions, by uploading the raw count files of interest. The “DEG Analysis Unit” consists of “Pair-wise DEG”, “3 conditions DEG”, and “Multi DEG”. The “Integrative Analysis Unit” then consists of “Venn diagram,” “Normalized count analysis,” and “Enrichment viewer.” The result files obtained from the DEG Analysis Unit can be used as input files for the Integrative Analysis Unit, which makes it easy to perform the bioinformatic studies on demand. <italic>B</italic>, analysis of the common and cell/tissue-specific effects of SFN on transcriptome using RNAseqChef. DEG, differentially expressed gene; SFN, Sulforaphane.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Cellular response to SFN is different among cell types.</bold><italic>A</italic>, schematic representation of the RNAseqChef analysis designed to highlight SFN-induced transcriptomic features and their cell-type dependency. Raw count data were obtained from public RNA-seq datasets of epithelial cells (Epi; GSE141740) and HaCaT keratinocytes (Ker; GSE185320), under control (Ctrl; DMSO-treated) and 10 μM SFN-treated conditions (each n = 2). Along with the workflow in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>, <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>, it takes approximately 5 min to complete all analyzing steps. <italic>B</italic>, transcriptome-based PCA of Ctrl and SFN-treated cells. <italic>C</italic>, Venn diagram of genes significantly upregulated by SFN treatment (using DESeq2 (FDR &lt; 0.01)). <italic>D</italic>, heatmap of commonly upregulated genes shown in (<italic>C</italic>). <italic>E</italic> and <italic>F</italic>, top-ranked functional pathways (<italic>E</italic>) and transcription factors (TFs) (<italic>F</italic>) were enriched in gene sets upregulated by SFN treatment, including 499 common genes (<italic>green</italic>), 1146 Epi unique genes (<italic>red</italic>), and 1212 Ker unique genes (<italic>blue</italic>), as shown in (<italic>C</italic>). Enrichment analysis was performed based on MSigDB hallmark (<italic>E</italic>) and DoRothEA regulon gene set (<italic>F</italic>). FDR &lt;0.05. <italic>G</italic>, normalized expression values of the representatives for common, Epi unique, and Ker unique genes upregulated by SFN. ∗∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01; ∗∗∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001. FDR, false discovery rate; PCA, Principal component analysis; SFN, Sulforaphane.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.2">
      <title>Biological responses to SFN treatment depend on cell types</title>
      <p id="p0030">Based on our criteria that the read depth should be more than 10 million reads per sample, we found reliable <italic>in vitro</italic> datasets of cultured human cells, epithelial cells (Epi: GSE141740), and keratinocytes (Ker: GSE185320), which were treated with control (Ctrl) or SFN (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). To characterize the transcriptomic features in response to SFN, we performed an integrative analysis of these datasets using RNAseqChef (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref><italic>A</italic>). It took approximately 5 min to complete all steps (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Movie S2</xref>). Principal component analysis (PCA) showed that the cell type datasets (Epi or Ker) with treatment (Ctrl or SFN) were distinctly positioned (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref><italic>B</italic>). To identify the common and cell type-specific genes affected by SFN treatment, we detected DEGs from each dataset using DESeq2 (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S3</xref>, <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>) and conducted Venn diagram analysis (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figs. 2</xref><italic>C</italic> and <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">S3</xref><italic>F</italic>). SFN treatment upregulated 499 genes in both cell types (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>, <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>). In contrast, 1146 and 1212 genes were upregulated in SFN-treated Epi and Ker, respectively (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref><italic>C</italic>). To clarify the biological relevance of SFN-associated genes, we performed enrichment analysis based on the MSigDB hallmark gene set (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figs. 2</xref><italic>E</italic> and <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">S3</xref>, <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>). Consistent with previous reports (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>), the top-ranked pathways related to the 499 commonly upregulated genes were the mammalian target of rapamycin complex 1 (mTORC1) signaling, apoptosis, reactive oxygen species (ROS) pathway, and glycolysis (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref><italic>E</italic>). In addition, transcription factor (TF) enrichment analysis based on the DoRothEA regulon gene set identified a well-known SFN-target NRF2, which transcriptionally activates antioxidant genes (<italic>TXNRD1, HMOX1,</italic> and <italic>NQO1</italic>) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figs. 2</xref><italic>F</italic> and <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">S3</xref><italic>E</italic>). In contrast, 1212 Ker-specific genes, but not 1146 Epi-specific genes, enriched inflammation-related pathways, such as interferon-γ (IFNγ) response (<italic>IRF1</italic> and <italic>ISG20</italic>), and TFs, such as RELA (targeting <italic>IRF1</italic>) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, <italic>E</italic> and <italic>G</italic>). We also analyzed downregulated genes in SFN-treated cells using enrichment analysis (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S3</xref><italic>F</italic>). The 242 commonly downregulated genes by SFN-enriched TFDP1/E2F targets (<italic>GINS1</italic> and <italic>SRSF2</italic>) (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S3</xref>, <italic>G</italic>–<italic>I</italic>). A total of 1652 Ker-specific genes, but not Epi-specific genes, enriched p53 pathway (<italic>CDKN1A</italic>) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figs. 2</xref><italic>G</italic> and <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">S3</xref>, <italic>G</italic> and <italic>H</italic>) and estrogen response (<italic>KRT13</italic> and <italic>KRT15</italic>) (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S3</xref>, <italic>G</italic>–<italic>I</italic>). Thus, we found that SFN has both common and cell type-specific effects using RNAseqChef analysis of multiple RNA-seq datasets.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.3">
      <title>SFN induces the unfolded protein response in an NRF2-independent manner</title>
      <p id="p0035">SFN has been reported to trigger an oxidative stress response through the activation of NRF2 (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>), but its NRF2-independent functions remain poorly understood. To address this, we performed a clustering analysis of genes commonly upregulated by SFN (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figs. 2</xref><italic>C</italic> and <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref><italic>A</italic>). For this purpose, we used normalized count data from control WT, SFN-treated WT, and SFN-treated NRF KO epithelial cells (GSE141740) for the clustering approach. NRF2 dependency was defined as whether NRF2 KO canceled the effects of SFN on gene expression. k-means clustering analysis detected 194 NRF2-dependent and 281 NRF2-independent upregulated genes (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref><italic>B</italic>). As expected, enrichment analysis showed that NRF2-dependent upregulated genes enriched both the ROS pathway and the NRF2 targets (such as <italic>NQO1</italic>, <italic>GCLM</italic>, and <italic>TXNRD1</italic>), while NRF2-independent upregulated genes did not at all (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, <italic>C</italic>–<italic>E</italic>), indicating that RNAseqChef had a secure clustering capacity. In contrast, NRF2-independent upregulated genes enriched the UPR and its regulator ATF6 targets (such as <italic>BiP</italic> (binding immunoglobulin protein, gene symbol <italic>HSPA5</italic>) and <italic>ERdj6</italic> (ER-resident protein, gene symbol <italic>DNAJC3</italic>)) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, <italic>C</italic>–<italic>E</italic>). Furthermore, similar results were obtained by EBSeq multiple comparison analyses of the three groups (control WT, SFN-WT, and SFN-NRF2 KO) by “3 conditions DEG” in RNAseqChef (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S4</xref><italic>A</italic> and <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Movie S3</xref>). We detected 293 NRF2-dependent upregulated genes that enriched the ROS pathway (<italic>q</italic> value: 1.1 × 10<sup>−4</sup>) and NRF2 targets (<italic>q</italic> value: 5.8 × 10<sup>−3</sup>) (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S4</xref>, <italic>B</italic>–<italic>E</italic>). We also detected 578 NRF2-independent upregulated genes that enriched UPR (<italic>q</italic> value: 1.4 × 10<sup>−3</sup>) and ATF6 targets (<italic>q</italic> value: 6.5 × 10<sup>−3</sup>) (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S4</xref>, <italic>F</italic>–<italic>I</italic>). We then performed a clustering analysis of 242 genes commonly downregulated by SFN and detected 91 NRF2-dependent and 151 NRF2-independent downregulated genes (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Figs. S3</xref><italic>F</italic> and <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">S5</xref><italic>A</italic>). NRF2-dependent downregulated genes enriched E2F targets and the TGFβ signaling pathway (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S5</xref>, <italic>B</italic> and <italic>C</italic>), but NRF2-independent downregulated genes did not.<fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>SFN induces the unfolded protein response in an NRF2-independent manner.</bold><italic>A</italic>, schematic representation of the RNAseqChef analysis designed to identify the NRF2-dependent or independent actions of SFN in epithelial cells. Gene extraction of the common genes from the normalized count data (control WT, SFN-treated WT and NRF2 KO, each n = 2) was performed in the “Normalized count analysis” section. Subsequent k-means clustering was done using the tab panel named “k-means clustering” in the same section. Enrichment analysis was performed by uploading the result file obtained from k-means clustering in the “Enrichment viewer” section. <italic>B</italic>, the k-means clustering approach separated 499 commonly upregulated genes (shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref><italic>C</italic>) into two groups based on NRF2 dependency. The <italic>magenta</italic> and <italic>green box</italic> indicate 281 NRF-independent and 194 NRF2-dependent upregulated genes, respectively. The 24 genes (in the <italic>bottom</italic> cluster of the heatmap) were not separated into the above groups because their expression patterns were not obvious. <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>, top-ranked functional pathways (<italic>C</italic>) and TFs (<italic>D</italic>) were enriched in gene sets upregulated by SFN treatment, including 475 ALL genes (sum of the following genes), 194 NRF2-dependent genes, and 281 NRF2-independent genes. Enrichment analysis was performed based on MSigDB hallmark (<italic>C</italic>) and DoRothEA regulon gene set (<italic>D</italic>). FDR &lt;0.05. <italic>E</italic>, TPM expression values of the representative NRF2-dependent and NRF2-independent genes that were upregulated by SFN. ∗∗∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001. FDR, false discovery rate; NRF2, nucleus factor-E2-related factor 2; SFN, Sulforaphane; TPM, Transcripts per million; WT, wild type.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p>
      <p id="p0040">UPR is induced by ER stress to attenuate protein synthesis, increase protein folding, and enhance the activity of protein degradation pathways, which are important for preventing pathological conditions such as amyloid disease and diabetes (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). ATF6 is an ER stress sensor for the UPR that upregulates cytoprotective pathways, including protein folding and ER homeostasis (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Although it has previously been shown that SFN modulates UPR through an NRF2-dependent mechanism (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>), it is unknown whether SFN enhances UPR without NRF2. To further examine the effect of NRF2 on UPR, we analyzed the RNA-seq data of constitutively active NRF2 (caNRF2)-expressing fibroblasts (GSE106097) (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). NRF2-dependent genes (<italic>Nqo1</italic> and <italic>Gclm</italic>), but not UPR genes (<italic>Atf4</italic>, <italic>BiP</italic>, and <italic>ERdj6</italic>), were significantly upregulated in caNRF2-expressed cells (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S6</xref><italic>A</italic>). Further, we examined the recent RNA-seq data of human uterine leiomyosarcoma SK-UT-1 cells that were treated with 5 μM SFN (GSE205777) (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Consistent with the results of Epi cells (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref><italic>E</italic>), both NRF2-target genes and UPR-related genes were upregulated in SFN-treated SK-UT-1 cells (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S6</xref><italic>B</italic>). These results suggested that SFN functions as a UPR inducer in an NRF2-independent manner.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.4">
      <title>Upregulated genes by SFN treatment depend on tissue types in diet-induced obese mice</title>
      <p id="p0045">To address SFN action <italic>in vivo</italic>, we analyzed the RNA-seq dataset of five major metabolic tissues, including the liver, skeletal muscle, brown adipose tissue (BAT), epididymal white adipose tissue (eWAT), and inguinal WAT (iWAT), in diet-induced obese mice in the presence or absence of SFN treatment (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). C57BL/6J mice were fed a high-fat diet (HFD, 60% of the calories from fat) for 16 weeks to induce obesity and were treated with daily intraperitoneal SFN injections (5 mg/kg, i.p.) during the last 1 week of the experimental period (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S7</xref><italic>A</italic>). SFN treatment resulted in body weight loss and improvement in obesity, where it was reported that NRF2-dependent antioxidant genes were upregulated in the skeletal muscle and that fatty acid synthesis genes were downregulated in the liver, BAT, and eWAT (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). However, the common and tissue-specific effects of SFN have not yet been explored using unbiased transcriptome analysis.</p>
      <p id="p0050">Uniform manifold approximation and projection (UMAP) placed the dataset derived from the same tissue in close proximity (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref><italic>A</italic>), indicating that each tissue type had different transcriptomic features. To identify the common and tissue-specific genes affected by SFN treatment, we detected DEG genes from each tissue type using DESeq2 and then conducted Venn diagram analysis (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figs. 4</xref><italic>B</italic> and <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">S7</xref>, <italic>B</italic> and <italic>C</italic>). Interestingly, there was no overlap of upregulated genes among the five tissues, and most intersections among more than two tissues consisted of fewer than ten genes, suggesting that SFN treatment induced distinct transcriptomic changes depending on the tissue type of HFD-fed obese mice. To gain insight into the biological role of the upregulated genes in each tissue type of SFN-treated HFD-fed mice, we performed an enrichment analysis of the tissue-specific upregulated genes using the MSigDB hallmark and DoRothEA regulon gene sets (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figs. 4</xref>, <italic>C</italic>–<italic>F</italic>, and <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">S8</xref>, <italic>A</italic>–<italic>C</italic>). The results showed that adipogenesis and its regulator PPARα were upregulated in the BAT; IFNα response and its regulator STAT1 were upregulated in the eWAT; UPR and ATF6 were upregulated in the liver; and ROS pathway and NRF2 were upregulated in the skeletal muscle. In particular, ATF6-targeted genes involved in UPR function, including protein folding (such as <italic>ERdj4/6, DNAJB1</italic>, and <italic>Hyou1</italic>), quality control and degradation (<italic>Edem1/2/3</italic> and <italic>Os9</italic>), and ER protein import (<italic>Sec61a/b</italic>), were upregulated in the liver (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref><italic>E</italic>), but not in other tissues, in SFN-treated HFD-fed mice. In contrast, muscle-unique upregulated genes included anti-oxidant and NRF2 targets (<italic>Txnrd1</italic> and <italic>Gclm</italic>) (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref><italic>F</italic>), although the <italic>Nrf2</italic> gene itself was moderately expressed in the muscle (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S8</xref><italic>D</italic>). These data revealed that SFN action significantly depends on the tissue type in HFD-fed obese mice.<fig id="fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>SFN treatment induces tissue-specific transcriptomic changes in obese mice.</bold><italic>A</italic>, transcriptome-based UMAP of five metabolic tissues such as BAT, eWAT, iWAT, liver, and skeletal muscle in high fat diet-fed obese mice. Data set is GSE181477 (untreated Ctrl (−) and SNF-treated (+); each n = 5, except for eWAT (n = 4)). <italic>B</italic>, Venn diagram of genes significantly upregulated by SFN treatment (FDR &lt; 0.05). <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>, top-ranked functional pathways (<italic>C</italic>) and TFs (<italic>D</italic>) were enriched in gene sets upregulated by SFN treatment, including 157 BAT unique genes (<italic>red</italic>), 299 eWAT unique genes (<italic>yellow</italic>), 1252 liver unique genes (<italic>blue</italic>) and 65 muscle unique genes (<italic>green</italic>), as shown in (<italic>B</italic>). Enrichment analysis was performed based on MSigDB hallmark (<italic>C</italic>) and DoRothEA regulon gene set (<italic>D</italic>). FDR &lt;0.05. <italic>E</italic>, volcano plot obtained from pair-wise DEG analysis (Ctrl <italic>versus</italic> SFN) of the liver in HFD-fed obese mice. As indicated with <italic>green dots,</italic> ATF6-targeted UPR genes were significantly upregulated by SFN treatment (FDR &lt; 0.05). <italic>F</italic>, TPM expression values of the representative skeletal muscle-unique genes upregulated by SFN. ∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; ∗∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01. BAT, brown adipose tissue; eWAT, epididymal white adipose tissue; FDR, false discovery rate; HFD, high-fat diet; iWAT, inguinal WAT; SFN, Sulforaphane; TPM, Transcripts per million; UPR, unfolded protein response; WT, wild type.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.5">
      <title>SFN treatment downregulates collagen and circadian rhythm genes in obese mice</title>
      <p id="p0055">Finally, we focused on the downregulated genes in SFN-treated HFD-fed obese mice. In contrast to the absence of commonly upregulated genes (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref><italic>B</italic>), SFN treatment downregulated three genes (<italic>Col6a2</italic>, <italic>Lum</italic>, and <italic>Rev-erbβ</italic> (nuclear receptor subfamily one group D member 1, gene symbol <italic>NR1D1</italic>)) in the five tissues tested (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>). In addition, the epithelial-mesenchymal transition pathway, which contained genes involved in fibrosis, wound healing, and metastasis, was enriched in the commonly downregulated genes among these tissue types (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S9</xref>, <italic>A</italic>–<italic>E</italic>). Several genes, including collagen (<italic>Col1a1/2/3</italic>, <italic>Col3a1, Col5a1</italic>, and <italic>Col6a1/2/3</italic>), <italic>Fn1</italic>, and <italic>Lum,</italic> were evidently decreased in the examined tissues of SFN-treated HFD-fed mice (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref><italic>C</italic>), which has been implicated in tissue fibrosis (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Furthermore, we detected BMAL1 (brain and muscle ARNT-like 1, gene symbol <italic>Arntl</italic>), a regulator of circadian rhythm, whose targets were enriched in the downregulated genes in BAT, iWAT, and skeletal muscle (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S9</xref>, <italic>A</italic>, <italic>C</italic>, and <italic>E</italic>). BMAL1/CLOCK-target genes that are involved in circadian oscillation (such as <italic>Rev-erbα/β</italic>) and clock-controlled energy metabolism genes (<italic>Dbp</italic> and <italic>Bhlhe40</italic>) were downregulated in more than two tissues of SFN-treated HFD-fed obese mice (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, <italic>B</italic> and <italic>D</italic>). To exclude the effect of <italic>in vivo</italic> environmental factors on circadian rhythms, we checked the expression levels of circadian genes in SFN-treated cells <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S10</xref>). SFN treatment reduced the expression of multiple circadian oscillators (<italic>REV-ERBβ</italic>, <italic>CRY1</italic>, and <italic>PER1/2/3</italic>) in both WT and NRF2 KO epithelial cells, although there were no evident changes in the mRNA levels of <italic>BMAL1</italic> and <italic>CLOCK</italic>. Thus, these results suggest that SFN downregulates collagen synthesis and circadian rhythms in multiple tissues and cultured cells. In addition, as was the unique tissue-type upregulated genes by SFN treatment (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>, <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>), we found the presence of unique tissue-type downregulated genes (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S11</xref>). Taken together, RNAseqChef analysis of multiple RNA-seq datasets demonstrated that SFN had common and tissue-specific effects <italic>in vivo</italic>.<fig id="fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>SFN treatment downregulates collagen genes and BMAL1/CLOCK target genes in obese mice.</bold><italic>A</italic>, Venn diagram of genes significantly downregulated by SFN treatment (FDR &lt; 0.05). <italic>B</italic>, TPM expression values of genes commonly downregulated by SFN in five metabolic tissues of HFD-fed obese mice. ∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; ∗∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01; ∗∗∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001. <italic>C</italic>, heatmap of the hallmark gene set “Epithelial mesenchymal transition,” which was downregulated in the tissues of SFN-treated obese mice, as shown in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S9</xref>. Fibrosis-associated genes are highlighted in <italic>red</italic>. <italic>D</italic>, TPM expression values of <italic>Bmal1</italic> and BMAL1/CLOCK target genes downregulated in multiple tissues of SFN-treated HFD-fed obese mice. ∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; ∗∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01; ∗∗∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001. FDR, false discovery rate; HFD, high-fat diet; SFN, Sulforaphane; TPM, Transcripts per million.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2">
    <title>Discussion</title>
    <p id="p0060">To maximize the comprehensive capacity of RNA-seq analysis in biological research fields, we developed a user-centered web application, RNAseqChef (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref><italic>A</italic>). The present study verified that RNAseqChef enabled us to perform DEG analysis, data integration, and visualization (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Movies S1–S3</xref>). As demonstrated in our SFN study, the performance (time) was about 5 min for visualizing all analyzing data (in the case of <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>) (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Movie S2</xref>). In addition, running RNAseqChef did not depend on the user's computer specs because data analysis was performed on the server. Because the count data of bulk RNA-seq are usually obtained from public databases, such as GREIN (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>), anyone can readily perform and reproduce integrative RNA-seq analysis using RNAseqChef. Furthermore, gene lists obtained from the other omics analyses (<italic>e.g.</italic>, ChIP-seq, ATAC-seq, and methylome collected in ChIP-atlas (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>)) can be used as an input file for the Integrative Analysis Unit in RNAseqChef to merge RNA-seq data with epigenome information (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref><italic>A</italic>). Thus, RNAseqChef would facilitate our understanding of the physiological and pathological processes in multiple omics layers.</p>
    <p id="p0065">Previous studies have shown that SFN has an anti-obesity function in an NRF2-dependent manner, but a transcriptomic characterization of SFN action has not been performed in detail. We found that SFN treatment specifically activated ATF6-mediated UPR in the liver of HFD-fed obese mice (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>, <italic>C</italic>–<italic>E</italic>). It has been reported that ATF6 is important for attenuating hepatic steatosis under ER stress triggers, such as HFD, and that hepatic ATF6-conditional knockout causes lipid accumulation in the liver through the upregulation of the PPARγ pathway that facilitates lipogenesis (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Accordingly, we speculated that SFN ameliorates hepatic lipid accumulation through an ATF6-dependent UPR. Consistent with this, SFN treatment decreased the expression of a series of genes responsible for acetyl-CoA synthesis (such as <italic>Me1</italic> and <italic>Acly</italic>), fatty acid synthesis from acetyl-CoA (<italic>Acaca</italic> and <italic>Fasn</italic>), fatty acid elongation and desaturation (<italic>Elovl6</italic> and <italic>Scd1</italic>), and lipid deposition (<italic>Pparγ</italic> and <italic>Cidec</italic>) (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S8</xref>, <italic>E</italic> and <italic>F</italic>). In addition, SFN treatment affected the expression levels of fibrosis-related collagen and circadian rhythm genes. Previous reports have shown that SFN attenuates hepatic fibrosis <italic>via</italic> the NRF2-mediated inhibition of TGFβ signaling (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Our RNA-seq analysis consistently showed that SFN treatment downregulated the TGFβ pathway in an NRF2-dependent manner (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S5</xref><italic>B</italic>), suggesting that SFN treatment suppresses the synthesis of profibrogenic proteins in obese mice. The core transcription factor BMAL1 in the circadian rhythm has been shown to regulate energy metabolism (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). We found that SFN treatment in obese mice decreased BMAL1-target genes, such as <italic>Dbp</italic> and <italic>Bhlhe40</italic> (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref><italic>D</italic>), which are important for the induction of PPARγ and SREBP-1c, which are key transcriptional factors involved in lipid metabolism (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). It is possible that the SFN-mediated regulation of circadian rhythms contributes to the anti-obesity effect.</p>
    <p id="p0070">Our RNA-seq analyses utilized high-quality public RNA-seq datasets from independent research groups and demonstrated the potential action of SFN. To validate our findings in this study, further studies will be needed to understand the contribution of the SFN-induced transcriptome to phenotypic effects and the molecular mechanism of SFN action, using different concentrations of SFN in various cells/tissues tested. Actually, previous reports have shown that SFN has a hormetic dose-dependent effect and exhibits different tissue distribution (<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>).</p>
    <p id="p0075">RNAseqChef was optimized for analyzing “bulk RNA-seq” count data from public databases or their sequencing results. Users can utilize count data, but not RNA-seq raw data (<italic>i.e.</italic>, fastq files), as input for this application. Thus, in the case that you cannot obtain the count data from the database, you would need to obtain fastq files from the Sequence Read Archive and then perform pre-processing such as quality control and mapping by using a command line or web services such as Galaxy (<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). In addition, RNAseqChef is not currently available for “single-cell RNA-seq” analysis. Beyond these issues, as a further advantage of RNAseqChef, the user can simply merge the RNA-seq dataset with epigenomic datasets, such as ChIP-seq and ATAC-seq, for an overview of multilayered omics data. Collectively, RNAseqChef would provide us with sufficient application to investigate RNA-seq datasets from biological and pharmacological effects to achieve standardization of data assessment.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec3">
    <title>Experimental procedures</title>
    <sec id="sec3.1">
      <title>Public datasets</title>
      <p id="p0080">Raw datasets from public databases were collected from the “GEO repository” (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/" id="intref0015">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</ext-link>). The following public datasets regarding the SFN-induced transcriptome were used: 10 μM SFN-treated epithelial cells (GSE141740), 10 μM SFN-treated HaCaT keratinocytes (GSE185320), caNRF2-expressing fibroblasts (GSE106097), 5 μM SFN-treated SK-UT-1 cells (GSE205777), and 5 mg/ml SFN injected obese mice fed a HFD (GSE181477). To generate the raw count data, the RNA-seq raw data were mapped to the human (or mouse) reference genome (hg19 or mm10) using STAR <italic>via</italic> rsem-calculate-expression in the RSEM package (<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). Raw counts and Transcripts per million (TPM)-normalized data were obtained from the results of rsem-calculate-expression. Deposited data are summarized in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Table S1</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec3.2">
      <title>RNAseqChef</title>
      <p id="p0085">To develop RNAseqChef, the Shiny package was used to build an interactive web application using the open-source R programming language (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=shiny" id="intref0020">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=shiny</ext-link>). A total of 79 R packages were used to create the core functions of RNAseqChef, as described in the source code (<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.5281/zenodo.7095218" id="intref0025">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7095218</ext-link>). Software and algorithms are summarized in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Table S1</xref>. The website for RNAseqChef is currently hosted on the shinyapps.io server (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://imeg-ku.shinyapps.io/RNAseqChef/" id="intref0030">https://imeg-ku.shinyapps.io/RNAseqChef/</ext-link>), which may have some limitations such as the capacity of the server and the number of simultaneous connections, and the terms of use as described by shinyapps.io (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.rstudio.com/about/shinyapps-terms-use/" id="intref0035">https://www.rstudio.com/about/shinyapps-terms-use/</ext-link>). To overcome these points, the RNAseqChef Docker image (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://hub.docker.com/r/omicschef/rnaseqchef" id="intref0040">https://hub.docker.com/r/omicschef/rnaseqchef</ext-link>) has been developed to allow local installation and use on a private computer and network.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec3.3">
      <title>DEG analysis in RNAseqChef</title>
      <p id="p0090">For pair-wise comparison analysis, DEG detection was performed in the “Pair-wise DEG” section that used the DESeq2 package (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) with an FDR cutoff value of 0.01 and 0.05 for <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> data, respectively. For multiple comparisons of the three groups, DEG detection was performed in the “3 conditions DEG” using the EBSeq package (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) with the following thresholds: fold change &gt;1.25, FDR &lt;0.01, and basemean &gt;1. For the visualization of DEGs, both MA-plot and boxplots were drawn using the ggpubr package (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=ggpubr" id="intref0045">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=ggpubr</ext-link>), and both volcano plots and scatter plots were drawn using ggplot2 in the tidyverse package (<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). In addition, a heat map was drawn using the ComplexHeatmap package (<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). For the comparison of DEGs from different datasets, Venn diagram analysis was performed using the Venn package (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=venn" id="intref0050">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=venn</ext-link>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec3.4">
      <title>Clustering analysis in RNAseqChef</title>
      <p id="p0095">To evaluate the transcriptomic similarity and heterogeneity of the RNA-seq data, PCA and UMAP were performed using the prcomp function and umap (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=umap" id="intref0055">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=umap</ext-link>) package, respectively. For gene classification based on NRF2-dependency, k-means clustering was performed using ComplexHeatmap (<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec3.5">
      <title>Enrichment analysis in RNAseqChef</title>
      <p id="p0100">To conduct functional enrichment analysis, the MSigDB hallmark and DoRothEA regulon gene sets were extracted from the msigdbr (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=msigdbr" id="intref0060">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=msigdbr</ext-link>) and dorothea packages, respectively (<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Functional enrichment analysis was performed using clusterProfiler (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>) with an FDR cut-off of 0.05. The results were visualized <italic>via</italic> dot plots and gene concept-network (cnet) plots using the ggplot2 and enrichplot (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://yulab-smu.top/biomedical-knowledge-mining-book/" id="intref0065">https://yulab-smu.top/biomedical-knowledge-mining-book/</ext-link>) packages, respectively (<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec3.6">
      <title>Quantification and statistical analysis</title>
      <p id="p0105">Statistical analyses were performed using the RNAseqChef software. A pairwise comparison test was performed using the Wald test of DESeq2. Multiple comparison tests were performed using the EBMultiTest function in EBSeq2. Enrichment analysis was performed using Fisher’s exact test. FDR, an adjusted <italic>p</italic> value, was calculated using Benjamini-Hochberg (BH) and Storey’s q-value methods for pairwise DEG detection and enrichment analysis, respectively. Significance was defined as an adjusted <italic>p</italic>-value &lt;0.05, indicated with an asterisk (∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, ∗∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01, ∗∗∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001).</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec4">
    <title>Data availability</title>
    <p id="p0110">The RNAseqChef software is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://imeg-ku.shinyapps.io/RNAseqChef/" id="intref0070">https://imeg-ku.shinyapps.io/RNAseqChef/</ext-link> hosted by the shinyapps.io server.</p>
    <p id="p0115">Source code is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.5281/zenodo.7095218" id="intref0075">10.5281/zenodo.7095218</ext-link>.</p>
    <p id="p0120">Docker image is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://hub.docker.com/r/omicschef/rnaseqchef" id="intref0080">https://hub.docker.com/r/omicschef/rnaseqchef</ext-link>.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec5">
    <title>Supporting information</title>
    <p id="p0125">This article contains <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">supporting information</xref>.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
    <title>Conflict of interest</title>
    <p id="p0130">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ref-list id="cebib0010">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="bib1">
      <label>1</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mortazavi</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Williams</surname>
            <given-names>B.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McCue</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schaeffer</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wold</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Mapping and quantifying mammalian transcriptomes by RNA-Seq</article-title>
        <source>Nat. Methods</source>
        <volume>5</volume>
        <year>2008</year>
        <fpage>621</fpage>
        <lpage>628</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18516045</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib2">
      <label>2</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Edgar</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Domrachev</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lash</surname>
            <given-names>A.E.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Gene expression Omnibus: NCBI gene expression and hybridization array data repository</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>30</volume>
        <year>2002</year>
        <fpage>207</fpage>
        <lpage>210</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11752295</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib3">
      <label>3</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ahn</surname>
            <given-names>Y.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hwang</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>X.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stephenson</surname>
            <given-names>K.K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Electrophilic tuning of the chemoprotective natural product sulforaphane</article-title>
        <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source>
        <volume>107</volume>
        <year>2010</year>
        <fpage>9590</fpage>
        <lpage>9595</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20439747</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib4">
      <label>4</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kensler</surname>
            <given-names>T.W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Egner</surname>
            <given-names>P.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Agyeman</surname>
            <given-names>A.S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Visvanathan</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Groopman</surname>
            <given-names>J.D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>J.G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Keap1-nrf2 signaling: a target for cancer prevention by sulforaphane</article-title>
        <source>Top Curr. Chem.</source>
        <volume>329</volume>
        <year>2013</year>
        <fpage>163</fpage>
        <lpage>177</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22752583</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib5">
      <label>5</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Santín-Márquez</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Alarcón-Aguilar</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>López-Diazguerrero</surname>
            <given-names>N.E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chondrogianni</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Königsberg</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Sulforaphane - role in aging and neurodegeneration</article-title>
        <source>Geroscience</source>
        <volume>41</volume>
        <year>2019</year>
        <fpage>655</fpage>
        <lpage>670</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30941620</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib6">
      <label>6</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cakır</surname>
            <given-names>I.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lining Pan</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hadley</surname>
            <given-names>C.K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>El-Gamal</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fadel</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Elsayegh</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Sulforaphane reduces obesity by reversing leptin resistance</article-title>
        <source>Elife</source>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <year>2022</year>
        <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e67368</object-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib7">
      <label>7</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Negi</surname>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kumar</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sharma</surname>
            <given-names>S.S.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Nrf2 and NF-κB modulation by sulforaphane counteracts multiple manifestations of diabetic neuropathy in rats and high glucose-induced changes</article-title>
        <source>Curr. Neurovasc. Res.</source>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <year>2011</year>
        <fpage>294</fpage>
        <lpage>304</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22023613</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib8">
      <label>8</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Martins</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Colaço</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Venâncio</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pires</surname>
            <given-names>M.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Oliveira</surname>
            <given-names>P.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rosa</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Potential effects of sulforaphane to fight obesity</article-title>
        <source>J. Sci. Food Agric.</source>
        <volume>98</volume>
        <year>2018</year>
        <fpage>2837</fpage>
        <lpage>2844</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29363750</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib9">
      <label>9</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Choi</surname>
            <given-names>K.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Y.S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>S.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shin</surname>
            <given-names>K.O.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>J.Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Sulforaphane attenuates obesity by inhibiting adipogenesis and activating the AMPK pathway in obese mice</article-title>
        <source>J. Nutr. Biochem.</source>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <year>2014</year>
        <fpage>201</fpage>
        <lpage>207</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24445045</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib10">
      <label>10</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Deng</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tao</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>S.Z.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jin</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Inhibition of 6-hydroxydopamine-induced endoplasmic reticulum stress by sulforaphane through the activation of Nrf2 nuclear translocation</article-title>
        <source>Mol. Med. Rep.</source>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <year>2012</year>
        <fpage>215</fpage>
        <lpage>219</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22552270</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib11">
      <label>11</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Oh</surname>
            <given-names>C.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>J.Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Min</surname>
            <given-names>A.K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>K.G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Harris</surname>
            <given-names>R.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>H.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Sulforaphane attenuates hepatic fibrosis via NF-E2-related factor 2-mediated inhibition of transforming growth factor-β/Smad signaling</article-title>
        <source>Free Radic. Biol. Med.</source>
        <volume>52</volume>
        <year>2012</year>
        <fpage>671</fpage>
        <lpage>682</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22155056</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib12">
      <label>12</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Z.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>X.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lan</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Activation of NRF2 ameliorates oxidative stress and cystogenesis in autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease</article-title>
        <source>Sci. Transl. Med.</source>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <year>2020</year>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <lpage>17</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib13">
      <label>13</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dong</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Su</surname>
            <given-names>X.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Duan</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wei</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Sulforaphane induces S-phase arrest and apoptosis via p53-dependent manner in gastric cancer cells</article-title>
        <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <year>2021</year>
        <fpage>2504</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33510228</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib14">
      <label>14</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Smith</surname>
            <given-names>A.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ball</surname>
            <given-names>S.S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bao</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bowater</surname>
            <given-names>R.P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Sulforaphane promotes ER stress, autophagy, and cell death: implications for cataract surgery</article-title>
        <source>J. Mol. Med.</source>
        <volume>95</volume>
        <year>2017</year>
        <fpage>553</fpage>
        <lpage>564</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28083623</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib15">
      <label>15</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nelson</surname>
            <given-names>J.W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sklenar</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Barnes</surname>
            <given-names>A.P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Minnier</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The START app: a web-based RNAseq analysis and visualization resource</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <volume>33</volume>
        <year>2017</year>
        <fpage>447</fpage>
        <lpage>449</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28171615</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib16">
      <label>16</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Harshbarger</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kratz</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Carninci</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Deiva: a web application for interactive visual analysis of differential gene expression profiles</article-title>
        <source>BMC Genomics</source>
        <volume>18</volume>
        <year>2017</year>
        <fpage>47</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28061742</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib17">
      <label>17</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ge</surname>
            <given-names>S.X.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Son</surname>
            <given-names>E.W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yao</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>iDEP: an integrated web application for differential expression and pathway analysis of RNA-Seq data</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
        <volume>19</volume>
        <year>2018</year>
        <fpage>534</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30567491</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib18">
      <label>18</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Leng</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dawson</surname>
            <given-names>J.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Thomson</surname>
            <given-names>J.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ruotti</surname>
            <given-names>V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rissman</surname>
            <given-names>A.I.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Smits</surname>
            <given-names>B.M.G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>EBSeq: an empirical Bayes hierarchical model for inference in RNA-seq experiments</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <volume>29</volume>
        <year>2013</year>
        <fpage>1035</fpage>
        <lpage>1043</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23428641</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib19">
      <label>19</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Love</surname>
            <given-names>M.I.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huber</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Anders</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA-seq data with DESeq2</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol.</source>
        <volume>15</volume>
        <year>2014</year>
        <fpage>550</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25516281</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib20">
      <label>20</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dina Kuo</surname>
            <given-names>H.C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sargsyan</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kong</surname>
            <given-names>A.N.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>UVB drives metabolic rewiring and epigenetic reprograming and protection by sulforaphane in human skin keratinocytes</article-title>
        <source>Chem. Res. Toxicol.</source>
        <volume>35</volume>
        <year>2022</year>
        <fpage>1220</fpage>
        <lpage>1233</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35700067</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib21">
      <label>21</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gilmour</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ahn</surname>
            <given-names>Y.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>de la Vega</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dinkova-Kostova</surname>
            <given-names>A.T.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The isothiocyanate sulforaphane inhibits mTOR in an NRF2-independent manner</article-title>
        <source>Phytomedicine</source>
        <volume>86</volume>
        <year>2021</year>
        <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">153062</object-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib22">
      <label>22</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jeon</surname>
            <given-names>Y.K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yoo</surname>
            <given-names>D.R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jang</surname>
            <given-names>Y.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jang</surname>
            <given-names>S.Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nam</surname>
            <given-names>M.J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Sulforaphane induces apoptosis in human hepatic cancer cells through inhibition of 6-phosphofructo-2-kinase/fructose-2,6-biphosphatase4, mediated by hypoxia inducible factor-1-dependent pathway</article-title>
        <source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source>
        <volume>1814</volume>
        <year>2011</year>
        <fpage>1340</fpage>
        <lpage>1348</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21640852</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib23">
      <label>23</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yanaka</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tauchi</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Suzuki</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shibahara</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Matsui</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Role of the Nrf-2 gene in protection and repair of gastric mucosa against oxidative stress</article-title>
        <source>Inflammopharmacology</source>
        <volume>13</volume>
        <year>2005</year>
        <fpage>83</fpage>
        <lpage>90</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16259730</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib24">
      <label>24</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Usui</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yamaguchi</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tanji</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tominaga</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ishigaki</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fukumoto</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Atf6α-null mice are glucose intolerant due to pancreatic β-cell failure on a high-fat diet but partially resistant to diet-induced insulin resistance</article-title>
        <source>Metabolism</source>
        <volume>61</volume>
        <year>2012</year>
        <fpage>1118</fpage>
        <lpage>1128</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22386934</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib25">
      <label>25</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Casas-Tinto</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sanchez-Garcia</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gomez-Velazquez</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rincon-Limas</surname>
            <given-names>D.E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fernandez-Funez</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The ER stress factor XBP1s prevents amyloid-beta neurotoxicity</article-title>
        <source>Hum. Mol. Genet.</source>
        <volume>20</volume>
        <year>2011</year>
        <fpage>2144</fpage>
        <lpage>2160</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21389082</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib26">
      <label>26</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shoulders</surname>
            <given-names>M.D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ryno</surname>
            <given-names>L.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Genereux</surname>
            <given-names>J.C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Moresco</surname>
            <given-names>J.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tu</surname>
            <given-names>P.G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Stress-independent activation of XBP1s and/or ATF6 reveals three functionally diverse ER proteostasis environments</article-title>
        <source>Cell Rep.</source>
        <volume>3</volume>
        <year>2013</year>
        <fpage>1279</fpage>
        <lpage>1292</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23583182</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib27">
      <label>27</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tai</surname>
            <given-names>H.C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chung</surname>
            <given-names>S.D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chien</surname>
            <given-names>C.T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>H.J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Sulforaphane improves ischemia-induced detrusor overactivity by downregulating the enhancement of associated endoplasmic reticulum stress, autophagy, and apoptosis in rat bladder</article-title>
        <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <year>2016</year>
        <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">36110</object-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib28">
      <label>28</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hiebert</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wietecha</surname>
            <given-names>M.S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cangkrama</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Haertel</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mavrogonatou</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stumpe</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Nrf2-mediated fibroblast reprogramming drives cellular senescence by targeting the matrisome</article-title>
        <source>Dev. Cell</source>
        <volume>46</volume>
        <year>2018</year>
        <fpage>145</fpage>
        <lpage>161.e10</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30016619</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib29">
      <label>29</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Q.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Falahati</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Khosh</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mohammed</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kang</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Corachán</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Targeting class I histone deacetylases in human uterine leiomyosarcoma</article-title>
        <source>Cells</source>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <year>2022</year>
        <fpage>3801</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36497061</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib30">
      <label>30</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Krishnan</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>X.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kao</surname>
            <given-names>W.Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Viker</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Butters</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Masuoka</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Lumican, an extracellular matrix proteoglycan, is a novel requisite for hepatic fibrosis</article-title>
        <source>Lab. Invest.</source>
        <volume>92</volume>
        <year>2012</year>
        <fpage>1712</fpage>
        <lpage>1725</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23007134</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib31">
      <label>31</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tsukui</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>K.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wetter</surname>
            <given-names>J.B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wilson-Kanamori</surname>
            <given-names>J.R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hazelwood</surname>
            <given-names>L.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Henderson</surname>
            <given-names>N.C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Collagen-producing lung cell atlas identifies multiple subsets with distinct localization and relevance to fibrosis</article-title>
        <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <year>2020</year>
        <fpage>1920</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32317643</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib32">
      <label>32</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Halberg</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Khan</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Trujillo</surname>
            <given-names>M.E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wernstedt-Asterholm</surname>
            <given-names>I.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Attie</surname>
            <given-names>A.D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sherwani</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Hypoxia-inducible factor 1alpha induces fibrosis and insulin resistance in white adipose tissue</article-title>
        <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>
        <volume>29</volume>
        <year>2009</year>
        <fpage>4467</fpage>
        <lpage>4483</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19546236</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib33">
      <label>33</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Williams</surname>
            <given-names>L.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McCann</surname>
            <given-names>F.E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cabrita</surname>
            <given-names>M.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Layton</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cribbs</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Knezevic</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Identifying collagen VI as a target of fibrotic diseases regulated by CREBBP/EP300</article-title>
        <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source>
        <volume>117</volume>
        <year>2020</year>
        <fpage>20753</fpage>
        <lpage>20763</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32759223</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib34">
      <label>34</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mahi</surname>
            <given-names>N.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Najafabadi</surname>
            <given-names>M.F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pilarczyk</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kouril</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Medvedovic</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Grein: an interactive web platform for Re-analyzing GEO RNA-seq data</article-title>
        <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <year>2019</year>
        <fpage>7580</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31110304</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib35">
      <label>35</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zou</surname>
            <given-names>Z.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ohta</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Miura</surname>
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Oki</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>ChIP-atlas 2021 update: a data-mining suite for exploring epigenomic landscapes by fully integrating ChIP-seq, ATAC-seq and bisulfite-seq data</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>50</volume>
        <year>2022</year>
        <fpage>W175</fpage>
        <lpage>W182</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35325188</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib36">
      <label>36</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hino</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nagaoka</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Oki</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Etoh</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hino</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nakao</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Mitochondrial stress induces AREG expression and epigenomic remodeling through c-JUN and YAP-mediated enhancer activation</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>50</volume>
        <year>2022</year>
        <fpage>9765</fpage>
        <lpage>9779</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36095121</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib37">
      <label>37</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>X.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Deng</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dong</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xue</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Hepatic conditional knockout of ATF6 exacerbates liver metabolic damage by repressing autophage through MTOR pathway</article-title>
        <source>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</source>
        <volume>505</volume>
        <year>2018</year>
        <fpage>45</fpage>
        <lpage>50</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30236984</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib38">
      <label>38</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yamamoto</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Takahara</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Oyadomari</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Okada</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sato</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Harada</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Induction of liver steatosis and lipid droplet formation in ATF6-knockout mice burdened with pharmacological endoplasmic reticulum stress</article-title>
        <source>Mol. Biol. Cell</source>
        <volume>21</volume>
        <year>2010</year>
        <fpage>2975</fpage>
        <lpage>2986</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20631254</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib39">
      <label>39</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Z.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>X.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Deficiency of intestinal Bmal1 prevents obesity induced by high-fat feeding</article-title>
        <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <year>2021</year>
        <fpage>5323</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34493722</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib40">
      <label>40</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Takahashi</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Inoue</surname>
            <given-names>I.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nakajima</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Seo</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nakano</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A promoter in the novel exon of hPPARγ directs the circadian expression of PPARγ</article-title>
        <source>J. Atheroscler. Thromb.</source>
        <volume>17</volume>
        <year>2010</year>
        <fpage>73</fpage>
        <lpage>83</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20093779</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib41">
      <label>41</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tian</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>X.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Guo</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Z.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Goldstein</surname>
            <given-names>J.L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>BHLHE40, a third transcription factor required for insulin induction of SREBP-1c mRNA in rodent liver</article-title>
        <source>Elife</source>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <year>2018</year>
        <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e36826</object-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib42">
      <label>42</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Veeranki</surname>
            <given-names>O.L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bhattacharya</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Marshall</surname>
            <given-names>J.R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Organ-specific exposure and response to sulforaphane, a key chemopreventive ingredient in broccoli: implications for cancer prevention</article-title>
        <source>Br. J. Nutr.</source>
        <volume>109</volume>
        <year>2013</year>
        <fpage>25</fpage>
        <lpage>32</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22464629</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib43">
      <label>43</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Calabrese</surname>
            <given-names>E.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kozumbo</surname>
            <given-names>W.J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The hormetic dose-response mechanism: nrf2 activation</article-title>
        <source>Pharmacol. Res.</source>
        <volume>167</volume>
        <year>2021</year>
        <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">105526</object-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib44">
      <label>44</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ye</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dinkova-Kostova</surname>
            <given-names>A.T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wade</surname>
            <given-names>K.L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shapiro</surname>
            <given-names>T.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Talalay</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Quantitative determination of dithiocarbamates in human plasma, serum, erythrocytes and urine: pharmacokinetics of broccoli sprout isothiocyanates in humans</article-title>
        <source>Clin. Chim. Acta</source>
        <volume>316</volume>
        <year>2002</year>
        <fpage>43</fpage>
        <lpage>53</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11750273</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib45">
      <label>45</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cornblatt</surname>
            <given-names>B.S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ye</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dinkova-Kostova</surname>
            <given-names>A.T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Erb</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fahey</surname>
            <given-names>J.W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Singh</surname>
            <given-names>N.K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Preclinical and clinical evaluation of sulforaphane for chemoprevention in the breast</article-title>
        <source>Carcinogenesis</source>
        <volume>28</volume>
        <year>2007</year>
        <fpage>1485</fpage>
        <lpage>1490</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17347138</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib46">
      <label>46</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yagishita</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fahey</surname>
            <given-names>J.W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dinkova-Kostova</surname>
            <given-names>A.T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kensler</surname>
            <given-names>T.W.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Broccoli or sulforaphane: is it the source or dose that matters?</article-title>
        <source>Molecules</source>
        <volume>24</volume>
        <year>2019</year>
        <fpage>3593</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31590459</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib47">
      <label>47</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jalili</surname>
            <given-names>V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Afgan</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gu</surname>
            <given-names>Q.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Clements</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Blankenberg</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Goecks</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The Galaxy platform for accessible, reproducible and collaborative biomedical analyses: 2020 update</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>48</volume>
        <year>2020</year>
        <fpage>W395</fpage>
        <lpage>W402</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32479607</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib48">
      <label>48</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref48">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dewey</surname>
            <given-names>C.N.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>RSEM: accurate transcript quantification from RNA-Seq data with or without a reference genome</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <year>2011</year>
        <fpage>323</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21816040</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib49">
      <label>49</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref49">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wickham</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Averick</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bryan</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chang</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McGowan</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>François</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Welcome to the tidyverse</article-title>
        <source>J. Open Source Softw.</source>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <year>2019</year>
        <fpage>1686</fpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib50">
      <label>50</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref50">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gu</surname>
            <given-names>Z.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Eils</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schlesner</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Complex heatmaps reveal patterns and correlations in multidimensional genomic data</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <volume>32</volume>
        <year>2016</year>
        <fpage>2847</fpage>
        <lpage>2849</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27207943</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib51">
      <label>51</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref51">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Garcia-Alonso</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Holland</surname>
            <given-names>C.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ibrahim</surname>
            <given-names>M.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Turei</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Saez-Rodriguez</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Benchmark and integration of resources for the estimation of human transcription factor activities</article-title>
        <source>Genome Res.</source>
        <volume>29</volume>
        <year>2019</year>
        <fpage>1363</fpage>
        <lpage>1375</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31340985</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib52">
      <label>52</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref52">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Guo</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dai</surname>
            <given-names>Z.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>clusterProfiler 4.0: a universal enrichment tool for interpreting omics data</article-title>
        <source>Innovation (Camb.)</source>
        <volume>2</volume>
        <year>2021</year>
        <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100141</object-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
  <bio>
    <graphic xlink:href="fx1"/>
    <p><bold>Kan Etoh</bold> is a postdoctoral researcher at the Department of Medical Cell Biology in Kumamoto University, Japan. He investigates the molecular mechanisms that underlie cell-type specificity and context-dependent stress response, particularly those related to aging and chronic inflammation, using a multi-omics approach such as transcriptomic and epigenomic analyses. He is now developing easy-to-use tools in systematic and automated omics data analysis to remove technical barriers for research community.</p>
  </bio>
  <sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supporting information</title>
    <p id="p0150">
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1">
        <caption>
          <title>Supporting information</title>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="mmc1.docx"/>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc2">
        <caption>
          <title>Movie S1-1</title>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="mmc2.mp4"/>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc3">
        <caption>
          <title>Movie S1-2</title>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="mmc3.mp4"/>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc4">
        <caption>
          <title>Movie S3</title>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="mmc4.mp4"/>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc5">
        <caption>
          <title>Movie S4</title>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="mmc5.mp4"/>
      </supplementary-material>
    </p>
  </sec>
  <ack id="ack0010">
    <title>Acknowledgments</title>
    <p id="p0135">We thank the members in our laboratory and institution for helpful discussions. Particularly, Dr Sugiko Watanabe and Dr Miyuki Inoue cooperated for SFN experiments. Ms Yuko Hino, Dr Tomoaki Koga and Dr Shinjiro Hino performed trial runs of RNAseqChef.</p>
    <sec id="sec6">
      <title>Author contributions</title>
      <p id="p0140">K. E. and M. N. conceptualization; K. E. and M. N. methodology; K. E. software; K. E. formal analysis; K. E. and M. N. investigation; K. E. data curation; K. E. and M. N. writing–original draft; K. E. visualization; K. E. and M. N. funding acquisition; M. N. validation, supervision, and project administration</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec7">
      <title>Funding and additional information</title>
      <p id="p0145">This work was supported by Grant-in-Aid for Early-Career Scientists from the <funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100001700</institution-id><institution>Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> [20K16145 to K. E.], <funding-source id="gs2"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100001691</institution-id><institution>JSPS</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> KAKENHI [21H02686, 20KK0185 to M. N.], and by the program of the Inter-University Research Network for High Depth Omics, IMEG, <funding-source id="gs3"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100004091</institution-id><institution>Kumamoto University</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (to M. N.).</p>
    </sec>
  </ack>
</back>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?origin publisher?>
<?FILEmeta_JBC104810 xml ?>
<?FILEmain xml ?>
<?FILEmain pdf ?>
<?FILEgr1 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr2 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr3 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr4 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr5 jpg ?>
<?FILEfx1 jpg ?>
<?FILEmmc1 docx ?>
<?FILEmmc2 jpg ?>
<?FILEmmc2 mp4 ?>
<?FILEmmc3 jpg ?>
<?FILEmmc3 mp4 ?>
<?FILEmmc4 jpg ?>
<?FILEmmc4 mp4 ?>
<?FILEmmc5 jpg ?>
<?FILEmmc5 mp4 ?>
<?properties open_access?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Biol Chem</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Biol Chem</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9258</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1083-351X</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">10267603</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S0021-9258(23)01838-0</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbc.2023.104810</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">104810</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Research Article</subject>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Editors' Pick</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>A web-based integrative transcriptome analysis, RNAseqChef, uncovers the cell/tissue type-dependent action of sulforaphane</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1">
        <name>
          <surname>Etoh</surname>
          <given-names>Kan</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2">
        <name>
          <surname>Nakao</surname>
          <given-names>Mitsuyoshi</given-names>
        </name>
        <email>mnakao@gpo.kumamoto-u.ac.jp</email>
        <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="aff1">Department of Medical Cell Biology, Institute of Molecular Embryology and Genetics, Kumamoto University, Kumamoto, Japan</aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>For correspondence: Mitsuyoshi Nakao <email>mnakao@gpo.kumamoto-u.ac.jp</email></corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>11</day>
      <month>5</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <month>6</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>11</day>
      <month>5</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>299</volume>
    <issue>6</issue>
    <elocation-id>104810</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>27</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© 2023 The Authors</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract id="abs0010">
      <p>RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) is a powerful technique for understanding cellular state and dynamics. However, comprehensive transcriptomic characterization of multiple RNA-seq datasets is laborious without bioinformatics training and skills. To remove the barriers to sequence data analysis in the research community, we have developed “RNAseqChef” (<underline>RNA</underline>-<underline>seq</underline> data <underline>c</underline>ontroller <underline>h</underline>ighlighting <underline>e</underline>xpression <underline>f</underline>eatures), a web-based platform of systematic transcriptome analysis that can automatically detect, integrate, and visualize differentially expressed genes and their biological functions. To validate its versatile performance, we examined the pharmacological action of sulforaphane (SFN), a natural isothiocyanate, on various types of cells and mouse tissues using multiple datasets <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic>. Notably, SFN treatment upregulated the ATF6-mediated unfolded protein response in the liver and the NRF2-mediated antioxidant response in the skeletal muscle of diet-induced obese mice. In contrast, the commonly downregulated pathways included collagen synthesis and circadian rhythms in the tissues tested. On the server of RNAseqChef, we simply evaluated and visualized all analyzing data and discovered the NRF2-independent action of SFN. Collectively, RNAseqChef provides an easy-to-use open resource that identifies context-dependent transcriptomic features and standardizes data assessment.</p>
    </abstract>
    <kwd-group id="kwrds0010">
      <title>Keywords</title>
      <kwd>RNAseqChef</kwd>
      <kwd>open resource</kwd>
      <kwd>transcriptomics</kwd>
      <kwd>sulforaphane</kwd>
      <kwd>NRF2 (<italic>NFE2L2</italic>)</kwd>
      <kwd>antioxidant response</kwd>
      <kwd>ATF6</kwd>
      <kwd>unfolded protein response</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
  </article-meta>
  <def-list>
    <title>Abbreviations</title>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0055">BAT</term>
      <def>
        <p>brown adipose tissue</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0065">DEG</term>
      <def>
        <p>differentially expressed gene</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0075">eWAT</term>
      <def>
        <p>epididymal white adipose tissue</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0085">GEO</term>
      <def>
        <p>Gene Expression Omnibus</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0095">HFD</term>
      <def>
        <p>high-fat diet</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0105">iWAT</term>
      <def>
        <p>inguinal WAT</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0115">NRF2</term>
      <def>
        <p>nucleus factor-E2-related factor 2</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0125">PCA</term>
      <def>
        <p>Principal component analysis</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0135">RNA-seq</term>
      <def>
        <p>RNA sequencing</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0145">ROS</term>
      <def>
        <p>reactive oxygen species</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0155">SFN</term>
      <def>
        <p>Sulforaphane</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0165">TF</term>
      <def>
        <p>transcription factor</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0175">UMAP</term>
      <def>
        <p>Uniform manifold approximation and projection</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0185">UPR</term>
      <def>
        <p>unfolded protein response</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
  </def-list>
  <notes>
    <p id="misc0010">Reviewed by members of the JBC Editorial Board. Edited by Brian Strahl</p>
  </notes>
</front>
<body>
  <p id="p0010">RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) is a core technology used for comprehensive gene expression analyses (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). RNA-seq datasets are deposited in public databases such as the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) so that researchers can freely utilize the available data (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Currently, more than 100,000 datasets derived from cell lines and tissues of various species are available for re-analyses, which are useful resources for those with a general interest in the life science field. However, a series of data investigations, including differentially expressed gene (DEG) analysis, data integration, clustering, functional analysis, and visualization, are considerably laborious for most researchers and scientists not specializing in bioinformatics.</p>
  <p id="p0015">Sulforaphane (SFN) is a natural isothiocyanate generated by cruciferous vegetables such as broccoli. SFN is known to interact with the active cysteine residues of KEAP1 (Kelch-like ECH-associated protein 1), resulting in the activation of nucleus factor-E2-related factor 2, NRF2 (<italic>NFE2L2</italic>), which is the master transcription factor for redox homeostasis (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). SFN treatment has anti-obesity and antidiabetic effects through NRF2 activation in multiple models, such as diet-induced obese mice and rodents (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Indeed, SFN-induced activation of NRF2 has been shown to ameliorate oxidative and endoplasmic reticulum (ER) stress, which causes excessive adipogenesis, lipid accumulation, inflammation, and fibrosis (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). However, recent studies have shown the cytotoxic effect of SFN in cancer cells <italic>via</italic> mitochondrial damage and apoptosis induction (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Although it is plausible that SFN actions depend on cellular status, little is known about the context-dependent effects of SFN. Furthermore, the NRF2-independent actions of SFN remain poorly understood.</p>
  <p id="p0020">Upon RNA-seq analysis of multiple datasets, numerous workflows are required for the user’s demands. However, existing web platforms are adjusted for the analysis of “single dataset” (controls <italic>versus</italic> subjects) but not “multiple datasets” ([controls <italic>versus</italic> subjects] × n). In this study, we developed RNAseqChef (an RNA-seq data controller highlighting expression features), a web-based systematic analysis of multiple RNA-seq datasets. Using this platform, we performed integrative transcriptome analysis of SFN-treated cultured cells and model mice. We found that SFN-induced ATF6-mediated unfolded protein response (UPR) without NRF2 activation, and that SFN-induced UPR occurred in the liver, but not in other metabolic tissues, in diet-induced obese mice. We also found that SFN treatment downregulated the expression of collagen and circadian rhythm-associated genes involved in fibrosis and lipid metabolism, respectively. Thus, SFN-induced transcriptomic changes depended on the cell/tissue type. RNAseqChef platform evaluates molecular features without special bioinformatic skills in biological and medical research fields and allows integration, simplification, user-centered, and standardization of data assessment.</p>
  <sec id="sec1">
    <title>Results</title>
    <sec id="sec1.1">
      <title>Design of RNAseqChef</title>
      <p id="p0025">RNAseqChef (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://imeg-ku.shinyapps.io/RNAseqChef/" id="intref0010">https://imeg-ku.shinyapps.io/RNAseqChef/</ext-link>) is a user-centered web-based application for the systematic integrative analysis of RNA-seq data (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figs. 1</xref><italic>A</italic> and <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">S1</xref>; <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Movie S1</xref>). The user’s graphical interface of RNAseqChef comprises “Menu”, “Settings”, “Output” and “Tab” panels, which do not require any special bioinformatics skills to navigate (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S2</xref>). In contrast to the existing web platforms (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>), users can analyze not only a single dataset but also integrate and evaluate multiple datasets (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref><italic>B</italic>). To establish the versatility of RNAseqChef, we divided its core functions into six sections, which enabled us to handle various types of input files (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref><italic>A</italic>). RNAseqChef consists of the following 2 units: DEG Analysis Unit (“Pair-wise”, “3 conditions DEG” and “Multi DEG”) and Integrative Analysis Unit (“Venn diagram”, “Normalized count analysis” and “Enrichment viewer”). The DEG Analysis Unit was optimized for the analysis of a single dataset to automatically perform DEG detection, pathway analysis, and data visualization by uploading the raw count data. “Pair-wise DEG” was adjusted for pair-wise comparison analysis, and “3 conditions DEG” was enhanced for multiple comparison analysis of three groups using EBSeq (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). “Multi DEG” was optimized for the analysis of time-series experiments using the DESeq2 likelihood ratio test (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). To increase the throughput for the pairwise analysis of multiple datasets and subsequent integrative analysis, we created the batch-mode in “Pair-wise DEG”, which sequentially performs DEG analysis of all uploaded files, and then outputs the following results: clustering plot, MA-plot, DEG result, lists of both upregulated and downregulated DEGs, and normalized count data. The results files obtained from the DEG Analysis Unit can be used as input files for the Integrative Analysis Unit, which makes it easy to perform a flexible analysis on demand (<italic>e.g.</italic>, <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref><italic>A</italic> and <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Movie S2</xref>). “Venn diagram” was optimized for Venn diagram and subsequent analysis (heatmap and pathway analysis). “Normalized count analysis” was adjusted for clustering analysis of normalized count data, and “Enrichment viewer” was optimized for functional pathway and promoter motif analysis. In addition, the pathway databases that are used for enrichment analysis in RNAseqChef can be referred to from the “MSigDB” (Molecular Signatures Database) and “DoRothEA regulon” in the “More” section of RNAseqChef.<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Overview of RNAseqChef (RNA-seq data controller highlighting gene expression feature).</bold><italic>A</italic>, RNAseqChef is a web-based platform of systematic transcriptome analysis and can automatically detect, integrate, and visualize the DEGs and their biological functions, by uploading the raw count files of interest. The “DEG Analysis Unit” consists of “Pair-wise DEG”, “3 conditions DEG”, and “Multi DEG”. The “Integrative Analysis Unit” then consists of “Venn diagram,” “Normalized count analysis,” and “Enrichment viewer.” The result files obtained from the DEG Analysis Unit can be used as input files for the Integrative Analysis Unit, which makes it easy to perform the bioinformatic studies on demand. <italic>B</italic>, analysis of the common and cell/tissue-specific effects of SFN on transcriptome using RNAseqChef. DEG, differentially expressed gene; SFN, Sulforaphane.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Cellular response to SFN is different among cell types.</bold><italic>A</italic>, schematic representation of the RNAseqChef analysis designed to highlight SFN-induced transcriptomic features and their cell-type dependency. Raw count data were obtained from public RNA-seq datasets of epithelial cells (Epi; GSE141740) and HaCaT keratinocytes (Ker; GSE185320), under control (Ctrl; DMSO-treated) and 10 μM SFN-treated conditions (each n = 2). Along with the workflow in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>, <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>, it takes approximately 5 min to complete all analyzing steps. <italic>B</italic>, transcriptome-based PCA of Ctrl and SFN-treated cells. <italic>C</italic>, Venn diagram of genes significantly upregulated by SFN treatment (using DESeq2 (FDR &lt; 0.01)). <italic>D</italic>, heatmap of commonly upregulated genes shown in (<italic>C</italic>). <italic>E</italic> and <italic>F</italic>, top-ranked functional pathways (<italic>E</italic>) and transcription factors (TFs) (<italic>F</italic>) were enriched in gene sets upregulated by SFN treatment, including 499 common genes (<italic>green</italic>), 1146 Epi unique genes (<italic>red</italic>), and 1212 Ker unique genes (<italic>blue</italic>), as shown in (<italic>C</italic>). Enrichment analysis was performed based on MSigDB hallmark (<italic>E</italic>) and DoRothEA regulon gene set (<italic>F</italic>). FDR &lt;0.05. <italic>G</italic>, normalized expression values of the representatives for common, Epi unique, and Ker unique genes upregulated by SFN. ∗∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01; ∗∗∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001. FDR, false discovery rate; PCA, Principal component analysis; SFN, Sulforaphane.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.2">
      <title>Biological responses to SFN treatment depend on cell types</title>
      <p id="p0030">Based on our criteria that the read depth should be more than 10 million reads per sample, we found reliable <italic>in vitro</italic> datasets of cultured human cells, epithelial cells (Epi: GSE141740), and keratinocytes (Ker: GSE185320), which were treated with control (Ctrl) or SFN (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). To characterize the transcriptomic features in response to SFN, we performed an integrative analysis of these datasets using RNAseqChef (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref><italic>A</italic>). It took approximately 5 min to complete all steps (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Movie S2</xref>). Principal component analysis (PCA) showed that the cell type datasets (Epi or Ker) with treatment (Ctrl or SFN) were distinctly positioned (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref><italic>B</italic>). To identify the common and cell type-specific genes affected by SFN treatment, we detected DEGs from each dataset using DESeq2 (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S3</xref>, <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>) and conducted Venn diagram analysis (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figs. 2</xref><italic>C</italic> and <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">S3</xref><italic>F</italic>). SFN treatment upregulated 499 genes in both cell types (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>, <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>). In contrast, 1146 and 1212 genes were upregulated in SFN-treated Epi and Ker, respectively (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref><italic>C</italic>). To clarify the biological relevance of SFN-associated genes, we performed enrichment analysis based on the MSigDB hallmark gene set (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figs. 2</xref><italic>E</italic> and <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">S3</xref>, <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>). Consistent with previous reports (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>), the top-ranked pathways related to the 499 commonly upregulated genes were the mammalian target of rapamycin complex 1 (mTORC1) signaling, apoptosis, reactive oxygen species (ROS) pathway, and glycolysis (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref><italic>E</italic>). In addition, transcription factor (TF) enrichment analysis based on the DoRothEA regulon gene set identified a well-known SFN-target NRF2, which transcriptionally activates antioxidant genes (<italic>TXNRD1, HMOX1,</italic> and <italic>NQO1</italic>) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figs. 2</xref><italic>F</italic> and <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">S3</xref><italic>E</italic>). In contrast, 1212 Ker-specific genes, but not 1146 Epi-specific genes, enriched inflammation-related pathways, such as interferon-γ (IFNγ) response (<italic>IRF1</italic> and <italic>ISG20</italic>), and TFs, such as RELA (targeting <italic>IRF1</italic>) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, <italic>E</italic> and <italic>G</italic>). We also analyzed downregulated genes in SFN-treated cells using enrichment analysis (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S3</xref><italic>F</italic>). The 242 commonly downregulated genes by SFN-enriched TFDP1/E2F targets (<italic>GINS1</italic> and <italic>SRSF2</italic>) (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S3</xref>, <italic>G</italic>–<italic>I</italic>). A total of 1652 Ker-specific genes, but not Epi-specific genes, enriched p53 pathway (<italic>CDKN1A</italic>) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figs. 2</xref><italic>G</italic> and <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">S3</xref>, <italic>G</italic> and <italic>H</italic>) and estrogen response (<italic>KRT13</italic> and <italic>KRT15</italic>) (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S3</xref>, <italic>G</italic>–<italic>I</italic>). Thus, we found that SFN has both common and cell type-specific effects using RNAseqChef analysis of multiple RNA-seq datasets.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.3">
      <title>SFN induces the unfolded protein response in an NRF2-independent manner</title>
      <p id="p0035">SFN has been reported to trigger an oxidative stress response through the activation of NRF2 (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>), but its NRF2-independent functions remain poorly understood. To address this, we performed a clustering analysis of genes commonly upregulated by SFN (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figs. 2</xref><italic>C</italic> and <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref><italic>A</italic>). For this purpose, we used normalized count data from control WT, SFN-treated WT, and SFN-treated NRF KO epithelial cells (GSE141740) for the clustering approach. NRF2 dependency was defined as whether NRF2 KO canceled the effects of SFN on gene expression. k-means clustering analysis detected 194 NRF2-dependent and 281 NRF2-independent upregulated genes (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref><italic>B</italic>). As expected, enrichment analysis showed that NRF2-dependent upregulated genes enriched both the ROS pathway and the NRF2 targets (such as <italic>NQO1</italic>, <italic>GCLM</italic>, and <italic>TXNRD1</italic>), while NRF2-independent upregulated genes did not at all (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, <italic>C</italic>–<italic>E</italic>), indicating that RNAseqChef had a secure clustering capacity. In contrast, NRF2-independent upregulated genes enriched the UPR and its regulator ATF6 targets (such as <italic>BiP</italic> (binding immunoglobulin protein, gene symbol <italic>HSPA5</italic>) and <italic>ERdj6</italic> (ER-resident protein, gene symbol <italic>DNAJC3</italic>)) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, <italic>C</italic>–<italic>E</italic>). Furthermore, similar results were obtained by EBSeq multiple comparison analyses of the three groups (control WT, SFN-WT, and SFN-NRF2 KO) by “3 conditions DEG” in RNAseqChef (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S4</xref><italic>A</italic> and <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Movie S3</xref>). We detected 293 NRF2-dependent upregulated genes that enriched the ROS pathway (<italic>q</italic> value: 1.1 × 10<sup>−4</sup>) and NRF2 targets (<italic>q</italic> value: 5.8 × 10<sup>−3</sup>) (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S4</xref>, <italic>B</italic>–<italic>E</italic>). We also detected 578 NRF2-independent upregulated genes that enriched UPR (<italic>q</italic> value: 1.4 × 10<sup>−3</sup>) and ATF6 targets (<italic>q</italic> value: 6.5 × 10<sup>−3</sup>) (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S4</xref>, <italic>F</italic>–<italic>I</italic>). We then performed a clustering analysis of 242 genes commonly downregulated by SFN and detected 91 NRF2-dependent and 151 NRF2-independent downregulated genes (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Figs. S3</xref><italic>F</italic> and <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">S5</xref><italic>A</italic>). NRF2-dependent downregulated genes enriched E2F targets and the TGFβ signaling pathway (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S5</xref>, <italic>B</italic> and <italic>C</italic>), but NRF2-independent downregulated genes did not.<fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>SFN induces the unfolded protein response in an NRF2-independent manner.</bold><italic>A</italic>, schematic representation of the RNAseqChef analysis designed to identify the NRF2-dependent or independent actions of SFN in epithelial cells. Gene extraction of the common genes from the normalized count data (control WT, SFN-treated WT and NRF2 KO, each n = 2) was performed in the “Normalized count analysis” section. Subsequent k-means clustering was done using the tab panel named “k-means clustering” in the same section. Enrichment analysis was performed by uploading the result file obtained from k-means clustering in the “Enrichment viewer” section. <italic>B</italic>, the k-means clustering approach separated 499 commonly upregulated genes (shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref><italic>C</italic>) into two groups based on NRF2 dependency. The <italic>magenta</italic> and <italic>green box</italic> indicate 281 NRF-independent and 194 NRF2-dependent upregulated genes, respectively. The 24 genes (in the <italic>bottom</italic> cluster of the heatmap) were not separated into the above groups because their expression patterns were not obvious. <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>, top-ranked functional pathways (<italic>C</italic>) and TFs (<italic>D</italic>) were enriched in gene sets upregulated by SFN treatment, including 475 ALL genes (sum of the following genes), 194 NRF2-dependent genes, and 281 NRF2-independent genes. Enrichment analysis was performed based on MSigDB hallmark (<italic>C</italic>) and DoRothEA regulon gene set (<italic>D</italic>). FDR &lt;0.05. <italic>E</italic>, TPM expression values of the representative NRF2-dependent and NRF2-independent genes that were upregulated by SFN. ∗∗∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001. FDR, false discovery rate; NRF2, nucleus factor-E2-related factor 2; SFN, Sulforaphane; TPM, Transcripts per million; WT, wild type.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p>
      <p id="p0040">UPR is induced by ER stress to attenuate protein synthesis, increase protein folding, and enhance the activity of protein degradation pathways, which are important for preventing pathological conditions such as amyloid disease and diabetes (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). ATF6 is an ER stress sensor for the UPR that upregulates cytoprotective pathways, including protein folding and ER homeostasis (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Although it has previously been shown that SFN modulates UPR through an NRF2-dependent mechanism (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>), it is unknown whether SFN enhances UPR without NRF2. To further examine the effect of NRF2 on UPR, we analyzed the RNA-seq data of constitutively active NRF2 (caNRF2)-expressing fibroblasts (GSE106097) (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). NRF2-dependent genes (<italic>Nqo1</italic> and <italic>Gclm</italic>), but not UPR genes (<italic>Atf4</italic>, <italic>BiP</italic>, and <italic>ERdj6</italic>), were significantly upregulated in caNRF2-expressed cells (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S6</xref><italic>A</italic>). Further, we examined the recent RNA-seq data of human uterine leiomyosarcoma SK-UT-1 cells that were treated with 5 μM SFN (GSE205777) (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Consistent with the results of Epi cells (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref><italic>E</italic>), both NRF2-target genes and UPR-related genes were upregulated in SFN-treated SK-UT-1 cells (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S6</xref><italic>B</italic>). These results suggested that SFN functions as a UPR inducer in an NRF2-independent manner.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.4">
      <title>Upregulated genes by SFN treatment depend on tissue types in diet-induced obese mice</title>
      <p id="p0045">To address SFN action <italic>in vivo</italic>, we analyzed the RNA-seq dataset of five major metabolic tissues, including the liver, skeletal muscle, brown adipose tissue (BAT), epididymal white adipose tissue (eWAT), and inguinal WAT (iWAT), in diet-induced obese mice in the presence or absence of SFN treatment (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). C57BL/6J mice were fed a high-fat diet (HFD, 60% of the calories from fat) for 16 weeks to induce obesity and were treated with daily intraperitoneal SFN injections (5 mg/kg, i.p.) during the last 1 week of the experimental period (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S7</xref><italic>A</italic>). SFN treatment resulted in body weight loss and improvement in obesity, where it was reported that NRF2-dependent antioxidant genes were upregulated in the skeletal muscle and that fatty acid synthesis genes were downregulated in the liver, BAT, and eWAT (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). However, the common and tissue-specific effects of SFN have not yet been explored using unbiased transcriptome analysis.</p>
      <p id="p0050">Uniform manifold approximation and projection (UMAP) placed the dataset derived from the same tissue in close proximity (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref><italic>A</italic>), indicating that each tissue type had different transcriptomic features. To identify the common and tissue-specific genes affected by SFN treatment, we detected DEG genes from each tissue type using DESeq2 and then conducted Venn diagram analysis (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figs. 4</xref><italic>B</italic> and <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">S7</xref>, <italic>B</italic> and <italic>C</italic>). Interestingly, there was no overlap of upregulated genes among the five tissues, and most intersections among more than two tissues consisted of fewer than ten genes, suggesting that SFN treatment induced distinct transcriptomic changes depending on the tissue type of HFD-fed obese mice. To gain insight into the biological role of the upregulated genes in each tissue type of SFN-treated HFD-fed mice, we performed an enrichment analysis of the tissue-specific upregulated genes using the MSigDB hallmark and DoRothEA regulon gene sets (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figs. 4</xref>, <italic>C</italic>–<italic>F</italic>, and <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">S8</xref>, <italic>A</italic>–<italic>C</italic>). The results showed that adipogenesis and its regulator PPARα were upregulated in the BAT; IFNα response and its regulator STAT1 were upregulated in the eWAT; UPR and ATF6 were upregulated in the liver; and ROS pathway and NRF2 were upregulated in the skeletal muscle. In particular, ATF6-targeted genes involved in UPR function, including protein folding (such as <italic>ERdj4/6, DNAJB1</italic>, and <italic>Hyou1</italic>), quality control and degradation (<italic>Edem1/2/3</italic> and <italic>Os9</italic>), and ER protein import (<italic>Sec61a/b</italic>), were upregulated in the liver (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref><italic>E</italic>), but not in other tissues, in SFN-treated HFD-fed mice. In contrast, muscle-unique upregulated genes included anti-oxidant and NRF2 targets (<italic>Txnrd1</italic> and <italic>Gclm</italic>) (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref><italic>F</italic>), although the <italic>Nrf2</italic> gene itself was moderately expressed in the muscle (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S8</xref><italic>D</italic>). These data revealed that SFN action significantly depends on the tissue type in HFD-fed obese mice.<fig id="fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>SFN treatment induces tissue-specific transcriptomic changes in obese mice.</bold><italic>A</italic>, transcriptome-based UMAP of five metabolic tissues such as BAT, eWAT, iWAT, liver, and skeletal muscle in high fat diet-fed obese mice. Data set is GSE181477 (untreated Ctrl (−) and SNF-treated (+); each n = 5, except for eWAT (n = 4)). <italic>B</italic>, Venn diagram of genes significantly upregulated by SFN treatment (FDR &lt; 0.05). <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>, top-ranked functional pathways (<italic>C</italic>) and TFs (<italic>D</italic>) were enriched in gene sets upregulated by SFN treatment, including 157 BAT unique genes (<italic>red</italic>), 299 eWAT unique genes (<italic>yellow</italic>), 1252 liver unique genes (<italic>blue</italic>) and 65 muscle unique genes (<italic>green</italic>), as shown in (<italic>B</italic>). Enrichment analysis was performed based on MSigDB hallmark (<italic>C</italic>) and DoRothEA regulon gene set (<italic>D</italic>). FDR &lt;0.05. <italic>E</italic>, volcano plot obtained from pair-wise DEG analysis (Ctrl <italic>versus</italic> SFN) of the liver in HFD-fed obese mice. As indicated with <italic>green dots,</italic> ATF6-targeted UPR genes were significantly upregulated by SFN treatment (FDR &lt; 0.05). <italic>F</italic>, TPM expression values of the representative skeletal muscle-unique genes upregulated by SFN. ∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; ∗∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01. BAT, brown adipose tissue; eWAT, epididymal white adipose tissue; FDR, false discovery rate; HFD, high-fat diet; iWAT, inguinal WAT; SFN, Sulforaphane; TPM, Transcripts per million; UPR, unfolded protein response; WT, wild type.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.5">
      <title>SFN treatment downregulates collagen and circadian rhythm genes in obese mice</title>
      <p id="p0055">Finally, we focused on the downregulated genes in SFN-treated HFD-fed obese mice. In contrast to the absence of commonly upregulated genes (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref><italic>B</italic>), SFN treatment downregulated three genes (<italic>Col6a2</italic>, <italic>Lum</italic>, and <italic>Rev-erbβ</italic> (nuclear receptor subfamily one group D member 1, gene symbol <italic>NR1D1</italic>)) in the five tissues tested (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>). In addition, the epithelial-mesenchymal transition pathway, which contained genes involved in fibrosis, wound healing, and metastasis, was enriched in the commonly downregulated genes among these tissue types (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S9</xref>, <italic>A</italic>–<italic>E</italic>). Several genes, including collagen (<italic>Col1a1/2/3</italic>, <italic>Col3a1, Col5a1</italic>, and <italic>Col6a1/2/3</italic>), <italic>Fn1</italic>, and <italic>Lum,</italic> were evidently decreased in the examined tissues of SFN-treated HFD-fed mice (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref><italic>C</italic>), which has been implicated in tissue fibrosis (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Furthermore, we detected BMAL1 (brain and muscle ARNT-like 1, gene symbol <italic>Arntl</italic>), a regulator of circadian rhythm, whose targets were enriched in the downregulated genes in BAT, iWAT, and skeletal muscle (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S9</xref>, <italic>A</italic>, <italic>C</italic>, and <italic>E</italic>). BMAL1/CLOCK-target genes that are involved in circadian oscillation (such as <italic>Rev-erbα/β</italic>) and clock-controlled energy metabolism genes (<italic>Dbp</italic> and <italic>Bhlhe40</italic>) were downregulated in more than two tissues of SFN-treated HFD-fed obese mice (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, <italic>B</italic> and <italic>D</italic>). To exclude the effect of <italic>in vivo</italic> environmental factors on circadian rhythms, we checked the expression levels of circadian genes in SFN-treated cells <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S10</xref>). SFN treatment reduced the expression of multiple circadian oscillators (<italic>REV-ERBβ</italic>, <italic>CRY1</italic>, and <italic>PER1/2/3</italic>) in both WT and NRF2 KO epithelial cells, although there were no evident changes in the mRNA levels of <italic>BMAL1</italic> and <italic>CLOCK</italic>. Thus, these results suggest that SFN downregulates collagen synthesis and circadian rhythms in multiple tissues and cultured cells. In addition, as was the unique tissue-type upregulated genes by SFN treatment (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>, <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>), we found the presence of unique tissue-type downregulated genes (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S11</xref>). Taken together, RNAseqChef analysis of multiple RNA-seq datasets demonstrated that SFN had common and tissue-specific effects <italic>in vivo</italic>.<fig id="fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>SFN treatment downregulates collagen genes and BMAL1/CLOCK target genes in obese mice.</bold><italic>A</italic>, Venn diagram of genes significantly downregulated by SFN treatment (FDR &lt; 0.05). <italic>B</italic>, TPM expression values of genes commonly downregulated by SFN in five metabolic tissues of HFD-fed obese mice. ∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; ∗∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01; ∗∗∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001. <italic>C</italic>, heatmap of the hallmark gene set “Epithelial mesenchymal transition,” which was downregulated in the tissues of SFN-treated obese mice, as shown in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S9</xref>. Fibrosis-associated genes are highlighted in <italic>red</italic>. <italic>D</italic>, TPM expression values of <italic>Bmal1</italic> and BMAL1/CLOCK target genes downregulated in multiple tissues of SFN-treated HFD-fed obese mice. ∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; ∗∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01; ∗∗∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001. FDR, false discovery rate; HFD, high-fat diet; SFN, Sulforaphane; TPM, Transcripts per million.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2">
    <title>Discussion</title>
    <p id="p0060">To maximize the comprehensive capacity of RNA-seq analysis in biological research fields, we developed a user-centered web application, RNAseqChef (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref><italic>A</italic>). The present study verified that RNAseqChef enabled us to perform DEG analysis, data integration, and visualization (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Movies S1–S3</xref>). As demonstrated in our SFN study, the performance (time) was about 5 min for visualizing all analyzing data (in the case of <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>) (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Movie S2</xref>). In addition, running RNAseqChef did not depend on the user's computer specs because data analysis was performed on the server. Because the count data of bulk RNA-seq are usually obtained from public databases, such as GREIN (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>), anyone can readily perform and reproduce integrative RNA-seq analysis using RNAseqChef. Furthermore, gene lists obtained from the other omics analyses (<italic>e.g.</italic>, ChIP-seq, ATAC-seq, and methylome collected in ChIP-atlas (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>)) can be used as an input file for the Integrative Analysis Unit in RNAseqChef to merge RNA-seq data with epigenome information (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref><italic>A</italic>). Thus, RNAseqChef would facilitate our understanding of the physiological and pathological processes in multiple omics layers.</p>
    <p id="p0065">Previous studies have shown that SFN has an anti-obesity function in an NRF2-dependent manner, but a transcriptomic characterization of SFN action has not been performed in detail. We found that SFN treatment specifically activated ATF6-mediated UPR in the liver of HFD-fed obese mice (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>, <italic>C</italic>–<italic>E</italic>). It has been reported that ATF6 is important for attenuating hepatic steatosis under ER stress triggers, such as HFD, and that hepatic ATF6-conditional knockout causes lipid accumulation in the liver through the upregulation of the PPARγ pathway that facilitates lipogenesis (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Accordingly, we speculated that SFN ameliorates hepatic lipid accumulation through an ATF6-dependent UPR. Consistent with this, SFN treatment decreased the expression of a series of genes responsible for acetyl-CoA synthesis (such as <italic>Me1</italic> and <italic>Acly</italic>), fatty acid synthesis from acetyl-CoA (<italic>Acaca</italic> and <italic>Fasn</italic>), fatty acid elongation and desaturation (<italic>Elovl6</italic> and <italic>Scd1</italic>), and lipid deposition (<italic>Pparγ</italic> and <italic>Cidec</italic>) (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S8</xref>, <italic>E</italic> and <italic>F</italic>). In addition, SFN treatment affected the expression levels of fibrosis-related collagen and circadian rhythm genes. Previous reports have shown that SFN attenuates hepatic fibrosis <italic>via</italic> the NRF2-mediated inhibition of TGFβ signaling (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Our RNA-seq analysis consistently showed that SFN treatment downregulated the TGFβ pathway in an NRF2-dependent manner (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig. S5</xref><italic>B</italic>), suggesting that SFN treatment suppresses the synthesis of profibrogenic proteins in obese mice. The core transcription factor BMAL1 in the circadian rhythm has been shown to regulate energy metabolism (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). We found that SFN treatment in obese mice decreased BMAL1-target genes, such as <italic>Dbp</italic> and <italic>Bhlhe40</italic> (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref><italic>D</italic>), which are important for the induction of PPARγ and SREBP-1c, which are key transcriptional factors involved in lipid metabolism (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). It is possible that the SFN-mediated regulation of circadian rhythms contributes to the anti-obesity effect.</p>
    <p id="p0070">Our RNA-seq analyses utilized high-quality public RNA-seq datasets from independent research groups and demonstrated the potential action of SFN. To validate our findings in this study, further studies will be needed to understand the contribution of the SFN-induced transcriptome to phenotypic effects and the molecular mechanism of SFN action, using different concentrations of SFN in various cells/tissues tested. Actually, previous reports have shown that SFN has a hormetic dose-dependent effect and exhibits different tissue distribution (<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>).</p>
    <p id="p0075">RNAseqChef was optimized for analyzing “bulk RNA-seq” count data from public databases or their sequencing results. Users can utilize count data, but not RNA-seq raw data (<italic>i.e.</italic>, fastq files), as input for this application. Thus, in the case that you cannot obtain the count data from the database, you would need to obtain fastq files from the Sequence Read Archive and then perform pre-processing such as quality control and mapping by using a command line or web services such as Galaxy (<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). In addition, RNAseqChef is not currently available for “single-cell RNA-seq” analysis. Beyond these issues, as a further advantage of RNAseqChef, the user can simply merge the RNA-seq dataset with epigenomic datasets, such as ChIP-seq and ATAC-seq, for an overview of multilayered omics data. Collectively, RNAseqChef would provide us with sufficient application to investigate RNA-seq datasets from biological and pharmacological effects to achieve standardization of data assessment.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec3">
    <title>Experimental procedures</title>
    <sec id="sec3.1">
      <title>Public datasets</title>
      <p id="p0080">Raw datasets from public databases were collected from the “GEO repository” (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/" id="intref0015">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</ext-link>). The following public datasets regarding the SFN-induced transcriptome were used: 10 μM SFN-treated epithelial cells (GSE141740), 10 μM SFN-treated HaCaT keratinocytes (GSE185320), caNRF2-expressing fibroblasts (GSE106097), 5 μM SFN-treated SK-UT-1 cells (GSE205777), and 5 mg/ml SFN injected obese mice fed a HFD (GSE181477). To generate the raw count data, the RNA-seq raw data were mapped to the human (or mouse) reference genome (hg19 or mm10) using STAR <italic>via</italic> rsem-calculate-expression in the RSEM package (<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). Raw counts and Transcripts per million (TPM)-normalized data were obtained from the results of rsem-calculate-expression. Deposited data are summarized in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Table S1</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec3.2">
      <title>RNAseqChef</title>
      <p id="p0085">To develop RNAseqChef, the Shiny package was used to build an interactive web application using the open-source R programming language (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=shiny" id="intref0020">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=shiny</ext-link>). A total of 79 R packages were used to create the core functions of RNAseqChef, as described in the source code (<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.5281/zenodo.7095218" id="intref0025">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7095218</ext-link>). Software and algorithms are summarized in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Table S1</xref>. The website for RNAseqChef is currently hosted on the shinyapps.io server (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://imeg-ku.shinyapps.io/RNAseqChef/" id="intref0030">https://imeg-ku.shinyapps.io/RNAseqChef/</ext-link>), which may have some limitations such as the capacity of the server and the number of simultaneous connections, and the terms of use as described by shinyapps.io (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.rstudio.com/about/shinyapps-terms-use/" id="intref0035">https://www.rstudio.com/about/shinyapps-terms-use/</ext-link>). To overcome these points, the RNAseqChef Docker image (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://hub.docker.com/r/omicschef/rnaseqchef" id="intref0040">https://hub.docker.com/r/omicschef/rnaseqchef</ext-link>) has been developed to allow local installation and use on a private computer and network.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec3.3">
      <title>DEG analysis in RNAseqChef</title>
      <p id="p0090">For pair-wise comparison analysis, DEG detection was performed in the “Pair-wise DEG” section that used the DESeq2 package (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) with an FDR cutoff value of 0.01 and 0.05 for <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> data, respectively. For multiple comparisons of the three groups, DEG detection was performed in the “3 conditions DEG” using the EBSeq package (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) with the following thresholds: fold change &gt;1.25, FDR &lt;0.01, and basemean &gt;1. For the visualization of DEGs, both MA-plot and boxplots were drawn using the ggpubr package (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=ggpubr" id="intref0045">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=ggpubr</ext-link>), and both volcano plots and scatter plots were drawn using ggplot2 in the tidyverse package (<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). In addition, a heat map was drawn using the ComplexHeatmap package (<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). For the comparison of DEGs from different datasets, Venn diagram analysis was performed using the Venn package (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=venn" id="intref0050">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=venn</ext-link>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec3.4">
      <title>Clustering analysis in RNAseqChef</title>
      <p id="p0095">To evaluate the transcriptomic similarity and heterogeneity of the RNA-seq data, PCA and UMAP were performed using the prcomp function and umap (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=umap" id="intref0055">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=umap</ext-link>) package, respectively. For gene classification based on NRF2-dependency, k-means clustering was performed using ComplexHeatmap (<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec3.5">
      <title>Enrichment analysis in RNAseqChef</title>
      <p id="p0100">To conduct functional enrichment analysis, the MSigDB hallmark and DoRothEA regulon gene sets were extracted from the msigdbr (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=msigdbr" id="intref0060">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=msigdbr</ext-link>) and dorothea packages, respectively (<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Functional enrichment analysis was performed using clusterProfiler (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>) with an FDR cut-off of 0.05. The results were visualized <italic>via</italic> dot plots and gene concept-network (cnet) plots using the ggplot2 and enrichplot (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://yulab-smu.top/biomedical-knowledge-mining-book/" id="intref0065">https://yulab-smu.top/biomedical-knowledge-mining-book/</ext-link>) packages, respectively (<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec3.6">
      <title>Quantification and statistical analysis</title>
      <p id="p0105">Statistical analyses were performed using the RNAseqChef software. A pairwise comparison test was performed using the Wald test of DESeq2. Multiple comparison tests were performed using the EBMultiTest function in EBSeq2. Enrichment analysis was performed using Fisher’s exact test. FDR, an adjusted <italic>p</italic> value, was calculated using Benjamini-Hochberg (BH) and Storey’s q-value methods for pairwise DEG detection and enrichment analysis, respectively. Significance was defined as an adjusted <italic>p</italic>-value &lt;0.05, indicated with an asterisk (∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, ∗∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01, ∗∗∗<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001).</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec4">
    <title>Data availability</title>
    <p id="p0110">The RNAseqChef software is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://imeg-ku.shinyapps.io/RNAseqChef/" id="intref0070">https://imeg-ku.shinyapps.io/RNAseqChef/</ext-link> hosted by the shinyapps.io server.</p>
    <p id="p0115">Source code is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.5281/zenodo.7095218" id="intref0075">10.5281/zenodo.7095218</ext-link>.</p>
    <p id="p0120">Docker image is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://hub.docker.com/r/omicschef/rnaseqchef" id="intref0080">https://hub.docker.com/r/omicschef/rnaseqchef</ext-link>.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec5">
    <title>Supporting information</title>
    <p id="p0125">This article contains <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">supporting information</xref>.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
    <title>Conflict of interest</title>
    <p id="p0130">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ref-list id="cebib0010">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="bib1">
      <label>1</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mortazavi</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Williams</surname>
            <given-names>B.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McCue</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schaeffer</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wold</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Mapping and quantifying mammalian transcriptomes by RNA-Seq</article-title>
        <source>Nat. Methods</source>
        <volume>5</volume>
        <year>2008</year>
        <fpage>621</fpage>
        <lpage>628</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18516045</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib2">
      <label>2</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Edgar</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Domrachev</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lash</surname>
            <given-names>A.E.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Gene expression Omnibus: NCBI gene expression and hybridization array data repository</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>30</volume>
        <year>2002</year>
        <fpage>207</fpage>
        <lpage>210</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11752295</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib3">
      <label>3</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ahn</surname>
            <given-names>Y.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hwang</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>X.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stephenson</surname>
            <given-names>K.K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Electrophilic tuning of the chemoprotective natural product sulforaphane</article-title>
        <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source>
        <volume>107</volume>
        <year>2010</year>
        <fpage>9590</fpage>
        <lpage>9595</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20439747</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib4">
      <label>4</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kensler</surname>
            <given-names>T.W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Egner</surname>
            <given-names>P.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Agyeman</surname>
            <given-names>A.S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Visvanathan</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Groopman</surname>
            <given-names>J.D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>J.G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Keap1-nrf2 signaling: a target for cancer prevention by sulforaphane</article-title>
        <source>Top Curr. Chem.</source>
        <volume>329</volume>
        <year>2013</year>
        <fpage>163</fpage>
        <lpage>177</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22752583</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib5">
      <label>5</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Santín-Márquez</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Alarcón-Aguilar</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>López-Diazguerrero</surname>
            <given-names>N.E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chondrogianni</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Königsberg</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Sulforaphane - role in aging and neurodegeneration</article-title>
        <source>Geroscience</source>
        <volume>41</volume>
        <year>2019</year>
        <fpage>655</fpage>
        <lpage>670</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30941620</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib6">
      <label>6</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cakır</surname>
            <given-names>I.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lining Pan</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hadley</surname>
            <given-names>C.K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>El-Gamal</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fadel</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Elsayegh</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Sulforaphane reduces obesity by reversing leptin resistance</article-title>
        <source>Elife</source>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <year>2022</year>
        <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e67368</object-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib7">
      <label>7</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Negi</surname>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kumar</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sharma</surname>
            <given-names>S.S.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Nrf2 and NF-κB modulation by sulforaphane counteracts multiple manifestations of diabetic neuropathy in rats and high glucose-induced changes</article-title>
        <source>Curr. Neurovasc. Res.</source>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <year>2011</year>
        <fpage>294</fpage>
        <lpage>304</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22023613</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib8">
      <label>8</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Martins</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Colaço</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Venâncio</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pires</surname>
            <given-names>M.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Oliveira</surname>
            <given-names>P.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rosa</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Potential effects of sulforaphane to fight obesity</article-title>
        <source>J. Sci. Food Agric.</source>
        <volume>98</volume>
        <year>2018</year>
        <fpage>2837</fpage>
        <lpage>2844</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29363750</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib9">
      <label>9</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Choi</surname>
            <given-names>K.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Y.S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>S.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shin</surname>
            <given-names>K.O.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>J.Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Sulforaphane attenuates obesity by inhibiting adipogenesis and activating the AMPK pathway in obese mice</article-title>
        <source>J. Nutr. Biochem.</source>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <year>2014</year>
        <fpage>201</fpage>
        <lpage>207</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24445045</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib10">
      <label>10</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Deng</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tao</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>S.Z.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jin</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Inhibition of 6-hydroxydopamine-induced endoplasmic reticulum stress by sulforaphane through the activation of Nrf2 nuclear translocation</article-title>
        <source>Mol. Med. Rep.</source>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <year>2012</year>
        <fpage>215</fpage>
        <lpage>219</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22552270</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib11">
      <label>11</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Oh</surname>
            <given-names>C.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>J.Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Min</surname>
            <given-names>A.K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>K.G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Harris</surname>
            <given-names>R.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>H.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Sulforaphane attenuates hepatic fibrosis via NF-E2-related factor 2-mediated inhibition of transforming growth factor-β/Smad signaling</article-title>
        <source>Free Radic. Biol. Med.</source>
        <volume>52</volume>
        <year>2012</year>
        <fpage>671</fpage>
        <lpage>682</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22155056</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib12">
      <label>12</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Z.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>X.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lan</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Activation of NRF2 ameliorates oxidative stress and cystogenesis in autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease</article-title>
        <source>Sci. Transl. Med.</source>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <year>2020</year>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <lpage>17</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib13">
      <label>13</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dong</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Su</surname>
            <given-names>X.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Duan</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wei</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Sulforaphane induces S-phase arrest and apoptosis via p53-dependent manner in gastric cancer cells</article-title>
        <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <year>2021</year>
        <fpage>2504</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33510228</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib14">
      <label>14</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Smith</surname>
            <given-names>A.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ball</surname>
            <given-names>S.S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bao</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bowater</surname>
            <given-names>R.P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Sulforaphane promotes ER stress, autophagy, and cell death: implications for cataract surgery</article-title>
        <source>J. Mol. Med.</source>
        <volume>95</volume>
        <year>2017</year>
        <fpage>553</fpage>
        <lpage>564</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28083623</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib15">
      <label>15</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nelson</surname>
            <given-names>J.W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sklenar</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Barnes</surname>
            <given-names>A.P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Minnier</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The START app: a web-based RNAseq analysis and visualization resource</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <volume>33</volume>
        <year>2017</year>
        <fpage>447</fpage>
        <lpage>449</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28171615</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib16">
      <label>16</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Harshbarger</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kratz</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Carninci</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Deiva: a web application for interactive visual analysis of differential gene expression profiles</article-title>
        <source>BMC Genomics</source>
        <volume>18</volume>
        <year>2017</year>
        <fpage>47</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28061742</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib17">
      <label>17</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ge</surname>
            <given-names>S.X.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Son</surname>
            <given-names>E.W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yao</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>iDEP: an integrated web application for differential expression and pathway analysis of RNA-Seq data</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
        <volume>19</volume>
        <year>2018</year>
        <fpage>534</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30567491</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib18">
      <label>18</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Leng</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dawson</surname>
            <given-names>J.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Thomson</surname>
            <given-names>J.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ruotti</surname>
            <given-names>V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rissman</surname>
            <given-names>A.I.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Smits</surname>
            <given-names>B.M.G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>EBSeq: an empirical Bayes hierarchical model for inference in RNA-seq experiments</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <volume>29</volume>
        <year>2013</year>
        <fpage>1035</fpage>
        <lpage>1043</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23428641</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib19">
      <label>19</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Love</surname>
            <given-names>M.I.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huber</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Anders</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA-seq data with DESeq2</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol.</source>
        <volume>15</volume>
        <year>2014</year>
        <fpage>550</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25516281</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib20">
      <label>20</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dina Kuo</surname>
            <given-names>H.C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sargsyan</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kong</surname>
            <given-names>A.N.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>UVB drives metabolic rewiring and epigenetic reprograming and protection by sulforaphane in human skin keratinocytes</article-title>
        <source>Chem. Res. Toxicol.</source>
        <volume>35</volume>
        <year>2022</year>
        <fpage>1220</fpage>
        <lpage>1233</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35700067</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib21">
      <label>21</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gilmour</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ahn</surname>
            <given-names>Y.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>de la Vega</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dinkova-Kostova</surname>
            <given-names>A.T.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The isothiocyanate sulforaphane inhibits mTOR in an NRF2-independent manner</article-title>
        <source>Phytomedicine</source>
        <volume>86</volume>
        <year>2021</year>
        <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">153062</object-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib22">
      <label>22</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jeon</surname>
            <given-names>Y.K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yoo</surname>
            <given-names>D.R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jang</surname>
            <given-names>Y.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jang</surname>
            <given-names>S.Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nam</surname>
            <given-names>M.J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Sulforaphane induces apoptosis in human hepatic cancer cells through inhibition of 6-phosphofructo-2-kinase/fructose-2,6-biphosphatase4, mediated by hypoxia inducible factor-1-dependent pathway</article-title>
        <source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source>
        <volume>1814</volume>
        <year>2011</year>
        <fpage>1340</fpage>
        <lpage>1348</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21640852</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib23">
      <label>23</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yanaka</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tauchi</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Suzuki</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shibahara</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Matsui</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Role of the Nrf-2 gene in protection and repair of gastric mucosa against oxidative stress</article-title>
        <source>Inflammopharmacology</source>
        <volume>13</volume>
        <year>2005</year>
        <fpage>83</fpage>
        <lpage>90</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16259730</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib24">
      <label>24</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Usui</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yamaguchi</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tanji</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tominaga</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ishigaki</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fukumoto</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Atf6α-null mice are glucose intolerant due to pancreatic β-cell failure on a high-fat diet but partially resistant to diet-induced insulin resistance</article-title>
        <source>Metabolism</source>
        <volume>61</volume>
        <year>2012</year>
        <fpage>1118</fpage>
        <lpage>1128</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22386934</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib25">
      <label>25</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Casas-Tinto</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sanchez-Garcia</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gomez-Velazquez</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rincon-Limas</surname>
            <given-names>D.E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fernandez-Funez</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The ER stress factor XBP1s prevents amyloid-beta neurotoxicity</article-title>
        <source>Hum. Mol. Genet.</source>
        <volume>20</volume>
        <year>2011</year>
        <fpage>2144</fpage>
        <lpage>2160</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21389082</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib26">
      <label>26</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shoulders</surname>
            <given-names>M.D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ryno</surname>
            <given-names>L.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Genereux</surname>
            <given-names>J.C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Moresco</surname>
            <given-names>J.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tu</surname>
            <given-names>P.G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Stress-independent activation of XBP1s and/or ATF6 reveals three functionally diverse ER proteostasis environments</article-title>
        <source>Cell Rep.</source>
        <volume>3</volume>
        <year>2013</year>
        <fpage>1279</fpage>
        <lpage>1292</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23583182</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib27">
      <label>27</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tai</surname>
            <given-names>H.C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chung</surname>
            <given-names>S.D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chien</surname>
            <given-names>C.T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>H.J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Sulforaphane improves ischemia-induced detrusor overactivity by downregulating the enhancement of associated endoplasmic reticulum stress, autophagy, and apoptosis in rat bladder</article-title>
        <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <year>2016</year>
        <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">36110</object-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib28">
      <label>28</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hiebert</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wietecha</surname>
            <given-names>M.S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cangkrama</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Haertel</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mavrogonatou</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stumpe</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Nrf2-mediated fibroblast reprogramming drives cellular senescence by targeting the matrisome</article-title>
        <source>Dev. Cell</source>
        <volume>46</volume>
        <year>2018</year>
        <fpage>145</fpage>
        <lpage>161.e10</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30016619</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib29">
      <label>29</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Q.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Falahati</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Khosh</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mohammed</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kang</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Corachán</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Targeting class I histone deacetylases in human uterine leiomyosarcoma</article-title>
        <source>Cells</source>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <year>2022</year>
        <fpage>3801</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36497061</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib30">
      <label>30</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Krishnan</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>X.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kao</surname>
            <given-names>W.Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Viker</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Butters</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Masuoka</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Lumican, an extracellular matrix proteoglycan, is a novel requisite for hepatic fibrosis</article-title>
        <source>Lab. Invest.</source>
        <volume>92</volume>
        <year>2012</year>
        <fpage>1712</fpage>
        <lpage>1725</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23007134</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib31">
      <label>31</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tsukui</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>K.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wetter</surname>
            <given-names>J.B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wilson-Kanamori</surname>
            <given-names>J.R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hazelwood</surname>
            <given-names>L.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Henderson</surname>
            <given-names>N.C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Collagen-producing lung cell atlas identifies multiple subsets with distinct localization and relevance to fibrosis</article-title>
        <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <year>2020</year>
        <fpage>1920</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32317643</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib32">
      <label>32</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Halberg</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Khan</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Trujillo</surname>
            <given-names>M.E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wernstedt-Asterholm</surname>
            <given-names>I.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Attie</surname>
            <given-names>A.D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sherwani</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Hypoxia-inducible factor 1alpha induces fibrosis and insulin resistance in white adipose tissue</article-title>
        <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>
        <volume>29</volume>
        <year>2009</year>
        <fpage>4467</fpage>
        <lpage>4483</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19546236</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib33">
      <label>33</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Williams</surname>
            <given-names>L.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McCann</surname>
            <given-names>F.E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cabrita</surname>
            <given-names>M.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Layton</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cribbs</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Knezevic</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Identifying collagen VI as a target of fibrotic diseases regulated by CREBBP/EP300</article-title>
        <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source>
        <volume>117</volume>
        <year>2020</year>
        <fpage>20753</fpage>
        <lpage>20763</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32759223</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib34">
      <label>34</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mahi</surname>
            <given-names>N.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Najafabadi</surname>
            <given-names>M.F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pilarczyk</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kouril</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Medvedovic</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Grein: an interactive web platform for Re-analyzing GEO RNA-seq data</article-title>
        <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <year>2019</year>
        <fpage>7580</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31110304</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib35">
      <label>35</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zou</surname>
            <given-names>Z.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ohta</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Miura</surname>
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Oki</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>ChIP-atlas 2021 update: a data-mining suite for exploring epigenomic landscapes by fully integrating ChIP-seq, ATAC-seq and bisulfite-seq data</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>50</volume>
        <year>2022</year>
        <fpage>W175</fpage>
        <lpage>W182</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35325188</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib36">
      <label>36</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hino</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nagaoka</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Oki</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Etoh</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hino</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nakao</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Mitochondrial stress induces AREG expression and epigenomic remodeling through c-JUN and YAP-mediated enhancer activation</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>50</volume>
        <year>2022</year>
        <fpage>9765</fpage>
        <lpage>9779</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36095121</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib37">
      <label>37</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>X.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Deng</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dong</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xue</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Hepatic conditional knockout of ATF6 exacerbates liver metabolic damage by repressing autophage through MTOR pathway</article-title>
        <source>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</source>
        <volume>505</volume>
        <year>2018</year>
        <fpage>45</fpage>
        <lpage>50</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30236984</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib38">
      <label>38</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yamamoto</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Takahara</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Oyadomari</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Okada</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sato</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Harada</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Induction of liver steatosis and lipid droplet formation in ATF6-knockout mice burdened with pharmacological endoplasmic reticulum stress</article-title>
        <source>Mol. Biol. Cell</source>
        <volume>21</volume>
        <year>2010</year>
        <fpage>2975</fpage>
        <lpage>2986</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20631254</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib39">
      <label>39</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Z.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>X.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Deficiency of intestinal Bmal1 prevents obesity induced by high-fat feeding</article-title>
        <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <year>2021</year>
        <fpage>5323</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34493722</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib40">
      <label>40</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Takahashi</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Inoue</surname>
            <given-names>I.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nakajima</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Seo</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nakano</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A promoter in the novel exon of hPPARγ directs the circadian expression of PPARγ</article-title>
        <source>J. Atheroscler. Thromb.</source>
        <volume>17</volume>
        <year>2010</year>
        <fpage>73</fpage>
        <lpage>83</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20093779</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib41">
      <label>41</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tian</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>X.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Guo</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Z.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Goldstein</surname>
            <given-names>J.L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>BHLHE40, a third transcription factor required for insulin induction of SREBP-1c mRNA in rodent liver</article-title>
        <source>Elife</source>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <year>2018</year>
        <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e36826</object-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib42">
      <label>42</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Veeranki</surname>
            <given-names>O.L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bhattacharya</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Marshall</surname>
            <given-names>J.R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Organ-specific exposure and response to sulforaphane, a key chemopreventive ingredient in broccoli: implications for cancer prevention</article-title>
        <source>Br. J. Nutr.</source>
        <volume>109</volume>
        <year>2013</year>
        <fpage>25</fpage>
        <lpage>32</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22464629</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib43">
      <label>43</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Calabrese</surname>
            <given-names>E.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kozumbo</surname>
            <given-names>W.J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The hormetic dose-response mechanism: nrf2 activation</article-title>
        <source>Pharmacol. Res.</source>
        <volume>167</volume>
        <year>2021</year>
        <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">105526</object-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib44">
      <label>44</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ye</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dinkova-Kostova</surname>
            <given-names>A.T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wade</surname>
            <given-names>K.L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shapiro</surname>
            <given-names>T.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Talalay</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Quantitative determination of dithiocarbamates in human plasma, serum, erythrocytes and urine: pharmacokinetics of broccoli sprout isothiocyanates in humans</article-title>
        <source>Clin. Chim. Acta</source>
        <volume>316</volume>
        <year>2002</year>
        <fpage>43</fpage>
        <lpage>53</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11750273</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib45">
      <label>45</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cornblatt</surname>
            <given-names>B.S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ye</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dinkova-Kostova</surname>
            <given-names>A.T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Erb</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fahey</surname>
            <given-names>J.W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Singh</surname>
            <given-names>N.K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Preclinical and clinical evaluation of sulforaphane for chemoprevention in the breast</article-title>
        <source>Carcinogenesis</source>
        <volume>28</volume>
        <year>2007</year>
        <fpage>1485</fpage>
        <lpage>1490</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17347138</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib46">
      <label>46</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yagishita</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fahey</surname>
            <given-names>J.W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dinkova-Kostova</surname>
            <given-names>A.T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kensler</surname>
            <given-names>T.W.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Broccoli or sulforaphane: is it the source or dose that matters?</article-title>
        <source>Molecules</source>
        <volume>24</volume>
        <year>2019</year>
        <fpage>3593</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31590459</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib47">
      <label>47</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jalili</surname>
            <given-names>V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Afgan</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gu</surname>
            <given-names>Q.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Clements</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Blankenberg</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Goecks</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The Galaxy platform for accessible, reproducible and collaborative biomedical analyses: 2020 update</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>48</volume>
        <year>2020</year>
        <fpage>W395</fpage>
        <lpage>W402</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32479607</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib48">
      <label>48</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref48">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dewey</surname>
            <given-names>C.N.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>RSEM: accurate transcript quantification from RNA-Seq data with or without a reference genome</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <year>2011</year>
        <fpage>323</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21816040</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib49">
      <label>49</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref49">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wickham</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Averick</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bryan</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chang</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McGowan</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>François</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Welcome to the tidyverse</article-title>
        <source>J. Open Source Softw.</source>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <year>2019</year>
        <fpage>1686</fpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib50">
      <label>50</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref50">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gu</surname>
            <given-names>Z.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Eils</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schlesner</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Complex heatmaps reveal patterns and correlations in multidimensional genomic data</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <volume>32</volume>
        <year>2016</year>
        <fpage>2847</fpage>
        <lpage>2849</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27207943</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib51">
      <label>51</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref51">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Garcia-Alonso</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Holland</surname>
            <given-names>C.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ibrahim</surname>
            <given-names>M.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Turei</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Saez-Rodriguez</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Benchmark and integration of resources for the estimation of human transcription factor activities</article-title>
        <source>Genome Res.</source>
        <volume>29</volume>
        <year>2019</year>
        <fpage>1363</fpage>
        <lpage>1375</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31340985</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib52">
      <label>52</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref52">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Guo</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dai</surname>
            <given-names>Z.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>clusterProfiler 4.0: a universal enrichment tool for interpreting omics data</article-title>
        <source>Innovation (Camb.)</source>
        <volume>2</volume>
        <year>2021</year>
        <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100141</object-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
  <bio>
    <graphic xlink:href="fx1"/>
    <p><bold>Kan Etoh</bold> is a postdoctoral researcher at the Department of Medical Cell Biology in Kumamoto University, Japan. He investigates the molecular mechanisms that underlie cell-type specificity and context-dependent stress response, particularly those related to aging and chronic inflammation, using a multi-omics approach such as transcriptomic and epigenomic analyses. He is now developing easy-to-use tools in systematic and automated omics data analysis to remove technical barriers for research community.</p>
  </bio>
  <sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supporting information</title>
    <p id="p0150">
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1">
        <caption>
          <title>Supporting information</title>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="mmc1.docx"/>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc2">
        <caption>
          <title>Movie S1-1</title>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="mmc2.mp4"/>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc3">
        <caption>
          <title>Movie S1-2</title>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="mmc3.mp4"/>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc4">
        <caption>
          <title>Movie S3</title>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="mmc4.mp4"/>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc5">
        <caption>
          <title>Movie S4</title>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="mmc5.mp4"/>
      </supplementary-material>
    </p>
  </sec>
  <ack id="ack0010">
    <title>Acknowledgments</title>
    <p id="p0135">We thank the members in our laboratory and institution for helpful discussions. Particularly, Dr Sugiko Watanabe and Dr Miyuki Inoue cooperated for SFN experiments. Ms Yuko Hino, Dr Tomoaki Koga and Dr Shinjiro Hino performed trial runs of RNAseqChef.</p>
    <sec id="sec6">
      <title>Author contributions</title>
      <p id="p0140">K. E. and M. N. conceptualization; K. E. and M. N. methodology; K. E. software; K. E. formal analysis; K. E. and M. N. investigation; K. E. data curation; K. E. and M. N. writing–original draft; K. E. visualization; K. E. and M. N. funding acquisition; M. N. validation, supervision, and project administration</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec7">
      <title>Funding and additional information</title>
      <p id="p0145">This work was supported by Grant-in-Aid for Early-Career Scientists from the <funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100001700</institution-id><institution>Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> [20K16145 to K. E.], <funding-source id="gs2"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100001691</institution-id><institution>JSPS</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> KAKENHI [21H02686, 20KK0185 to M. N.], and by the program of the Inter-University Research Network for High Depth Omics, IMEG, <funding-source id="gs3"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100004091</institution-id><institution>Kumamoto University</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (to M. N.).</p>
    </sec>
  </ack>
</back>
