<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?properties open_access?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">10320090</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37158246</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkad349</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gkad349</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI00010</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Web Server Issue</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>αCharges: partial atomic charges for AlphaFold structures in high quality</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9047-0334</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Schindler</surname>
          <given-names>Ondřej</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>CEITEC – Central European Institute of Technology, Masaryk University</institution>, 625 00 Brno, <country country="CZ">Czech Republic</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>National Centre for Biomolecular Research, Faculty of Science, Masaryk University</institution>, 625 00 Brno, <country country="CZ">Czech Republic</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9472-2589</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Berka</surname>
          <given-names>Karel</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Department of Physical Chemistry, Faculty of Science, Palacký University Olomouc</institution>, 779 00 Olomouc, <country country="CZ">Czech Republic</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3619-6434</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Cantara</surname>
          <given-names>Alessio</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>CEITEC – Central European Institute of Technology, Masaryk University</institution>, 625 00 Brno, <country country="CZ">Czech Republic</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>National Centre for Biomolecular Research, Faculty of Science, Masaryk University</institution>, 625 00 Brno, <country country="CZ">Czech Republic</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3395-3196</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Křenek</surname>
          <given-names>Aleš</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Institute of Computer Science, Masaryk University</institution>, 602 00 Brno, <country country="CZ">Czech Republic</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7266-1789</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Tichý</surname>
          <given-names>Dominik</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Faculty of Informatics, Masaryk University</institution>, 602 00 Brno, <country country="CZ">Czech Republic</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0296-2452</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Raček</surname>
          <given-names>Tomáš</given-names>
        </name>
        <!--krab1k@mail.muni.cz-->
        <aff><institution>CEITEC – Central European Institute of Technology, Masaryk University</institution>, 625 00 Brno, <country country="CZ">Czech Republic</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>National Centre for Biomolecular Research, Faculty of Science, Masaryk University</institution>, 625 00 Brno, <country country="CZ">Czech Republic</country></aff>
        <xref rid="COR2" ref-type="corresp"/>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3840-8760</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Svobodová</surname>
          <given-names>Radka</given-names>
        </name>
        <!--radka.svobodova@mail.muni.cz-->
        <aff><institution>CEITEC – Central European Institute of Technology, Masaryk University</institution>, 625 00 Brno, <country country="CZ">Czech Republic</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>National Centre for Biomolecular Research, Faculty of Science, Masaryk University</institution>, 625 00 Brno, <country country="CZ">Czech Republic</country></aff>
        <xref rid="COR1" ref-type="corresp"/>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="COR1">To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +420 54949 4860; Email: <email>radka.svobodova@mail.muni.cz</email></corresp>
      <corresp id="COR2">Correspondence may also be addressed to Tomáš Raček. Tel: +420 54949 6568; Email: <email>krab1k@mail.muni.cz</email></corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <day>05</day>
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2023-05-09">
      <day>09</day>
      <month>5</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>09</day>
      <month>5</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>51</volume>
    <issue>W1</issue>
    <fpage>W11</fpage>
    <lpage>W16</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>24</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>17</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>18</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2023. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Nucleic Acids Research.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xlink:href="gkad349.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <p>The AlphaFold2 prediction algorithm opened up the possibility of exploring proteins’ structural space at an unprecedented scale. Currently, &gt;200 million protein structures predicted by this approach are deposited in AlphaFoldDB, covering entire proteomes of multiple organisms, including humans. Predicted structures are, however, stored without detailed functional annotations describing their chemical behaviour. Partial atomic charges, which map electron distribution over a molecule and provide a clue to its chemical reactivity, are an important example of such data. We introduce the web application αCharges: a tool for the quick calculation of partial atomic charges for protein structures from AlphaFoldDB. The charges are calculated by the recent empirical method SQE+qp, parameterised for this class of molecules using robust quantum mechanics charges (B3LYP/6-31G*/NPA) on PROPKA3 protonated structures. The computed partial atomic charges can be downloaded in common data formats or visualised via the powerful Mol* viewer. The αCharges application is freely available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://alphacharges.ncbr.muni.cz" ext-link-type="uri">https://alphacharges.ncbr.muni.cz</ext-link> with no login requirement.</p>
    </abstract>
    <abstract abstract-type="graphical">
      <title>Graphical Abstract</title>
      <p>
        <fig position="float" id="ga1">
          <label>Graphical Abstract</label>
          <caption>
            <p>A schema describing the 𝛂Charges workflow: A structure is obtained from AlphaFoldDB and protonated by PROPKA3. Its charges are calculated by SQE+qp and visualized with Mol*.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="gkad349figgra1" position="float"/>
        </fig>
      </p>
    </abstract>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Ministry of Education</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100009122</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>LM2023055</award-id>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>IOCB Tech Foundation</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="6"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec sec-type="intro" id="SEC1">
    <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
    <p>The AlphaFold2 prediction algorithm (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>) provided us with markedly greater insight into the structural space of proteins. Specifically, the set of 200 000 experimentally determined protein structures in the Protein Data Bank (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>) is currently extended by &gt;200 million predicted protein structures in AlphaFoldDB (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). This enables the research community to consider and hypothesise on scientific questions that could not have been touched until now.</p>
    <p>It is beneficial to enrich the predicted protein structures with properties describing their chemical behaviour to support this research. A typical example of such data is partial atomic charges (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), which map the electron distribution over the molecule and provide a clue to its chemical reactivity. Partial atomic charges enable us to compare binding sites, including their polarity (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>), identify hydrophobic membrane parts (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), or drive protein-protein interactions (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). They are also used as inputs for molecular docking (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), molecular dynamics (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>), and other simulations (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).</p>
    <p>The most reliable way to compute partial atomic charges is using quantum mechanics (QM) (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), which can provide electron density distribution among molecular orbitals. Afterwards, its mapping to atoms can be calculated by population analyses, e.g. Natural population analysis (NPA) (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Unfortunately, QM methods are very time-consuming, and therefore only applicable to small molecules.</p>
    <p>A faster alternative is the usage of empirical charge calculation methods (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), which mimic QM approaches and are based on significantly less complex empirical equation systems describing the charge distribution. These empirical methods are parameterised using QM charges calculated by a certain combination of a QM method and a population analysis. Charges computed by the empirical method mimic QM charges used in the parameterisation process. Even though the empirical methods are fast, it is challenging to apply them to proteins. One reason is that proteins are very large systems, and the empirical methods must be optimised to handle them. Moreover, proteins are homogeneous (i.e. they contain atoms with similar neighbourhoods), complicating the parameterisation of empirical methods. For these reasons, empirical charge calculation methods applicable to proteins have been developed in the last several years. We developed the SQE+qp method (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), which is currently the best-performing approach for proteins. We are also the authors of ACC II (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), a web server that provides charge calculation for almost any structure using 20 empirical methods. ACC II also includes the SQE+qp approach.</p>
    <p>A limitation of ACC II is that it requires a protonated protein structure. Additionally, it implicitly deals with electroneutral molecules (i.e. molecules that have a zero total charge). The total charge is computed as a sum of the formal charges of individual atoms specified in the input file. A structure with a non-zero total charge can be provided. However, the user has to compute it by him or herself and include it in the input file. Moreover, the empirical methods in ACC II are only parameterised for electroneutral molecules. On the other hand, protein structures produced by the AlphaFold2 algorithm and contained in AlphaFoldDB do not include hydrogens, and after protonation, most of them are not electroneutral.</p>
    <p>For this reason, we introduce αCharges, which solves all these challenges and provides the following functionality:</p>
    <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
        <p>The input protein structure from AlphaFoldDB is protonated using PROPKA3 (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) based on the pH value provided by the user (physiological pH is used as the default value).</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>After protonation, the total charge of the protein is computed and used as an input for the SQE+qp method.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>The SQE+qp method is parameterised directly for protein-like structures.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>αCharges integrates the Mol* viewer (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>), a cutting-edge molecular visualiser also used in AlphaFoldDB (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), PDBe (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>) and RCSB PDB (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>).</p>
      </list-item>
    </list>
    <p>Therefore, αCharges provides high-quality partial atomic charges for AlphaFoldDB structures in one click. The user only has to provide the UniProt ID of the protein, and no additional knowledge or preprocessing is required.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="SEC2">
    <title>DESCRIPTION OF THE WEB SERVER</title>
    <p>The application back end is written in Python, using the Flask web framework (<ext-link xlink:href="https://flask.palletsprojects.com/" ext-link-type="uri">https://flask.palletsprojects.com/</ext-link>). The front end is built with the Bootstrap library (<ext-link xlink:href="https://getbootstrap.com/" ext-link-type="uri">https://getbootstrap.com/</ext-link>).</p>
    <sec id="SEC2-1">
      <title>SQE+qp method</title>
      <p>The computation of partial atomic charges is carried out according to the SQE+qp model (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), which belongs to the family of electronegativity equalisation methods, like the popular EEM (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>), QEq (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) or SQE (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>).</p>
      <p>As SQE added bond information to the EEM formalism, SQE+qp further improved it by adding a parameterised initial charge for each atomic type. In this context, an atomic type represents a class of atoms with similar characteristics (e.g. all carbon atoms with only single bonds or all hydrogen atoms bound to oxygen atoms).</p>
      <p>These initial charges and other model parameters have to be chosen appropriately for the given class of molecules (e.g. peptides, drug-like molecules, nucleic acids) to compute high-quality partial atomic charges.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2-2">
      <title>αCharges workflow</title>
      <p>One of the major design decisions for αCharges was to provide the user with an intuitive interface that would facilitate the calculation of partial atomic charges without needing to configure all the parameters of the process. The workflow is depicted in Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and can be described in several steps:</p>
      <list list-type="bullet">
        <list-item>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Downloading the structure from AlphaFoldDB API:</italic> The first step is to enter the UniProt ID (or AlphaFoldDB ID) of a selected protein structure into the textbox on the landing page. The structure is downloaded in PDB format if the ID is valid. Currently, structures are downloaded in the latest version (i.e. AlphaFoldDB version 4, as of February 2023). However, if a user clicks the <italic toggle="yes">Setup calculation</italic> button, any prior version can be selected.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Addition of hydrogens by PDB2PQR/PROPKA3:</italic> Once the structure is downloaded, adding hydrogen atoms is the next step. For this purpose, αCharges uses PDB2PQR (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) with the PROPKA3 library (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). By default, the protonation is done using the physiological pH of 7.2. However, any value between 0 and 14 can be specified on the <italic toggle="yes">Setup</italic> page.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Calculation of charges by SQE+qp:</italic> If the protonation succeeds, partial atomic charges can be computed. Since the input structure might be large (i.e. tens of thousands of atoms), even quite effective empirical methods such as SQE+qp might be too memory-demanding and slow, since they have a cubic computational complexity with respect to the number of bonds in the molecule.</p>
          <p>To overcome the issue of computation complexity, αCharges uses the Cutoff/Cover approach (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>), which first divides the molecule into smaller regions (spheres centred around individual residues). Then, the computation is carried out independently for each region. In the next step, the partial atomic charges are corrected so that their sum equals the desired total molecular charge. First, the correction is computed for each small region. Then, the charges of the whole structure are revised in the same way.</p>
          <p>The quality of the parameters for the empirical charge calculation method heavily influences the quality of the resulting charges. αCharges uses parameters fitted to reproduce B3LYP/6-31G*/NPA charges originally parameterised on the set of peptides and later optimised for proteins. Charges computed using these parameters were shown to achieve an excellent agreement with the reference charges (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>).</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Visualisation of the charges with Mol*:</italic> After calculating partial atomic charges, the user is redirected to the Results page, whose central part is Mol* viewer (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Mol* was extended to support the visualisation of partial atomic charges at several levels of protein structure depending on the chosen view. The default <italic toggle="yes">cartoon</italic> representation colours each residue by the sum of the charges of its atoms. The two other visualisation modes are <italic toggle="yes">ball &amp; stick</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">surface</italic>.</p>
          <p>The values of charges are mapped onto a linear blue-white-red gradient, where blue means a positive charge, white signifies zero charge, and red equals a negative charge. Two main colouring types are available in the application. In the default <italic toggle="yes">relative colouring</italic>, the gradient is mapped to the charges such that the highest and lowest charges are represented by the most saturated shades of blue and red, respectively. If a user wants to generate several images of various structures to compare the charge distribution, <italic toggle="yes">absolute colouring</italic> can be used. In this case, the maximum value of positive and negative charge can be configured manually.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Download of computed charges:</italic> Although the visual representation of the charges is undoubtedly valuable for humans, the charges can also be downloaded if further processing is required. αCharges includes files of several formats in a downloaded ZIP file for user convenience. These include:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>PDB file with added hydrogens</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>PQR file with added hydrogens and calculated charges</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>mmCIF file with added hydrogens and calculated charges</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>a simple TXT file with calculated charges</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </list-item>
      </list>
      <fig position="float" id="F1">
        <label>Figure 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Schematic depiction of αCharges workflow. The schema includes a structure of porin (UniProt ID: A0A2E5IBK2) originating from <italic toggle="yes">Euryarchaeota archaeon</italic>.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="gkad349fig1" position="float"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2-3">
      <title>Limitations</title>
      <p>αCharges cannot compute partial atomic charges for proteins that contain structural errors because of an incorrect AlphaFold2 prediction. Furthermore, PROPKA3 is unable to protonate some structures correctly. In these cases, an appropriate error message is given to the user. The message lists all atoms that were identified as problematic. After clicking on their names, they are highlighted in Mol* so the user can visually inspect the issues.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="results" id="SEC3">
    <title>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</title>
    <p>We put the application through extensive testing to confirm that it is stable and reliable. Details of this testing can be found in the Supplementary Data.</p>
    <p>Furthermore, we provide three use cases demonstrating various applications of αCharges. They are presented interactively on the αCharges webpage.</p>
    <sec id="SEC3-1">
      <title>Example I: P-glycoprotein</title>
      <p>P-glycoprotein is one of the ABC transporter proteins that decrease drug accumulation in cancer cells (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). It is a 170kDa protein consisting of a nucleotide-binding domain and a transmembrane domain (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). We used a P-glycoprotein structure model from <italic toggle="yes">Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> (UniProt ID P34712). Visualising the charges (Figure <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) computed by αCharges demonstrates the differences in charge distribution between the transmembrane parts and extracellular/intracellular ones.</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F2">
        <label>Figure 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Structure of P-glycoprotein from <italic toggle="yes">Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> (UniProt ID: P34712). Partial atomic charges calculated by αCharges are visualised on the protein’s surface. They show distinct areas of the protein: The nonpolar transmembrane part (mostly very light blue due to the charge being around zero on the surface) and the polar surface of extracellular and cytoplasmic parts (with a mosaic of blue positive and red negative charges).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="gkad349fig2" position="float"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC3-2">
      <title>Example II: pepsin</title>
      <p>Pepsin is an enzyme that plays a major role in protein digestion in the stomach. It is secreted as a zymogen and activated by the acidic pH created by the stomach parietal cells. Pepsin is most effective at a pH of approximately 1.5 to 2, and becomes inactive when the pH rises above 6 (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). The enzyme denatures at a pH 8 (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Differences in the charge distribution between its active form (pH 2) and inactive form (pH 7) can be seen in this use case (Figure <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The alkaline environment causes an increase in negative charges, which contributes to the structural instability of the pepsin, causing the shift to an inactive form of the protein (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>).</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F3">
        <label>Figure 3.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Structure of pepsin (UniProt ID: P00791), partial atomic charges calculated by αCharges are visualised on the cartoon model of the protein showing significant charge differences between an active form (left image, pH 2) and an inactive form (right image, pH 7).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="gkad349fig3" position="float"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC3-3">
      <title>Example III: PIN proteins</title>
      <p>The PIN family proteins control plant growth by regulating auxin export from the cytosol to the extracellular space (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Eight types of PIN transport proteins are known (PIN1 to PIN8) and they are divided into two classes: canonical PINs (PIN1-4 and PIN7) and non-canonical PINs (PIN5, PIN6 and PIN8) (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). This year, structures of three of them were discovered and published (PIN1 (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>), PIN3 (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>) and PIN8 (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>)), while structures of the remaining ones are waiting to be revealed. But thanks to AlphaFoldDB, we can see their predicted structure and compare their charge distribution.</p>
      <p>Charge distribution of canonical PINs is very similar, even though sequence and structure strongly differ. It can be seen especially when we compare PIN3 and PIN7 (see Figure <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, top images). On the other hand, charge distribution of non-canonical PINs differs from each other and also from canonical PINs (see PIN5 in Figure <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, bottom image).</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F4">
        <label>Figure 4.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Structure of PIN3 (top left image, UniProt ID: Q9S7Z8), PIN7 (top right, UniProt ID: Q940Y5) and PIN5 (bottom image, UniProt ID: Q9FFD0) from <italic toggle="yes">A. thaliana</italic>. Partial atomic charges calculated by αCharges are visualised in a cartoon model.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="gkad349fig4" position="float"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="SEC4">
    <title>CONCLUSION</title>
    <p>In this article, we presented αCharges, a novel web application for calculating partial atomic charges on protein structures produced by the AlphaFold2 algorithm and available in AlphaFoldDB. αCharges utilises the SQE+qp empirical charge calculation method, parameterised using B3LYP/6-31G*/NPA quantum mechanical charges. αCharges allows users to download charges (in PQR, mmCIF, or plaintext formats) or visualise them via three main structure visualisation models (cartoon, ball &amp; stick, and surface). The web application is easy to use and is platform-independent. Documentation explaining the usage of the tool is provided on the webpage.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="SEC5">
    <title>DATA AVAILABILITY</title>
    <p>αCharges application is freely available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://alphacharges.ncbr.muni.cz" ext-link-type="uri">https://alphacharges.ncbr.muni.cz</ext-link> (hosted by the highly available Masaryk University computing cloud) with no login requirement. The user manual for the application is available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/sb-ncbr/AlphaCharges/wiki" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/sb-ncbr/AlphaCharges/wiki</ext-link>, while the source code is accessible at GitHub under the MIT licence at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/sb-ncbr/AlphaCharges/" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/sb-ncbr/AlphaCharges/</ext-link> and is also available in the Supplementary Data. The code is also available on Zenodo at <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7844436" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7844436</ext-link>.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
      <label>gkad349_Supplemental_Files</label>
      <media xlink:href="gkad349_supplemental_files.zip">
        <caption>
          <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
        </caption>
      </media>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack id="ACK1">
    <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
    <p>The authors would like to thank Vladimír Horský for his valuable comments and proofreading.</p>
    <p>Computational resources were supplied by the project ‘e-Infrastruktura CZ’ (e-INFRA CZ LM2023054) supported by the Ministry of Education, Youth and Sports of the Czech Republic.</p>
    <p>Core Facility Biological Data Management and Analysis of CEITEC Masaryk University, supported by ELIXIR CZ research infrastructure (MEYS Grant No: LM2023055) is gratefully acknowledged for the obtaining of the scientific data presented in this paper.</p>
  </ack>
  <sec id="SEC6">
    <title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title>
    <p><ext-link xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/nar/article-lookup/doi/10.1093/nar/gkad349#supplementary-data" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Data</ext-link> are available at NAR Online.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="SEC7">
    <title>FUNDING</title>
    <p>Ministry of Education, Youth and Sports of the Czech Republic: ELIXIR CZ [LM2023055]; IOCB Tech Foundation: The Martina Roeselová Memorial Fellowship [to O.S.]. Funding for open access charge: Masaryk University as per its Read and Publish agreement with the Oxford University Press.</p>
    <p><italic toggle="yes">Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p>
  </sec>
  <ref-list id="REF1">
    <title>REFERENCES</title>
    <ref id="B1">
      <label>1.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jumper</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pritzel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Figurnov</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ronneberger</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tunyasuvunakool</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Žídek</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Potapenko</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Highly accurate protein structure prediction with AlphaFold</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2021</year>; <volume>596</volume>:<fpage>583</fpage>–<lpage>589</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34265844</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B2">
      <label>2.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Varadi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Anyango</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Appasamy</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bage</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berrisford</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Choudhary</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bertoni</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deshpande</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leines</surname><given-names>G.D.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>PDBe and PDBe-KB: providing high-quality, up-to-date and integrated resources of macromolecular structures to support basic and applied research and education</article-title>. <source>Protein Sci.</source><year>2022</year>; <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>e4439</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36173162</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B3">
      <label>3.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Varadi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Anyango</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deshpande</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Natassia</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yordanova</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stroe</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laydon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>AlphaFold Protein Structure Database: massively expanding the structural coverage of protein-sequence space with high-accuracy models</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2022</year>; <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>D439</fpage>–<lpage>D444</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34791371</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B4">
      <label>4.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Raček</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schindler</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Toušek</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Horský</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koča</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Svobodová</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Atomic Charge Calculator II: web-based tool for the calculation of partial atomic charges</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2020</year>; <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>W591</fpage>–<lpage>W596</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32402071</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B5">
      <label>5.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kangas</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tidor</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Electrostatic complementarity at ligand binding sites: application to chorismate mutase</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Chem. B</source>. <year>2001</year>; <volume>105</volume>:<fpage>880</fpage>–<lpage>888</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B6">
      <label>6.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gitlin</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carbeck</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whitesides</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Why are proteins charged? Networks of charge–charge interactions in proteins measured by charge ladders and capillary electrophoresis</article-title>. <source>Angew. Chem.</source><year>2006</year>; <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>3022</fpage>–<lpage>3060</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16619322</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B7">
      <label>7.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Critical assessment of the automated AutoDock as a new docking tool for virtual screening</article-title>. <source>Proteins</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>65</volume>:<fpage>549</fpage>–<lpage>554</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16988956</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B8">
      <label>8.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rappé</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goddard III</surname><given-names>W.A.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Charge equilibration for molecular dynamics simulations</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Chem.</source><year>1991</year>; <volume>95</volume>:<fpage>3358</fpage>–<lpage>3363</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B9">
      <label>9.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nazarian</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Camp</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sholl</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>A comprehensive set of high-quality point charges for simulations of metal–organic frameworks</article-title>. <source>Chem. Mater.</source><year>2016</year>; <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>785</fpage>–<lpage>793</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B10">
      <label>10.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Boda</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nonner</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Computing induced charges in inhomogeneous dielectric media: application in a Monte Carlo simulation of complex ionic systems</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. E</source>. <year>2004</year>; <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>046702</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B11">
      <label>11.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Shankar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><source>Principles of Quantum Mechanics</source>. <year>2012</year>; <publisher-loc>NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B12">
      <label>12.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weinhold</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Natural bond orbital analysis of near-Hartree–Fock water dimer</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Phys.</source><year>1983</year>; <volume>78</volume>:<fpage>4066</fpage>–<lpage>4073</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B13">
      <label>13.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weinstock</surname><given-names>R.B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weinhold</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Natural population analysis</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Phys.</source><year>1985</year>; <volume>83</volume>:<fpage>735</fpage>–<lpage>746</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B14">
      <label>14.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Schindler</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raček</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maršavelski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koča</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Svobodová</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Optimized SQE atomic charges for peptides accessible via a web application</article-title>. <source>J. Cheminform.</source><year>2021</year>; <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>45</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34193251</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B15">
      <label>15.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Søndergaard</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olsson</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rostkowski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Improved treatment of ligands and coupling effects in empirical calculation and rationalization of pKa values</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Theory Comput.</source><year>2011</year>; <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>2284</fpage>–<lpage>2295</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26606496</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B16">
      <label>16.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Olsson</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Søndergaard</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rostkowski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>PROPKA3: consistent treatment of internal and surface residues in empirical pKa predictions</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Theory Comput.</source><year>2011</year>; <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>525</fpage>–<lpage>537</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26596171</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B17">
      <label>17.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sehnal</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bittrich</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deshpande</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Svobodová</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bazgier</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Velankar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burley</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koča</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Mol* Viewer: modern web app for 3D visualization and analysis of large biomolecular structures</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2021</year>; <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>W431</fpage>–<lpage>W437</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33956157</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B18">
      <label>18.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Burley</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bhikadiya</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bittrich</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crichlow</surname><given-names>G.V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Christie</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dalenberg</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Di Costanzo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>RCSB Protein Data Bank: powerful new tools for exploring 3D structures of biological macromolecules for basic and applied research and education in fundamental biology, biomedicine, biotechnology, bioengineering and energy sciences</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2021</year>; <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>D437</fpage>–<lpage>D451</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33211854</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B19">
      <label>19.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mortier</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shankar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Electronegativity equalization method for the calculation of atomic charges in molecules</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>1986</year>; <volume>108</volume>:<fpage>4315</fpage>–<lpage>4320</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B20">
      <label>20.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nistor</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Polihronov</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Müser</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mosey</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>A generalization of the charge equilibration method for nonmetallic materials</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Phys.</source><year>2006</year>; <volume>125</volume>:<fpage>094108</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16965073</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B21">
      <label>21.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dolinsky</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCammon</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>PDB2PQR: an automated pipeline for the setup of Poisson–Boltzmann electrostatics calculations</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2004</year>; <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>W665</fpage>–<lpage>W667</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15215472</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B22">
      <label>22.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ionescu</surname><given-names>C.-M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sehnal</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Falginella</surname><given-names>F.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pant</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pravda</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bouchal</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Svobodová Vařeková</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Geidl</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koča</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>AtomicChargeCalculator: interactive web-based calculation of atomic charges in large biomolecular complexes and drug-like molecules</article-title>. <source>J. Cheminform.</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>50</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26500704</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B23">
      <label>23.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Leslie</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deeley</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Multidrug resistance proteins: role of P-glycoprotein, MRP1, MRP2, and BCRP (ABCG2) in tissue defense</article-title>. <source>Toxicol. Appl. Pharmacol.</source><year>2005</year>; <volume>204</volume>:<fpage>216</fpage>–<lpage>237</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15845415</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B24">
      <label>24.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Szewczyk</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grimard</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C.-W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Doshi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caya</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Villaluz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pardon</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cregger</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Structures of P-glycoprotein reveal its conformational flexibility and an epitope on the nucleotide-binding domain</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source><year>2013</year>; <volume>110</volume>:<fpage>13386</fpage>–<lpage>13391</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23901103</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B25">
      <label>25.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Heda</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Toro</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tombazzi</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Physiology, pepsin</article-title>. <source>StatPearls</source>. <year>2022</year>; <publisher-loc>Treasure Island, FL</publisher-loc><publisher-name>StatPearls Publishing</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B26">
      <label>26.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Stanforth</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilcox</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chater</surname><given-names>P.I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brownlee</surname><given-names>I.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zakhour</surname><given-names>M.I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Banecki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Pepsin properties, structure, and its accurate measurement: a narrative review</article-title>. <source>Ann. Esophagus</source>. <year>2022</year>; <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>31</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B27">
      <label>27.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yada</surname><given-names>R.Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>N-terminal portion acts as an initiator of the inactivation of pepsin at neutral pH</article-title>. <source>Protein Eng. Des. Sel.</source><year>2001</year>; <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>669</fpage>–<lpage>674</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B28">
      <label>28.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Grahame</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dupuis</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bryksa</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yada</surname><given-names>R.Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Improving the alkaline stability of pepsin through rational protein design using renin, an alkaline-stable aspartic protease, as a structural and functional reference</article-title>. <source>Enzyme Microb. Technol.</source><year>2021</year>; <volume>150</volume>:<fpage>109871</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34489030</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B29">
      <label>29.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ung</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Winkler</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kolb</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Janacek</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dedic</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stokes</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hammes</surname><given-names>U.Z.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Structures and mechanism of the plant PIN-FORMED auxin transporter</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2022</year>; <volume>609</volume>:<fpage>605</fpage>–<lpage>610</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35768502</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B30">
      <label>30.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Structural insights into auxin recognition and efflux by Arabidopsis PIN1</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2022</year>; <volume>609</volume>:<fpage>611</fpage>–<lpage>615</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35917925</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B31">
      <label>31.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Z.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Structures and mechanisms of the Arabidopsis auxin transporter PIN3</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2022</year>; <volume>609</volume>:<fpage>616</fpage>–<lpage>621</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35917926</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?properties open_access?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">10320090</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37158246</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkad349</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gkad349</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI00010</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Web Server Issue</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>αCharges: partial atomic charges for AlphaFold structures in high quality</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9047-0334</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Schindler</surname>
          <given-names>Ondřej</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>CEITEC – Central European Institute of Technology, Masaryk University</institution>, 625 00 Brno, <country country="CZ">Czech Republic</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>National Centre for Biomolecular Research, Faculty of Science, Masaryk University</institution>, 625 00 Brno, <country country="CZ">Czech Republic</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9472-2589</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Berka</surname>
          <given-names>Karel</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Department of Physical Chemistry, Faculty of Science, Palacký University Olomouc</institution>, 779 00 Olomouc, <country country="CZ">Czech Republic</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3619-6434</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Cantara</surname>
          <given-names>Alessio</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>CEITEC – Central European Institute of Technology, Masaryk University</institution>, 625 00 Brno, <country country="CZ">Czech Republic</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>National Centre for Biomolecular Research, Faculty of Science, Masaryk University</institution>, 625 00 Brno, <country country="CZ">Czech Republic</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3395-3196</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Křenek</surname>
          <given-names>Aleš</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Institute of Computer Science, Masaryk University</institution>, 602 00 Brno, <country country="CZ">Czech Republic</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7266-1789</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Tichý</surname>
          <given-names>Dominik</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Faculty of Informatics, Masaryk University</institution>, 602 00 Brno, <country country="CZ">Czech Republic</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0296-2452</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Raček</surname>
          <given-names>Tomáš</given-names>
        </name>
        <!--krab1k@mail.muni.cz-->
        <aff><institution>CEITEC – Central European Institute of Technology, Masaryk University</institution>, 625 00 Brno, <country country="CZ">Czech Republic</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>National Centre for Biomolecular Research, Faculty of Science, Masaryk University</institution>, 625 00 Brno, <country country="CZ">Czech Republic</country></aff>
        <xref rid="COR2" ref-type="corresp"/>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3840-8760</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Svobodová</surname>
          <given-names>Radka</given-names>
        </name>
        <!--radka.svobodova@mail.muni.cz-->
        <aff><institution>CEITEC – Central European Institute of Technology, Masaryk University</institution>, 625 00 Brno, <country country="CZ">Czech Republic</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>National Centre for Biomolecular Research, Faculty of Science, Masaryk University</institution>, 625 00 Brno, <country country="CZ">Czech Republic</country></aff>
        <xref rid="COR1" ref-type="corresp"/>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="COR1">To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +420 54949 4860; Email: <email>radka.svobodova@mail.muni.cz</email></corresp>
      <corresp id="COR2">Correspondence may also be addressed to Tomáš Raček. Tel: +420 54949 6568; Email: <email>krab1k@mail.muni.cz</email></corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <day>05</day>
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2023-05-09">
      <day>09</day>
      <month>5</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>09</day>
      <month>5</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>51</volume>
    <issue>W1</issue>
    <fpage>W11</fpage>
    <lpage>W16</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>24</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>17</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>18</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2023. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Nucleic Acids Research.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xlink:href="gkad349.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <p>The AlphaFold2 prediction algorithm opened up the possibility of exploring proteins’ structural space at an unprecedented scale. Currently, &gt;200 million protein structures predicted by this approach are deposited in AlphaFoldDB, covering entire proteomes of multiple organisms, including humans. Predicted structures are, however, stored without detailed functional annotations describing their chemical behaviour. Partial atomic charges, which map electron distribution over a molecule and provide a clue to its chemical reactivity, are an important example of such data. We introduce the web application αCharges: a tool for the quick calculation of partial atomic charges for protein structures from AlphaFoldDB. The charges are calculated by the recent empirical method SQE+qp, parameterised for this class of molecules using robust quantum mechanics charges (B3LYP/6-31G*/NPA) on PROPKA3 protonated structures. The computed partial atomic charges can be downloaded in common data formats or visualised via the powerful Mol* viewer. The αCharges application is freely available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://alphacharges.ncbr.muni.cz" ext-link-type="uri">https://alphacharges.ncbr.muni.cz</ext-link> with no login requirement.</p>
    </abstract>
    <abstract abstract-type="graphical">
      <title>Graphical Abstract</title>
      <p>
        <fig position="float" id="ga1">
          <label>Graphical Abstract</label>
          <caption>
            <p>A schema describing the 𝛂Charges workflow: A structure is obtained from AlphaFoldDB and protonated by PROPKA3. Its charges are calculated by SQE+qp and visualized with Mol*.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="gkad349figgra1" position="float"/>
        </fig>
      </p>
    </abstract>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Ministry of Education</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100009122</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>LM2023055</award-id>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>IOCB Tech Foundation</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="6"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec sec-type="intro" id="SEC1">
    <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
    <p>The AlphaFold2 prediction algorithm (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>) provided us with markedly greater insight into the structural space of proteins. Specifically, the set of 200 000 experimentally determined protein structures in the Protein Data Bank (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>) is currently extended by &gt;200 million predicted protein structures in AlphaFoldDB (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). This enables the research community to consider and hypothesise on scientific questions that could not have been touched until now.</p>
    <p>It is beneficial to enrich the predicted protein structures with properties describing their chemical behaviour to support this research. A typical example of such data is partial atomic charges (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), which map the electron distribution over the molecule and provide a clue to its chemical reactivity. Partial atomic charges enable us to compare binding sites, including their polarity (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>), identify hydrophobic membrane parts (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), or drive protein-protein interactions (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). They are also used as inputs for molecular docking (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), molecular dynamics (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>), and other simulations (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).</p>
    <p>The most reliable way to compute partial atomic charges is using quantum mechanics (QM) (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), which can provide electron density distribution among molecular orbitals. Afterwards, its mapping to atoms can be calculated by population analyses, e.g. Natural population analysis (NPA) (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Unfortunately, QM methods are very time-consuming, and therefore only applicable to small molecules.</p>
    <p>A faster alternative is the usage of empirical charge calculation methods (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), which mimic QM approaches and are based on significantly less complex empirical equation systems describing the charge distribution. These empirical methods are parameterised using QM charges calculated by a certain combination of a QM method and a population analysis. Charges computed by the empirical method mimic QM charges used in the parameterisation process. Even though the empirical methods are fast, it is challenging to apply them to proteins. One reason is that proteins are very large systems, and the empirical methods must be optimised to handle them. Moreover, proteins are homogeneous (i.e. they contain atoms with similar neighbourhoods), complicating the parameterisation of empirical methods. For these reasons, empirical charge calculation methods applicable to proteins have been developed in the last several years. We developed the SQE+qp method (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), which is currently the best-performing approach for proteins. We are also the authors of ACC II (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), a web server that provides charge calculation for almost any structure using 20 empirical methods. ACC II also includes the SQE+qp approach.</p>
    <p>A limitation of ACC II is that it requires a protonated protein structure. Additionally, it implicitly deals with electroneutral molecules (i.e. molecules that have a zero total charge). The total charge is computed as a sum of the formal charges of individual atoms specified in the input file. A structure with a non-zero total charge can be provided. However, the user has to compute it by him or herself and include it in the input file. Moreover, the empirical methods in ACC II are only parameterised for electroneutral molecules. On the other hand, protein structures produced by the AlphaFold2 algorithm and contained in AlphaFoldDB do not include hydrogens, and after protonation, most of them are not electroneutral.</p>
    <p>For this reason, we introduce αCharges, which solves all these challenges and provides the following functionality:</p>
    <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
        <p>The input protein structure from AlphaFoldDB is protonated using PROPKA3 (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) based on the pH value provided by the user (physiological pH is used as the default value).</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>After protonation, the total charge of the protein is computed and used as an input for the SQE+qp method.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>The SQE+qp method is parameterised directly for protein-like structures.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>αCharges integrates the Mol* viewer (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>), a cutting-edge molecular visualiser also used in AlphaFoldDB (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), PDBe (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>) and RCSB PDB (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>).</p>
      </list-item>
    </list>
    <p>Therefore, αCharges provides high-quality partial atomic charges for AlphaFoldDB structures in one click. The user only has to provide the UniProt ID of the protein, and no additional knowledge or preprocessing is required.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="SEC2">
    <title>DESCRIPTION OF THE WEB SERVER</title>
    <p>The application back end is written in Python, using the Flask web framework (<ext-link xlink:href="https://flask.palletsprojects.com/" ext-link-type="uri">https://flask.palletsprojects.com/</ext-link>). The front end is built with the Bootstrap library (<ext-link xlink:href="https://getbootstrap.com/" ext-link-type="uri">https://getbootstrap.com/</ext-link>).</p>
    <sec id="SEC2-1">
      <title>SQE+qp method</title>
      <p>The computation of partial atomic charges is carried out according to the SQE+qp model (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), which belongs to the family of electronegativity equalisation methods, like the popular EEM (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>), QEq (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) or SQE (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>).</p>
      <p>As SQE added bond information to the EEM formalism, SQE+qp further improved it by adding a parameterised initial charge for each atomic type. In this context, an atomic type represents a class of atoms with similar characteristics (e.g. all carbon atoms with only single bonds or all hydrogen atoms bound to oxygen atoms).</p>
      <p>These initial charges and other model parameters have to be chosen appropriately for the given class of molecules (e.g. peptides, drug-like molecules, nucleic acids) to compute high-quality partial atomic charges.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2-2">
      <title>αCharges workflow</title>
      <p>One of the major design decisions for αCharges was to provide the user with an intuitive interface that would facilitate the calculation of partial atomic charges without needing to configure all the parameters of the process. The workflow is depicted in Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and can be described in several steps:</p>
      <list list-type="bullet">
        <list-item>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Downloading the structure from AlphaFoldDB API:</italic> The first step is to enter the UniProt ID (or AlphaFoldDB ID) of a selected protein structure into the textbox on the landing page. The structure is downloaded in PDB format if the ID is valid. Currently, structures are downloaded in the latest version (i.e. AlphaFoldDB version 4, as of February 2023). However, if a user clicks the <italic toggle="yes">Setup calculation</italic> button, any prior version can be selected.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Addition of hydrogens by PDB2PQR/PROPKA3:</italic> Once the structure is downloaded, adding hydrogen atoms is the next step. For this purpose, αCharges uses PDB2PQR (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) with the PROPKA3 library (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). By default, the protonation is done using the physiological pH of 7.2. However, any value between 0 and 14 can be specified on the <italic toggle="yes">Setup</italic> page.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Calculation of charges by SQE+qp:</italic> If the protonation succeeds, partial atomic charges can be computed. Since the input structure might be large (i.e. tens of thousands of atoms), even quite effective empirical methods such as SQE+qp might be too memory-demanding and slow, since they have a cubic computational complexity with respect to the number of bonds in the molecule.</p>
          <p>To overcome the issue of computation complexity, αCharges uses the Cutoff/Cover approach (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>), which first divides the molecule into smaller regions (spheres centred around individual residues). Then, the computation is carried out independently for each region. In the next step, the partial atomic charges are corrected so that their sum equals the desired total molecular charge. First, the correction is computed for each small region. Then, the charges of the whole structure are revised in the same way.</p>
          <p>The quality of the parameters for the empirical charge calculation method heavily influences the quality of the resulting charges. αCharges uses parameters fitted to reproduce B3LYP/6-31G*/NPA charges originally parameterised on the set of peptides and later optimised for proteins. Charges computed using these parameters were shown to achieve an excellent agreement with the reference charges (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>).</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Visualisation of the charges with Mol*:</italic> After calculating partial atomic charges, the user is redirected to the Results page, whose central part is Mol* viewer (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Mol* was extended to support the visualisation of partial atomic charges at several levels of protein structure depending on the chosen view. The default <italic toggle="yes">cartoon</italic> representation colours each residue by the sum of the charges of its atoms. The two other visualisation modes are <italic toggle="yes">ball &amp; stick</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">surface</italic>.</p>
          <p>The values of charges are mapped onto a linear blue-white-red gradient, where blue means a positive charge, white signifies zero charge, and red equals a negative charge. Two main colouring types are available in the application. In the default <italic toggle="yes">relative colouring</italic>, the gradient is mapped to the charges such that the highest and lowest charges are represented by the most saturated shades of blue and red, respectively. If a user wants to generate several images of various structures to compare the charge distribution, <italic toggle="yes">absolute colouring</italic> can be used. In this case, the maximum value of positive and negative charge can be configured manually.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Download of computed charges:</italic> Although the visual representation of the charges is undoubtedly valuable for humans, the charges can also be downloaded if further processing is required. αCharges includes files of several formats in a downloaded ZIP file for user convenience. These include:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>PDB file with added hydrogens</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>PQR file with added hydrogens and calculated charges</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>mmCIF file with added hydrogens and calculated charges</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>a simple TXT file with calculated charges</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </list-item>
      </list>
      <fig position="float" id="F1">
        <label>Figure 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Schematic depiction of αCharges workflow. The schema includes a structure of porin (UniProt ID: A0A2E5IBK2) originating from <italic toggle="yes">Euryarchaeota archaeon</italic>.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="gkad349fig1" position="float"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2-3">
      <title>Limitations</title>
      <p>αCharges cannot compute partial atomic charges for proteins that contain structural errors because of an incorrect AlphaFold2 prediction. Furthermore, PROPKA3 is unable to protonate some structures correctly. In these cases, an appropriate error message is given to the user. The message lists all atoms that were identified as problematic. After clicking on their names, they are highlighted in Mol* so the user can visually inspect the issues.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="results" id="SEC3">
    <title>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</title>
    <p>We put the application through extensive testing to confirm that it is stable and reliable. Details of this testing can be found in the Supplementary Data.</p>
    <p>Furthermore, we provide three use cases demonstrating various applications of αCharges. They are presented interactively on the αCharges webpage.</p>
    <sec id="SEC3-1">
      <title>Example I: P-glycoprotein</title>
      <p>P-glycoprotein is one of the ABC transporter proteins that decrease drug accumulation in cancer cells (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). It is a 170kDa protein consisting of a nucleotide-binding domain and a transmembrane domain (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). We used a P-glycoprotein structure model from <italic toggle="yes">Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> (UniProt ID P34712). Visualising the charges (Figure <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) computed by αCharges demonstrates the differences in charge distribution between the transmembrane parts and extracellular/intracellular ones.</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F2">
        <label>Figure 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Structure of P-glycoprotein from <italic toggle="yes">Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> (UniProt ID: P34712). Partial atomic charges calculated by αCharges are visualised on the protein’s surface. They show distinct areas of the protein: The nonpolar transmembrane part (mostly very light blue due to the charge being around zero on the surface) and the polar surface of extracellular and cytoplasmic parts (with a mosaic of blue positive and red negative charges).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="gkad349fig2" position="float"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC3-2">
      <title>Example II: pepsin</title>
      <p>Pepsin is an enzyme that plays a major role in protein digestion in the stomach. It is secreted as a zymogen and activated by the acidic pH created by the stomach parietal cells. Pepsin is most effective at a pH of approximately 1.5 to 2, and becomes inactive when the pH rises above 6 (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). The enzyme denatures at a pH 8 (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Differences in the charge distribution between its active form (pH 2) and inactive form (pH 7) can be seen in this use case (Figure <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The alkaline environment causes an increase in negative charges, which contributes to the structural instability of the pepsin, causing the shift to an inactive form of the protein (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>).</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F3">
        <label>Figure 3.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Structure of pepsin (UniProt ID: P00791), partial atomic charges calculated by αCharges are visualised on the cartoon model of the protein showing significant charge differences between an active form (left image, pH 2) and an inactive form (right image, pH 7).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="gkad349fig3" position="float"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC3-3">
      <title>Example III: PIN proteins</title>
      <p>The PIN family proteins control plant growth by regulating auxin export from the cytosol to the extracellular space (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Eight types of PIN transport proteins are known (PIN1 to PIN8) and they are divided into two classes: canonical PINs (PIN1-4 and PIN7) and non-canonical PINs (PIN5, PIN6 and PIN8) (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). This year, structures of three of them were discovered and published (PIN1 (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>), PIN3 (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>) and PIN8 (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>)), while structures of the remaining ones are waiting to be revealed. But thanks to AlphaFoldDB, we can see their predicted structure and compare their charge distribution.</p>
      <p>Charge distribution of canonical PINs is very similar, even though sequence and structure strongly differ. It can be seen especially when we compare PIN3 and PIN7 (see Figure <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, top images). On the other hand, charge distribution of non-canonical PINs differs from each other and also from canonical PINs (see PIN5 in Figure <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, bottom image).</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F4">
        <label>Figure 4.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Structure of PIN3 (top left image, UniProt ID: Q9S7Z8), PIN7 (top right, UniProt ID: Q940Y5) and PIN5 (bottom image, UniProt ID: Q9FFD0) from <italic toggle="yes">A. thaliana</italic>. Partial atomic charges calculated by αCharges are visualised in a cartoon model.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="gkad349fig4" position="float"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="SEC4">
    <title>CONCLUSION</title>
    <p>In this article, we presented αCharges, a novel web application for calculating partial atomic charges on protein structures produced by the AlphaFold2 algorithm and available in AlphaFoldDB. αCharges utilises the SQE+qp empirical charge calculation method, parameterised using B3LYP/6-31G*/NPA quantum mechanical charges. αCharges allows users to download charges (in PQR, mmCIF, or plaintext formats) or visualise them via three main structure visualisation models (cartoon, ball &amp; stick, and surface). The web application is easy to use and is platform-independent. Documentation explaining the usage of the tool is provided on the webpage.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="SEC5">
    <title>DATA AVAILABILITY</title>
    <p>αCharges application is freely available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://alphacharges.ncbr.muni.cz" ext-link-type="uri">https://alphacharges.ncbr.muni.cz</ext-link> (hosted by the highly available Masaryk University computing cloud) with no login requirement. The user manual for the application is available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/sb-ncbr/AlphaCharges/wiki" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/sb-ncbr/AlphaCharges/wiki</ext-link>, while the source code is accessible at GitHub under the MIT licence at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/sb-ncbr/AlphaCharges/" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/sb-ncbr/AlphaCharges/</ext-link> and is also available in the Supplementary Data. The code is also available on Zenodo at <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7844436" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7844436</ext-link>.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
      <label>gkad349_Supplemental_Files</label>
      <media xlink:href="gkad349_supplemental_files.zip">
        <caption>
          <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
        </caption>
      </media>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack id="ACK1">
    <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
    <p>The authors would like to thank Vladimír Horský for his valuable comments and proofreading.</p>
    <p>Computational resources were supplied by the project ‘e-Infrastruktura CZ’ (e-INFRA CZ LM2023054) supported by the Ministry of Education, Youth and Sports of the Czech Republic.</p>
    <p>Core Facility Biological Data Management and Analysis of CEITEC Masaryk University, supported by ELIXIR CZ research infrastructure (MEYS Grant No: LM2023055) is gratefully acknowledged for the obtaining of the scientific data presented in this paper.</p>
  </ack>
  <sec id="SEC6">
    <title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title>
    <p><ext-link xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/nar/article-lookup/doi/10.1093/nar/gkad349#supplementary-data" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Data</ext-link> are available at NAR Online.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="SEC7">
    <title>FUNDING</title>
    <p>Ministry of Education, Youth and Sports of the Czech Republic: ELIXIR CZ [LM2023055]; IOCB Tech Foundation: The Martina Roeselová Memorial Fellowship [to O.S.]. Funding for open access charge: Masaryk University as per its Read and Publish agreement with the Oxford University Press.</p>
    <p><italic toggle="yes">Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p>
  </sec>
  <ref-list id="REF1">
    <title>REFERENCES</title>
    <ref id="B1">
      <label>1.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jumper</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pritzel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Figurnov</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ronneberger</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tunyasuvunakool</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Žídek</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Potapenko</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Highly accurate protein structure prediction with AlphaFold</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2021</year>; <volume>596</volume>:<fpage>583</fpage>–<lpage>589</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34265844</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B2">
      <label>2.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Varadi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Anyango</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Appasamy</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bage</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berrisford</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Choudhary</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bertoni</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deshpande</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leines</surname><given-names>G.D.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>PDBe and PDBe-KB: providing high-quality, up-to-date and integrated resources of macromolecular structures to support basic and applied research and education</article-title>. <source>Protein Sci.</source><year>2022</year>; <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>e4439</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36173162</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B3">
      <label>3.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Varadi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Anyango</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deshpande</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Natassia</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yordanova</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stroe</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laydon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>AlphaFold Protein Structure Database: massively expanding the structural coverage of protein-sequence space with high-accuracy models</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2022</year>; <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>D439</fpage>–<lpage>D444</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34791371</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B4">
      <label>4.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Raček</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schindler</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Toušek</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Horský</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koča</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Svobodová</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Atomic Charge Calculator II: web-based tool for the calculation of partial atomic charges</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2020</year>; <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>W591</fpage>–<lpage>W596</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32402071</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B5">
      <label>5.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kangas</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tidor</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Electrostatic complementarity at ligand binding sites: application to chorismate mutase</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Chem. B</source>. <year>2001</year>; <volume>105</volume>:<fpage>880</fpage>–<lpage>888</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B6">
      <label>6.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gitlin</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carbeck</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whitesides</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Why are proteins charged? Networks of charge–charge interactions in proteins measured by charge ladders and capillary electrophoresis</article-title>. <source>Angew. Chem.</source><year>2006</year>; <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>3022</fpage>–<lpage>3060</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16619322</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B7">
      <label>7.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Critical assessment of the automated AutoDock as a new docking tool for virtual screening</article-title>. <source>Proteins</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>65</volume>:<fpage>549</fpage>–<lpage>554</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16988956</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B8">
      <label>8.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rappé</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goddard III</surname><given-names>W.A.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Charge equilibration for molecular dynamics simulations</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Chem.</source><year>1991</year>; <volume>95</volume>:<fpage>3358</fpage>–<lpage>3363</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B9">
      <label>9.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nazarian</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Camp</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sholl</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>A comprehensive set of high-quality point charges for simulations of metal–organic frameworks</article-title>. <source>Chem. Mater.</source><year>2016</year>; <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>785</fpage>–<lpage>793</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B10">
      <label>10.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Boda</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nonner</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Computing induced charges in inhomogeneous dielectric media: application in a Monte Carlo simulation of complex ionic systems</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. E</source>. <year>2004</year>; <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>046702</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B11">
      <label>11.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Shankar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><source>Principles of Quantum Mechanics</source>. <year>2012</year>; <publisher-loc>NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B12">
      <label>12.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weinhold</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Natural bond orbital analysis of near-Hartree–Fock water dimer</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Phys.</source><year>1983</year>; <volume>78</volume>:<fpage>4066</fpage>–<lpage>4073</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B13">
      <label>13.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weinstock</surname><given-names>R.B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weinhold</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Natural population analysis</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Phys.</source><year>1985</year>; <volume>83</volume>:<fpage>735</fpage>–<lpage>746</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B14">
      <label>14.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Schindler</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raček</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maršavelski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koča</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Svobodová</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Optimized SQE atomic charges for peptides accessible via a web application</article-title>. <source>J. Cheminform.</source><year>2021</year>; <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>45</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34193251</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B15">
      <label>15.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Søndergaard</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olsson</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rostkowski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Improved treatment of ligands and coupling effects in empirical calculation and rationalization of pKa values</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Theory Comput.</source><year>2011</year>; <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>2284</fpage>–<lpage>2295</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26606496</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B16">
      <label>16.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Olsson</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Søndergaard</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rostkowski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>PROPKA3: consistent treatment of internal and surface residues in empirical pKa predictions</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Theory Comput.</source><year>2011</year>; <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>525</fpage>–<lpage>537</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26596171</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B17">
      <label>17.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sehnal</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bittrich</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deshpande</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Svobodová</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bazgier</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Velankar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burley</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koča</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Mol* Viewer: modern web app for 3D visualization and analysis of large biomolecular structures</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2021</year>; <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>W431</fpage>–<lpage>W437</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33956157</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B18">
      <label>18.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Burley</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bhikadiya</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bittrich</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crichlow</surname><given-names>G.V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Christie</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dalenberg</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Di Costanzo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>RCSB Protein Data Bank: powerful new tools for exploring 3D structures of biological macromolecules for basic and applied research and education in fundamental biology, biomedicine, biotechnology, bioengineering and energy sciences</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2021</year>; <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>D437</fpage>–<lpage>D451</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33211854</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B19">
      <label>19.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mortier</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shankar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Electronegativity equalization method for the calculation of atomic charges in molecules</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>1986</year>; <volume>108</volume>:<fpage>4315</fpage>–<lpage>4320</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B20">
      <label>20.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nistor</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Polihronov</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Müser</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mosey</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>A generalization of the charge equilibration method for nonmetallic materials</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Phys.</source><year>2006</year>; <volume>125</volume>:<fpage>094108</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16965073</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B21">
      <label>21.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dolinsky</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCammon</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>PDB2PQR: an automated pipeline for the setup of Poisson–Boltzmann electrostatics calculations</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2004</year>; <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>W665</fpage>–<lpage>W667</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15215472</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B22">
      <label>22.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ionescu</surname><given-names>C.-M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sehnal</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Falginella</surname><given-names>F.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pant</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pravda</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bouchal</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Svobodová Vařeková</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Geidl</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koča</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>AtomicChargeCalculator: interactive web-based calculation of atomic charges in large biomolecular complexes and drug-like molecules</article-title>. <source>J. Cheminform.</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>50</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26500704</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B23">
      <label>23.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Leslie</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deeley</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Multidrug resistance proteins: role of P-glycoprotein, MRP1, MRP2, and BCRP (ABCG2) in tissue defense</article-title>. <source>Toxicol. Appl. Pharmacol.</source><year>2005</year>; <volume>204</volume>:<fpage>216</fpage>–<lpage>237</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15845415</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B24">
      <label>24.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Szewczyk</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grimard</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C.-W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Doshi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caya</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Villaluz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pardon</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cregger</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Structures of P-glycoprotein reveal its conformational flexibility and an epitope on the nucleotide-binding domain</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source><year>2013</year>; <volume>110</volume>:<fpage>13386</fpage>–<lpage>13391</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23901103</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B25">
      <label>25.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Heda</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Toro</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tombazzi</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Physiology, pepsin</article-title>. <source>StatPearls</source>. <year>2022</year>; <publisher-loc>Treasure Island, FL</publisher-loc><publisher-name>StatPearls Publishing</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B26">
      <label>26.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Stanforth</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilcox</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chater</surname><given-names>P.I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brownlee</surname><given-names>I.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zakhour</surname><given-names>M.I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Banecki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Pepsin properties, structure, and its accurate measurement: a narrative review</article-title>. <source>Ann. Esophagus</source>. <year>2022</year>; <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>31</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B27">
      <label>27.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yada</surname><given-names>R.Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>N-terminal portion acts as an initiator of the inactivation of pepsin at neutral pH</article-title>. <source>Protein Eng. Des. Sel.</source><year>2001</year>; <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>669</fpage>–<lpage>674</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B28">
      <label>28.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Grahame</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dupuis</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bryksa</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yada</surname><given-names>R.Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Improving the alkaline stability of pepsin through rational protein design using renin, an alkaline-stable aspartic protease, as a structural and functional reference</article-title>. <source>Enzyme Microb. Technol.</source><year>2021</year>; <volume>150</volume>:<fpage>109871</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34489030</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B29">
      <label>29.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ung</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Winkler</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kolb</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Janacek</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dedic</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stokes</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hammes</surname><given-names>U.Z.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Structures and mechanism of the plant PIN-FORMED auxin transporter</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2022</year>; <volume>609</volume>:<fpage>605</fpage>–<lpage>610</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35768502</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B30">
      <label>30.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Structural insights into auxin recognition and efflux by Arabidopsis PIN1</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2022</year>; <volume>609</volume>:<fpage>611</fpage>–<lpage>615</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35917925</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B31">
      <label>31.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Z.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Structures and mechanisms of the Arabidopsis auxin transporter PIN3</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2022</year>; <volume>609</volume>:<fpage>616</fpage>–<lpage>621</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35917926</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
