<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?origin publisher?>
<?FILEmeta_CSBJ2381 xml ?>
<?FILEmain xml ?>
<?FILEmain pdf ?>
<?FILEgr1 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr2 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr3 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr4 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr5 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr6 jpg ?>
<?FILEmmc1 pdf ?>
<?FILEmmc2 zip ?>
<?FILEmmc3 docx ?>
<?properties open_access?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Comput Struct Biotechnol J</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Comput Struct Biotechnol J</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Computational and Structural Biotechnology Journal</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">2001-0370</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Research Network of Computational and Structural Biotechnology</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">10708961</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2001-0370(23)00417-8</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.csbj.2023.11.003</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Method Article</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>JLOH: Inferring loss of heterozygosity blocks from sequencing data</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005">
        <name>
          <surname>Schiavinato</surname>
          <given-names>Matteo</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
        <xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0010">
        <name>
          <surname>del Olmo</surname>
          <given-names>Valentina</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
        <xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0015">
        <name>
          <surname>Muya</surname>
          <given-names>Victor Njenga</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
        <xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
        <xref rid="aff0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
        <xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0020">
        <name>
          <surname>Gabaldón</surname>
          <given-names>Toni</given-names>
        </name>
        <email>toni.gabaldon@bsc.es</email>
        <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
        <xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
        <xref rid="aff0020" ref-type="aff">d</xref>
        <xref rid="aff0025" ref-type="aff">e</xref>
        <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="aff0005"><label>a</label>Barcelona Supercomputing Centre (BSC-CNS), Plaça Eusebi Güell, 1-3, 08034 Barcelona, Spain</aff>
      <aff id="aff0010"><label>b</label>Institute for Research in Biomedicine (IRB Barcelona), The Barcelona Institute of Science and Technology, Baldiri Reixac, 10, 08028 Barcelona, Spain</aff>
      <aff id="aff0015"><label>c</label>Eskişehir Osmangazi University, Büyükdere Meşelik Yerleşkesi, 26040 Odunpazarı, Eskişehir, Turkey</aff>
      <aff id="aff0020"><label>d</label>Catalan Institution for Research and Advanced Studies (ICREA), Barcelona, Spain</aff>
      <aff id="aff0025"><label>e</label>Centro de Investigación Biomédica En Red de Enfermedades Infecciosas (CIBERINFEC), Barcelona, Spain</aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="cor1"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author at: Barcelona Supercomputing Centre (BSC-CNS), Plaça Eusebi Güell, 1-3, 08034 Barcelona, Spain. <email>toni.gabaldon@bsc.es</email></corresp>
      <fn id="fn1">
        <label>1</label>
        <p id="ntp0005">Current address: Eskişehir Osmangazi University, Büyükdere Meşelik Yerleşkesi, 26040 Odunpazarı/Eskişehir.</p>
      </fn>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>07</day>
      <month>11</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>07</day>
      <month>11</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>21</volume>
    <fpage>5738</fpage>
    <lpage>5750</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>4</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>1</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>1</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© 2023 The Authors</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract id="ab0010">
      <p>Heterozygosity is a genetic condition in which two or more alleles are found at a genomic locus. Individuals that are the offspring of genetically divergent yet still interfertile parents (e.g. hybrids) are highly heterozygous. One of the most studied aspects in the genomes of these individuals is the loss of their original heterozygosity (LOH) when multi-allelic sites lose one of their two alleles by converting it to the other, or by remaining hemizygous at that site. The region undergoing LOH may involve a single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) or a longer stretch of DNA. LOH is deeply interconnected with adaptation but the in silico techniques to infer evolutionary relevant LOH blocks are hardly standardised, and a general tool to infer and analyse them across genomic contexts and species is missing. Here, we present JLOH, a computational toolkit for the inference and exploration of LOH blocks in genomes with at least 1% heterozygosity. JLOH only requires commonly available genomic sequencing data as input. Starting from mapped reads, called variants and a reference genome sequence, JLOH infers candidate LOH blocks based on SNP density (SNPs/kbp) and read coverage per position. Considering that most organisms that undergo extensive LOH are hybrids, JLOH has been designed to capture any subgenomic LOH pattern, assigning each LOH block to its subgenome of origin.</p>
    </abstract>
    <abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="ab0015">
      <title>Highlights</title>
      <p>
        <list list-type="simple" id="li0005">
          <list-item id="u0005">
            <label>•</label>
            <p id="p0005">Loss of heterozygosity (LOH) is a known driver of adaptation.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item id="u0010">
            <label>•</label>
            <p id="p0010">A general tool to extract LOH blocks regardless of the species context was missing.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item id="u0015">
            <label>•</label>
            <p id="p0015">JLOH is a tool to infer and analyse LOH blocks from sequencing data.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item id="u0020">
            <label>•</label>
            <p id="p0020">JLOH is fast, scalable, and able to highlight differences in LOH profiles down to the strain level.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </p>
    </abstract>
    <kwd-group id="keys0005">
      <title>Keywords</title>
      <kwd>Heterozygosity</kwd>
      <kwd>LOH</kwd>
      <kwd>Hybrids</kwd>
      <kwd>Variation</kwd>
      <kwd>Sequencing</kwd>
      <kwd>Pipeline</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec id="sec0005">
    <label>1</label>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <p id="p0030">Heterozygosity is the genetic condition that exists when two or more alleles are present at a specific genomic locus. Genomes with ploidy higher than one can exhibit different degrees of genomic heterozygosity, which is generally described as the amount of heterozygous sites across their sequence. Genomic heterozygosity entails genetic diversity, and a wider pool of alleles upon which selection can act. Heterozygosity is widespread and pervades all non-haploid organisms. Whenever there is more than one copy of a chromosome there can be a certain inherent degree of heterozygosity deriving from differences in the sequences of the different chromosomal copies. The more the parents of an individual are divergent in terms of genome sequence, the more heterozygosity plays a role in the adaptation of that individual to the environment. An extreme example are hybrids, i.e. organisms which are either the offspring of two diverged individuals from different species (inter-species hybrids) or from genetically distant populations of the same species (intra-species hybrids) <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. Hybridisation is pervasive across the eukaryotic tree of life, and is at the origin of many lineages of fungi, plants, and other eukaryotes <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. Hybrids carry a chimeric genome, resulting from the combination of divergent chromosomes from the parental organisms, i.e. homeologous chromosomes <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. As a result, non-haploid hybrids are highly heterozygous, as homeologous chromosome loci can present different alleles inherited from each of the parents. The level of heterozygosity will depend on the initial divergence of the parental lineages, and will subsequently evolve by processes that include differential loss of chromosomes and recombination between homeologous genomic regions <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Some of these processes lead to loss of heterozygosity (LOH) resulting in particular genomic patterns in which homozygous and heterozygous segments (called blocks) alternate along a chromosome <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. Although hybrids represent the most extreme case of heterozygous genomes, non-hybrid genomes may also reach high heterozygosity levels when the parental individuals are highly divergent, or evolutionary times are large. Differences in LOH patterns are often the main source of variability among heterozygous populations, and they can be the main drivers of phenotypic differences <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Hence, there is a growing interest in accurately inferring LOH patterns in population genomics studies. In recent years, many studies have focused on studying LOH in relation to the biology and evolution of hybrids <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, but also in non-hybrid contexts such as cancer <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, and niche adaptation <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. One area of current research is the evolution of hybrid lineages such as those of the yeast genus <italic>Saccharomyces</italic>
<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. The <italic>Saccharomyces</italic> genus harbours eight <italic>sensu stricto</italic> species which can all hybridise between each other, resulting in hybrids with different levels of parental genetic divergence. Moreover, certain strains of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> yeasts are so genetically divergent that their offspring is considered <italic>de facto</italic> hybrid <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. <italic>Saccharomyces</italic> hybrids have been documented, which carry a subgenomic sequence divergence of 25% or more <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, underscoring the ability of these species to hybridise across large evolutionary distances. In the past decade, many studies have focused on inferring LOH patterns from genomes of yeast hybrids, resulting in novel insights on hybrid genome evolution that facilitate comparative analyses <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. Detecting LOH patterns is, therefore, crucial for the study of population structures as well as to understand which genotypes are specific to a population. The study of the emerging LOH patterns may reveal <italic>loci</italic> and genome features in general that are relevant for specific phenotypes (e.g. cold tolerance in certain yeasts). This knowledge is highly transferable in many biotechnology sectors where organisms are used as production platforms and their genotypes / phenotypes optimised for a specific scope (i.e. yeast hybrids in beer, cider or wine production). Scientists working with hybrid crops (e.g. wheat, tobacco) regularly study LOH blocks emerging in domesticated plants. This knowledge is also transferable to clinical studies, as it has been shown that certain pathogens rapidly adapt to hospital settings through LOH <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Besides that, LOH patterns may also be used to ensure the genomic coherence of a specific group of individuals, which may be important for a specific analysis or industrial scope.</p>
    <p id="p0035">Most approaches to infer LOH patterns at the genome-wide level are based on mapping short read sequencing data to a genome reference <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. One of the earliest pipelines is YMAP <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. This pipeline was designed to analyse variation data from the human pathogen <italic>Candida albicans</italic>, taking as input microarray, high-throughput sequencing or RAD-Seq data. Among other things, YMAP would return an LOH profile extracted from the SNP profiles deriving from read mapping. Generally, LOH information is extracted from the combination of SNP data and read coverage data. However, these data are most often analysed semi-manually, using ad-hoc pipelines and parameters which are hardly reproducible in other environments. An example of this is a recently published pipeline named MuloYDH <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. MuloYDH is designed to analyse the variation landscape in hybrid yeast genomes, inferring also LOH blocks from variation data. The pipeline includes many custom scripts wrapped into a bash script with a handful of tunable arguments, which hinders the customization of the analysis. A few programs exist to infer LOH tracts in specific setups such as cancer data <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, which poses different challenges due to its low heterozygosity levels. A general tool requiring only common input data types, not designed for a specific use-case, and able to work with hybrid genomes was missing. Considering that the study of LOH is gaining momentum, we undertook a more general approach, reducing the input requirements to the bare minimum and implementing a scalable computational solution that returns reproducible results in a highly-parallelized fashion with easy parameter customization. We imagined the typical use-case of a general LOH inference software and implemented a toolkit named “JLOH”, which performs a series of steps to infer and analyse LOH blocks starting from mapped reads, single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) and a reference genome sequence. These three input data types are highly common in genomic analyses, therefore allowing those who are already performing variation studies to add one extra layer of information to their workflow (i.e. LOH blocks) without generating new files or having to deal with cumbersome pipeline setup processes. JLOH uses SNP density to define heterozygous and homozygous regions of the provided reference genome sequence, and from those regions infers candidate LOH blocks using read coverage information as a means of validation. JLOH has been designed to work with both hybrid and non-hybrid input data provided that sufficient heterozygosity levels are present (1% or more). This may allow researchers to disentangle complex LOH blocks in hybrid subgenomes as well as to simply detect common LOH patterns within a non-hybrid population. We first test JLOH’s ability to infer LOH blocks from simulated read data that is progressively more divergent from the reference genome onto which they are mapped. We then test its performance on public sequencing data from <italic>Saccharomyces</italic> hybrids <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref> and from the pathogenic hybrid species <italic>Candida orthopsilosis</italic>. Our results show that JLOH is reliable in inferring LOH blocks in all these settings with great accuracy.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec0010">
    <label>2</label>
    <title>Materials &amp; methods</title>
    <sec id="sec0015">
      <label>2.1</label>
      <title>Code implementation for LOH block inference</title>
      <p id="p0040">The main module of JLOH is “jloh extract”, which infers LOH blocks from three input files: a reference genome sequence, a BAM file with reads mapped onto this genome, and a VCF file containing single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) that were called from these mapped reads (<xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). SNPs are separated in homozygous and heterozygous based on their genotype annotation (0/0, 0/1, 1/1, 1/2) and their allele frequencies (“AF” annotation in VCF format). Both SNP groups are clustered by reciprocal distance as long as they form a cluster with a SNP density (SNPs/kbp) greater or equal to the one passed via the --min-snps-kbp parameter. By passing two comma-separated integer values, it allows the user to set a different SNP/kbp threshold for heterozygous and homozygous SNPs (e.g. --min-snps-kbp 15,3), which is key to eliminate many false positives in the final results (see benchmark results below). Heterozygous intervals are discarded. The complementary ones, which have a heterozygous SNP density below the threshold, are the raw candidate LOH blocks. First, they are screened for the presence of homozygous SNPs. Those with a density of homozygous SNPs above --min-snps-kbp are assumed to be candidate blocks that retained a haplotype different from the one of the reference genome. The ones with a density below, instead, are assumed to carry the same haplotype of the reference genome. Any overlap with heterozygous intervals is trimmed down from the candidate blocks, and candidate blocks shorter than --coarseness are discarded. Surviving candidates are inspected in terms of their read coverage. Those candidates with less covered positions than --min-frac-cov are discarded. The coverage is then compared with --overhang positions upstream and downstream of the block. Blocks with coverage lower than --hemi * surrounding coverage are considered hemizygous. Any other block is considered homozygous. The final LOH blocks are reported both in a BED file and in a more human-readable tab-separated format (TSV) file, the latter containing all the information about each block.<fig id="fig0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Schematic representing the rationale of “jloh extract”. <bold>A</bold>) SNPs are parsed by the program from the provided VCF file(s), subdividing them into heterozygous (gray) and homozygous (cyan). <bold>B</bold>) Regions rich in heterozygous SNPs are identified (light gray) based on SNP density criteria. Dotted red lines represent intervals containing heterozygous SNPs that do not fit the SNP density thresholds either due to the number of SNPs (c) or to the distance between them (w). <bold>C</bold>) Candidate LOH blocks, i.e. regions depleted in heterozygous SNPs are extracted (cyan), which are complementary to the identified heterozygous regions. <bold>D</bold>) Coverage per position is assessed for each candidate LOH block (cyan) and zygosity is inferred from it (horizontal light gray bars). <bold>E</bold>) When using data from hybrids, homozygous SNPs are used to subdivide candidate LOH blocks into reference (REF, orange) and alternative (ALT, cyan) allele based on the same mechanism explained in (B) for heterozygous SNPs. <bold>F</bold>) If specified by the user, candidate LOH blocks overlapping known LOH blocks are filtered out, leaving only the newly found ones.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0005">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1" id="lk0005"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec0020">
      <label>2.2</label>
      <title>Application to hybrid genomes with known parentals</title>
      <p id="p0045">The “extract” module can assign an LOH block to a particular subgenome when working with a hybrid species that has known parentals. This is activated using the --assign-blocks parameter. This mode runs the same algorithm twice, once per parental genome. Note that the large majority of hybrids come from unknown parents: in that case, this assignment is not possible and this mode cannot be used. The --assign-blocks mode requires two BAMs, two VCFs, and two reference genomes, one per parental species of the hybrid. The BAMs and the VCFs must be derived from mapping the reads sequenced from the hybrid onto the two parental genomes separately, with parameters that allow crossmapping between subgenomes. Through this crossmapping, differences between subgenomes will be the ground heterozygous SNPs for the algorithm and will be handled accordingly by the “extract” module. The inferred LOH blocks will represent genomic regions where the hybrid has lost inter-subgenomic diversity, losing one of the subgenomic alleles but retaining the other.</p>
      <p id="p0050">The two parental genomes may have regions of high similarity. These regions are likely to produce a very small number of SNPs, hence looking like LOH blocks. However, since they are already very similar at the parental level, these regions must not be considered. To take this into account, JLOH has a module named “g2g” (“genome to genome”). “jloh g2g” uses nucmer <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref> to align the two parental genomes onto each other, and highlight regions that contain differences. The produced BED file can be passed directly to “jloh extract” as argument for the --regions parameter.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec0025">
      <label>2.3</label>
      <title>Analysing SNP density distribution</title>
      <p id="p0055">JLOH is a toolkit composed of multiple modules (<xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). Besides “jloh extract”, the second most important “jloh stats”. In a non-simulated scenario, the density and distribution of hetero- and homozygous variants across the genome can be highly variable. Moreover, heterozygous and homozyous SNPs may be found at the same region making the detection of zygosity hard on the algorithm. A region should be considered heterozygous only if its level of heterozygosity is comparable to the genomic average, and the same goes for homozygosity. Hence, simply detecting clusters of heterozygous or homozygous SNPs proved to be a too-naïve approach. For this reason we introduced the --min-snps-kbp parameter. This parameter has a default setting (--min-snps-kbp 5,1) that works reasonably well with genomes that carry 1–5% divergence. However, since each genome has its own evolutionary history, the heterozygous and homozygous SNP densities may not be trivial. To account for this the user can run the “jloh stats” module, which computes the mean density of homo- and heterozygous variants across the genome in windows of adjustable size. It detects and reports to the user the SNP density distribution quantiles which can be used to set the --min-snps-kbp parameter in an informed way. The assumptions here are two: 1) LOH blocks will be found at low heterozygous SNP densities; 2) their homozygous SNP density defines their proximity to the reference genome. The module produces a table with quantiles and the user may choose among them based on how relaxed the block selection must be; lower quantiles are more permissive.<fig id="fig0010"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Schematic displaying the different modules available within the JLOH toolkit, with brief explanation.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0010">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2" id="lk0010"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec0030">
      <label>2.4</label>
      <title>Simulated data generation</title>
      <p id="p0060">To test the validity of the “jloh extract” algorithm, a series of hybrid genomes with known LOH blocks were simulated starting from the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> S288C genome <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. The R64–1–1 assembly of the S288C strain of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> was used for the generation of simulated data. In total, 24 diverging versions of the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> genome were simulated, each with a different genetic divergence (1%, 3%, 5%,10%, 15%, 20%) and rate of loss of heterozygosity (10%, 20%, 30%, 40%). These operations were carried on with a custom python script included in the JLOH suite as “jloh sim”. The genome sequence was broken into arbitrary haplotypes of --mean-haplotype-size average size. The size of each haplotype was taken from a normal distribution centered around this average value. The choice of a normal distribution was done merely to have some fluctuations in the output haplotype sizes that would better simulate a real-world scenario, and does not reflect the biological size of haplotypes. Then, each haplotype was assigned a certain sequence divergence, with average defined by the --divergence parameter. As for the haplotype size, also the haplotype divergence was taken from a normal distribution centered around the declared average sequence divergence. This ensured the presence of some outliers (e.g. a hyper-variable region) that helped mimicking a real-life scenario. We highlight that, to simulate the divergence, we simply introduced random mutations in each of the simulated haplotypes until reaching the desired level of divergence. A haplotype with 5% assigned divergence and 10 Kbp size, for example, would have seen the introduction of 500 SNPs in random positions. Admittedly, this is not a procedure that follows any biological model, as no thorough knowledge of heterozygous SNP distributions are available, but we consider it a good proxy to understand how JLOH performance is affected by level of heterozygosity. Some of the haplotypes were left with no sequence divergence, representing true positive LOH blocks. Note that this process generated only heterozygous SNPs.</p>
      <p id="p0065">This module was run 24 times, each with a different combination of sequence divergence and LOH rate as mentioned above. Then, each of these 24 diverging genome versions was concatenated with the original <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> S288C genome sequence and reads were simulated from the concatenated version. These simulated reads represented hybrid reads, which is a complex scenario for “jloh extract” to tackle. A number of reads was estimated in order to reach approximately 10X and 30X coverage of a <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> hybrid genome, respectively; the calculation resulted in 1 and 3 million reads respectively, with a genome size of 24 Mbp and read length 2 × 125 nt. These values were used to simulate reads in wgsim (<underline>https://github.com/lh3/wgsim</underline>) as the “-N” parameter, with the following other parameters: -d 1000 -s 200 − 1 125 − 2 125. Combining the divergence rate, the LOH rate, and the simulated coverage, the simulated dataset was composed of 48 simulated samples.</p>
      <p id="p0070">Long PacBio RS-II reads were simulated with pgsim v3.0.0 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref> using mostly default parameters except --strategy wgs --method errhmm --errhmm data/ERRHMM-RSII.model --depth 30.0. This set of parameters returned simulated PacBio reads at 30X coverage. Reads were simulated only from the simulated genomes carrying 15% and 20% divergence with the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> genome sequence (see above).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec0035">
      <label>2.5</label>
      <title>Testing read mapping impact</title>
      <p id="p0075">The SNPs that “jloh extract” uses to infer LOH blocks are derived from short read mapping. When assessing the degree of LOH, the sequence divergence between reads and reference genome is a key factor. Hence, the limits of read mapping were tested in relationship to the sequence divergence. A genome with 20% sequence divergence from the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> genome sequence was simulated using “jloh sim”. It then was concatenated to the original <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> genome and 125 nt paired-end reads were simulated from this concatenation to imitate a highly heterozygous genome using the same simulation parameters described above. Reads were then mapped onto the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> genome alone, using two common mapping software with distinct algorithms: bowtie2 and BLAT <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. Reads were mapped with both tools with progressively less stringent minimum sequence identity between reads and reference (from 100% to 70% in steps of 5%). In the case of bowtie2 this is controlled by the --score-min and --mp parameters, which were set to --score-min L,0.0,-x and --mp 6,2, where x is a fraction of the read length. To achieve the required sequence identity thresholds, the “x” in --score-min was set to 0.0, 0.3, 0.6, 0.9, 1.2, 1.5, and 1.8. In the case of BLAT, the -minIdentity parameter allowed a more direct control over the minimum sequence identity. The amount of reads that were mapped in each run by each program was then quantified and used as measurement for read mapping reliability under the assumption that the perfect scenario is where all reads get to be mapped and heterozygous SNPs emerge from divergent regions.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec0040">
      <label>2.6</label>
      <title>Read mapping and variant calling</title>
      <p id="p0080">Simulated short reads were mapped against the reference genomes of their parental species independently. The mapping was conducted with HISAT2 v2.1.0 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref> using very relaxed parameters (--score-min L,0.0,−1.0 --mp 6,2 --rfg 5,3 --rdg 5,3 -I 0 -X 1000). Simulated long reads were mapped with Minimap2 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref> with parameters -H -x map-pb -a. The following steps of the workflow were applied to both short and long reads. The mapping records were filtered and sorted by genome coordinate using samtools v1.15 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, removing secondary alignments and unmapped reads (-F 0 ×0100 -F 0 ×4). Filtered mapping records were used to call short variants using bcftools v1.15 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. First, reads were piled up using bcftools pileup (--annotate FORMAT/AD,FORMAT/ADF,FORMAT/ADR,FORMAT/DP,FORMAT/SP,INFO/AD,INFO/ADF,INFO/ADR --output-type v --skip-indels). Then, pileups were used to perform SNP calling using bcftools call (--multiallelic-caller –variants-only); indels were not considered. Raw SNPs were filtered removing those with QUAL ≥ 20, AF ≥ 0.05, DP ≥ 4, and MQ0F ≤ 0.05. This filtering was conducted with all2vcf (<underline>https://github.com/MatteoSchiavinato/all2vcf</underline>). The final lists of SNPs from either parent of a hybrid were passed to JLOH to detect LOH blocks.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec0045">
      <label>2.7</label>
      <title>LOH block inference sensitivity and specificity</title>
      <p id="p0085">To test the sensitivity and specificity of “jloh extract”, a series of runs were performed with each of the 48 simulated data sets described above. Some parameters were kept fixed in all runs: SNPs were considered heterozygous if their alternative allele frequency (AF) was within 0.3 an 0.7 (--min-af 0.3 --max-af 0.7); candidate blocks were required to be at least 50% covered by reads (--min-frac-cov 0.5); blocks were considered hemizygous if their average coverage per position was lower or equal to 75% of their 5000 bp flanking regions (--hemi 0.75 --overhang 5000). The variable parameters were instead the minimum block length (--min-length) and the SNP density thresholds (--min-snps-kbp). The --min-length parameter was set at 500, 1000, 2000, 5000 or 10000 bp. The SNP density thresholds were set to the 5th, 10th, 15th and 50th quantile as detected via “jloh stats” (see above) A total of 960 runs represented all possible combinations between simulated samples and parameters. From each run, the true positives (TP), true negatives (TN), false positives (FP) and false negatives (FN) were assessed. We defined them as follows. TP: genome positions that are part of an LOH block introduced upon simulation, and are also within a block found by “jloh extract”. FP: genome positions that are not part of a simulated LOH block, but are within a block found by “jloh extract”. TN: genome positions that are not part of a simulated LOH block, and are also not within a block found by “jloh extract”. FN: genome positions that are part of an LOH block introduced upon simulation, but are not within a block found by ”jloh extract”. Consequently, the sensitivity or true positive rate (TP rate) is obtained via TP / (TP + FN) and the specificity or true negative rate (TN rate) is obtained via TN / (TN + FP). These values oscillate between 0 and 1. Runs with both metrics above 0.75 were considered “good”, while runs with both metrics above 0.90 were considered “excellent”. All these calculations were done with the custom python script “tp_tn_rates.py” available within the JLOH github repository (<underline>https://github.com/Gabaldonlab/jloh</underline>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec0050">
      <label>2.8</label>
      <title>Reanalysis of public data</title>
      <p id="p0090">To further test the potential of the “jloh extract” module, data from public sequencing libraries compiled in a previous study <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref> was downloaded. Among these samples, only five had their LOH blocks called <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. These five samples are available in SRA under the SRA codes ERR1111502, ERR1111503, ERR3010130, SRR2967902, and SRR2967903. All these samples represent hybrids between <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> and <italic>S. paradoxus</italic>. To better identify the strains in the results their strain name was used. Respectively: UFMGCMY651, UFMGCMY652, CBS7002, AWRI1501 and AWRI1502. Reads from these five samples were preprocessed using Trimmomatic (v0.39, Bolger et al., 2014). Trimming was conducted using the following parameters on all the read files: LEADING:20 TRAILING:20 SLIDINGWINDOW:4:25 AVGQUAL:20 MINLEN:35. Accession codes and related genomic assignments can be found in Supplementary File S1. Reference genomes and versions used here were the same used by Bendixsen et al. (2021).</p>
      <p id="p0095">To map reads and extract SNPs the same workflow described above for simulated data was used. The same <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> reference genome sequence described above was used in conjunction with the ASM207905v1 assembly of the CBS432 strain of <italic>S. paradoxus</italic>
<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. The generated VCFs and BAMs were passed to “jloh extract” to infer LOH blocks with the same fixed parameters described for the simulated data. In addition, we set the following two parameters: --min-length 1000 --min-snps-kbp 15,3.</p>
      <p id="p0100">The mapped reads in BAM format were used to extract read coverage per position over all chromosomes of the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> and the <italic>S. paradoxus</italic> parental genomes. The coverage information was then binned in windows of 10,000 bp, calculating the mean coverage per position of each window. The difference in coverage between the two groups of windows was assessed using a Mann-Whitney test (signif. p &lt; 0.05, two-sided). The LOH blocks inferred with “jloh extract” on these two parental genomes with the same reads and the derived SNPs were then crossed with these 10 kbp windows. We attempted to assign each window to either <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> or <italic>S. paradoxus</italic> depending on the amount of basepairs in its span that overlapped LOH blocks from either one of the two parents. The assignment of windows along each chromosome was then plotted using a custom R script. Genes that could be involved in the LOH anomaly were extracted using <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> transcript sequences as template. These sequences were mapped against the <italic>S. paradoxus</italic> genome sequence using gmap (-f gff3_gene) <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. Transcripts mapping in positions 1–370,000 of the <italic>S. paradoxus</italic> chromosome 12 were extracted, and their corresponding protein sequences were submitted to the Pannzer2 webserver for GO annotation <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. The list of gene symbols and relative GO terms was analysed in R using clusterProfiler <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. A list of EntrezIDs was obtained from the gene symbols, and the enrichment of their corresponding GO terms was assessed with the enrichGO() function (ont = "ALL", pvalueCutoff = 0.05, pAdjustMethod = "BH", qvalueCutoff = 0.2, minGSSize = 5, maxGSSize = 500).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec0055">
      <label>2.9</label>
      <title>LOH block inference in <italic>C. orthopsilosis</italic> clades</title>
      <p id="p0105">To show the potential of “jloh extract” in detecting differences in LOH blocks from different clades of the same hybrid species, a set of sequencing data from the hybrid fungal pathogen <italic>C. orthopsilosis</italic> was used. The strains represented in the data belonged to four separate clades of <italic>C. orthopsilosis</italic>. Specifically, the usefulness of “jloh stats” and SNP density quantiles in distinguishing groups of samples by inferred LOH was assessed. Sequencing libraries used were retrieved from BioProjects PRJEB4430 and PRJNA322245 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. The ASM31587v1 version <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref> of the <italic>C. orthopsilosis</italic> reference genome sequence was used for the read mapping and LOH block inference. Reads were trimmed using Trimmomatic v0.39 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. Mapping and variant calling was performed using PerSVade v.1.02.4 using 5000 as minimum chromosome length and a value of 20 as minimum coverage. Variants passing quality filters by at least two out of the tree software that PerSVade uses were included in the analysis.</p>
      <p id="p0110">The “jloh stats” module was run using genomic variants extracted from strains belonging to each of the four clades of <italic>C. orthopsilosis</italic> hybrids. The SNPs/kbp quantiles were collected for all strains, and an average quantile value per clade was calculated for quantiles Q5, Q10, Q15, Q50, Q85, Q90 and Q95 (Supplementary File S2). The “jloh extract” module was then run to call LOH blocks for all samples using the listed quantiles to set the --min-snps-kbp parameter. Candidate blocks were required to be 90% covered by reads (--min-frac-cov 0.9) and only SNPs annotated as “PASS” were kept (--filter-mode pass). Bedtools v2.30.0 multiinter <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref> was then used to find overlapping LOH blocks between all strains and between strains belonging to the same clade. Files harbouring LOH blocks were loaded and visually examined with IGV v2.8.13 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec0060">
      <label>2.10</label>
      <title>LOH block inference in <italic>C. metapsilosis</italic></title>
      <p id="p0115">Sequencing libraries for samples BP57 (SZMC8022) and PL448 were retrieved from BioProject PRJNA238968 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. The chimeric assembly of hybrid BP57 was used as reference genome (Mixão et al., <italic>under revision</italic>). Read filtering, mapping and variant calling was performed as described in the section above. The “jloh stats” module was run prior to LOH block inference in order to obtain the optimal SNP density parameters for each of the two strains. The “jloh extract” module was then run using Q50 quantile values in the --min-snps-kbp parameter. Candidate blocks were required to be 90% covered by reads (--min-frac-cov 0.9) and only SNPs annotated as “PASS” were kept (--filter-mode pass). The “jloh plot” module was used to visualise the resulting LOH blocks.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec0065">
      <label>2.11</label>
      <title>LOH block inference in more complex genomes</title>
      <p id="p0120">Divergent copies of the human chromosome X were obtained with “jloh sim” (--divergence 0.01 --max-divergence 0.1 --loh 0.1) using the hg38 genome version as template. First, a divergent copy was obtained and its generated haplotypes saved with the --out-haplotyes parameter. Then, a second copy was obtained using the same parameters and passing the haplotypes of the first (--use-existing-hap), so that the artificially generated LOH blocks would coincide. The two simulated copies of the chromosome X were concatenated via command line. Reads were simulated from the concatenated reference using wgsim (<underline>https://github.com/lh3/wgsim</underline>, -N 6000000 −1 125 −2 125). Simulating 6 million read pairs (-N 6000000) ensured an average coverage of ∼10x over the X chromosome, compatible with common variant calling setups. Reads were mapped and SNPs were called using the same workflow described in the methods section “2.6”. LOH blocks were inferred with “jloh extract” limiting the output blocks to a minimum size of 5 kbp (--min-length 5000).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec0070">
      <label>2.12</label>
      <title>Comparison with existing tools</title>
      <p id="p0125">The ability of “jloh extract” to retrieve LOH blocks was compared to that of the online available software YMAP <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. To that end, an account was created on the YMAP webserver (<underline>http://lovelace.cs.umn.edu/Ymap/</underline>). To test the software, datasets corresponding to pair-end Illumina sequencing files of four <italic>C. orthopsilosis</italic> hybrid strains were uploaded using <italic>C. orthopsilosis</italic> Co90–125 (CGD) as reference genome, baseline ploidy and ploidy of experiment set to 2.0 and chromosome-end bias correction. The representative chosen strains for this comparison were s1799 (clade 1), B8323 (clade 2), s151 (clade 3) and s282 (clade 4) <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. Resulting LOH patterns and distribution were visualised using the “SNP/LOH only” option in linear plots. LOH plots were downloaded using the EPS format option. The same datasets were then used to run the “jloh extract” using the Q50 parameters obtained in the “stats” module and plots were generated with the “plot” module using a 10 kb window size.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec0075">
      <label>2.13</label>
      <title>Code specifics</title>
      <p id="p0130">The core algorithm of JLOH is coded in python (v3.9.7) using the pybedtools v0.8.2 module for most interval-related operations <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref> and self-written python functions for deeper analyses. The analysis carried on in this study has been performed with a pipeline written in nextflow v21.04.3 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref> which went from read mapping to LOH block extraction. The pipeline containing the data simulation and fidelity testing steps, together with its configuration file and a shell script to run it, is provided in the “workflows” directory of JLOH’s github repository (<underline>https://github.com/Gabaldonlab/jloh</underline>). The pipeline has been run on a single node of a computing cluster. The node had 48 processors (2.1 GHz each) and 94 GB RAM.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec0080">
    <label>3</label>
    <title>Results</title>
    <sec id="sec0085">
      <label>3.1</label>
      <title>Read mapping limits resolution at high sequence divergence</title>
      <p id="p0135">The tool presented in this work strongly relies on read mapping. This operation is most often conducted with known tools such as bowtie2, hisat2, bwa or BLAT <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, among others. The first three are common fast aligners that use similar seed-and-extend strategies to map reads. In order to be precise and reliable, seeds must not be shorter than 18–20 bp. The latter, instead, is a command-line tool equipped with the same algorithm of BLAST and which searches for matches of any small tag (8–12 bp) from the query sequences (the reads) into the provided reference genome, extending each match and providing a score. These programs may fail to properly map all reads in the dataset when no exact seed is found. For example, if the reads are on average 20% divergent from the reference genome sequence, there will be an average of 20 SNPs per 100 bp, which in a seed of 20 bp turns into 4 mismatches expected in the seed. Most alignment tools require exact seed matches or tolerate at most 1 mismatch in the seed, limiting the alignment in regions with extreme SNP density. To demonstrate this limit we used the genome of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> to simulate a diploid set of reads with an internal 20% divergence between its two sets of chromosomes (see methods). We conducted the simulation with “jloh sim”, which creates a simulated copy of a genome sequence carrying a random assortment of haplotypes each with its own divergence against the reference (see methods). Hence, while the average divergence of the simulated dataset was 20%, it also contained haplotypes with lower or greater divergences. We then mapped this read set back onto the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> genome using bowtie2 and BLAT. These two algorithms were chosen due to their radically different mapping algorithms. Bowtie2, hisat2 and bwa, instead, share most of their mapping strategy (especially hisat2 and bowtie2). With both tools we performed several runs at progressively more relaxed criteria in terms of minimum accepted sequence identity between reads and reference (from 100% to 70% in steps of 5%); results are shown in <xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0005"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Mapping rates obtained with either Bowtie2 or BLAT at different thresholds of minimum sequence identity.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0035">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th><bold>min. identity</bold></th><th><bold>Bowtie2</bold></th><th><bold>BLAT</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="char">100</td><td>51.06%</td><td>51.60%</td></tr><tr><td align="char">95</td><td>65.59%</td><td>65.81%</td></tr><tr><td align="char">90</td><td>65.95%</td><td>66.92%</td></tr><tr><td align="char">85</td><td>66.53%</td><td>68.86%</td></tr><tr><td align="char">80</td><td>66.76%</td><td>69.51%</td></tr><tr><td align="char">75</td><td>66.84%</td><td>69.59%</td></tr><tr><td align="char">70</td><td>66.87%</td><td>69.60%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
      <p id="p0140">As expected, relaxing the parameters down to 70% minimum identity between reads and reference increased the mapping rate. However, both software still failed to map more than 30% of the reads even with the most permissive parameters. A quick look at the coverage per position showed that the haplotypes with the least coverage were also having the highest divergence between <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> and the simulated copy used to generate the reads. Hence, we concluded that read mappers fail to identify good alignment seeds to extend reads in these regions, therefore leaving them uncovered. A possible solution to this problem is the use of long reads, the mapping of which relies on a cluster of seeds and can accommodate more mismatches (discussed later). Furthermore, reference genomes generated from a genotype that is as close as possible to the analysed reads will aid in reducing the number of mismatches at the mapping stage. This approach, however, is possible only when the species in question is well-studied, and is particularly hard with hybrids. The latter, in fact, often have unknown parents and must be analysed with the genome of a close relative. Nevertheless, users may have to take this into account when planning an analysis with the tool we present, as higher sequence divergences may introduce false positives in the results.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec0090">
      <label>3.2</label>
      <title>Sensitivity and specificity</title>
      <p id="p0145">We benchmarked the accuracy of “jloh extract” in detecting LOH blocks from Illumina sequencing data. We set up a test that included the simulation of data containing known LOH blocks and the retrieval of LOH blocks with “jloh extract” combined with “jloh stats” to study the SNPs/kbp distribution. Simulated data were used despite the big amount of real NGS data available, in order to have objective true positives and true negatives. We first used “jloh sim” to simulate a series of yeast hybrid genomes carrying different levels of allelic divergence between homeologous chromosomes (1%, 3%, 5%, 10%, 15%, 20%) and different amounts of LOH (10%, 20%, 30%, 40% of the genome). The LOH blocks introduced in the simulation defined the true positives of the test, as their location was known. Then, from each of these simulated hybrid genomes we simulated short sequencing reads, mapped them against the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> genome sequence, and called SNPs. We passed the called SNPs to “jloh stats” to detect the chosen SNP distribution quantiles (Q5, Q10, Q15, Q50), and we then ran “jloh extract” multiple times (one per relevant quantile) to retrieve LOH blocks. The inferred LOH blocks were then compared with the known simulated blocks. We note that the fact that “sim” and “extract” are both part of the same toolkit is merely for practical reasons but they are independent programs that do not have any intercommunication and therefore cannot influence each other’s results. To assess the impact of different parameter choices, we repeated this benchmark over different parameter settings. The tested parameters were: 1) the minimum length to retain a candidate LOH block (500, 1000, 2000, 5000 and 10000 bp); 2) the simulated sequencing depth (10X or 30X); 3) the SNP density quantile to use as threshold to isolate candidate LOH blocks (Q5, Q10, Q15, Q50). We note that the last parameter is a quantile applied to both the heterozygous and the homozygous SNP densities. It is generated by “jloh stats”, and is passed to the --min-snps-kbp parameter of “jloh extract”. All possible combinations of these parameters, the LOH rates, and the divergence rates resulted in 960 runs.</p>
      <p id="p0150">We calculated the true positive rate (TP rate, or sensitivity) and the true negative rate (TN rate, or specificity) from each of the runs (<xref rid="sec0140" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Fig. S1</xref>, Supplementary File S3). The sensitivity reflects the ability of JLOH to identify bona fide LOH blocks (true positives), while the specificity reflects its ability to avoid reporting false positives in the results. All 960 runs had sensitivity ≥ 0.90, of which a notable 93.3% reached a sensitivity of 0.99, attesting to the ability of “jloh extract” to find the LOH blocks that were introduced from the simulation script. When looking at specificity, which is higher in absence of false positives, 68.3% of the run had it ≥ 0.90. This means that, combining sensitivity and specificity, 68.3% of the runs had both statistics ≥ 0.90 (<xref rid="sec0140" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Fig. S1</xref>).</p>
      <p id="p0155">To investigate further why certain runs had low specificity we categorized JLOH’s performance in each run by considering as “good” the runs that had both sensitivity and specificity ≥ 0.75, and as “excellent” those that had both ≥ 0.90 (Supplementary File S4). A quick look at the run specifics showed us that the runs with the most false positives (i.e. those affecting specificity) were those where the simulated divergence was higher (15% or 20%), while other parameters did not particularly influence the quality of the results (<xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, <xref rid="sec0140" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Fig. S2, S3, S4, S5</xref>). At 1% divergence 90% of the runs were excellent and 100% were good. At 3% and 5% divergence all runs were excellent. At 10% divergence, 92.5% of the runs were excellent, meaning that “jloh extract” is very capable of inferring LOH blocks in the 1–10% divergence range, and the results carry little false positives. At 15% divergence, however, only 27.5% of the runs were excellent. Of these 44 excellent runs, 36 were performed with very long minimum block size (5000–10000 bp), and 28 with higher (30X) simulated sequencing depth. Also, the algorithm’s precision lowered linearly with the increasing of the simulated LOH rate in the divergent genome, with 24 out of 44 runs being from 10% LOH rate, 12 from 20%, 8 from 30%, and none from 40%. This suggests that increasing divergences lead to patches of the genome left uncovered due to the read mapping issues described in the previous section, which emerge especially with short reads. Nearly all the introduced LOH blocks are recovered even at high divergence, but many false positives were introduced which lower the specificity score. The minimum length criterion of selection partially quenches this effect by weeding out short uncovered patches, but the results become less reliable. These effects were amplified when looking at runs performed with reads derived from genomes that were 20% divergent. None of the runs were excellent, and only 10% were good. Of these good runs, almost all of them were obtained from 30X simulated depth reads, 10000 bp minimum block length, and low LOH rates (10% or 20%). All in all, we concluded that there is a technical limit to reliable LOH block inference based on short read mapping, and this limit is placed around 15% sequence divergence, above which a fraction of reads will fail to find a seed to extend due to excessive divergence.<fig id="fig0015"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Sensitivity (TP) vs specificity (TN) rates in all the runs performed with simulated data, subdivided in facets corresponding to the simulated sequence divergence between subgenomes of the simulated hybrid data. Divergence rates are indicated from 0.01 (1%) to 0.20 (20%). The orange box in each facet represents “good” runs (TP and TN ≥ 0.75) while the red box represents “excellent” runs (TP and TN ≥ 0.9).</p></caption><alt-text id="at0015">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3" id="lk0015"/></fig></p>
      <p id="p0160">To prove that read length is responsible for this effect we simulated PacBio RSII long reads from the 15% and 20% divergent simulated genomes described above combined with the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> genome sequence. We note that PacBio RSII long reads do not suffer from the inaccuracy that previous PacBio reads suffered, reaching 99% accuracy upon error correction <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. This combination mimics the context of a 15% or 20% divergent hybrid, as described above for the short reads experiment. These two genomes carry LOH blocks introduced by the “jloh sim” module of our program, hence allowing us to estimate true positive and true negative rates. We mapped these simulated hybrid reads against the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> genome sequence, called SNPs and used them to infer LOH blocks with “jloh extract”. Indeed, the true positive rate and true negative rate increased substantially. The 15% divergent run returned a TP rate of 1 and a TN rate of 0.93. The 20% run, instead, returned a TP rate of 1 and a TN rate of 0.91. In both cases, the results obtained were substantially better than the ones obtained with short reads. Hence, we concluded that using long reads solves the mapping issues that hamper LOH inference in hybrids from highly divergent parents.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec0095">
      <label>3.3</label>
      <title>Comparison with existing tools</title>
      <p id="p0165">We then attempted to compare JLOH’s efficacy in retrieving LOH blocks against existing software, namely MuloYDH <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref> and YMAP <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. We used public <italic>C. orthopsilosis</italic> sequencing data for this comparison. One of the major disadvantages of using YMAP was the fact that only 15 G of memory is available for each user. Once uploaded, each of our datasets used 100–450 M of memory, limiting the amount of samples that can be analysed at the same time to 30–40 samples, which might be insufficient for some studies. Additionally, when having a large number of datasets, uploading the files individually and one by one without a batch-upload option is highly inconvenient and time consuming for the user. Concerning data upload, we found recurrent errors and stalled uploads when the fastq files exceeded 500 Mb of size. Once the uploads were complete, there was no available downloading option to export the LOH tracks as a high resolution PNG or PDF file from the website. The only working option was to download an EPS file which is an unsupported file format for most image visualisation softwares that requires specialised programs such as Adobe Illustrator.</p>
      <p id="p0170">In terms of LOH detection, we used YMAP and JLOH to infer LOH blocks in four <italic>C. orthopsilosis</italic> strains (one representative strain from each of the four clades) and compared the results. We observed that, for the most part, the inference of LOH was consistent using both methods (<xref rid="sec0140" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Fig. S6</xref>). However, JLOH provides the user with a greater range of options that allow tailoring the analysis depending on the parental genome divergence and SNP density which YMAP does not yet offer. Additionally, given that using JLOH the user can choose the window size for plotting LOH blocks (which YMAP does not allow), the level of resolution is increased and under the user’s control.</p>
      <p id="p0175">MuloYDH failed to complete the run due to multiple errors or returned empty output files. Hence, a comparison with existing software was unfortunately not possible, which underscores the need for a general purpose solution. All in all, based on our benchmark, we concluded that nearly 70% of the parameter and testing space resulted in very reliable LOH block detection, and that sequence divergence between reads and reference is the most influential factor in affecting the fidelity of results.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec0100">
      <label>3.4</label>
      <title>Scalability</title>
      <p id="p0180">We assessed the scalability of JLOH in terms of CPU usage, and the impact of the dataset size on the computational time. The latter refers to the ability of JLOH to tackle progressively larger sets of SNPs without losing efficiency. To perform this test, we generated a simulated, divergent copy of the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> genome using the “sim” module of JLOH. The copy had 10% sequence divergence and 30% of its sequence was carrying simulated LOH blocks, with a mean simulated block length of 5000 bp. Then, we simulated reads from these two genomes following the same procedure described in previous paragraphs, and called SNPs with these reads by mapping them against the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> genome and the divergent simulated copy of it. These SNPs, their source SAM file, and the reference genomes were the inputs for our scalability testing. The dataset was composed of 697,494 SNPs inferred from mapping 3 * 10<sup>6</sup> read pairs of length 2 × 125 nt over the combination of the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> genome and the simulated divergent copy (24 Mbp in total).</p>
      <p id="p0185">To test the scalability in terms of CPU usage, we ran the “extract” module with the whole dataset as input in separate jobs using from 1 to 48 cores, in steps of 4. Results are shown in <xref rid="sec0140" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Fig. S7</xref>, panel “A”.</p>
      <p id="p0190">To test the dataset size impact on computational time, we formed four subsets from the previously mentioned simulated data. These subsets represented: 1) the whole genome composed of 16 chromosomes + the mitochondrial chromosome; 2) chromosomes I-IV; 3) chromosomes I-VIII; 4) chromosomes I-XII. Then, we ran the same JLOH extract command on each subset, and logged the elapsed computational time. Results are shown in <xref rid="sec0140" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Fig. S7</xref>, panel “B”. Results show that the computational time gain derived from CPU parallelization reaches a plateau at about 10 CPUs, while the computational time increases linearly with input data size.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec0105">
      <label>3.5</label>
      <title>Estimating appropriate SNP density thresholds</title>
      <p id="p0195">As we discussed previously, the parameter regulating the minimum density of heterozygous and homozygous SNPs (--min-snps-kbp) for candidate blocks is key for a successful block inference. The “jloh stats” module aids the user in choosing the right setting for this parameter by modelling the SNP density distribution and providing quantiles that the user may use as thresholds. To test the robustness of this idea we used hybrids from <italic>C. orthopsilosis</italic>, a species of emergent fungal pathogens that belong to the <italic>C. parapsilosis</italic> species complex <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. These hybrids represent a good test case, as they carry substantial heterozygosity and the majority of isolates sequenced to date are hybrids with the exception of one homozygous (parental) lineage <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. The second parent remains unknown. All <italic>C. orthopsilosis</italic> hybrids descend from four independent hybridisation events between the same two parents which are approximately 5% divergent (<xref rid="fig0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>) <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. The four hybridisation events gave rise to four hybrid clades which are very different in terms of SNP density and patterns of LOH <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. These differences make <italic>C. orthopsilosis</italic> hybrids a good case study to test how setting different minimum SNPs/kbp thresholds may influence the efficiency of LOH block calling.<fig id="fig0020"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>(A) Tree based on variants depicting phylogenetic relationships between <italic>C. orthopsilosis</italic> hybrid strains. The four known clades are marked. (B) Average of homozygous and heterozygous SNP densities of <italic>C. orthopsilosis</italic> strains belonging to clades 1–4.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0020">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4" id="lk0020"/></fig></p>
      <p id="p0200">In general, average block size was inversely proportional to the quantile value and Q50 yielded the highest amount of blocks for all hybrids (<xref rid="fig0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, panel “A”; <xref rid="fig0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>; Supplementary File S2; <xref rid="sec0140" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Fig. S8</xref>). Each of the four different hybridisation events between <italic>C. orthopsilosis</italic> parental strains gave rise to a different clade of hybrids. Because of this shared evolutionary history, hybrids that belong to the same clade share similar LOH patterns (i.e. specific coordinates of LOH blocks), which differ from those of hybrids belonging to another clade. We took advantage of this clade specificity to assess which parameters would be optimal for LOH inference, as a good parameter set is expected to reflect the clade of origin for each strain whereas false positives and negatives would blur the clade-specific evolutionary signal. We selected four representative strains of each clade and assessed the overlap between LOH blocks called within and between clades. Parameter values leading to the highest overlap of blocks between samples of the same clade without increasing the overlap between different clades were considered most suitable (<xref rid="fig0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, panel “B”). Our results clearly show that blocks called with parameters set at the Q50 quantile of SNPs/kbp resulted in the highest specificity in detecting shared LOH blocks between strains of the same clade (<xref rid="fig0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, panel “B”; <xref rid="sec0140" ref-type="sec">Supplementary File S5</xref>).<fig id="fig0025"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>The number of inferred LOH blocks and their size depend on the different quantile values used (A) number, size of LOH blocks and total bp of LOH in all <italic>C. orthopsilosis</italic> hybrid strains using different quantile values. (B) Number of shared LOH blocks between four representative strains of each clade.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0025">Fig. 5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5" id="lk0025"/></fig></p>
      <p id="p0205">In sum, the number of minimum SNPs per kilobase considered to define blocks does influence the results of the LOH block inference. Therefore, the “jloh stats” module represents a helpful tool to optimise LOH block calling parameters according to specific experimental settings and scientific question, such as the quest for shared blocks between strains that we used in this paragraph.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec0110">
      <label>3.6</label>
      <title>Reanalysing public variation data</title>
      <p id="p0210">With the provided framework, it is possible to extract LOH blocks from pre-existing variation SNP data that was used for other purposes. To demonstrate the advantage of JLOH in this context, we processed five genome sequencing samples from a dataset of publicly available hybrid yeasts <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref> taken from a collection of 204 publicly available yeast hybrid samples which the authors characterised in terms of their environment (e.g. beer, wine, olive). Within that study, the authors extract LOH from five <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> x <italic>S. paradoxus</italic> hybrids only. These hybrids were generated in three separate original studies <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>, <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>, <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>. These strains were UFMGCMY651, UFMGCMY652, CBS7002, AWRI1501 and AWRI1502. By making a consensus of the LOH blocks called in the five hybrids, the authors extract an LOH propensity for each region of each chromosome, and show that the majority of chromosome 12 was showing a remarkably strong signal of LOH favouring the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> alleles (Figure 8 in Bendixsen et al., 2021). Our results confirm this trend but also show further information when stratified by individual strains. When looking at the LOH propensity of chromosome 12 of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> (<xref rid="fig0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>, panel “A”), four out of the five strains show the expected <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> predominance in terms of haplotype, but one (CBS7002) shows an LOH profile that is almost entirely favouring <italic>S. paradoxus</italic> alleles. This trend would not be visible when making a consensus of the five strains, as the other four have a strong coherent signal that would skew the consensus result towards <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>’s alleles. We then looked at the complementary results that we obtained on chromosome 12 of <italic>S. paradoxus</italic> (<xref rid="fig0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>, panel “B”). These results look coherent with the ones obtained on <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, as the same four strains show LOH predominantly favouring <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> alleles. Strain CBS7002, as in <xref rid="fig0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>A, displays a different trend. The initial part of chromosome 12 (approx. 1–370 kbp) shows LOH favouring <italic>S. paradoxus</italic> in line with the results observed on chromosome 12 of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, while the remaining part of the chromosome shows LOH towards <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>. This is, of course, impossible: in both cases the suggested LOH allele is the alternative allele (either <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> or <italic>S. paradoxus</italic> depending on the chromosome), which indicates the possibility that a third genotype is in play in this scenario, which is neither the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> nor the <italic>S. paradoxus</italic> genome used for the analysis. Sample CBS7002 comes from a study where researchers studied a quasi-domesticated hybrid strain of <italic>S. cerevisiae x S. paradoxus</italic> adapted to an olive industrial processing environment <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>. The authors describe it as a hybrid which lost most of its <italic>S. paradoxus</italic> subgenome due to LOH in favour of the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> subgenome. <xref rid="fig0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> clearly shows how, in this isolate, the first portion of chromosome 12 has instead fully retained the <italic>S. paradoxus</italic> alleles. We speculate that the alleles carried by the <italic>S. paradoxus</italic> subgenome in this region of chromosome 12 may have been more advantageous for this particular strain and were preferentially retained. We analysed the gene content of the first 370,000 positions of chromosome 12. Associated GO terms showed a high abundance of transmembrane proteins involved in membrane transport, although no GO term was significantly enriched. These types of proteins have been described as enriched in this hybrid by the original authors <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>.<fig id="fig0030"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Density of LOH signal along chromosome 12 of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> (<bold>A</bold>) and of <italic>S. paradoxus</italic> (<bold>B</bold>) computed in windows of 10 kb in five <italic>S. cerevisiae x S. paradoxus</italic> hybrids. The figure was generated with “jloh plot”. Colors represent allele assignment (REF or ALT) while color intensity represents the fraction of positions in each window that were in a predicted LOH block. Note that in (<bold>A</bold>) “blue” corresponds to <italic>S. paradoxus</italic> alleles while in (<bold>B</bold>) it corresponds to <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> alleles, as it generally represents the alternative allele.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0030">Fig. 6</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr6" id="lk0030"/></fig></p>
      <p id="p0215">Another interesting deduction that we make from this analysis regards samples AWRI1501 and AWRI1502, which show diverging LOH patterns despite coming from the same study <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. Both AWRI1501 and AWRI1502 samples are hybrid yeasts commercialised from the Australian company Maurivin (<underline>https://www.maurivin.com/</underline>). However, while it was used as a <italic>S. cerevisiae x S. paradoxus</italic> hybrid in Bendixsen et al. (2021), according to Maurivin AWRI1502 is actually a <italic>S. cerevisiae x S. cariocanus</italic> hybrid. <italic>S. cariocanus</italic> is phylogenetically close to <italic>S. paradoxus</italic> and has been recognised as an independent species about 20 years ago <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>. This attests to the ability of JLOH to distinguish LOH blocks even down to individual strains, and all in all, we concluded that JLOH is able to infer reliable LOH blocks and aid in generating biologically relevant knowledge.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec0115">
      <label>3.7</label>
      <title>LOH block inference in more complex genomes</title>
      <p id="p0220">Using fungal genomes, we detected 1% of heterozygosity as the lower detection limit of “jloh extract”. Although the JLOH algorithm has been developed with fungal genomes as templates, its underlying idea may be applied to any genome that carries at least 1% heterozygosity between its homologous chromosomes (or “homeologs”, in the case of hybrids). The human X chromosome alone is 13x larger than the genome of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, it is much more repetitive and carries many non-coding DNA sequences. Therefore, it poses a bigger challenge in the read mapping and variant calling steps, which could hinder proper LOH block recovery. Hence, we used the X chromosome sequence from the hg38 human genome version as template to create two simulated copies of it with 1% divergence from the template each. We artificially introduced ∼500 LOH blocks (avg. size 25 kbp) in the same positions among copies. We then concatenated the two copies and simulated reads from the concatenated version. This way, we generated a set of reads that carried a diploid genotype with low heterozygosity and known LOH blocks that could be used as a means of validation. We note that 1% heterozygosity is higher than what is expected between human homologs. We mapped the reads against the original X chromosome sequence, called variants, and inferred LOH block susing “jloh extract”. We limited the output blocks at a minimum length of 5 kbp, compatible with the size of the manually introduced LOH blocks. The results contained 1280 blocks, 1057 of which (82,5%) overlapped by 75% or more of their sequence with introduced LOH blocks. We note that 979 (76,5%) of the inferred blocks overlapped with the “true positives” with 90% of their sequence or more. The high number of inferred blocks (1280 inferred vs 587 introduced) is due to some level of fragmentation of the blocks inferred by “jloh extract” when compared with the ones introduced with “jloh sim”. We therefore concluded that the complexity of the human X chromosome is not a challenge to the inference algorithm, and that the real limit is posed by the density of heterozygous SNPs instead.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec0120">
    <label>4</label>
    <title>Discussion</title>
    <p id="p0225">In this study we introduce JLOH, a computational toolkit for inferring and analysing LOH blocks from SNP calling and read mapping data. To the best of our knowledge, only two tools exist that allow the extraction of LOH blocks starting from sequencing data, both focusing specifically on yeasts <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. However, given their discussed limitations, a general-purpose, parallelizable, and straightforward command-line tool requiring common input such as FASTA, BAM and VCF formatted files was timely.</p>
    <p id="p0230">We here described the design and rationale of the JLOH algorithm and showcase its applicability. We first demonstrated that the level of sequence divergence sensibly affected the quality of the retrieved LOH blocks. We stress that this divergence may be interpreted in two ways: on one hand it could represent the divergence between the sequenced read set and the reference genome in a normal, non-hybrid organism. On the other hand, if working with a hybrid species, it represents the divergence between the two subgenomes. At 1–10% divergence, compatible with intra-species diversity as well as the subgenome divergence of many known inter-species hybrids <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>, <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>, <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>, JLOH was able to retrieve almost all the known LOH blocks with great precision. At higher divergence (15–20%) instead, we noticed a big impact of read mapping onto the results. In fact, we established a connection between the high number of true positives generated by “jloh extract” and the inability of read mappers to map all the reads when working with short reads. In situations where read mappers fail to map reads from one subgenome onto the other, “jloh extract” will infer a hemizygous block that lost one of the two alleles, as the read coverage halves in such areas. Hence, we established that when the reads and the reference genome have a sequence divergence of 15% or more, LOH blocks inferred from short read mapping become unreliable. This limit is determined by the read mapping algorithms and their need for a seed identical sequence of sufficient length. Through our simulation of PacBio RSII long reads, we demonstrated that longer reads alleviate the issue and improve LOH detection in hybrids with highly divergent sub-genomes. Future studies will have to take this into account when planning variant calling experiments on highly divergent genomes.</p>
    <p id="p0235">One of the research areas in which the study of LOH is of particular relevance is the analysis of hybrid genomes, as it has been demonstrated that LOH may efficiently drive their adaptation <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. JLOH is particularly useful in this context, since it can work with a paired dataset representing variant and mapping information from a hybrid’s subgenomes and reference sequences from their parental genomes. The mapping has to be conducted onto the two parental genomes independently, generating two variant sets and two read mapping record sets. As shown in our results, it is important to account for the expected sequence divergence between subgenomes as it may sensibly affect the read mapping step and therefore the LOH block inference. Through homozygous SNPs, when run in --assign-blocks mode “jloh extract” will also annotate to which parental each LOH block belongs to. To the best of our knowledge, this is a novel aspect.</p>
    <p id="p0240">In many cases, one of the two parental species of a hybrid is unknown, and so its genome is likely unavailable. This, however, does not impede the usage of JLOH as long as the other parental genome is available. As demonstrated here with the <italic>C. orthopsilosis</italic> hybrids, it is still possible to retrieve LOH blocks by mapping the reads from the hybrid against the genome sequence of one of the parents. Heterozygous SNPs will still be annotated and homozygous SNPs will display whether the block has been inherited from the parent used as reference (REF) or from another allele (ALT). This applies to contexts where both parents are missing, too. To showcase this, we inferred LOH blocks in two strains (BP57 and PL448) of the known hybrid <italic>Candida metapsilosis</italic>
<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref> using the BP57 chimeric genome assembly as reference. Using this approach, we could distinguish between regions of LOH and heterozygosity despite not being able to infer the original haplotype of each block. As expected, given that the two strains belong to the same clade, they displayed largely similar patterns and distribution of LOH blocks. Notably, in the original study <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, Pryszcz et al. reported that in strain PL448 one chromosome had undergone LOH through its entire sequence. Our results recapitulate this finding: we observe a complete lack of heterozygosity in scaffold 6 of strain PL448 (<xref rid="sec0140" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Fig. S9</xref>, panel “B”). On the contrary, this scaffold was highly heterozygous in BP57 (<xref rid="sec0140" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Fig. S9</xref>, panel “A”). Hence, we suggest that JLOH may be used also in situations whereby only the hybrid genome sequence is available, still providing biologically relevant information.</p>
    <p id="p0245">We used the <italic>C. orthopsilosis</italic> dataset also to showcase the effect of SNP density thresholds. <italic>C. orthopsilosis</italic> is a yeast hybrid with known intra-species population diversity, and our dataset comprised four clades originated from independent hybridisation events of the same parental lineages. We used “jloh stats” to calculate the density (SNPs/kbp) distribution of hetero- and homozygous SNPs over a genome sequence in windows of fixed size. We ran it for each sample and then averaged the SNP density distributions by clade. As shown in the code implementation, “jloh stats” returns the informative quantiles of the SNP density distribution of both hetero- and homozygous SNPs. For Q5, Q10, Q15, Q50, Q85, Q90 and Q95 we averaged the quantile value among samples by clade. Then, we used this value in “jloh extract” through the --min-snps-kbp parameter, which we have shown to impact the results due to its interconnection to SNP density and divergence. Our results (<xref rid="sec0140" ref-type="sec">Supplementary File S5</xref>, <xref rid="fig0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>) showed a high degree of variability depending on the quantile used. In particular, when using Q50, we were able to capture clade-specific blocks and see differences in the clades without losing too much signal. While we stress that this is not the optimal quantile for any LOH-based analysis with JLOH, we suggest the user to select a quantile that is compatible with the experimental design. For example, if the analysed dataset does not have high intraspecific diversity, lower quantiles will allow the recovery of the majority of LOH blocks.</p>
    <p id="p0250">Clade-specific signal such as the one showed with <italic>C. orthopsilosis</italic> hybrids can be easily visualized with “jloh plot”, as we have shown by re-inferring LOH on five hybrids from <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> and <italic>S. paradoxus</italic>. Simply displaying the inferred LOH blocks from these five strains showed how different each can be, as was the case for strain CBS7002. Future studies may leverage this simple workflow to highlight differences between clades, strains, or even individuals, and may uncover unknown differences or mislabellings in datasets with an intuitive visualisation.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec0125">
    <title>Funding</title>
    <p id="p0255">TG group acknowledges support from the <funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100004837</institution-id><institution>Spanish Ministry of Science and Innovation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> for grants PID2021-126067NB-I00, CPP2021-008552, PCI2022-135066-2, and PDC2022-133266-I00, cofounded by ERDF “A way of making Europe”; from the Catalan Research Agency (<funding-source id="gs2"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100003030</institution-id><institution>AGAUR</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>) SGR01551; from the <funding-source id="gs3">European Union’s Horizon 2020</funding-source> research and innovation programme (ERC-2016-724173); from the <funding-source id="gs4"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000936</institution-id><institution>Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (Grant GBMF9742); from the “<funding-source id="gs5">La Caixa</funding-source>” foundation (Grant LCF/PR/HR21/00737), and from the <funding-source id="gs6"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100004587</institution-id><institution>Instituto de Salud Carlos III</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (IMPACT Grant IMP/00019 and <funding-source id="gs7">CIBERINFEC</funding-source> CB21/13/00061- ISCIII-SGEFI/ERDF). This project also received funding from the <funding-source id="gs8">European Union’s Horizon 2020</funding-source> research and innovation programme under the Marie Skłodowska-Curie grant agreement No 754433.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec0130">
    <title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title>
    <p id="p0260">TG and MS designed the experiments. MS, TG and VdO modelled the computational problem. MS coded the software. MS and VNM tested the software. MS and VdO performed the analysis. TG supervised the project. All authors have read and accepted the manuscript.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
    <title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title>
    <p id="p0265">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ref-list id="bibliog0005">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="bib1">
      <label>1</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref1">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Arnold</surname>
            <given-names>M.L.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Natural hybridization as an evolutionary process</article-title>
        <source>Annu Rev Ecol Syst</source>
        <volume>23</volume>
        <year>1992</year>
        <fpage>237</fpage>
        <lpage>261</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib2">
      <label>2</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref2">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gabaldón</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Patterns and impacts of nonvertical evolution in eukaryotes: a paradigm shift</article-title>
        <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>
        <volume>1476</volume>
        <year>2020</year>
        <fpage>78</fpage>
        <lpage>92</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32860228</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib3">
      <label>3</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref3">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Schneemann</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>De Sanctis</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Roze</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bierne</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Welch</surname>
            <given-names>J.J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The geometry and genetics of hybridization</article-title>
        <source>Evolution</source>
        <volume>74</volume>
        <year>2020</year>
        <fpage>2575</fpage>
        <lpage>2590</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33150956</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib4">
      <label>4</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref4">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Forche</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Large-scale chromosomal changes and associated fitness consequences in pathogenic fungi</article-title>
        <source>Curr Fungal Infect Rep</source>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <year>2014</year>
        <fpage>163</fpage>
        <lpage>170</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25685251</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib5">
      <label>5</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref5">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liang</surname>
            <given-names>S.-H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bennett</surname>
            <given-names>R.J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The impact of gene dosage and heterozygosity on the diploid pathobiont candida albicans</article-title>
        <source>J Fungi</source>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <year>2020</year>
        <fpage>10</fpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib6">
      <label>6</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref6">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Schiavinato</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bodrug-Schepers</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dohm</surname>
            <given-names>J.C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Himmelbauer</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Subgenome evolution in allotetraploid plants</article-title>
        <source>Plant J</source>
        <volume>106</volume>
        <year>2021</year>
        <fpage>672</fpage>
        <lpage>688</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33547826</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib7">
      <label>7</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref7">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Smukowski Heil</surname>
            <given-names>C.S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>DeSevo</surname>
            <given-names>C.G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pai</surname>
            <given-names>D.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tucker</surname>
            <given-names>C.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hoang</surname>
            <given-names>M.L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dunham</surname>
            <given-names>M.J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Loss of heterozygosity drives adaptation in hybrid yeast</article-title>
        <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
        <volume>34</volume>
        <year>2017</year>
        <fpage>1596</fpage>
        <lpage>1612</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28369610</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib8">
      <label>8</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref8">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nieto Feliner</surname>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Casacuberta</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wendel</surname>
            <given-names>J.F.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Genomics of evolutionary novelty in hybrids and polyploids</article-title>
        <source>Front Genet</source>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <year>2020</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib9">
      <label>9</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref9">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lancaster</surname>
            <given-names>S.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Payen</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Heil</surname>
            <given-names>C.S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dunham</surname>
            <given-names>M.J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Fitness benefits of loss of heterozygosity in Saccharomyces hybrids</article-title>
        <source>Genome Res</source>
        <volume>29</volume>
        <year>2019</year>
        <fpage>1685</fpage>
        <lpage>1692</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31548357</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib10">
      <label>10</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref10">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ryland</surname>
            <given-names>G.L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Doyle</surname>
            <given-names>M.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Goode</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Boyle</surname>
            <given-names>S.E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Choong</surname>
            <given-names>D.Y.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rowley</surname>
            <given-names>S.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bowtell</surname>
            <given-names>D.D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tothill</surname>
            <given-names>R.W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Campbell</surname>
            <given-names>I.G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Loss of heterozygosity: what is it good for?</article-title>
        <source>BMC Med Genom</source>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <year>2015</year>
        <fpage>45</fpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib11">
      <label>11</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref11">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Steensels</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gallone</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Verstrepen</surname>
            <given-names>K.J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Interspecific hybridization as a driver of fungal evolution and adaptation</article-title>
        <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>
        <volume>19</volume>
        <year>2021</year>
        <fpage>485</fpage>
        <lpage>500</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33767366</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib12">
      <label>12</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref12">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gabaldón</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Hybridization and the origin of new yeast lineages</article-title>
        <source>FEMS Yeast Res</source>
        <volume>20</volume>
        <year>2020</year>
        <fpage>foaa040</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32658267</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib13">
      <label>13</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref13">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bendixsen</surname>
            <given-names>D.P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Frazão</surname>
            <given-names>J.G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stelkens</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Saccharomyces yeast hybrids on the rise</article-title>
        <source>Yeast</source>
        <volume>39</volume>
        <year>2022</year>
        <fpage>40</fpage>
        <lpage>54</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34907582</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib14">
      <label>14</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref14">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hovhannisyan</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Saus</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ksiezopolska</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hinks Roberts</surname>
            <given-names>A.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Louis</surname>
            <given-names>E.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gabaldón</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Integrative omics analysis reveals a limited transcriptional shock after yeast interspecies hybridization</article-title>
        <source>Front Genet</source>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <year>2020</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib15">
      <label>15</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref15">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ksiezopolska</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gabaldón</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Evolutionary emergence of drug resistance in candida opportunistic pathogens</article-title>
        <source>Genes</source>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <year>2018</year>
        <fpage>461</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30235884</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib16">
      <label>16</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref16">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pankajam</surname>
            <given-names>A.V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dash</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Saifudeen</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dutta</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nishant</surname>
            <given-names>K.T.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Loss of heterozygosity and base mutation rates vary among saccharomyces cerevisiae hybrid strains</article-title>
        <source>G3 Genes</source>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <year>2020</year>
        <fpage>3309</fpage>
        <lpage>3319</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib17">
      <label>17</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref17">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pryszcz</surname>
            <given-names>L.P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Németh</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Saus</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ksiezopolska</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hegedűsová</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nosek</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wolfe</surname>
            <given-names>K.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gacser</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gabaldón</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The genomic aftermath of hybridization in the opportunistic pathogen candida metapsilosis</article-title>
        <source>PLOS Genet</source>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <year>2015</year>
        <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e1005626</object-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib18">
      <label>18</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref18">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bendixsen</surname>
            <given-names>D.P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Peris</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stelkens</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Patterns of genomic instability in interspecific yeast hybrids with diverse ancestries</article-title>
        <source>Front Fungal Biol</source>
        <year>2021</year>
        <fpage>2</fpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib19">
      <label>19</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref19">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lamour</surname>
            <given-names>K.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mudge</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gobena</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hurtado-Gonzales</surname>
            <given-names>O.P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schmutz</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kuo</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Miller</surname>
            <given-names>N.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rice</surname>
            <given-names>B.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Raffaele</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cano</surname>
            <given-names>L.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Genome sequencing and mapping reveal loss of heterozygosity as a mechanism for rapid adaptation in the vegetable pathogen Phytophthora capsici</article-title>
        <source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interactions®</source>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <year>2012</year>
        <fpage>1350</fpage>
        <lpage>1360</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib20">
      <label>20</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref20">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pengelly</surname>
            <given-names>R.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rowaiye</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pickard</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Moran</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dayal</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tapper</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mirnezami</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cecil</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mohamed</surname>
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Carr</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Analysis of mutation and loss of heterozygosity by whole-exome sequencing yields insights into pseudomyxoma peritonei</article-title>
        <source>J Mol Diagn</source>
        <volume>20</volume>
        <year>2018</year>
        <fpage>635</fpage>
        <lpage>642</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29936255</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib21">
      <label>21</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref21">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Abbey</surname>
            <given-names>D.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Funt</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lurie-Weinberger</surname>
            <given-names>M.N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Thompson</surname>
            <given-names>D.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Regev</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Myers</surname>
            <given-names>C.L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Berman</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>YMAP: a pipeline for visualization of copy number variation and loss of heterozygosity in eukaryotic pathogens</article-title>
        <source>Genome Med</source>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <year>2014</year>
        <fpage>100</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25505934</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib22">
      <label>22</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref22">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tattini</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tellini</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mozzachiodi</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>D’Angiolo</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Loeillet</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nicolas</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liti</surname>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Accurate tracking of the mutational landscape of diploid hybrid genomes</article-title>
        <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
        <volume>36</volume>
        <year>2019</year>
        <fpage>2861</fpage>
        <lpage>2877</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31397846</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib23">
      <label>23</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref23">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sathirapongsasuti</surname>
            <given-names>J.F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Horst</surname>
            <given-names>B.A.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Brunner</surname>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cochran</surname>
            <given-names>A.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Binder</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Quackenbush</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nelson</surname>
            <given-names>S.F.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Exome sequencing-based copy-number variation and loss of heterozygosity detection: ExomeCNV</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <volume>27</volume>
        <year>2011</year>
        <fpage>2648</fpage>
        <lpage>2654</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21828086</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib24">
      <label>24</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref24">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>Z.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>CLImAT-HET: detecting subclonal copy number alterations and loss of heterozygosity in heterogeneous tumor samples from whole-genome sequencing data</article-title>
        <source>BMC Med Genom</source>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <year>2017</year>
        <fpage>15</fpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib25">
      <label>25</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref25">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Goffeau</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Barrell</surname>
            <given-names>B.G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bussey</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Davis</surname>
            <given-names>R.W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dujon</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Feldmann</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Galibert</surname>
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hoheisel</surname>
            <given-names>J.D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jacq</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Johnston</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Life with 6000 Genes</article-title>
        <source>Science</source>
        <volume>274</volume>
        <year>1996</year>
        <fpage>546</fpage>
        <lpage>567</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8849441</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib26">
      <label>26</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref26">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ono</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hamada</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Asai</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>PBSIM3: a simulator for all types of PacBio and ONT long reads</article-title>
        <source>NAR Genom Bioinforma</source>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <year>2022</year>
        <fpage>lqac092</fpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib27">
      <label>27</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref27">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Langmead</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Salzberg</surname>
            <given-names>S.L.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2</article-title>
        <source>Nat Methods</source>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <year>2012</year>
        <fpage>357</fpage>
        <lpage>359</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22388286</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib28">
      <label>28</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref28">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kent</surname>
            <given-names>W.J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>BLAT---the BLAST-like alignment tool</article-title>
        <source>Genome Res</source>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <year>2002</year>
        <fpage>656</fpage>
        <lpage>664</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11932250</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib29">
      <label>29</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref29">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Paggi</surname>
            <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bennett</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Salzberg</surname>
            <given-names>S.L.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Graph-based genome alignment and genotyping with HISAT2 and HISAT-genotype</article-title>
        <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
        <volume>37</volume>
        <year>2019</year>
        <fpage>907</fpage>
        <lpage>915</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31375807</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib30">
      <label>30</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref30">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Minimap2: pairwise alignment for nucleotide sequences</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <volume>34</volume>
        <year>2018</year>
        <fpage>3094</fpage>
        <lpage>3100</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29750242</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib31">
      <label>31</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref31">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Handsaker</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wysoker</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fennell</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ruan</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Homer</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Marth</surname>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Abecasis</surname>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Durbin</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <collab>and 1000 Genome Project Data Processing Subgroup</collab>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The sequence alignment/Map format and SAMtools</article-title>
        <source>Bioinforma Oxf Engl</source>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <year>2009</year>
        <fpage>2078</fpage>
        <lpage>2079</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib32">
      <label>32</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref32">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Danecek</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bonfield</surname>
            <given-names>J.K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liddle</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Marshall</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ohan</surname>
            <given-names>V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pollard</surname>
            <given-names>M.O.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Whitwham</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Keane</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McCarthy</surname>
            <given-names>S.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Davies</surname>
            <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Twelve years of SAMtools and BCFtools</article-title>
        <source>GigaScience</source>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <year>2021</year>
        <fpage>giab008</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33590861</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib33">
      <label>33</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref33">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yue</surname>
            <given-names>J.-X.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Aigrain</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hallin</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Persson</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Oliver</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bergström</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Coupland</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Warringer</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lagomarsino</surname>
            <given-names>M.C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Contrasting evolutionary genome dynamics between domesticated and wild yeasts</article-title>
        <source>Nat Genet</source>
        <volume>49</volume>
        <year>2017</year>
        <fpage>913</fpage>
        <lpage>924</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28416820</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib34">
      <label>34</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref34">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>T.D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Watanabe</surname>
            <given-names>C.K.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>GMAP: a genomic mapping and alignment program for mRNA and EST sequences</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <volume>21</volume>
        <year>2005</year>
        <fpage>1859</fpage>
        <lpage>1875</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15728110</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib35">
      <label>35</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref35">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Törönen</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Medlar</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Holm</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>PANNZER2: a rapid functional annotation web server</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
        <volume>46</volume>
        <year>2018</year>
        <fpage>W84</fpage>
        <lpage>W88</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29741643</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib36">
      <label>36</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref36">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Guo</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dai</surname>
            <given-names>Z.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Feng</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhou</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tang</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhan</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>clusterProfiler 4.0: a universal enrichment tool for interpreting omics data</article-title>
        <source>Innovation</source>
        <volume>2</volume>
        <year>2021</year>
        <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100141</object-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib37">
      <label>37</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref37">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pryszcz</surname>
            <given-names>L.P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Németh</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gácser</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gabaldón</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Genome comparison of candida orthopsilosis clinical strains reveals the existence of hybrids between two distinct subspecies</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol Evol</source>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <year>2014</year>
        <fpage>1069</fpage>
        <lpage>1078</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24747362</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib38">
      <label>38</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref38">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Schröder</surname>
            <given-names>M.S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vicente</surname>
            <given-names>K.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>de</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Prandini</surname>
            <given-names>T.H.R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hammel</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Higgins</surname>
            <given-names>D.G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bagagli</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wolfe</surname>
            <given-names>K.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Butler</surname>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Multiple origins of the pathogenic yeast candida orthopsilosis by separate hybridizations between two parental species</article-title>
        <source>PLoS Genet</source>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <year>2016</year>
        <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e1006404</object-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib39">
      <label>39</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref39">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Riccombeni</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vidanes</surname>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Proux-Wéra</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wolfe</surname>
            <given-names>K.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Butler</surname>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Sequence and analysis of the genome of the pathogenic yeast Candida orthopsilosis</article-title>
        <source>PLoS One</source>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <year>2012</year>
        <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e35750</object-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib40">
      <label>40</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref40">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bolger</surname>
            <given-names>A.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lohse</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Usadel</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Trimmomatic: a flexible trimmer for Illumina sequence data</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <volume>30</volume>
        <year>2014</year>
        <fpage>2114</fpage>
        <lpage>2120</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24695404</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib41">
      <label>41</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref41">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Quinlan</surname>
            <given-names>A.R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hall</surname>
            <given-names>I.M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>BEDTools: a flexible suite of utilities for comparing genomic features</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <volume>26</volume>
        <year>2010</year>
        <fpage>841</fpage>
        <lpage>842</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20110278</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib42">
      <label>42</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref42">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Thorvaldsdóttir</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Robinson</surname>
            <given-names>J.T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mesirov</surname>
            <given-names>J.P.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Integrative Genomics Viewer (IGV): high-performance genomics data visualization and exploration</article-title>
        <source>Brief Bioinform</source>
        <volume>14</volume>
        <year>2013</year>
        <fpage>178</fpage>
        <lpage>192</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22517427</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib43">
      <label>43</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref43">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dale</surname>
            <given-names>R.K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pedersen</surname>
            <given-names>B.S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Quinlan</surname>
            <given-names>A.R.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Pybedtools: a flexible Python library for manipulating genomic datasets and annotations</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <volume>27</volume>
        <year>2011</year>
        <fpage>3423</fpage>
        <lpage>3424</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21949271</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib44">
      <label>44</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref44">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Di Tommaso</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chatzou</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Floden</surname>
            <given-names>E.W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Barja</surname>
            <given-names>P.P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Palumbo</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Notredame</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Nextflow enables reproducible computational workflows</article-title>
        <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
        <volume>35</volume>
        <year>2017</year>
        <fpage>316</fpage>
        <lpage>319</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28398311</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib45">
      <label>45</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref45">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Durbin</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Fast and accurate long-read alignment with Burrows-Wheeler transform</article-title>
        <source>Bioinforma Oxf Engl</source>
        <volume>26</volume>
        <year>2010</year>
        <fpage>589</fpage>
        <lpage>595</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib46">
      <label>46</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref46">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Marx</surname>
            <given-names>V.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Method of the year: long-read sequencing</article-title>
        <source>Nat Methods</source>
        <volume>20</volume>
        <year>2023</year>
        <fpage>6</fpage>
        <lpage>11</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36635542</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib47">
      <label>47</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref47">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tavanti</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Davidson</surname>
            <given-names>A.D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gow</surname>
            <given-names>N.A.R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Maiden</surname>
            <given-names>M.C.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Odds</surname>
            <given-names>F.C.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title><italic>Candida orthopsilosis</italic> and <italic>Candida metapsilosis</italic> spp. nov. To Replace <italic>Candida parapsilosis</italic> Groups II and III</article-title>
        <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
        <volume>43</volume>
        <year>2005</year>
        <fpage>284</fpage>
        <lpage>292</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15634984</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib48">
      <label>48</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref48">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Barbosa</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Almeida</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Safar</surname>
            <given-names>S.V.B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Santos</surname>
            <given-names>R.O.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Morais</surname>
            <given-names>P.B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nielly-Thibault</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Leducq</surname>
            <given-names>J.-B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Landry</surname>
            <given-names>C.R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gonçalves</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rosa</surname>
            <given-names>C.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Evidence of natural hybridization in brazilian wild lineages of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol Evol</source>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <year>2016</year>
        <fpage>317</fpage>
        <lpage>329</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26782936</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib49">
      <label>49</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref49">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Borneman</surname>
            <given-names>A.R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Forgan</surname>
            <given-names>A.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kolouchova</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fraser</surname>
            <given-names>J.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schmidt</surname>
            <given-names>S.A.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Whole genome comparison reveals high levels of inbreeding and strain redundancy across the spectrum of commercial wine strains of Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title>
        <source>G3 Genes</source>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <year>2016</year>
        <fpage>957</fpage>
        <lpage>971</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib50">
      <label>50</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref50">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pontes</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Čadež</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gonçalves</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sampaio</surname>
            <given-names>J.P.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A quasi-domesticate relic hybrid population of saccharomyces cerevisiae × s. paradoxus adapted to olive brine</article-title>
        <source>Front Genet</source>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <year>2019</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib51">
      <label>51</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref51">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Naumov</surname>
            <given-names>G.I.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>James</surname>
            <given-names>S.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Naumova</surname>
            <given-names>E.S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Louis</surname>
            <given-names>E.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Roberts</surname>
            <given-names>I.N.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Three new species in the Saccharomyces sensu stricto complex: Saccharomyces cariocanus, Saccharomyces kudriavzevii and Saccharomyces mikatae</article-title>
        <source>Int J Syst Evol Microbiol</source>
        <volume>50</volume>
        <year>2000</year>
        <fpage>1931</fpage>
        <lpage>1942</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11034507</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib52">
      <label>52</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref52">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mixão</surname>
            <given-names>V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>del Olmo</surname>
            <given-names>V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hegedűsová</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Saus</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pryszcz</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cillingová</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nosek</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gabaldón</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Genome analysis of five recently described species of the CUG-Ser clade uncovers Candida theae as a new hybrid lineage with pathogenic potential in the Candida parapsilosis species complex</article-title>
        <source>DNA Res Int J Rapid Publ Rep Genes Genomes</source>
        <volume>29</volume>
        <year>2022</year>
        <fpage>dsac010</fpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib53">
      <label>53</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref53">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>O’Brien</surname>
            <given-names>C.E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhai</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ola</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bergin</surname>
            <given-names>S.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ó Cinnéide</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>O’Connor</surname>
            <given-names>Í.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rolling</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Miranda</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Babady</surname>
            <given-names>N.E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hohl</surname>
            <given-names>T.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Identification of a novel Candida metapsilosis isolate reveals multiple hybridization events</article-title>
        <source>G3 Genes</source>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <year>2021</year>
        <fpage>jkab367</fpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib54">
      <label>54</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref54">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Steenwyk</surname>
            <given-names>J.L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lind</surname>
            <given-names>A.L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ries</surname>
            <given-names>L.N.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>dos Reis</surname>
            <given-names>T.F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Silva</surname>
            <given-names>L.P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Almeida</surname>
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bastos</surname>
            <given-names>R.W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>de Campos Fraga da Silva</surname>
            <given-names>T.F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bonato</surname>
            <given-names>V.L.D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pessoni</surname>
            <given-names>A.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Pathogenic allodiploid hybrids of Aspergillus fungi</article-title>
        <source>Curr Biol CB</source>
        <volume>30</volume>
        <year>2020</year>
        <fpage>2495</fpage>
        <lpage>2507</lpage>
        <comment>e7</comment>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32502407</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib55">
      <label>55</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref55">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Theelen</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mixão</surname>
            <given-names>V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ianiri</surname>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Goh</surname>
            <given-names>J.P.Z.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dijksterhuis</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Heitman</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dawson</surname>
            <given-names>T.L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gabaldón</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Boekhout</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Multiple hybridization events punctuate the evolutionary trajectory of malassezia furfur</article-title>
        <source>mBio</source>
        <volume>13</volume>
        <year>2022</year>
        <fpage>e03853</fpage>
        <lpage>21</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35404119</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
  <sec id="sec0140" sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <label>Appendix A</label>
    <title>Supplementary material</title>
    <p id="p0280"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ec0005"><caption><p>Supplementary Figures.</p></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.pdf"/></supplementary-material>.</p>
    <p id="p0285"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ec0010"><caption><p>Supplementary material.</p></caption><media xlink:href="mmc2.zip"/></supplementary-material>.</p>
    <p id="p0290"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ec0015"><caption><p>Supplementary material.</p></caption><media xlink:href="mmc3.docx"/></supplementary-material>.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="da0005">
    <title>Data Availability</title>
    <p id="p0025">No new data was generated for this study. All the code and related files are available at the JLOH github repository (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/Gabaldonlab/jloh" id="ir0005">https://github.com/Gabaldonlab/jloh</ext-link>) together with a nextflow workflow to generate a simulated test dataset to assess the tool’s functionalities.</p>
  </sec>
  <ack id="ack0005">
    <title>Acknowledgments</title>
    <p id="p0270">We thank Leszek Pryszcz and Veronica Mixão for their original scripts, which have been the groundwork of this software. We thank Devin Bendixsen for kindly providing the results of their analysis published in 2021 to facilitate comparison with our results.</p>
  </ack>
  <fn-group>
    <fn id="sec0135" fn-type="supplementary-material">
      <label>Appendix A</label>
      <p id="p0275">Supplementary data associated with this article can be found in the online version at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.csbj.2023.11.003" id="ir0010">doi:10.1016/j.csbj.2023.11.003</ext-link>.</p>
    </fn>
  </fn-group>
</back>
