<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Biol</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Biol</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>BMC Biology</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1741-7007</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">10080885</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37024838</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1574</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12915-023-01574-6</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Software</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title><italic>RNAlysis</italic>: analyze your RNA sequencing data without writing a single line of code</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2285-1343</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Teichman</surname>
          <given-names>Guy</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>guyteichman@gmail.com</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Cohen</surname>
          <given-names>Dror</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
        <name>
          <surname>Ganon</surname>
          <given-names>Or</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
        <name>
          <surname>Dunsky</surname>
          <given-names>Netta</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
        <name>
          <surname>Shani</surname>
          <given-names>Shachar</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Gingold</surname>
          <given-names>Hila</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Rechavi</surname>
          <given-names>Oded</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.12136.37</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1937 0546</institution-id><institution>Department of Neurobiology, Wise Faculty of Life Sciences and Sagol School of Neuroscience, </institution><institution>Tel Aviv University, </institution></institution-wrap>Tel Aviv, Israel </aff>
      <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.6451.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000121102151</institution-id><institution>Department of Biology, </institution><institution>Technion – Israel Institute of Technology, </institution></institution-wrap>Haifa, Israel </aff>
      <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.12136.37</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1937 0546</institution-id><institution>Sagol Brain Institute, Sourasky Medical Center, </institution><institution>Neurological Institute, Tel Aviv and Sagol School of Neuroscience, Tel Aviv University, </institution></institution-wrap>Tel Aviv, Israel </aff>
      <aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.12136.37</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1937 0546</institution-id><institution>Sackler Faculty of Medicine, </institution><institution>Tel Aviv University, </institution></institution-wrap>Tel Aviv, Israel </aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>7</day>
      <month>4</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>7</day>
      <month>4</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>21</volume>
    <elocation-id>74</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>29</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>17</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2023</copyright-statement>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract id="Abs1">
      <sec>
        <title>Background</title>
        <p id="Par1">Among the major challenges in next-generation sequencing experiments are exploratory data analysis, interpreting trends, identifying potential targets/candidates, and visualizing the results clearly and intuitively. These hurdles are further heightened for researchers who are not experienced in writing computer code since most available analysis tools require programming skills. Even for proficient computational biologists, an efficient and replicable system is warranted to generate standardized results.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Results</title>
        <p id="Par2">We have developed <italic>RNAlysis</italic>, a modular Python-based analysis software for RNA sequencing data. <italic>RNAlysis</italic> allows users to build customized analysis pipelines suiting their specific research questions, going all the way from raw FASTQ files (adapter trimming, alignment, and feature counting), through exploratory data analysis and data visualization, clustering analysis, and gene set enrichment analysis. <italic>RNAlysis</italic> provides a friendly graphical user interface, allowing researchers to analyze data without writing code. We demonstrate the use of <italic>RNAlysis</italic> by analyzing RNA sequencing data from different studies using <italic>C.</italic>
<italic>elegans</italic> nematodes. We note that the software applies equally to data obtained from any organism with an existing reference genome.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Conclusions</title>
        <p id="Par3"><italic>RNAlysis</italic> is suitable for investigating various biological questions, allowing researchers to more accurately and reproducibly run comprehensive bioinformatic analyses. It functions as a gateway into RNA sequencing analysis for less computer-savvy researchers, but can also help experienced bioinformaticians make their analyses more robust and efficient, as it offers diverse tools, scalability, automation, and standardization between analyses.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Supplementary Information</title>
        <p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12915-023-01574-6.</p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
      <title>Keywords</title>
      <kwd>RNA sequencing</kwd>
      <kwd>Clustering analysis</kwd>
      <kwd>Gene set enrichment analysis</kwd>
      <kwd>Data visualization</kwd>
      <kwd>Pipeline</kwd>
      <kwd>Graphical interface</kwd>
      <kwd>Differential expression</kwd>
      <kwd>Computational analysis</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group>
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000781</institution-id>
            <institution>European Research Council</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>335624</award-id>
        <principal-award-recipient>
          <name>
            <surname>Rechavi</surname>
            <given-names>Oded</given-names>
          </name>
        </principal-award-recipient>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group>
        <funding-source>
          <institution>Israeli Science Foundation</institution>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>1339/17</award-id>
        <principal-award-recipient>
          <name>
            <surname>Rechavi</surname>
            <given-names>Oded</given-names>
          </name>
        </principal-award-recipient>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group>
        <funding-source>
          <institution>Eric and Wendy Fund for Strategic Innovation</institution>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>0140001000</award-id>
        <principal-award-recipient>
          <name>
            <surname>Rechavi</surname>
            <given-names>Oded</given-names>
          </name>
        </principal-award-recipient>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group>
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100018779</institution-id>
            <institution>Milner Foundation</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group>
        <funding-source>
          <institution>Morris Kahn Foundation</institution>
        </funding-source>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
        <meta-value>© The Author(s) 2023</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec id="Sec1">
    <title>Background
</title>
    <p id="Par13">RNA sequencing continues to grow in popularity as an investigative tool for biologists. A vast variety of RNA sequencing analysis methods allow researchers to compare gene expression levels between different biological specimens or experimental conditions, cluster genes based on their expression patterns, and characterize expression changes in genes involved in specific biological functions and pathways.</p>
    <p id="Par14">Specific tools exist to perform the tasks described above (see the <xref rid="Sec12" ref-type="sec">Discussion</xref> section and Additional File <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1 for a detailed comparison of available tools). However, most analysis tools can only perform a subset of these tasks. Any out-of-the-ordinary research questions require researchers to write customized analysis scripts, which may not be easy to share or replicate. Moreover, many of the existing tools require users to be familiar with reading and writing code, making them usable only by researchers experienced in computer programming.</p>
    <p id="Par15"><italic>RNAlysis</italic> offers a solution to these problems by (1) using a modular approach, allowing users to either analyze their data step-by-step, or construct reproducible analysis pipelines from individual functions; and (2) providing an intuitive and flexible graphical user interface (GUI), allowing users to answer a wide variety of biological questions, whether they are general or highly specific, and explore their data interactively without writing a single line of code. <italic>RNAlysis</italic> includes thorough documentation and step-by-step guided analyses, to help new users to learn the software quickly and acquire good data analysis practices (available online or as Additional File <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Tutorial).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec2">
    <title>Implementation</title>
    <p id="Par16"><italic>RNAlysis</italic> was designed to perform three major tasks: (1) pre-processing and exploratory data analysis; (2) finding gene sets of interest through filtering, clustering, and set operations; (3) visualizing intersections between gene sets and performing enrichment analysis on those sets (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>The workflow of <italic>RNAlysis.</italic>
<bold>Top section:</bold> a typical analysis with <italic>RNAlysis</italic> can start at any stage from raw/trimmed FASTQ files, through more processed data tables such as count matrices, differential expression tables, or any form of tabular data. <bold>Middle section:</bold> data tables can be filtered, normalized, and transformed with a wide variety of functions, allowing users to clean up their data, fine-tune their analysis to their biological questions, or prepare the data for downstream analysis. <italic>RNAlysis</italic> also provides users with a broad assortment of customizable clustering methods to help recognize genes with similar expression patterns, and visualization methods to aid in data exploration. All of these functions can be arranged into customized Pipelines that can be applied to multiple tables in one click, or exported and shared with others. <bold>Bottom section:</bold> Once users have focused their data tables into gene sets of interest, or imported such gene sets from another source, they can use <italic>RNAlysis</italic> to visualize the intersections between different gene sets, extract lists of genes from any set operations applied to their gene sets and data tables, and perform enrichment analysis for their gene sets, using either public datasets such as GO and KEGG or customized, user-defined enrichment attributes</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12915_2023_1574_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
    <sec id="Sec3">
      <title>Input</title>
      <p id="Par17"><italic>RNAlysis</italic> can interface with existing tools, such as <italic>CutAdapt</italic>, <italic>kallisto</italic>, <italic>bowtie2</italic>, <italic>featureCounts</italic>, <italic>limma</italic>, and <italic>DESeq2</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], to enable users to run basic adapter-trimming, RNA sequencing quantification, read alignment, feature counting, and differential expression analysis through a graphical user interface. That is to say, users can begin their analysis with <italic>RNAlysis</italic> with sequencing data at any stage. Alternatively, users can load into <italic>RNAlysis</italic> data tables that were generated elsewhere. <italic>RNAlysis</italic> has a tab interface, which allows users to examine and analyze multiple data tables in parallel, seamlessly switching between them.</p>
      <p id="Par18"><italic>RNAlysis</italic> can accept data from any organism. <italic>RNAlysis</italic> can analyze gene expression matrices (raw or normalized), differential expression tables, or user-defined gene sets of interest. Moreover, <italic>RNAlysis</italic> accepts annotations for user-defined attributes of genes. Since <italic>RNAlysis</italic> works with tabular data, <italic>RNAlysis</italic> is applicable to any type of data table.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4">
      <title>Data validation and pre-processing</title>
      <p id="Par19">First, <italic>RNAlysis</italic> allows users to validate their data by summarizing and visualizing its patterns and distribution. For instance, users may compare the distribution of gene expression between samples through scatter plots and pair plots, or examine general trends in the data, as well as potential batch effects, via clustergram plots and PCA projections.</p>
      <p id="Par20">Moreover, <italic>RNAlysis</italic> allows users to pre-process their data by normalizing it through one of the various methods (such as median of ratios, relative log ratio, trimmed mean of M-values, and more) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], filtering out lowly-expressed genes, and eliminating rows with missing data from their tables.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec5">
      <title>Data filtering and clustering</title>
      <p id="Par21">After data pre-processing, users can filter their data tables according to a broad array of parameters, depending on the nature of their data and biological questions. These filtering functions can be applied in particular orders and combinations to suit the user’s specific needs. These functions include, among many others, filtering by statistical significance and/or the direction and magnitude of fold change, filtering genomic features by their type, performing set operations between different data tables and gene sets (for instance — intersections, differences, majority vote intersections, and so on) between tables, etc.</p>
      <p id="Par22">One of the powerful features of <italic>RNAlysis</italic> is the ability to easily extract gene lists from set operations applied to the user’s tables and gene sets, and use these lists in downstream analyses. Users can do this by applying a pre-defined set operation (like intersection or difference) or by hand-picking subsets of interest through an interactive graphical platform.</p>
      <p id="Par23">Finally, <italic>RNAlysis</italic> allows users to cluster genes based on the similarity of their expression patterns. <italic>RNAlysis</italic> supports an extensive selection of clustering algorithms, including distance-based clustering (K-Means, K-Medoids, Hierarchical clustering), density-based clustering (HDBSCAN) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], and ensemble-based clustering (a modified version of the CLICOM algorithm) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].</p>
      <p id="Par24">Moreover, <italic>RNAlysis</italic> provides users with a wide array of distance metrics for clustering analysis. This includes the implementation of distance metrics that were specially developed for biological applications, such as time-course gene expression data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], and distance metrics that were empirically found to best suit transcriptomics analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec6">
      <title>Modularity and building customized pipelines</title>
      <p id="Par25">Filtered data tables can be saved or loaded at any stage during the analysis. The operations performed on the data and their order will be automatically reflected in the output files' names. Additionally, any operation applied to the data can be undone with a single click, and <italic>RNAlysis</italic> displays the history of commands applied to each table in the order they were applied.</p>
      <p id="Par26">As mentioned earlier, users can “bundle” any of the functions <italic>RNAlysis</italic> offers into distinct Pipelines, which can then be applied in the same order and with the same parameters to any number of similar data tables. This helps users to save time and avoid mistakes and inconsistencies when analyzing a large number of datasets. Pipelines can also be exported and shared with other researchers, who can then use these Pipelines on any machine that installed <italic>RNAlysis</italic>. This feature makes analysis pipelines easier to report and share, increasing the reproducibility and transparency of bioinformatic results.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec7">
      <title>Enrichment analysis</title>
      <p id="Par27">After applying the analyses mentioned above to summarize data tables down to gene sets of interest, users can carry out enrichment analysis for those gene sets. Gene set enrichment analysis is a collection of methods for identifying classes of genes, biological processes, or pathways that are over- or under-represented in a gene set of interest [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Enrichment analysis is highly prevalent in RNA sequencing analysis since it allows researchers to associate a differentially-expressed gene set with underlying biological functions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p>
      <p id="Par28"><italic>RNAlysis</italic> supports multiple approaches and statistical methods for enrichment analysis, including classic gene set enrichment analysis, permutation tests [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], background-free enrichment analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], and enrichment for ordinal or continuous variables.</p>
      <p id="Par29"><italic>RNAlysis</italic> can automatically retrieve enrichment analysis annotations of all major model organisms from widely accepted databases such as Gene Ontology categories and KEGG pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. However, unlike many other analysis pipelines, <italic>RNAlysis</italic> also accepts annotations for user-defined attributes and groups (see Additional File <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1). This allows users to tailor their analyses to their specific needs and biological questions.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec8">
      <title>Documentation and accessibility</title>
      <p id="Par30">While <italic>RNAlysis</italic> can be operated entirely within a graphical interface, all the functions and features <italic>RNAlysis</italic> offers can also be imported and used in standard Python scripts, allowing users with coding experience to further automate and customize their bioinformatic analyses. Pipelines that are generated with the graphical interface can be imported and used through the programmatic interface and vice versa, maximizing the reproducibility and shareability of analyses performed with <italic>RNAlysis</italic>.</p>
      <p id="Par31">Moreover, whenever <italic>RNAlysis</italic> integrates with external tools and packages for tasks such as alignment or differential expression, <italic>RNAlysis</italic> will export the exact command line or R script used to produce the results, allowing all users to share the full details of their analysis.</p>
      <p id="Par32"><italic>RNAlysis</italic> includes extensive documentation to guide new and returning users. A user guide and a tutorial offer a bird’s eye view of the modules and features of <italic>RNAlysis</italic>, along with video demonstrations, usage examples, and recommended practices. A frequently asked questions page offers solutions to common questions and issues posed by users of <italic>RNAlysis</italic>. The remainder of the documentation provides a complete reference of the functions and features available in <italic>RNAlysis</italic>. Users can look up specific entries for a more thorough review of their theoretical background, use cases, and optional parameters.</p>
      <p id="Par33"><italic>RNAlysis</italic> can either be installed as a Python package on all standard operating systems, or downloaded as a stand-alone application, which does not require users to install any mandatory dependencies. This simplifies the acquisition process of <italic>RNAlysis</italic>, eliminating the initial barrier of entry for less computationally-oriented users.</p>
      <p id="Par34">The project is available as an open-source, public GitHub repository. Numerous test cases are also provided within the package, which are executed automatically every time the source code is updated, ensuring that data analysis with <italic>RNAlysis</italic> remains consistent and reliable.</p>
      <p id="Par35"><italic>RNAlysis</italic> is powered by various open-source projects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] which are installed automatically and used when needed.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec9">
    <title>Results</title>
    <p id="Par36">We examined the ability of <italic>RNAlysis</italic> to facilitate analyses of multiple different publicly available datasets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. First, we analyzed time-series gene expression data, using clustering analyses to group genes based on their expression pattern. Then, we demonstrated the analysis of multiple RNA sequencing datasets from raw FASTQ files, showing the applications of analysis Pipelines and set operations between datasets. A step-by-step tutorial of these analyses is available in the online <italic>RNAlysis</italic> documentation (also available as Additional File <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Tutorial).</p>
    <sec id="Sec10">
      <title>Analysis #1: Exploring gene expression patterns across the development of <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></title>
      <p id="Par37">In the first analysis, we examined a dataset describing average gene expression under different developmental stages of <italic>Caenorhabditis</italic>
<italic>elegans</italic> nematodes, derived from the control samples of many publicly available RNA sequencing experiments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>].</p>
      <p id="Par38">Exploratory data analysis revealed that the different developmental stages show the highest correlations between contiguous developmental stages (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A), and PCA uncovered a semi-circular pattern, with over 75% of the data’s variance explained by the first two principal components (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B). Interestingly, the first principal component arranges the samples by their relative germline content, with embryos and adult nematodes on one end, L1–L3 larvae on the other, and L4 larvae in between. The second principal component arranges the samples by their developmental stage, with embryos at the top of the graph and adults at the bottom.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Exploratory data analysis reveals patterns in time-series gene expression data. <bold>A</bold> Principal component analysis projection of the time-series data. Depicted are the first two principal components, explaining &gt; 75% of the variance in the data. Data was power-transformed and standardized before the analysis. <bold>B</bold> Pair-plot, depicting the pairwise Spearman correlation between each pair of samples, and a histogram of normalized gene expression in each sample. Each dot represents the log of normalized expression of a single gene</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12915_2023_1574_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
      <p id="Par39">Next, we extracted clustering results at three different resolutions by using exemplars from three different classes of clustering algorithms: a distance-based algorithm (K-Medoids) (Additional File <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figure S1), a density-based algorithm (HDBSCAN) (Additional File <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: Figure S2), and an ensemble-based algorithm (CLICOM) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). While one of the most challenging aspects of RNA sequencing clustering analysis is the requirement to specify in advance the number of clusters, <italic>RNAlysis</italic> provides unbiased clustering methods that can either estimate a good number of clusters to detect, or require no such input at all — instead specifying the smallest cluster size that would be of interest to the user.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Clustering analysis of time-series gene expression data. <bold>A</bold> Clustering analysis of the data using modified CLICOM clustering, using five underlying clustering setups, an evidence threshold of 50%, and a minimal cluster size of 75 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Clusters are sorted by their size. Each graph depicts the power-transformed and standardized expression of all genes in the cluster, with the center lines denoting the clusters’ means and standard deviations across developmental stages of <italic>C.</italic>
<italic>elegans</italic> nematodes. <bold>B</bold> PCA projection of the power-transformed and standardized gene expression data. Each dot represents a gene. The points are colored according to the cluster they belong in the CLICOM clustering result depicted in <bold>A</bold></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12915_2023_1574_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
      <p id="Par40">While the data examined here only contains a single entry for each experimental condition, <italic>RNAlysis</italic> is well suited for clustering analysis of replicate data, since it's able to cluster each batch of replicates separately and combine the results of those batches, resulting in more accurate and robust clustering results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p>
      <p id="Par41">Finally, we plotted the expression level of specific genes of interest under the different developmental stages (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A) and performed GO enrichment analysis on one of the clusters we previously detected, revealing a robust enrichment for neuropeptide signaling pathways (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>B).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Gene expression plots and enrichment analysis of time-series gene expression data. <bold>A</bold> Normalized gene expression values of the time-series data for the two sample genes <italic>oma-1</italic> (WBGene00003664) and <italic>skn-1</italic> (WBGene00004804). <bold>B</bold> GO enrichment ontology graph, depicting enrichment results for cluster #9 (genes whose expression decreases along development from L1s to adults) (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The graph depicts the hierarchical relationship between the GO terms. Each GO term was colored according to its log<sub>2</sub> (Fold Enrichment) score if it was statistically significant (<italic>q</italic>-value ≤ 0.05)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12915_2023_1574_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec11">
      <title>Analysis #2: Measuring the effect of stress on the expression of small RNA factors</title>
      <p id="Par42">In the second analysis, we analyzed three datasets that examined the effects of three different stress conditions (osmotic stress, heat shock, and starvation) on gene expression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. This is a replication of our previously published analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] done with an earlier version of <italic>RNAlysis</italic> (version 1.3.5, 2019), where the purpose was to examine the effects of stress exposure on the expression of small RNA factors. This analysis shows how <italic>RNAlysis</italic> facilitates answering highly specific biological questions in an intuitive manner.</p>
      <p id="Par43">We started the analysis with raw FASTQ files, applying adapter trimming, pseudo-alignment, transcript expression quantification, and differential expression analysis to the three datasets, all executed through the <italic>RNAlysis</italic> graphic interface.</p>
      <p id="Par44">Next, we examined the distribution of differentially expressed genes under each condition with a Volcano Plot (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>A) and extracted from each differential expression table the lists of significantly up-regulated and down-regulated genes. This step was automated by building and applying a Pipeline, allowing us to analyze all three tables in the exact same manner with the click of a button.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Analysis of stress-induced gene expression changes. <bold>A</bold> Volcano plot depicting differential expression results, comparing worms that experienced starvation (str) to worms that grew under normal conditions. Each dot represents a gene. Differentially expressed genes with log<sub>2</sub> (fold change) ≥ 1 were painted in red, and differentially expressed genes with log<sub>2</sub> (fold change) ≤  − 1 were painted in blue. <bold>B</bold> A proportional Venn Diagram depicting the intersections between genes that are significantly downregulated under heat shock, osmotic stress, or starvation, compared to their matching control samples. <bold>C</bold> Log<sub>2</sub> (Fold enrichment) score for a curated list of epigenetic genes, in the set of genes significantly downregulated under all stress conditions. The <italic>p</italic>-value for enrichment was calculated using 10,000 random gene sets identical in size to the tested group. *** indicates adj. <italic>p</italic>-value ≤ 0.001</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12915_2023_1574_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p>
      <p id="Par45">Following these filtering steps, we examined the intersection of the up- and down-regulated genes between the different stress conditions (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>B) and extracted the list of genes that are significantly up/down-regulated under all stress conditions. We then created an appropriate background set for enrichment analysis by calculating the union gene lists of all genes which are sufficiently expressed under at least one stress condition.</p>
      <p id="Par46">Finally, we ran an enrichment analysis on the stress-downregulated genes, measuring whether they are significantly enriched for a user-defined list of epigenetic-related genes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>C). We found the stress-downregulated genes to be significantly enriched for epigenetic-related genes, as previously shown [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Enrichment for user-defined attributes is a feature unique to <italic>RNAlysis</italic>, allowing users to answer highly specific biological questions. This means that the users are not limited to widely available datasets, but can directly analyze any gene sets and attributes of interest without the need to write any code.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec12">
    <title>Discussion</title>
    <p id="Par47"><italic>RNAlysis</italic> offers researchers a robust, scalable, and easy-to-use tool to analyze RNA sequencing data. <italic>RNAlysis</italic> was designed not only to be intuitive and approachable for new users, but also to provide a high degree of efficiency, control, and robustness to experienced bioinformaticians.</p>
    <p id="Par48">Other useful software tools for the analysis of RNA sequencing data exist (see Additional File <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1). For example, <italic>Galaxy</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>] is a web-based scientific analysis platform for the analysis of biological data. <italic>Galaxy</italic> offers many shared features with <italic>RNAlysis</italic>, including integration of existing analysis tools, extensive documentation, shareable pipelines, and the ability to filter, sort, and intersect data tables. Galaxy has a large following [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>] and supports a wide array of established tools from various fields of bioinformatics. Contrary to <italic>Galaxy</italic>, <italic>RNAlysis</italic> aims to simplify commonly used actions for RNA sequencing analysis in particular, such as filtering and set operations. This is done by providing users with dozens of ready-made filtering functions relevant to RNA sequencing data and supporting set operations on an arbitrary number of datasets with an intuitive, point-and-click interface. Moreover, <italic>RNAlysis</italic> offers analysis methods that are especially useful to RNA sequencing data, such as advanced clustering methods and enrichment analysis for user-defined attributes, which are not available on <italic>Galaxy</italic>.</p>
    <p id="Par49">Tools such as <italic>ARPIR</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] and <italic>NetSeekR</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>] can take users all the way from the alignment of reads and differential expression analysis through GO enrichment and other tertiary analyses such as gene network analysis. Other tools like <italic>ideal</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], <italic>PIVOT</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>], and <italic>DEBrowser</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>] provide users with a graphical interface to perform differential expression analysis and enrichment analysis.</p>
    <p id="Par50">While these tools allow less experienced bioinformaticians to perform basic transcriptomic analysis, they are limited in their capability to filter datasets, perform set operations between datasets, use more advanced clustering algorithms, or automate and streamline data analysis with pipelines. In contrast to these tools, <italic>RNAlysis</italic> is highly modular and customizable, allowing users to tailor their investigations to their biological questions through advanced data filtering, intersecting multiple datasets, and a high degree of control over analysis parameters at every stage of the process. Moreover, <italic>RNAlysis</italic> can analyze RNA sequencing experiments from start to finish since it supports pre-processing, alignment, and quantification utilities of FASTQ files.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec13">
    <title>Conclusions</title>
    <p id="Par51"><italic>RNAlysis</italic> offers a modular toolbox for RNA sequencing data analysis, with the unique combination of an intuitive graphical interface and highly customizable analysis workflows, making it distinct from many other RNA sequencing analysis tools.</p>
    <p id="Par52">We believe that the ability to build customized and reproducible analysis pipelines, combined with the user-friendly interface, will allow researchers to gain novel biological insights from RNA sequencing data easily.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec14">
    <title>Methods</title>
    <p id="Par53">For a detailed description of the analysis pipelines used to generate the results displayed here, see Additional File <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Tutorial.</p>
    <sec id="Sec15">
      <title>Statistical analysis</title>
      <p id="Par54">GO Enrichment analysis (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) was performed as follows: GO annotations were retrieved through the GO Solr search engine API called GOlr. Annotations were filtered using the parameters described in Additional File <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Tutorial: kept only annotations for <italic>C.</italic>
<italic>elegans</italic> (taxon ID 6239), excluded “NOT” annotations. Annotations were propagated using the ELIM algorithm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. <italic>P</italic>-values were calculated using the hypergeometric test, and corrected for multiple comparisons using the Benjamini/Yekutieli FDR method for general or negatively correlated tests [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>].</p>
      <p id="Par55">Enrichment for user-defined attributes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) was performed as follows: Annotations were generated as described in Additional File <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Tutorial. P-value was calculated using a permutation test, using 10,000 random gene groups identical in size to that of the examined group of differentially expressed genes. <italic>P</italic>-value was then calculated using the formula <italic>p</italic> = <italic>(successes</italic> + <italic>1)/(repeats</italic> + <italic>1)</italic>, where success are defined as randomized gene set with a proportion of positively-annotated genes equal to or larger than the proportion in the test set. This formula results in a positively-biased estimator of the real <italic>p</italic>-value (a conservative estimate of the <italic>p</italic>-value).</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec16">
    <title>Availability and requirements</title>
    <p id="Par56">
      <bold>Project name:</bold>
      <italic>RNAlysis.</italic>
    </p>
    <p id="Par57">
      <bold>Project home page:</bold>
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/GuyTeichman/RNAlysis">https://github.com/GuyTeichman/RNAlysis</ext-link>
    </p>
    <p id="Par58"><bold>Operating system(s):</bold> Platform independent</p>
    <p id="Par59"><bold>Programming language:</bold> Python 3</p>
    <p id="Par60"><bold>Other requirements:</bold> Python 3.7.9 or higher (optional), GraphViz 3.0 or higher (optional), kallisto 0.44.0 or higher (optional), bowtie2 2.3.5 or higher (optional), R 4.0.0 or higher (optional), Microsoft C++ Build Tools 14.0 or higher (optional, on Windows computers only), Perl 5.9 or higher (optional)</p>
    <p id="Par61"><bold>License:</bold> MIT</p>
    <p id="Par62">Any restrictions to use by non-academics: none</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Information</title>
    <sec id="Sec17">
      <p>
        <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1">
          <media xlink:href="12915_2023_1574_MOESM1_ESM.xlsx">
            <caption>
              <p><bold>Additional file 1: Table S1.</bold> Comparison between RNAlysis and other existing analysis tools.</p>
            </caption>
          </media>
        </supplementary-material>
        <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2">
          <media xlink:href="12915_2023_1574_MOESM2_ESM.pdf">
            <caption>
              <p><bold>Additional file 2:</bold> Tutorial.</p>
            </caption>
          </media>
        </supplementary-material>
        <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3">
          <media xlink:href="12915_2023_1574_MOESM3_ESM.pdf">
            <caption>
              <p><bold>Additional file 3: Figure S1.</bold> K-Medoids Clustering analysis of time-series gene expression data. Clustering analysis of the data using K-Medoids clustering, after selecting an appropriate number of clusters (K = 11) using the Gap Statistic method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. Clusters are sorted by their size. Each graph depicts the power-transformed and standardized expression of all genes in the cluster, with the center lines denoting the clusters' Medoids and standard deviations across developmental stages of <italic>C. elegans</italic> nematodes.</p>
            </caption>
          </media>
        </supplementary-material>
        <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4">
          <media xlink:href="12915_2023_1574_MOESM4_ESM.pdf">
            <caption>
              <p><bold>Additional file 4: Figure S2.</bold> HDBSCAN Clustering analysis of time-series gene expression data. Clustering analysis of the data using HDBSCAN clustering, with a minimal cluster size of 75 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Clusters are sorted by their size. Each graph depicts the power-transformed and standardized expression of all genes in the cluster, with the center lines denoting the clusters' means and standard deviations across developmental stages of <italic>C. elegans</italic> nematodes.</p>
            </caption>
          </media>
        </supplementary-material>
      </p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <glossary>
    <title>Abbreviations</title>
    <def-list>
      <def-item>
        <term>GUI</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par4">Graphical user interface</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>GO</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par5">Gene Ontology</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>PCA</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par6">Principal component analysis</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>RNA-Seq</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par7">RNA sequencing</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>MRN</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par8">Median ratio normalization</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>TMM</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par9">Trimmed mean of M-values</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>RLE</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par10">Relative log expression</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>WT</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par11">Wild type</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>KEGG</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par12">Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
    </def-list>
  </glossary>
  <fn-group>
    <fn>
      <p>
        <bold>Publisher's Note</bold>
      </p>
      <p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
    </fn>
    <fn>
      <p>Or Ganon, Netta Dunsky, and Shachar Shani contributed equally to this work.</p>
    </fn>
  </fn-group>
  <ack>
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <p>We thank all members of the Rechavi lab for fruitful discussions, feedback, and support.</p>
  </ack>
  <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
    <title>Authors’ contributions</title>
    <p>G.T., O.G., N.D., and S.S. conceived the software. G.T. designed and developed the software. D.C. and H.G. helped with the design of the software. D.C. created the figure illustrations. H.G. helped with testing the software. All authors helped with the writing of the paper. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
    <sec id="FPar1">
      <title>Authors’ information</title>
      <p id="Par63">G.T. (Twitter handle @Guyteichman)</p>
      <p id="Par64">O.G. (Twitter handle @ElegantNematode)</p>
      <p id="Par65">O.R. (Twitter handle @OdedRechavi)</p>
    </sec>
  </notes>
  <notes notes-type="funding-information">
    <title>Funding</title>
    <p>O.R. is grateful to funding from the Eric and Wendy Schmidt Fund for Strategic Innovation (Polymath Award #0140001000) and the generous support from the Morris Kahn foundation. G.T. is grateful to the Milner Foundation. The Rechavi lab is funded by ERC grant #335624 and the Israel Science Foundation (grant#1339/17).</p>
  </notes>
  <notes notes-type="data-availability">
    <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
    <p>The following previously published data sets were used:</p>
    <p>Dodd W, Tang L, Lone JC, Wimberly K, Wu CW, Consalvo C, Wright JE, Pujol N, Choe KP (2018) NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus ID GSE107704 (36). Role of SKN-1 in dpy-7 and osmotic gene induction.</p>
    <p>Finger F, Ottens F, Springhorn A, Drexel T, Proksch L, Metz S, Cochella L, Hoppe T (2019) NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus ID GSE124178 (37). RNA-seq: WT under proteotoxic stress conditions.</p>
    <p>Schreiner W, PPagliuso D, CGarrigues JM, Chen JS, Aalto AP, Pasquinelli AE (2019) NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus ID GSE132838 (38). RNA Sequencing of CTRL and Heat Stressed C. elegans [RNA-seq].</p>
  </notes>
  <notes>
    <title>Declarations</title>
    <notes id="FPar3">
      <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
      <p id="Par66">Not applicable.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes id="FPar4">
      <title>Consent for publication</title>
      <p id="Par67">Not applicable.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes id="FPar5" notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p id="Par68">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
    </notes>
  </notes>
  <ref-list id="Bib1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="CR1">
      <label>1.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Martin M. Cutadapt removes adapter sequences from high-throughput sequencing reads. EMBnet.journal. 2011;17(1):10–2 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://journal.embnet.org/index.php/embnetjournal/article/view/200/479">https://journal.embnet.org/index.php/embnetjournal/article/view/200/479</ext-link>. Cited 4 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR2">
      <label>2.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bray NL, Pimentel H, Melsted P, Pachter L. Near-optimal probabilistic RNA-seq quantification. Nat Biotechnol 2016 345. 2016;34(5):525–7 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nature.com/articles/nbt.3519">https://www.nature.com/articles/nbt.3519</ext-link>. Cited 4 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR3">
      <label>3.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Love MI, Huber W, Anders S. Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA-seq data with DESeq2. Genome Biol. 2014;15(12):1–21 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13059-014-0550-8">https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13059-014-0550-8</ext-link>. Cited 4 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR4">
      <label>4.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Soneson C, Love MI, Robinson MD. Differential analyses for RNA-seq: transcript-level estimates improve gene-level inferences. F1000Research. 2015;4:1521 /pmc/articles/PMC4712774/.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR5">
      <label>5.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Langmead B, Salzberg SL. Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2. Nat Methods 2012 94. 2012;9(4):357–9 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nature.com/articles/nmeth.1923">https://www.nature.com/articles/nmeth.1923</ext-link>. Cited 2 Feb 2023.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR6">
      <label>6.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Liao Y, Smyth GK, Shi W. featureCounts: an efficient general purpose program for assigning sequence reads to genomic features. Bioinformatics. 2014;30(7):923–30 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/bioinformatics/article/30/7/923/232889">https://academic.oup.com/bioinformatics/article/30/7/923/232889</ext-link>. Cited 2 Feb 2023.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR7">
      <label>7.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ritchie ME, Phipson B, Wu D, Hu Y, Law CW, Shi W, et al. limma powers differential expression analyses for RNA-sequencing and microarray studies. Nucleic Acids Res. 2015;43(7):e47–e47 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/nar/article/43/7/e47/2414268">https://academic.oup.com/nar/article/43/7/e47/2414268</ext-link>. Cited 5 Feb 2023.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR8">
      <label>8.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Law CW, Chen Y, Shi W, Smyth GK. Voom: Precision weights unlock linear model analysis tools for RNA-seq read counts. Genome Biol. 2014;15(2):1–17 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/gb-2014-15-2-r29">https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/gb-2014-15-2-r29</ext-link>. Cited 5 Feb 2023</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR9">
      <label>9.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bullard JH, Purdom E, Hansen KD, Dudoit S. Evaluation of statistical methods for normalization and differential expression in mRNA-Seq experiments. BMC Bioinformatics. 2010;11(1):1–13 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bmcbioinformatics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1471-2105-11-94">https://bmcbioinformatics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1471-2105-11-94</ext-link>. Cited 4 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR10">
      <label>10.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Robinson MD, Oshlack A. A scaling normalization method for differential expression analysis of RNA-seq data. Genome Biol. 2010;11(3):1–9 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/gb-2010-11-3-r25">https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/gb-2010-11-3-r25</ext-link>. Cited 4 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR11">
      <label>11.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Anders S, Huber W. Differential expression analysis for sequence count data. Genome Biol. 2010;11(10):1–12 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/gb-2010-11-10-r106">https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/gb-2010-11-10-r106</ext-link>. Cited 4 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR12">
      <label>12.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Maza E, Frasse P, Senin P, Bouzayen M, Zouine M. Comparison of normalization methods for differential gene expression analysis in RNA-Seq experiments: A matter of relative size of studied transcriptomes. Commun Integr Biol. 2013;6(6):e25849 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.4161/cib.25849">https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.4161/cib.25849</ext-link>. Cited 4 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR13">
      <label>13.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">McInnes L, Healy J, Astels S. hdbscan: Hierarchical density based clustering. J Open Source Softw. 2017;2(11):205 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.00205">http://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.00205</ext-link>. Cited 26 Jun 2020.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR14">
      <label>14.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mimaroglu S, Yagci M. CLICOM: Cliques for combining multiple clusterings. Expert Syst Appl [Internet]. 2012;39(2):1889–901. [cited 2020 Jul 9]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0957417411011705">https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0957417411011705</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR15">
      <label>15.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Son</surname>
            <given-names>YS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Baek</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A modified correlation coefficient based similarity measure for clustering time-course gene expression data</article-title>
        <source>Pattern Recognit Lett</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>29</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <fpage>232</fpage>
        <lpage>242</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.patrec.2007.09.015</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR16">
      <label>16.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jaskowiak PA, Campello RJGB, Costa IG. On the selection of appropriate distances for gene expression data clustering. BMC Bioinformatics. 2014;15(S2):S2 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bmcbioinformatics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1471-2105-15-S2-S2">https://bmcbioinformatics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1471-2105-15-S2-S2</ext-link>. Cited 26 Jun 2020.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR17">
      <label>17.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Subramanian A, Tamayo P, Mootha VK, Mukherjee S, Ebert BL, Gillette MA, et al. Gene set enrichment analysis: A knowledge-based approach for interpreting genome-wide expression profiles. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2005;102(43):15545–50 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/abs/10.1073/pnas.0506580102">https://www.pnas.org/doi/abs/10.1073/pnas.0506580102</ext-link>. Cited 4 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR18">
      <label>18.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kanehisa M, Goto S. KEGG: kyoto encyclopedia of genes and genomes. Nucleic Acids Res. 2000;28(1):27–30.Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/10592173/">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/10592173/</ext-link>. Cited 4 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR19">
      <label>19.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ashburner</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ball</surname>
            <given-names>CA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Blake</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Botstein</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Butler</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cherry</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Gene Ontology: tool for the unification of biology</article-title>
        <source>Nat Genet</source>
        <year>2000</year>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>25</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/75556</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 10802651?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10802651</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR20">
      <label>20.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Phipson B, Smyth GK. Permutation P-values should never be zero: Calculating exact P-values when permutations are randomly drawn. Stat Appl Genet Mol Biol. 2010;9(1):Article39 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.degruyter.com/document/doi/10.2202/1544-6115.1585/html">https://www.degruyter.com/document/doi/10.2202/1544-6115.1585/html</ext-link>. Cited 4 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR21">
      <label>21.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Eden E, Lipson D, Yogev S, Yakhini Z. Discovering Motifs in Ranked Lists of DNA Sequences. PLOS Comput Biol. 2007;3(3):e39 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/article?id=10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030039">https://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/article?id=10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030039</ext-link>. Cited 4 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR22">
      <label>22.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wagner F. The XL-mHG test for gene set enrichment. PeerJ Prepr [Internet]. 2017;5:e1962v3. [cited 2022 Nov 4]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/preprints/1962">https://peerj.com/preprints/1962</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR23">
      <label>23.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kanehisa M, Furumichi M, Sato Y, Kawashima M, Ishiguro-Watanabe M. KEGG for taxonomy-based analysis of pathways and genomes. Nucleic Acids Res. 2022;51(D1):D587–92 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/nar/advance-article/doi/10.1093/nar/gkac963/6775388">https://academic.oup.com/nar/advance-article/doi/10.1093/nar/gkac963/6775388</ext-link>. Cited 4 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR24">
      <label>24.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Carbon</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Douglass</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Good</surname>
            <given-names>BM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Unni</surname>
            <given-names>DR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Harris</surname>
            <given-names>NL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mungall</surname>
            <given-names>CJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The Gene Ontology resource: enriching a GOld mine</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
        <year>2021</year>
        <volume>49</volume>
        <issue>D1</issue>
        <fpage>D325</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkaa1113</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33290552</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR25">
      <label>25.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Virtanen P, Gommers R, Oliphant TE, Haberland M, Reddy T, Cournapeau D, et al. SciPy 1.0: fundamental algorithms for scientific computing in Python. Nat Methods. 2020;17(3):261–72 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41592-019-0686-2">https://www.nature.com/articles/s41592-019-0686-2</ext-link>. Cited 4 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR26">
      <label>26.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Heyer LJ, Kruglyak S, Yooseph S. Exploring expression data identification and analysis of coexpressed genes. Genome Res. 1999;9(11):1106–15 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genome.cshlp.org/content/9/11/1106.full">http://genome.cshlp.org/content/9/11/1106.full</ext-link>. Cited 26 Jun 2020.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR27">
      <label>27.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Harris CR, Millman KJ, van der Walt SJ, Gommers R, Virtanen P, Cournapeau D, et al. Array programming with NumPy. Nat 2020 5857825. 2020;585(7825):357–62. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-020-2649-2">https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-020-2649-2</ext-link>. Cited 4 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR28">
      <label>28.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hunter</surname>
            <given-names>JD</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Matplotlib: A 2D graphics environment</article-title>
        <source>Comput Sci Eng</source>
        <year>2007</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <fpage>90</fpage>
        <lpage>95</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/MCSE.2007.55</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR29">
      <label>29.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lam SK, Pitrou A, Seibert S. Numba: A LLVM-based Python JIT Compiler. In: Proceedings of LLVM-HPC 2015: 2nd Workshop on the LLVM Compiler Infrastructure in HPC - Held in conjunction with SC 2015: The International Conference for High Performance Computing, Networking, Storage and Analysis [Internet]. Association for Computing Machinery; 2015. [cited 2022 Nov 4]. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/2833157.2833162</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR30">
      <label>30.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mckinney</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Data Structures for Statistical Computing in Python</source>
        <year>2010</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR31">
      <label>31.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pedregosa F, Michel V, Grisel O, Blondel M, Prettenhofer P, et al. Scikit-learn: Machine Learning in Python. J Mach Learn Res. 2011;12(85):2825–30 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jmlr.org/papers/v12/pedregosa11a.html">http://jmlr.org/papers/v12/pedregosa11a.html</ext-link>. Cited 4 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR32">
      <label>32.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Waskom ML. seaborn: statistical data visualization. J Open Source Softw. 2021;6(60):3021 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.03021">https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.03021</ext-link>. Cited 4 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR33">
      <label>33.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Seabold S, Perktold J. statsmodels: Econometric and statistical modeling with Python. In: 9th Python in Science Conference [Internet]. 2010. [cited 2022 Nov 4]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://statsmodels.sourceforge.net/">http://statsmodels.sourceforge.net/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR34">
      <label>34.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lex</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gehlenborg</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Strobelt</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vuillemot</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pfister</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>UpSet: Visualization of intersecting sets</article-title>
        <source>IEEE Trans Vis Comput Graph</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>20</volume>
        <issue>12</issue>
        <fpage>1983</fpage>
        <lpage>1992</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TVCG.2014.2346248</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 26356912?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26356912</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR35">
      <label>35.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Davis P, Zarowiecki M, Arnaboldi V, Becerra A, Cain S, Chan J, et al. WormBase in 2022—data, processes, and tools for analyzing Caenorhabditis elegans. Genetics. 2022;220(4):iyac003 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/genetics/article/220/4/iyac003/6521733">https://academic.oup.com/genetics/article/220/4/iyac003/6521733</ext-link>. Cited 13 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR36">
      <label>36.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dodd W, Tang L, Lone JC, Wimberly K, Wu CW, Consalvo C, et al. A damage sensor associated with the cuticle coordinates three core environmental stress responses in caenorhabditis elegans. Genetics. 2018;208(4):1467–82 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29487136/">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29487136/</ext-link>. Cited 30 Nov 2020.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR37">
      <label>37.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Finger F, Ottens F, Springhorn A, Drexel T, Proksch L, Metz S, et al. Olfaction regulates organismal proteostasis and longevity via microRNA-dependent signalling Nature Metabolism. Nature Research. 2019;1:350–9 Available from: /pmc/articles/PMC6751085/?report=abstract. Cited 30 Nov 2020.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR38">
      <label>38.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Schreiner WP, Pagliuso DC, Garrigues JM, Chen JS, Aalto AP, Pasquinelli AE. Remodeling of the Caenorhabditis elegans non-coding RNA transcriptome by heat shock. Nucleic Acids Res. 2019;47(18):9829–41 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31396626/">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31396626/</ext-link>. Cited 30 Nov 2020.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR39">
      <label>39.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sloutsky R, Jimenez N, Swamidass SJ, Naegle KM. Accounting for noise when clustering biological data. Brief Bioinform [Internet]. 2013;14(4):423–36. [cited 2020 Jun 26]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/bib/article-abstract/14/4/423/192812">https://academic.oup.com/bib/article-abstract/14/4/423/192812</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR40">
      <label>40.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Houri-Zeevi L, Teichman G, Gingold H, Rechavi O. Stress resets ancestral heritable small RNA responses. eLife [Internet]. 2021;10. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://elifesciences.org/articles/65797">https://elifesciences.org/articles/65797</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR41">
      <label>41.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Goecks J, Nekrutenko A, Taylor J, Afgan E, Ananda G, Baker D, et al. Galaxy: a comprehensive approach for supporting accessible, reproducible, and transparent computational research in the life sciences. Genome Biol. 2010;11(8):1–13 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/gb-2010-11-8-r86">https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/gb-2010-11-8-r86</ext-link>. Cited 2 Feb 2023.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR42">
      <label>42.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Afgan E, Baker D, Batut B, Van Den Beek M, Bouvier D, Ech M, et al. The Galaxy platform for accessible, reproducible and collaborative biomedical analyses: 2018 update. Nucleic Acids Res. 2018;46(W1):W537-44 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/nar/article/46/W1/W537/5001157">https://academic.oup.com/nar/article/46/W1/W537/5001157</ext-link>. Cited 4 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR43">
      <label>43.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Spinozzi G, Tini V, Adorni A, Falini B, Martelli MP. ARPIR: automatic RNA-Seq pipelines with interactive report. BMC Bioinformatics. 2020;21(19):1–14 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bmcbioinformatics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12859-020-03846-2">https://bmcbioinformatics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12859-020-03846-2</ext-link>. Cited 4 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR44">
      <label>44.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Srivastava H, Ferrell D, Popescu GV. NetSeekR: a network analysis pipeline for RNA-Seq time series data. BMC Bioinformatics. 2022;23(1):1–14 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bmcbioinformatics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12859-021-04554-1">https://bmcbioinformatics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12859-021-04554-1</ext-link>. Cited 4 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR45">
      <label>45.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marini F, Linke J, Binder H. ideal: an R/Bioconductor package for interactive differential expression analysis. BMC Bioinformatics. 2020;21(1):1–16 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bmcbioinformatics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12859-020-03819-5">https://bmcbioinformatics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12859-020-03819-5</ext-link>. Cited 4 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR46">
      <label>46.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhu Q, Fisher SA, Dueck H, Middleton S, Khaladkar M, Kim J. PIVOT: Platform for interactive analysis and visualization of transcriptomics data. BMC Bioinformatics. 2018;19(6):1–8 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bmcbioinformatics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12859-017-1994-0">https://bmcbioinformatics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12859-017-1994-0</ext-link>. Cited 4 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR47">
      <label>47.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kucukural A, Yukselen O, Ozata DM, Moore MJ, Garber M. DEBrowser: Interactive differential expression analysis and visualization tool for count data 06 Biological Sciences 0604 Genetics 08 Information and Computing Sciences 0806 Information Systems. BMC Genomics. 2019;20(1):1–12 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bmcgenomics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12864-018-5362-x">https://bmcgenomics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12864-018-5362-x</ext-link>. Cited 4 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR48">
      <label>48.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Alexa ÃA, Rahnenführer J, Lengauer T. Improved scoring of functional groups from gene expression data by decorrelating GO graph structure. Bioinformatics. 2006;22(13):1600–7 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/bioinformatics/article-abstract/22/13/1600/193669">https://academic.oup.com/bioinformatics/article-abstract/22/13/1600/193669</ext-link>. Cited 14 Jul 2020.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR49">
      <label>49.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Benjamini Y, Yekutieli D. The control of the false discovery rate in multiple testing under dependency. Ann Stat. 2001;29(4):1165–88. Available from: 10.1214/aos/1013699998<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://projecteuclid.org/journals/annals-of-statistics/volume-29/issue-4/The-control-of-the-false-discovery-rate-in-multiple-testing/10.1214/aos/1013699998.full">https://projecteuclid.org/journals/annals-of-statistics/volume-29/issue-4/The-control-of-the-false-discovery-rate-in-multiple-testing/10.1214/aos/1013699998.full</ext-link>. Cited 29 Nov 2022.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR50">
      <label>50.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yan M, Ye K. Determining the Number of Clusters Using the Weighted Gap Statistic. Biometrics [Internet]. 2007;63(4):1031–7. [cited 2020 Jun 26]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.wiley.com/10.1111/j.1541-0420.2007.00784.x">http://doi.wiley.com/10.1111/j.1541-0420.2007.00784.x</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
