<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?origin publisher?>
<?FILEmeta_MCPRO100682 xml ?>
<?FILEmain xml ?>
<?FILEmain pdf ?>
<?FILEgr1 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr2 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr3 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr4 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr5 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr6 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr7 jpg ?>
<?FILEga1 jpg ?>
<?properties open_access?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Cell Proteomics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol Cell Proteomics</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Molecular &amp; Cellular Proteomics : MCP</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1535-9476</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1535-9484</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">10716774</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S1535-9476(23)00193-7</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mcpro.2023.100682</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100682</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Technological Innovation and Resources</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>IDPpub: Illuminating the Dark Phosphoproteome Through PubMed Mining</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1">
        <name>
          <surname>Savage</surname>
          <given-names>Sara R.</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
        <xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">‡</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2">
        <name>
          <surname>Zhang</surname>
          <given-names>Yaoyun</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
        <xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">‡</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3">
        <name>
          <surname>Jaehnig</surname>
          <given-names>Eric J.</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4">
        <name>
          <surname>Liao</surname>
          <given-names>Yuxing</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5">
        <name>
          <surname>Shi</surname>
          <given-names>Zhiao</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6">
        <name>
          <surname>Pham</surname>
          <given-names>Huy Anh</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7">
        <name>
          <surname>Xu</surname>
          <given-names>Hua</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8">
        <name>
          <surname>Zhang</surname>
          <given-names>Bing</given-names>
        </name>
        <email>bing.zhang@bcm.edu</email>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
        <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Lester and Sue Smith Breast Center, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, Texas, USA</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Molecular and Human Genetics, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, Texas, USA</aff>
      <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Melax Technologies Inc, Houston, Texas, USA</aff>
      <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Section of Biomedical Informatics and Data Science, School of Medicine, Yale University, Connecticut, USA</aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>For correspondence: Bing Zhang <email>bing.zhang@bcm.edu</email></corresp>
      <fn id="fn1">
        <label>‡</label>
        <p id="ntpara0010">These authors contributed equally to this work.</p>
      </fn>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>21</day>
      <month>11</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <month>1</month>
      <year>2024</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>21</day>
      <month>11</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>23</volume>
    <issue>1</issue>
    <elocation-id>100682</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>17</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© 2023 The Authors</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract id="abs0010">
      <p>Global phosphoproteomics experiments quantify tens of thousands of phosphorylation sites. However, data interpretation is hampered by our limited knowledge on functions, biological contexts, or precipitating enzymes of the phosphosites. This study establishes a repository of phosphosites with associated evidence in biomedical abstracts, using deep learning–based natural language processing techniques. Our model for illuminating the dark phosphoproteome through PubMed mining (IDPpub) was generated by fine-tuning BioBERT, a deep learning tool for biomedical text mining. Trained using sentences containing protein substrates and phosphorylation site positions from 3000 abstracts, the IDPpub model was then used to extract phosphorylation sites from all MEDLINE abstracts. The extracted proteins were normalized to gene symbols using the National Center for Biotechnology Information gene query, and sites were mapped to human UniProt sequences using ProtMapper and mouse UniProt sequences by direct match. Precision and recall were calculated using 150 curated abstracts, and utility was assessed by analyzing the CPTAC (Clinical Proteomics Tumor Analysis Consortium) pan-cancer phosphoproteomics datasets and the PhosphoSitePlus database. Using 10-fold cross validation, pairs of correct substrates and phosphosite positions were extracted with an average precision of 0.93 and recall of 0.94. After entity normalization and site mapping to human reference sequences, an independent validation achieved a precision of 0.91 and recall of 0.77. The IDPpub repository contains 18,458 unique human phosphorylation sites with evidence sentences from 58,227 abstracts and 5918 mouse sites in 14,610 abstracts. This included evidence sentences for 1803 sites identified in CPTAC studies that are not covered by manually curated functional information in PhosphoSitePlus. Evaluation results demonstrate the potential of IDPpub as an effective biomedical text mining tool for collecting phosphosites. Moreover, the repository (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://idppub.ptmax.org" id="PC_linkwFgyMZUVzu">http://idppub.ptmax.org</ext-link>), which can be automatically updated, can serve as a powerful complement to existing resources.</p>
    </abstract>
    <abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0015">
      <title>Graphical Abstract</title>
      <fig id="undfig1" position="anchor">
        <graphic xlink:href="ga1"/>
      </fig>
    </abstract>
    <abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0020">
      <title>Highlights</title>
      <p>
        <list list-type="simple" id="ulist0010">
          <list-item id="u0010">
            <label>•</label>
            <p id="p0010">IDPpub utilizes BioBERT to extract phosphorylation sites.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item id="u0015">
            <label>•</label>
            <p id="p0015">Alignment of extracted phosphorylation sites to reference sequences.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item id="u0020">
            <label>•</label>
            <p id="p0020">Identified evidence sentences for tumor-associated sites.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item id="u0025">
            <label>•</label>
            <p id="p0025">Web portal to explore evidence sentences for phosphorylation sites.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </p>
    </abstract>
    <abstract abstract-type="teaser" id="abs0025">
      <title>In Brief</title>
      <p>Phosphorylation sites have important functions but are poorly annotated in public databases. We developed IDPpub, a pipeline that uses BioBERT to extract phosphorylation sites from biomedical abstracts. We align the sites to human and mouse reference sequences to facilitate computational applications and intersection with mass spectrometry experiments. The evidence sentences can be used to identify regulating enzymes and biological functions. All data are available in a web portal for easy search.</p>
    </abstract>
    <kwd-group id="kwrds0010">
      <title>Keywords</title>
      <kwd>phosphoproteomics</kwd>
      <kwd>text mining</kwd>
      <kwd>natural language processing</kwd>
      <kwd>deep learning</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
  </article-meta>
  <def-list>
    <title>Abbreviations</title>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0035">BERT</term>
      <def>
        <p>Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0045">CPTAC</term>
      <def>
        <p>Clinical Proteomics Tumor Analysis Consortium</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0055">NCBI</term>
      <def>
        <p>National Center for Biotechnology Information</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0065">NLP</term>
      <def>
        <p>natural language processing</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0075">PTM</term>
      <def>
        <p>post-translational modification</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
  </def-list>
</front>
<body>
  <p id="p0030">Phosphorylation, the addition of a phosphate group to a substrate protein, is an essential component of biological signaling. This process, which affects over 75% of all human proteins (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>), frequently modulates a protein’s stability or function. Advances in mass spectrometry and phosphopeptide enrichment methods, such as immobilized affinity chromatography, now enable the high-throughput identification of the phosphorylation events in cells and tissues. Phosphosites from these high-throughput experiments are frequently archived in databases such as UniProt (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>) and PhosphoSitePlus (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). The same databases that collect high-throughput sites often also provide manual curation of sites that have been well studied and have a known impact on the function of a protein from the scientific literature. Because manual curation is time consuming, it cannot keep pace with the explosion of reported biological research findings, and therefore, relatively few sites in these databases have annotated biological functions. In fact, only 4% of the sites in PhosphoSitePlus have been annotated with a function. The “dark” phosphoproteome makes determining how sites of interest identified in a high-throughput experiment contribute to a clinical or biological phenotype a challenge.</p>
  <p id="p0035">As a complement to manual curation, natural language processing (NLP) techniques can extract research findings from the literature text automatically. Previous works have built several information extraction systems to extract the protein substrate and phosphosite location of the phosphorylation event. Both rule-based (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) and machine learning–based approaches (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>) have been used. The rule-based RLIMS-P system utilized a comprehensive set of syntactic–semantic patterns for extraction of phosphorylation events (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Another system leveraged the patterns in RLIMS-P, trigger words such as “phosphorylation” and “autophosphorylated,” and other context features to build an automatic Support Vector Machine model (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). However, these systems were built to find specific subsets of phosphorylation sites, such as those mentioned with the phosphorylating kinase (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) or those involved in protein–protein interactions (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). In addition, the results from these models are not normalized for use in downstream computational analyses.</p>
  <p id="p0040">Because there are no open source methods for extracting phosphorylation sites with evidence sentences, we built a new NLP-based system to address the aforementioned challenges. The current state-of-art deep learning framework for NLP, Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers (BERT), provides a model that embeds linguistic and domain knowledge and that can be fine-tuned for downstream tasks, such as relation extraction. BioBERT (BERT for biomedical text mining) was initiated using the original model of BERT and was fine-tuned using biomedical abstracts in MEDLINE and full texts in PubMed Central (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>).</p>
  <p id="p0045">We used a gold standard training dataset of 3000 biomedical abstracts that were curated with substrate protein and corresponding site position pairs to fine-tune BioBERT models. Specific low-throughput sites studied through conventional targeted methods are more likely to be listed in the abstract of articles than are sites identified in high-throughput studies. As such, abstracts from low-throughput studies are more likely to mention functionally relevant phosphorylated sites.</p>
  <p id="p0050">This information extraction system was then applied to all abstracts in the entire NLM MEDLINE database. Mentions of protein substrates and site locations were normalized to standardized nomenclature using gene/protein synonyms and regular expressions. Thus, a repository of phosphosites on substrates mentioned in each abstract was generated, together with the evidence sentences. Finally, a web portal was constructed to provide a service to search phosphorylation information using substrates and site locations as queries.</p>
  <sec id="sec1">
    <title>Experimental Procedures</title>
    <sec id="sec1.1">
      <title>Abstract Processing</title>
      <p id="p0055">Titles and text of abstracts for both training and prediction were downloaded from the National Library of Medicine (MEDLINE version 2020-12-14) and prepared as follows.</p>
      <sec id="sec1.1.1">
        <title>Preprocessing</title>
        <p id="p0060">In the preprocessing step, abstracts were split into sentences by sentence boundary detection using the OpenNLP sentence detector in CLAMP (Melax Tech), version 1.6.6 (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Tokens were identified in the sentence and separated by the default tokenization tool based on lexicons and regular expressions, and parts of speech were tagged with the default OpenNLP tagger in CLAMP.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec1.1.2">
        <title>Named Entity Recognition</title>
        <p id="p0065">Named entity recognition (NER) was performed using CLAMP to classify tokens into two semantic types: gene/protein name and phosphosites.</p>
        <sec id="sec1.1.2.1">
          <title>Gene/Protein Name Recognition</title>
          <p id="p0070">Gene/protein names were recognized using a hybrid method. An API for the NER software BERN (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) was first used for deep learning–based gene/protein recognition. Next, the synonyms collected from PhosphoSitePlus were used as a complementary resource for dictionary lookup-based gene/protein recognition. A token was classified with the term “Substrate” if it was recognized by either BERN or the dictionary lookup.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec1.1.2.2">
          <title>Site Recognition</title>
          <p id="p0075">The amino acid positions of phosphosites were recognized by regular expressions consisting of cue words and numbers, such as serine-20, serine residues 20, S20, etc. (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). A token was classified with the term “Phosphosite” if it fit any of the regular expressions.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Keywords of different site expressions</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Serine</th><th>Threonine</th><th>Tyrosine</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>S</td><td>t</td><td>y</td></tr><tr><td>ser</td><td>thr</td><td>tyr</td></tr><tr><td>serines</td><td>threonines</td><td>tyrosines</td></tr><tr><td>serine</td><td>threonine</td><td>tyrosine</td></tr><tr><td>ps</td><td>pt</td><td>py</td></tr><tr><td>pser</td><td>pthr</td><td>ptyr</td></tr><tr><td>pserines</td><td>pthreonines</td><td>ptyrosines</td></tr><tr><td>pserine</td><td>pthreonine</td><td>ptyrosine</td></tr><tr><td>phosphos</td><td>phosphot</td><td>phosphoy</td></tr><tr><td>phosphoser</td><td>phosphothr</td><td>phosphotyr</td></tr><tr><td>phosphoserines</td><td>phosphothreonines</td><td>phosphotyrosines</td></tr><tr><td>phosphoserine</td><td>phosphothreonine</td><td>phosphotyrosine</td></tr><tr><td>phosphorusserines</td><td>phosphorusthreonines</td><td>phosphorustyrosines</td></tr><tr><td>phosphorusserine</td><td>phosphorusthreonine</td><td>phosphorustyrosine</td></tr><tr><td>serinesresidues</td><td>threoninesresidues</td><td>tyrosinesresidues</td></tr><tr><td>serineresidues</td><td>threonineresidues</td><td>tyrosineresidues</td></tr><tr><td>serinesresidue</td><td>threoninesresidue</td><td>tyrosinesresidue</td></tr><tr><td>serineresidue</td><td>threonineresidue</td><td>tyrosineresidue</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.2">
      <title>Training Data Annotation</title>
      <p id="p0080">Using the regulatory sites file from PhosphoSitePlus and the kinase–substrate relationships in Signor (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>) as a guide, we randomly selected 3000 biomedical abstracts that mentioned a phosphorylation site. To prepare a positive set of phosphosites on substrate proteins, a relationship between the correct “Substrate” and “Phosphosite” within the same sentence in an abstract was manually annotated using CLAMP. Token boundaries for the correct substrate and phosphosite were adjusted if the NER process did not correctly extract the token. A negative set was generated from all other tokens classified as “Substrate” within the same sentence as a token classified “Phosphosite.” If the candidate substrate and/or phosphosite were also mentioned in the abstract title, then the title was added to the end of the sentence. For each unique “Substrate” and “Phosphosite” pair in each sentence, the token labeled “Substrate” was replaced with the word “@SUBSTRATE$” and the token labeled “Phosphosite” was replaced with the word “@PHOSPHOSITE$”.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.3">
      <title>Fine-Tuning BioBERT for Relation Extraction</title>
      <p id="p0085">The set of sentences containing positive and negative substrate and phosphosite pairs was used to train BioBERT (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>) to classify a relationship between a potential substrate and a potential phosphosite. Ten-fold cross validation was used to fine tune BioBERT with a maximum length of 150, batch size of 32, 3 epochs, and a learning rate of 5 × 10<sup>−5</sup>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.4">
      <title>Model Validation</title>
      <p id="p0090">From the regulatory sites file from PhosphoSitePlus and the kinase–substrate relationships in Signor, we randomly selected an additional 150 biomedical abstracts that mentioned a phosphorylation site and were not used for training. These abstracts were processed with the same method as those used for training.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.5">
      <title>Concept Normalization and Postprocessing</title>
      <p id="p0095">The protein substrates and phosphosites were normalized to standard forms. Substrates were normalized to gene symbols by using the first result from the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) gene search API. First, common description words such as “human,” “mutant,” “wild type,” “recombinant,” and “endogenous” were removed from the identified term. Then the modified term AND “human [Organism]” was submitted to the gene search API. For the mouse search, “mouse” was also removed from any identified term. Then the modified term AND “10090[Taxonomy ID]” was submitted to the gene search API.</p>
      <p id="p0100">Phosphosites were normalized to the unified form of the single letter amino acid code followed by the number location. For example, both “serine-20” and “serine residue 20” were normalized to S20 using regular expressions. If an amino acid was not extracted as part of the phosphosite entity, all preceding words in the sentence were searched using regular expressions for any form of “serine,” “tyrosine,” or “threonine.” Phosphosites were discarded if no site position was identified or if an S, T, or Y was followed by a 0 (<italic>e.g</italic>., S003).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.6">
      <title>ProtMapper Filtering</title>
      <p id="p0105">Normalized phosphorylation sites were submitted to ProtMapper (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>) for mapping to human reference protein sequences using the default parameters. Sites were discarded if ProtMapper indicated “NO_MAPPING_FOUND” or if ProtMapper was unable to process the site. For comparison with PhosphoSitePlus, the site positions mapped to the human reference sequences were used.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.7">
      <title>Mouse site Filtering</title>
      <p id="p0110">PubTator (NCBI) (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) was used to identify abstracts with the mouse species annotation (taxonomy ID: 10090). Predicted protein substrates for these abstracts were submitted to the NCBI gene search for mouse gene IDs as described in the “<italic>Concept normalization and postprocessing</italic>” section. Mouse protein sequences were acquired from SwissProt in October 2023, and ID mapping was performed using the AnnotationDbi R package (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) and org.Mm.eg.db (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Mouse phosphorylation sites were filtered to those with an exact amino acid match in the protein sequence at the position identified in the sentence.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.8">
      <title>Kinase and Phosphatase Annotation</title>
      <p id="p0115">Human protein kinases were downloaded from KinBase (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://kinase.com/web/current/kinbase/genes/SpeciesID/9606/" id="intref0015">http://kinase.com/web/current/kinbase/genes/SpeciesID/9606/</ext-link>) (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) and SwissProt (keyword:“Kinase [KW-0418]” AND reviewed:yes AND organism:“<italic>Homo sapiens</italic> (Human) [9606]”) (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>) in November 2021. Human phosphatases were downloaded from DEPOD (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) and filtered to those with an “active” status and in a protein phosphatase family (AP, CDC25, DUSP, EYA, FCP, HP1, HP2, LMWPTP, NagD, PPM, PPP, PTP, RTR1, and SSU72) in November 2021. Mouse protein kinases were downloaded from KinBase (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://kinase.com/web/current/kinbase/genes/SpeciesID/10090/" id="intref0020">http://kinase.com/web/current/kinbase/genes/SpeciesID/10090/</ext-link>) in October 2023. Mouse protein phosphatases were downloaded from SwissProt (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) in October 2023 with the keyword KW-0904 (keyword:KW-0904 AND reviewed:true AND model_organism:10090). All extracted genes from sentences with a positive prediction for a phosphorylation site were submitted to the NCBI gene search as described in the “<italic>Concept normalization and postprocessing” section</italic>. Genes were annotated as kinases or phosphatases if the gene symbol after normalization matched a kinase or phosphatase gene symbol in the downloaded lists.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.9">
      <title>Comparison to PhosphoSitePlus</title>
      <p id="p0120">Phosphorylation site information and the regulatory site tables were downloaded from PhosphoSitePlus (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>) in January 2023. The kinase–substrate table was downloaded from PhosphoSitePlus in September 2023. All tables were filtered to the human organism and a “-p” modification. For kinase–substrate comparison, autophosphorylation events were excluded.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.10">
      <title>Comparison to Clinical Proteomics Tumor Analysis Consortium Phosphoproteomics Data</title>
      <p id="p0125">Clinical Proteomics Tumor Analysis Consortium (CPTAC) pan-cancer data were acquired from Ref. (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Spearman correlation between ING5-T152 phosphorylation abundance and HALLMARK activity scores and between AKT1 activity scores and all phosphorylation sites were performed using LinkedOmicsKB (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.11">
      <title>Website Development</title>
      <p id="p0130">Finalized results were stored in an SQLite database (version 3.7.17). The website was developed with PHP (version 5.6) and Slim framework (version 3) on the backend. The frontend was based on Fomantic UI (version 2.8), and search results are displayed in a table with Bootstrap-table (version 1.21). The graph was built with D3.js (version 7).</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2">
    <title>Results</title>
    <sec id="sec2.1">
      <title>Deep Learning NLP Model Generation to Automatically Extract Phosphosites</title>
      <p id="p0135">The NLP pipeline (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>) to generate a model identifying phosphosites on proteins consists of multiple steps: (1) preprocessing abstracts to extract tokens from sentences, (2) named entity recognition (NER) to identify protein names and amino acid positions for corresponding sites, (3) manual corpus annotation to curate a gold standard positive training set, and (4) relation recognition and fine-tuning of a pretrained deep learning NLP method to automatically identify the substrate–phosphosite pairs.<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p><bold>Model pipeline to extract phosphorylation sites from abstracts.</bold> Abstract text was separated into sentences and tokenized, and named entity recognition was performed using regular expressions and BERN to label potential substrates and potential site positions. Substrate and site pairs were encoded in each sentence, which was then classified using BioBERT. BioBERT, Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers for biomedical text mining.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p>
      <p id="p0140">To create a gold standard list of phosphosites mentioned in abstracts to use for training and validation, we downloaded the Regulatory Sites file from PhosphoSitePlus and the sites with known kinases from Signor. We used only human sites and generated a list containing the amino acid location of the phosphosite, the gene symbol of its substrate protein, and the associated PubMed Manuscript ID. We randomly selected 3000 abstracts from this list to use for model training.</p>
      <p id="p0145">The abstracts were broken into sentences and tokens using CLAMP, and NER was used to label tokens as protein names or site positions. Regular expressions and dictionary look-up were used to identify site positions, whereas BERN was used to identify protein names. Manual annotation of the corpus was performed to identify which site position belonged to which protein within a single sentence. All other candidate site positions and candidate substrates were used as negative relationships. There were 16,729 sentences for positive relationships and 27,591 sentences for negative relationships. We used 10-fold cross validation to fine-tune BioBERT to generate 10 models that could classify a relationship between a potential substrate and potential site. The 10 models had an average precision of 92.7%, recall of 94.3%, specificity of 95.5%, and F1 score of 93.5% (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>).<fig id="fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p><bold>Model performance for identifying the correct substrate and site pairs in 10-fold cross validation.</bold><italic>Boxes</italic> indicate median and interquartile range for the results from 10 models.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p>
      <p id="p0150">We manually curated an additional 150 abstracts with phosphosites and used these for independent model validation. Majority voting of the 10 models performed slightly better than the individual model with the best cross F1 score (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). Unanimous voting of the 10 models had the best precision but worst recall (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>).<fig id="fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p><bold>Independent performance on correctly identifying phosphorylation sites from 150 abstracts.</bold> Three different methods were used to combine the results from 10 different models. A substrate and site in a sentence was classified as a positive if six or more models classified it as 1 (majority), all 10 models classified it as 1 (unanimous), or if the best performing model classified it as 1 (best).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.2">
      <title>Normalization of Phosphosite Representation to Human Sequences</title>
      <p id="p0155">After extracting phosphosites from the literature, the sites need to be normalized to have a consistent format for downstream analysis. Site positions were transformed using regular expressions to a single letter amino acid code followed by the numerical position (<italic>e.g.</italic>, S315). To prioritize sites that could be mapped to human genes, protein names were transformed to gene symbols using the top human result from NCBI. After normalization, the model precision on the validation set for individual phosphosites in specific PMIDs was 0.58 with a recall of 0.81. This validation involves an additional component beyond the BioBERT classification step as both the correct substrate and site must be extracted and the correct gene symbol must be selected for the substrate. For example, in the sentence “Rsk was phosphorylated on Thr573 by ERK1,” majority voting by the 10 fine-tuned BioBERT models might correctly classify Thr573 as a phosphorylation site on the substrate Rsk. However, an error may occur when transforming Rsk to the gene symbol RPS6KA1 and Thr573 to T573. Indeed, most of the precision loss at this step was due to the incorrect selection of gene symbols from the originally identified terms. To improve the precision of the results, we used ProtMapper to map the identified phosphosite to human reference protein sequences. Any site that could not be mapped to the reference was discarded. This improved precision to 0.91 with a slight drop in recall to 0.77.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.3">
      <title>Data Statistics of the Extracted Substrate–Site Pairs</title>
      <p id="p0160">To systematically illuminate the dark phosphoproteome, we used our model, named IDPpub, to extract phosphorylation sites in all MEDLINE abstracts. We identified phosphorylation sites in 253,443 abstracts. After entity normalization and ProtMapper filtering, we extracted from 58,227 abstracts 18,458 unique phosphorylation sites that could be mapped to human proteins. These covered 46% of the human phosphorylation sites with low-throughput evidence in PhosphoSitePlus and 57% of the human sites with regulatory information (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). Importantly, we extracted sentences for 11,634 sites that did not have regulatory information in or were not linked to low-throughput publications by PhosphoSitePlus.<fig id="fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p><bold>Numbers of sites with annotated regulatory information from PhosphoSitePlus, low-throughput publications from PhosphoSitePlus, and extracted sentences from IDPpub</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p>
      <p id="p0165">The CPTAC studies on 10 cancer types have identified over 125,000 human phosphorylation sites using mass spectrometry (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Only 3% of these sites have annotated regulatory information in PhosphoSitePlus. The human phosphorylation sites extracted from abstracts by IDPpub included 4117 CPTAC phosphorylation sites, 1803 of which have no annotated regulatory information. In addition, extracted sentences may describe roles in disease that are not captured in PhosphoSitePlus. For example, DOCK1-Y1811 has no annotated regulatory information in PhosphoSitePlus but has a role in cell growth and invasion in glioblastoma according to the extracted publication (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). In addition, ING5-T152 is regulated by the cell cycle (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) and involved in tumor cell proliferation. This site was positively correlated with proliferation-related cell signatures across multiple cancer types (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). Some additional examples are found in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.<fig id="fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p><bold>Spearman’s correlation between ING5 T152 phosphorylation abundance and the HALLMARK E2F Target score in four CPTAC cancer studies.</bold> CPTAC, Clinical Proteomics Tumor Analysis Consortium.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Examples of extracted phosphorylation site evidence not curated in PhosphoSitePlus for phosphosites identified in CPTAC studies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Substrate</th><th>Site</th><th>PMID</th><th>Sentence</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>DOCK1</td><td>Y1811</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="22080864" id="intref0035">22080864</ext-link></td><td>Here, we report that PDGFRα signaling in glioblastomas leads to Src-dependent phosphorylation of the guanine nucleotide exchange factor <bold>Dock180</bold> at <bold>tyrosine 1811 (Dock180(Y1811))</bold> that results in activation of the GTPase Rac1 and subsequent cell growth and invasion</td></tr><tr><td>ING5</td><td>T152</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25860957" id="intref0040">25860957</ext-link></td><td>In summary we identified a phosphorylation site at <bold>threonine 152</bold> of I<bold>NG5</bold> that is cell cycle regulated, and we observed that <bold>ING5</bold> is necessary for tumor cell proliferation, without any apparent dependency on the tumor suppressor p53</td></tr><tr><td>ZNF148</td><td>S306</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32060966" id="intref0045">32060966</ext-link></td><td>The clinical analysis indicates that SDHB deficiency is associated with elevated <bold>ZNF148</bold> levels, and <bold>ZNF148-S306</bold> phosphorylation level displays a positive correlation with poor prognosis in GIST patients</td></tr><tr><td>PXN</td><td>S178</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32064167" id="intref0050">32064167</ext-link></td><td>Hepatitis B virus X protein promotes tumor invasion and poor prognosis in hepatocellular carcinoma <italic>via</italic> phosphorylation of <bold>paxillin</bold> at <bold>Serine 178</bold> by activation of the c-Jun NH2-terminal kinase</td></tr><tr><td>ITPRID2</td><td>S92</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="26947549" id="intref0055">26947549</ext-link></td><td>From these results, we demonstrate that phospho-<bold>SSFA2 (pS92)</bold> is related to the prognosis of early resected lung adenocarcinomas</td></tr><tr><td>TMIGD2</td><td>S220</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="27838321" id="intref0060">27838321</ext-link></td><td>Trans-homophilic dimerization of <bold>IGPR-1</bold> stimulates the phosphorylation of <bold>serine 220 (Ser220)</bold>, which is required for <bold>IGPR-1</bold> to regulate endothelial barrier function and angiogenesis</td></tr><tr><td>NES</td><td>T315</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="28002641" id="intref0065">28002641</ext-link></td><td><bold>Nestin</bold> phosphorylation at <bold>threonines 315</bold> and 1299 correlates with proliferation and metastasis of human pancreatic cancer</td></tr><tr><td>EPHA2</td><td>S897</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30412282" id="intref0070">30412282</ext-link></td><td><italic>In vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> experiments revealed that <bold>EPHA2</bold> mutations could lead to ligand independent phosphorylation of <bold>Ser897,</bold> and promote lymphatic metastasis of ICC, in which NOTCH1 signaling pathway played an important role</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Identified substrates and sites are noted in bold.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.4">
      <title>Extracted Sentences Support Conclusions From Phosphoproteomics Experiments</title>
      <p id="p0170">Phosphoproteomics data can be used as a readout of the activity of kinases and phosphatases, the enzymes responsible for adding or removing phosphate groups. We correlated all phosphorylation site abundances with AKT1 activity scores in the CPTAC pan-cancer datasets to identify potential substrates of AKT1 in cancer. Based on the meta <italic>p</italic> value of the association across 10 CPTAC cancer cohorts, the top associated site was AKT1S1 T246, which is a marker of AKT1 activity (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) and contributes to the activity score. The third best correlated site, AFDN S1799 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>), had no current annotation in relation to AKT1 in either PhosphositePlus (Cell Signaling Technology) or Signor. In contrast, IDPpub extracted a sentence from a study identifying AFDN S1799 as a target of AKT in breast cancer cells (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). There are many similar examples connecting a phosphorylation site identified in the CPTAC data to a regulatory kinase that has not been associated with the site in PhosphoSitePlus (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<fig id="fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p><bold>Spearman’s correlation between AFDN S1799 phosphorylation abundance and AKT1 kinase activity scores in four CPTAC cancer studies.</bold> CPTAC, Clinical Proteomics Tumor Analysis Consortium.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr6"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Examples of kinases for phosphorylation sites not curated in PhosphoSitePlus but extracted by IDPpub</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Kinase</th><th>Substrate</th><th>Site position</th><th>Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>AKT</td><td>AFDN</td><td>S1799</td><td align="char">24269953</td></tr><tr><td>IKKβ</td><td>MTDH</td><td>S298</td><td align="char">25849741</td></tr><tr><td>CDK1</td><td>PRC1</td><td>T470</td><td align="char">17438553</td></tr><tr><td>CDK5</td><td>PPP1R1B</td><td>T75</td><td align="char">1295672,<break/>1474424,<break/>1546412,<break/>22820052</td></tr><tr><td>ERK</td><td>ZNF148</td><td>S306</td><td align="char">32060966</td></tr><tr><td>GSK3β</td><td>KIF1A</td><td>S402</td><td align="char">33067366</td></tr><tr><td>PKA</td><td>NOS1</td><td>S1417</td><td align="char">23012472</td></tr><tr><td>CaMKII</td><td>NOS1</td><td>S852</td><td align="char">33121174</td></tr><tr><td>FYN</td><td>G6PD</td><td>Y401</td><td align="char">32863204</td></tr><tr><td>GSK3β</td><td>IKZF1</td><td>S391</td><td align="char">32807499</td></tr><tr><td>TrkB</td><td>APP</td><td>Y762</td><td align="char">32782380</td></tr><tr><td>GSK3β</td><td>NPM1</td><td>T95</td><td align="char">32686519</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
      <p id="p0175">To support the identification of regulatory information from sentences, we further annotated all kinases and phosphatases in the sentences. We identified 20,614 co-occurrences between a kinase and a phosphorylation site in 29,080 sentences. About 20% of the co-occurrences between kinases and phosphorylation sites represented known kinase–substrate relationships from PhosphoSitePlus. Furthermore, these co-occurrences covered 31% of the known human kinase–substrate relationships in PhosphoSitePlus.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.5">
      <title>Extension to Model Organisms</title>
      <p id="p0180">While human phosphorylation sites are the most widely studied, information on phosphorylation sites on model organisms is also important. We used PubTator to identify species information for the 253,443 abstracts with extracted phosphorylation sites. Over half (131,435) of the abstracts were annotated with human, whereas the second most common species was mouse (Taxonomy ID: 10090) with 59,719 abstracts. Fewer than 5% of the abstracts were annotated with other model species. We performed the post-processing steps for the abstracts annotated with mouse to identify mouse gene IDs and protein sequences. We filtered for any sites with an exact match between the site position extracted from the sentence and the mouse protein sequence for that gene. After filtering, we found 5918 phosphorylation sites in 14,610 abstracts.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.6">
      <title>Repository</title>
      <p id="p0185">We generated a searchable repository of all phosphorylation sites extracted from abstracts, which can be accessed at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://idppub.ptmax.org" id="PC_linkJilmGpIydx">http://idppub.ptmax.org</ext-link> (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>). We provide three versions of the extracted sites in the web portal. The first is the set of phosphorylation sites aligned to human proteins. The second is the set of phosphorylation sites that match mouse proteins. The third is the full results without gene normalization, and these results are annotated with taxonomy information from PubTator so that they can be filtered for specific species. For each version, a user can search for an individual gene, an individual single site on a gene, or a list of sites. The web portal provides a bar plot illustrating the number of sentences containing each site and a table of extracted sentences with links to the publications. The substrate, the phosphosite, and any co-occurring kinases and phosphatases are highlighted in each sentence. The sentences can be further searched for the exact match of terms, such as “apoptosis” or “tumor,” which could be used to filter for function or disease relations.<fig id="fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p><bold>Example of the IDPpub web portal results for MTDH</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr7"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec3">
    <title>Discussion</title>
    <p id="p0190">Mass spectrometry–based phosphoproteomics profiling offers tremendous potential for biological discoveries, but interpretation of phosphoproteomics sites identified from such studies is hampered by our limited knowledge on functions, biological contexts, or precipitating enzymes of the phosphosites. Extracting what is known from the literature is time consuming and often requires advanced biological knowledge. This study takes a hybrid approach combining deep learning–based NLP models and domain knowledge–based rules to automatically extract substrates, the positions of phosphorylated amino acids on these substrates, and corresponding evidence sentences from biomedical abstracts.</p>
    <p id="p0195">The evidence sentences extracted can quickly be assessed for potential biological context without scanning entire articles and can also point users to interesting articles for further reading. After identifying a set of phosphosites associated with a phenotype, scientists are currently limited to the functional information in manually curated databases such as PhosphoSitePlus. The literature must be searched for information not yet present in curated databases for all other sites individually. With IDPpub, users can quickly find additional evidence from all PubMed abstracts for phosphosites in bulk. Similarly, manually curated kinase–substrate information is poor in databases, with phosphatase–substrate information even more minimal. We have added annotations for kinases and phosphatases that co-occur in the same sentence as phosphorylation sites. While a co-occurrence does not necessarily indicate a true relationship, these annotations can help identify potential regulating enzymes.</p>
    <p id="p0200">We developed IDPpub to be as accurate as possible while also prioritizing high recall as sentences containing false-positive relationships can be easily discarded upon manual review. However, IDPpub could still be improved in future iterations. While the model is reasonably accurate in selecting the correct substrate for a phosphorylation site in a sentence, the normalization to a gene symbol is still challenging. This is partly because of nonunique names for proteins. For example, “PDK1” may refer to either 3-phosphoinositide-dependent protein kinase-1 (protein name PDK1, gene symbol <italic>PDPK1</italic>) or pyruvate dehydrogenase kinase 1 (gene symbol <italic>PDK1</italic>). In addition, accuracy of selecting the correct gene symbol is also diminished by inaccurate boundary detection of the NER step. For example, the model may identify “CRK” as the substrate instead of the full string “CRK-II.” This issue accounts for the drop in performance between the initial cross validation and validation of the BioBERT step on an additional 150 abstracts. For the training data, manual curation included setting the correct boundaries for both substrates and sites within a sentence to optimize the training of the relation extraction task. For the 150 test abstracts, we did not adjust the NER-defined boundaries as that would not be feasible to apply to the full database for prediction. In the future, correct boundary detection and identification of substrates in a sentence can be improved using new models (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>).</p>
    <p id="p0205">Improvements could also be made for extracting the correct site position. MESH terms could be used to filter biomedical articles to avoid false recognition of cell or chemical names, such as T-4 cells, that have a similar naming convention to the notations used for designating amino acid positions that are phosphosites. Also, normalizing the location of a site is still a major issue in the field of phosphoproteomics. Site localization is typically reported based on a reference protein sequence, which may come from one of several different sequence databases and can vary over time and between different protein isoforms. Manually searching the literature for a site identified in a phosphoproteomics experiment is a challenge because the manuscripts studying that site may list a completely different position that could even be over 100 amino acids away. For example, Bailey <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) described phosphorylation of tau on T149 and T153, which correspond to numbering on isoform 8 but are analogous to T466 and T470 on the canonical tau isoform. In IDPpub, we align the sites to the human UniProt sequences using ProtMapper. This improves consistency with PhosphoSitePlus but may not easily be applied to nonhuman studies or those where other human protein sequence databases are used as references. Indeed, identifying the species associated with phosphorylation sites mentioned in an abstract is a significant challenge, even from a manual reading. In our study, we aligned the sites to protein sequences from human and mouse, which were associated with 50% and 20% of the abstracts containing extracted phosphorylation sites, respectively. Furthermore, we provided a table that includes all sites extracted from sentences without alignment, along with the PubTator-annotated species information for the corresponding abstracts. This table can be valuable for filtering phosphosites in organisms beyond human and mouse.</p>
    <p id="p0210">The utility of IDPpub can be extended through the mining of full biomedical texts, which will increase the number of extracted sites and evidence sentences. Importantly, IDPpub can be automatically updated with newly published articles, providing continual utility to the community. Moreover, IDPpub can be modified with new regular expressions to capture additional post-translational modifications (PTMs). The ability to quickly filter primary literature for manual review enhances the usability of the data from high-throughput studies measuring various types of PTMs. Moving forward, we will also develop new models to identify and normalize other important elements from the sentences containing extracted PTM sites, such as the enzyme manipulating the PTM and the regulatory function of the modification. These enhancements will facilitate downstream analyses such as functional enrichment of a set of phosphorylation sites. Furthermore, with the accurate identification of enzyme–substrate relationships, we can further refine the analysis of binding motifs for regulatory enzymes.</p>
    <p id="p0215">In summary, the current implementation of IDPpub and its search tools are valuable complements to existing phosphorylation information portals. Ongoing improvements will further contribute to a deeper understanding of the phosphoproteome and other PTMomes.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec4">
    <title>Data Availability</title>
    <p id="p0220">All identified phosphosites and associated sentences can be searched and browsed at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://idppub.ptmax.org" id="PC_linkV5BPnkd2jB">http://idppub.ptmax.org</ext-link>. The whole dataset can also be downloaded from the website through the download link.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
    <title>Conflict of interest</title>
    <p id="p0225">The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ref-list id="cebib0010">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="bib1">
      <label>1</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sharma</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>D’Souza</surname>
            <given-names>R.C.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tyanova</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schaab</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wiśniewski</surname>
            <given-names>J.R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cox</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Ultradeep human phosphoproteome reveals a distinct regulatory nature of Tyr and Ser/Thr-based signaling</article-title>
        <source>Cell Rep.</source>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <year>2014</year>
        <fpage>1583</fpage>
        <lpage>1594</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25159151</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib2">
      <label>2</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <collab>UniProt Consortium</collab>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>UniProt: the universal protein knowledgebase in 2021</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>49</volume>
        <year>2021</year>
        <fpage>D480</fpage>
        <lpage>D489</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33237286</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib3">
      <label>3</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hornbeck</surname>
            <given-names>P.V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Murray</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kornhauser</surname>
            <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Latham</surname>
            <given-names>V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Skrzypek</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>PhosphoSitePlus, 2014: mutations, PTMs and recalibrations</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>43</volume>
        <year>2015</year>
        <fpage>D512</fpage>
        <lpage>D520</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25514926</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib4">
      <label>4</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Torii</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Arighi</surname>
            <given-names>C.N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Q.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>C.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vijay-Shanker</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>RLIMS-P 2.0: a generalizable rule-based information extraction system for literature mining of protein phosphorylation information</article-title>
        <source>IEEE/ACM Trans. Comput. Biol. Bioinform.</source>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <year>2015</year>
        <fpage>17</fpage>
        <lpage>29</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26357075</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib5">
      <label>5</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Raja</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Natarajan</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Mining protein phosphorylation information from biomedical literature using NLP parsing and support vector machines</article-title>
        <source>Comput. Methods Programs Biomed.</source>
        <volume>160</volume>
        <year>2018</year>
        <fpage>57</fpage>
        <lpage>64</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29728247</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib6">
      <label>6</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Elangovan</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pires</surname>
            <given-names>D.E.V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Davis</surname>
            <given-names>M.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Verspoor</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Large-scale protein-protein post-translational modification extraction with distant supervision and confidence calibrated BioBERT</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinform.</source>
        <volume>23</volume>
        <year>2022</year>
        <fpage>4</fpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib7">
      <label>7</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yoon</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>So</surname>
            <given-names>C.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>BioBERT: a pre-trained biomedical language representation model for biomedical text mining</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <volume>36</volume>
        <year>2020</year>
        <fpage>1234</fpage>
        <lpage>1240</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31501885</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib8">
      <label>8</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Soysal</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jiang</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pakhomov</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Clamp - a toolkit for efficiently building customized clinical natural language processing pipelines</article-title>
        <source>J. Am. Med. Inform. Assoc.</source>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <year>2018</year>
        <fpage>331</fpage>
        <lpage>336</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29186491</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib9">
      <label>9</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>So</surname>
            <given-names>C.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jeon</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jeong</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Choi</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A neural named entity recognition and multi-type normalization tool for biomedical text mining</article-title>
        <source>IEEE Access</source>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <year>2019</year>
        <fpage>73729</fpage>
        <lpage>73740</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib10">
      <label>10</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Licata</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lo Surdo</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Iannuccelli</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Palma</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Micarelli</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Perfetto</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>SIGNOR 2.0, the SIGnaling Network open resource 2.0: 2019 update</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>48</volume>
        <year>2020</year>
        <fpage>D504</fpage>
        <lpage>D510</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31665520</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib11">
      <label>11</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11">
        <comment>[preprint]</comment>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bachman</surname>
            <given-names>J.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sorger</surname>
            <given-names>P.K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gyori</surname>
            <given-names>B.M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Assembling a corpus of phosphoproteomic annotations using ProtMapper to normalize site information from databases and text mining</article-title>
        <source>bioRxiv</source>
        <year>2022</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/822668</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib12">
      <label>12</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wei</surname>
            <given-names>C.-H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Allot</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Leaman</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>Z.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>PubTator central: automated concept annotation for biomedical full text articles</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>47</volume>
        <year>2019</year>
        <fpage>W587</fpage>
        <lpage>W593</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31114887</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib13">
      <label>13</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pagès</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Carlson</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Falcon</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>AnnotationDbi: manipulation of SQLite-based annotations in bioconductor. R package version 1.62.2</article-title>
        <source>Bioconductor</source>
        <year>2023</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18129/B9.bioc.AnnotationDbi</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib14">
      <label>14</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Carlson</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>org.Mm.eg.db: genome wide annotation for mouse. R package version 3.8.2</article-title>
        <source>Bioconductor</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18129/B9.bioc.org.Mm.eg.db</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib15">
      <label>15</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Manning</surname>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Whyte</surname>
            <given-names>D.B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Martinez</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hunter</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sudarsanam</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The protein kinase complement of the human genome</article-title>
        <source>Science</source>
        <volume>298</volume>
        <year>2002</year>
        <fpage>1912</fpage>
        <lpage>1934</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12471243</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib16">
      <label>16</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Damle</surname>
            <given-names>N.P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Köhn</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The human DEPhOsphorylation Database DEPOD: 2019 update</article-title>
        <source>Database</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/database/baz133</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib17">
      <label>17</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17">
        <article-title>UniProt: the universal protein knowledgebase in 2023</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>51</volume>
        <year>2023</year>
        <fpage>D523</fpage>
        <lpage>D531</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36408920</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib18">
      <label>18</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dou</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Da Veiga Leprevost</surname>
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Geffen</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Calinawan</surname>
            <given-names>A.P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Aguet</surname>
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Proteogenomic data and resources for pan-cancer analysis</article-title>
        <source>Cancer Cell</source>
        <volume>41</volume>
        <year>2023</year>
        <fpage>1397</fpage>
        <lpage>1406</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37582339</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib19">
      <label>19</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liao</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Savage</surname>
            <given-names>S.R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dou</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shi</surname>
            <given-names>Z.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yi</surname>
            <given-names>X.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jiang</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A proteogenomics data-driven knowledge base of human cancer</article-title>
        <source>Cell Syst.</source>
        <volume>14</volume>
        <year>2023</year>
        <fpage>777</fpage>
        <lpage>787.e5</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37619559</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib20">
      <label>20</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Feng</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>K.-W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>X.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cheng</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Activation of Rac1 by Src-dependent phosphorylation of Dock180(Y1811) mediates PDGFRα-stimulated glioma tumorigenesis in mice and humans</article-title>
        <source>J. Clin. Invest.</source>
        <volume>121</volume>
        <year>2011</year>
        <fpage>4670</fpage>
        <lpage>4684</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22080864</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib21">
      <label>21</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Linzen</surname>
            <given-names>U.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lilischkis</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pandithage</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schilling</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ullius</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lüscher-Firzlaff</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>ING5 is phosphorylated by CDK2 and controls cell proliferation independently of p53</article-title>
        <source>PLoS One</source>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <year>2015</year>
        <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0123736</object-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib22">
      <label>22</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kovacina</surname>
            <given-names>K.S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>G.Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bae</surname>
            <given-names>S.S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Guzzetta</surname>
            <given-names>A.W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schaefer</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Birnbaum</surname>
            <given-names>M.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Identification of a proline-rich Akt substrate as a 14-3-3 binding partner</article-title>
        <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
        <volume>278</volume>
        <year>2003</year>
        <fpage>10189</fpage>
        <lpage>10194</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12524439</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib23">
      <label>23</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Elloul</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kedrin</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Knoblauch</surname>
            <given-names>N.W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Beck</surname>
            <given-names>A.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Toker</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The adherens junction protein afadin is an AKT substrate that regulates breast cancer cell migration</article-title>
        <source>Mol. Cancer Res.</source>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <year>2014</year>
        <fpage>464</fpage>
        <lpage>476</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24269953</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib24">
      <label>24</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Allot</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Peng</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wei</surname>
            <given-names>C.-H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Phan</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>Z.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>LitVar: a semantic search engine for linking genomic variant data in PubMed and PMC</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>46</volume>
        <year>2018</year>
        <fpage>W530</fpage>
        <lpage>W536</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29762787</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib25">
      <label>25</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bailey</surname>
            <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Covy</surname>
            <given-names>J.P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Melrose</surname>
            <given-names>H.L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rousseau</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Watkinson</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Knight</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>LRRK2 phosphorylates novel tau epitopes and promotes tauopathy</article-title>
        <source>Acta Neuropathol.</source>
        <volume>126</volume>
        <year>2013</year>
        <fpage>809</fpage>
        <lpage>827</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24113872</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
  <ack id="ack0010">
    <title>Acknowledgments</title>
    <p id="p0230">This work was supported by the <funding-source id="gs2"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000002</institution-id><institution>National Institutes of Health</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> grants from the <funding-source id="gs4"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000054</institution-id><institution>National Cancer Institute</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (grant nos.: U24 CA271076 and R01 CA245903, by <funding-source id="gs6"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100004917</institution-id><institution>Cancer Prevention &amp; Research Institute of Texas</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> Awards RR160027 and RP220050, and funding from the McNair Medical Institute at The <funding-source id="gs8"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100001234</institution-id><institution>Robert and Janice McNair Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>.</p>
    <sec id="sec5">
      <title>Funding and additional information</title>
      <p id="p0235">B. Z. is a <funding-source id="gs5"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100004917</institution-id><institution>Cancer Prevention &amp; Research Institute of Texas</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> scholar in cancer research and a McNair scholar.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec6">
      <title>Author contributions</title>
      <p id="p0240">S. R. S., E. J. J., and B. Z. conceptualization; Y. Z. and H. X. methodology; Y. Z., Y. L., Z. S., and H. A. P. software; S. R. S. and Y. Z. validation; S. R. S. and Y. Z. formal analysis; S. R. S. investigation; H. X. resources; S. R. S. and E. J. J. data curation; S. R. S. and Y. Z. writing–original draft; E. J. J., Y. L., Z. S., and B. Z. writing–review &amp; editing; S. R. S. visualization; H. X. and B. Z. supervision; B. Z. project administration; H. X. and B. Z. funding acquisition.</p>
    </sec>
  </ack>
</back>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?origin publisher?>
<?FILEmeta_MCPRO100682 xml ?>
<?FILEmain xml ?>
<?FILEmain pdf ?>
<?FILEgr1 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr2 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr3 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr4 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr5 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr6 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr7 jpg ?>
<?FILEga1 jpg ?>
<?properties open_access?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Cell Proteomics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol Cell Proteomics</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Molecular &amp; Cellular Proteomics : MCP</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1535-9476</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1535-9484</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">10716774</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S1535-9476(23)00193-7</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mcpro.2023.100682</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100682</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Technological Innovation and Resources</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>IDPpub: Illuminating the Dark Phosphoproteome Through PubMed Mining</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1">
        <name>
          <surname>Savage</surname>
          <given-names>Sara R.</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
        <xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">‡</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2">
        <name>
          <surname>Zhang</surname>
          <given-names>Yaoyun</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
        <xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">‡</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3">
        <name>
          <surname>Jaehnig</surname>
          <given-names>Eric J.</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4">
        <name>
          <surname>Liao</surname>
          <given-names>Yuxing</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5">
        <name>
          <surname>Shi</surname>
          <given-names>Zhiao</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6">
        <name>
          <surname>Pham</surname>
          <given-names>Huy Anh</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7">
        <name>
          <surname>Xu</surname>
          <given-names>Hua</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8">
        <name>
          <surname>Zhang</surname>
          <given-names>Bing</given-names>
        </name>
        <email>bing.zhang@bcm.edu</email>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
        <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Lester and Sue Smith Breast Center, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, Texas, USA</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Molecular and Human Genetics, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, Texas, USA</aff>
      <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Melax Technologies Inc, Houston, Texas, USA</aff>
      <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Section of Biomedical Informatics and Data Science, School of Medicine, Yale University, Connecticut, USA</aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>For correspondence: Bing Zhang <email>bing.zhang@bcm.edu</email></corresp>
      <fn id="fn1">
        <label>‡</label>
        <p id="ntpara0010">These authors contributed equally to this work.</p>
      </fn>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>21</day>
      <month>11</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <month>1</month>
      <year>2024</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>21</day>
      <month>11</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>23</volume>
    <issue>1</issue>
    <elocation-id>100682</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>17</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© 2023 The Authors</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract id="abs0010">
      <p>Global phosphoproteomics experiments quantify tens of thousands of phosphorylation sites. However, data interpretation is hampered by our limited knowledge on functions, biological contexts, or precipitating enzymes of the phosphosites. This study establishes a repository of phosphosites with associated evidence in biomedical abstracts, using deep learning–based natural language processing techniques. Our model for illuminating the dark phosphoproteome through PubMed mining (IDPpub) was generated by fine-tuning BioBERT, a deep learning tool for biomedical text mining. Trained using sentences containing protein substrates and phosphorylation site positions from 3000 abstracts, the IDPpub model was then used to extract phosphorylation sites from all MEDLINE abstracts. The extracted proteins were normalized to gene symbols using the National Center for Biotechnology Information gene query, and sites were mapped to human UniProt sequences using ProtMapper and mouse UniProt sequences by direct match. Precision and recall were calculated using 150 curated abstracts, and utility was assessed by analyzing the CPTAC (Clinical Proteomics Tumor Analysis Consortium) pan-cancer phosphoproteomics datasets and the PhosphoSitePlus database. Using 10-fold cross validation, pairs of correct substrates and phosphosite positions were extracted with an average precision of 0.93 and recall of 0.94. After entity normalization and site mapping to human reference sequences, an independent validation achieved a precision of 0.91 and recall of 0.77. The IDPpub repository contains 18,458 unique human phosphorylation sites with evidence sentences from 58,227 abstracts and 5918 mouse sites in 14,610 abstracts. This included evidence sentences for 1803 sites identified in CPTAC studies that are not covered by manually curated functional information in PhosphoSitePlus. Evaluation results demonstrate the potential of IDPpub as an effective biomedical text mining tool for collecting phosphosites. Moreover, the repository (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://idppub.ptmax.org" id="PC_linkwFgyMZUVzu">http://idppub.ptmax.org</ext-link>), which can be automatically updated, can serve as a powerful complement to existing resources.</p>
    </abstract>
    <abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0015">
      <title>Graphical Abstract</title>
      <fig id="undfig1" position="anchor">
        <graphic xlink:href="ga1"/>
      </fig>
    </abstract>
    <abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0020">
      <title>Highlights</title>
      <p>
        <list list-type="simple" id="ulist0010">
          <list-item id="u0010">
            <label>•</label>
            <p id="p0010">IDPpub utilizes BioBERT to extract phosphorylation sites.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item id="u0015">
            <label>•</label>
            <p id="p0015">Alignment of extracted phosphorylation sites to reference sequences.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item id="u0020">
            <label>•</label>
            <p id="p0020">Identified evidence sentences for tumor-associated sites.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item id="u0025">
            <label>•</label>
            <p id="p0025">Web portal to explore evidence sentences for phosphorylation sites.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </p>
    </abstract>
    <abstract abstract-type="teaser" id="abs0025">
      <title>In Brief</title>
      <p>Phosphorylation sites have important functions but are poorly annotated in public databases. We developed IDPpub, a pipeline that uses BioBERT to extract phosphorylation sites from biomedical abstracts. We align the sites to human and mouse reference sequences to facilitate computational applications and intersection with mass spectrometry experiments. The evidence sentences can be used to identify regulating enzymes and biological functions. All data are available in a web portal for easy search.</p>
    </abstract>
    <kwd-group id="kwrds0010">
      <title>Keywords</title>
      <kwd>phosphoproteomics</kwd>
      <kwd>text mining</kwd>
      <kwd>natural language processing</kwd>
      <kwd>deep learning</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
  </article-meta>
  <def-list>
    <title>Abbreviations</title>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0035">BERT</term>
      <def>
        <p>Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0045">CPTAC</term>
      <def>
        <p>Clinical Proteomics Tumor Analysis Consortium</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0055">NCBI</term>
      <def>
        <p>National Center for Biotechnology Information</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0065">NLP</term>
      <def>
        <p>natural language processing</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0075">PTM</term>
      <def>
        <p>post-translational modification</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
  </def-list>
</front>
<body>
  <p id="p0030">Phosphorylation, the addition of a phosphate group to a substrate protein, is an essential component of biological signaling. This process, which affects over 75% of all human proteins (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>), frequently modulates a protein’s stability or function. Advances in mass spectrometry and phosphopeptide enrichment methods, such as immobilized affinity chromatography, now enable the high-throughput identification of the phosphorylation events in cells and tissues. Phosphosites from these high-throughput experiments are frequently archived in databases such as UniProt (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>) and PhosphoSitePlus (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). The same databases that collect high-throughput sites often also provide manual curation of sites that have been well studied and have a known impact on the function of a protein from the scientific literature. Because manual curation is time consuming, it cannot keep pace with the explosion of reported biological research findings, and therefore, relatively few sites in these databases have annotated biological functions. In fact, only 4% of the sites in PhosphoSitePlus have been annotated with a function. The “dark” phosphoproteome makes determining how sites of interest identified in a high-throughput experiment contribute to a clinical or biological phenotype a challenge.</p>
  <p id="p0035">As a complement to manual curation, natural language processing (NLP) techniques can extract research findings from the literature text automatically. Previous works have built several information extraction systems to extract the protein substrate and phosphosite location of the phosphorylation event. Both rule-based (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) and machine learning–based approaches (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>) have been used. The rule-based RLIMS-P system utilized a comprehensive set of syntactic–semantic patterns for extraction of phosphorylation events (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Another system leveraged the patterns in RLIMS-P, trigger words such as “phosphorylation” and “autophosphorylated,” and other context features to build an automatic Support Vector Machine model (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). However, these systems were built to find specific subsets of phosphorylation sites, such as those mentioned with the phosphorylating kinase (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) or those involved in protein–protein interactions (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). In addition, the results from these models are not normalized for use in downstream computational analyses.</p>
  <p id="p0040">Because there are no open source methods for extracting phosphorylation sites with evidence sentences, we built a new NLP-based system to address the aforementioned challenges. The current state-of-art deep learning framework for NLP, Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers (BERT), provides a model that embeds linguistic and domain knowledge and that can be fine-tuned for downstream tasks, such as relation extraction. BioBERT (BERT for biomedical text mining) was initiated using the original model of BERT and was fine-tuned using biomedical abstracts in MEDLINE and full texts in PubMed Central (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>).</p>
  <p id="p0045">We used a gold standard training dataset of 3000 biomedical abstracts that were curated with substrate protein and corresponding site position pairs to fine-tune BioBERT models. Specific low-throughput sites studied through conventional targeted methods are more likely to be listed in the abstract of articles than are sites identified in high-throughput studies. As such, abstracts from low-throughput studies are more likely to mention functionally relevant phosphorylated sites.</p>
  <p id="p0050">This information extraction system was then applied to all abstracts in the entire NLM MEDLINE database. Mentions of protein substrates and site locations were normalized to standardized nomenclature using gene/protein synonyms and regular expressions. Thus, a repository of phosphosites on substrates mentioned in each abstract was generated, together with the evidence sentences. Finally, a web portal was constructed to provide a service to search phosphorylation information using substrates and site locations as queries.</p>
  <sec id="sec1">
    <title>Experimental Procedures</title>
    <sec id="sec1.1">
      <title>Abstract Processing</title>
      <p id="p0055">Titles and text of abstracts for both training and prediction were downloaded from the National Library of Medicine (MEDLINE version 2020-12-14) and prepared as follows.</p>
      <sec id="sec1.1.1">
        <title>Preprocessing</title>
        <p id="p0060">In the preprocessing step, abstracts were split into sentences by sentence boundary detection using the OpenNLP sentence detector in CLAMP (Melax Tech), version 1.6.6 (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Tokens were identified in the sentence and separated by the default tokenization tool based on lexicons and regular expressions, and parts of speech were tagged with the default OpenNLP tagger in CLAMP.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec1.1.2">
        <title>Named Entity Recognition</title>
        <p id="p0065">Named entity recognition (NER) was performed using CLAMP to classify tokens into two semantic types: gene/protein name and phosphosites.</p>
        <sec id="sec1.1.2.1">
          <title>Gene/Protein Name Recognition</title>
          <p id="p0070">Gene/protein names were recognized using a hybrid method. An API for the NER software BERN (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) was first used for deep learning–based gene/protein recognition. Next, the synonyms collected from PhosphoSitePlus were used as a complementary resource for dictionary lookup-based gene/protein recognition. A token was classified with the term “Substrate” if it was recognized by either BERN or the dictionary lookup.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec1.1.2.2">
          <title>Site Recognition</title>
          <p id="p0075">The amino acid positions of phosphosites were recognized by regular expressions consisting of cue words and numbers, such as serine-20, serine residues 20, S20, etc. (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). A token was classified with the term “Phosphosite” if it fit any of the regular expressions.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Keywords of different site expressions</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Serine</th><th>Threonine</th><th>Tyrosine</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>S</td><td>t</td><td>y</td></tr><tr><td>ser</td><td>thr</td><td>tyr</td></tr><tr><td>serines</td><td>threonines</td><td>tyrosines</td></tr><tr><td>serine</td><td>threonine</td><td>tyrosine</td></tr><tr><td>ps</td><td>pt</td><td>py</td></tr><tr><td>pser</td><td>pthr</td><td>ptyr</td></tr><tr><td>pserines</td><td>pthreonines</td><td>ptyrosines</td></tr><tr><td>pserine</td><td>pthreonine</td><td>ptyrosine</td></tr><tr><td>phosphos</td><td>phosphot</td><td>phosphoy</td></tr><tr><td>phosphoser</td><td>phosphothr</td><td>phosphotyr</td></tr><tr><td>phosphoserines</td><td>phosphothreonines</td><td>phosphotyrosines</td></tr><tr><td>phosphoserine</td><td>phosphothreonine</td><td>phosphotyrosine</td></tr><tr><td>phosphorusserines</td><td>phosphorusthreonines</td><td>phosphorustyrosines</td></tr><tr><td>phosphorusserine</td><td>phosphorusthreonine</td><td>phosphorustyrosine</td></tr><tr><td>serinesresidues</td><td>threoninesresidues</td><td>tyrosinesresidues</td></tr><tr><td>serineresidues</td><td>threonineresidues</td><td>tyrosineresidues</td></tr><tr><td>serinesresidue</td><td>threoninesresidue</td><td>tyrosinesresidue</td></tr><tr><td>serineresidue</td><td>threonineresidue</td><td>tyrosineresidue</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.2">
      <title>Training Data Annotation</title>
      <p id="p0080">Using the regulatory sites file from PhosphoSitePlus and the kinase–substrate relationships in Signor (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>) as a guide, we randomly selected 3000 biomedical abstracts that mentioned a phosphorylation site. To prepare a positive set of phosphosites on substrate proteins, a relationship between the correct “Substrate” and “Phosphosite” within the same sentence in an abstract was manually annotated using CLAMP. Token boundaries for the correct substrate and phosphosite were adjusted if the NER process did not correctly extract the token. A negative set was generated from all other tokens classified as “Substrate” within the same sentence as a token classified “Phosphosite.” If the candidate substrate and/or phosphosite were also mentioned in the abstract title, then the title was added to the end of the sentence. For each unique “Substrate” and “Phosphosite” pair in each sentence, the token labeled “Substrate” was replaced with the word “@SUBSTRATE$” and the token labeled “Phosphosite” was replaced with the word “@PHOSPHOSITE$”.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.3">
      <title>Fine-Tuning BioBERT for Relation Extraction</title>
      <p id="p0085">The set of sentences containing positive and negative substrate and phosphosite pairs was used to train BioBERT (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>) to classify a relationship between a potential substrate and a potential phosphosite. Ten-fold cross validation was used to fine tune BioBERT with a maximum length of 150, batch size of 32, 3 epochs, and a learning rate of 5 × 10<sup>−5</sup>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.4">
      <title>Model Validation</title>
      <p id="p0090">From the regulatory sites file from PhosphoSitePlus and the kinase–substrate relationships in Signor, we randomly selected an additional 150 biomedical abstracts that mentioned a phosphorylation site and were not used for training. These abstracts were processed with the same method as those used for training.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.5">
      <title>Concept Normalization and Postprocessing</title>
      <p id="p0095">The protein substrates and phosphosites were normalized to standard forms. Substrates were normalized to gene symbols by using the first result from the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) gene search API. First, common description words such as “human,” “mutant,” “wild type,” “recombinant,” and “endogenous” were removed from the identified term. Then the modified term AND “human [Organism]” was submitted to the gene search API. For the mouse search, “mouse” was also removed from any identified term. Then the modified term AND “10090[Taxonomy ID]” was submitted to the gene search API.</p>
      <p id="p0100">Phosphosites were normalized to the unified form of the single letter amino acid code followed by the number location. For example, both “serine-20” and “serine residue 20” were normalized to S20 using regular expressions. If an amino acid was not extracted as part of the phosphosite entity, all preceding words in the sentence were searched using regular expressions for any form of “serine,” “tyrosine,” or “threonine.” Phosphosites were discarded if no site position was identified or if an S, T, or Y was followed by a 0 (<italic>e.g</italic>., S003).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.6">
      <title>ProtMapper Filtering</title>
      <p id="p0105">Normalized phosphorylation sites were submitted to ProtMapper (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>) for mapping to human reference protein sequences using the default parameters. Sites were discarded if ProtMapper indicated “NO_MAPPING_FOUND” or if ProtMapper was unable to process the site. For comparison with PhosphoSitePlus, the site positions mapped to the human reference sequences were used.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.7">
      <title>Mouse site Filtering</title>
      <p id="p0110">PubTator (NCBI) (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) was used to identify abstracts with the mouse species annotation (taxonomy ID: 10090). Predicted protein substrates for these abstracts were submitted to the NCBI gene search for mouse gene IDs as described in the “<italic>Concept normalization and postprocessing</italic>” section. Mouse protein sequences were acquired from SwissProt in October 2023, and ID mapping was performed using the AnnotationDbi R package (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) and org.Mm.eg.db (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Mouse phosphorylation sites were filtered to those with an exact amino acid match in the protein sequence at the position identified in the sentence.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.8">
      <title>Kinase and Phosphatase Annotation</title>
      <p id="p0115">Human protein kinases were downloaded from KinBase (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://kinase.com/web/current/kinbase/genes/SpeciesID/9606/" id="intref0015">http://kinase.com/web/current/kinbase/genes/SpeciesID/9606/</ext-link>) (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) and SwissProt (keyword:“Kinase [KW-0418]” AND reviewed:yes AND organism:“<italic>Homo sapiens</italic> (Human) [9606]”) (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>) in November 2021. Human phosphatases were downloaded from DEPOD (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) and filtered to those with an “active” status and in a protein phosphatase family (AP, CDC25, DUSP, EYA, FCP, HP1, HP2, LMWPTP, NagD, PPM, PPP, PTP, RTR1, and SSU72) in November 2021. Mouse protein kinases were downloaded from KinBase (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://kinase.com/web/current/kinbase/genes/SpeciesID/10090/" id="intref0020">http://kinase.com/web/current/kinbase/genes/SpeciesID/10090/</ext-link>) in October 2023. Mouse protein phosphatases were downloaded from SwissProt (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) in October 2023 with the keyword KW-0904 (keyword:KW-0904 AND reviewed:true AND model_organism:10090). All extracted genes from sentences with a positive prediction for a phosphorylation site were submitted to the NCBI gene search as described in the “<italic>Concept normalization and postprocessing” section</italic>. Genes were annotated as kinases or phosphatases if the gene symbol after normalization matched a kinase or phosphatase gene symbol in the downloaded lists.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.9">
      <title>Comparison to PhosphoSitePlus</title>
      <p id="p0120">Phosphorylation site information and the regulatory site tables were downloaded from PhosphoSitePlus (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>) in January 2023. The kinase–substrate table was downloaded from PhosphoSitePlus in September 2023. All tables were filtered to the human organism and a “-p” modification. For kinase–substrate comparison, autophosphorylation events were excluded.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.10">
      <title>Comparison to Clinical Proteomics Tumor Analysis Consortium Phosphoproteomics Data</title>
      <p id="p0125">Clinical Proteomics Tumor Analysis Consortium (CPTAC) pan-cancer data were acquired from Ref. (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Spearman correlation between ING5-T152 phosphorylation abundance and HALLMARK activity scores and between AKT1 activity scores and all phosphorylation sites were performed using LinkedOmicsKB (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.11">
      <title>Website Development</title>
      <p id="p0130">Finalized results were stored in an SQLite database (version 3.7.17). The website was developed with PHP (version 5.6) and Slim framework (version 3) on the backend. The frontend was based on Fomantic UI (version 2.8), and search results are displayed in a table with Bootstrap-table (version 1.21). The graph was built with D3.js (version 7).</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2">
    <title>Results</title>
    <sec id="sec2.1">
      <title>Deep Learning NLP Model Generation to Automatically Extract Phosphosites</title>
      <p id="p0135">The NLP pipeline (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>) to generate a model identifying phosphosites on proteins consists of multiple steps: (1) preprocessing abstracts to extract tokens from sentences, (2) named entity recognition (NER) to identify protein names and amino acid positions for corresponding sites, (3) manual corpus annotation to curate a gold standard positive training set, and (4) relation recognition and fine-tuning of a pretrained deep learning NLP method to automatically identify the substrate–phosphosite pairs.<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p><bold>Model pipeline to extract phosphorylation sites from abstracts.</bold> Abstract text was separated into sentences and tokenized, and named entity recognition was performed using regular expressions and BERN to label potential substrates and potential site positions. Substrate and site pairs were encoded in each sentence, which was then classified using BioBERT. BioBERT, Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers for biomedical text mining.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p>
      <p id="p0140">To create a gold standard list of phosphosites mentioned in abstracts to use for training and validation, we downloaded the Regulatory Sites file from PhosphoSitePlus and the sites with known kinases from Signor. We used only human sites and generated a list containing the amino acid location of the phosphosite, the gene symbol of its substrate protein, and the associated PubMed Manuscript ID. We randomly selected 3000 abstracts from this list to use for model training.</p>
      <p id="p0145">The abstracts were broken into sentences and tokens using CLAMP, and NER was used to label tokens as protein names or site positions. Regular expressions and dictionary look-up were used to identify site positions, whereas BERN was used to identify protein names. Manual annotation of the corpus was performed to identify which site position belonged to which protein within a single sentence. All other candidate site positions and candidate substrates were used as negative relationships. There were 16,729 sentences for positive relationships and 27,591 sentences for negative relationships. We used 10-fold cross validation to fine-tune BioBERT to generate 10 models that could classify a relationship between a potential substrate and potential site. The 10 models had an average precision of 92.7%, recall of 94.3%, specificity of 95.5%, and F1 score of 93.5% (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>).<fig id="fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p><bold>Model performance for identifying the correct substrate and site pairs in 10-fold cross validation.</bold><italic>Boxes</italic> indicate median and interquartile range for the results from 10 models.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p>
      <p id="p0150">We manually curated an additional 150 abstracts with phosphosites and used these for independent model validation. Majority voting of the 10 models performed slightly better than the individual model with the best cross F1 score (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). Unanimous voting of the 10 models had the best precision but worst recall (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>).<fig id="fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p><bold>Independent performance on correctly identifying phosphorylation sites from 150 abstracts.</bold> Three different methods were used to combine the results from 10 different models. A substrate and site in a sentence was classified as a positive if six or more models classified it as 1 (majority), all 10 models classified it as 1 (unanimous), or if the best performing model classified it as 1 (best).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.2">
      <title>Normalization of Phosphosite Representation to Human Sequences</title>
      <p id="p0155">After extracting phosphosites from the literature, the sites need to be normalized to have a consistent format for downstream analysis. Site positions were transformed using regular expressions to a single letter amino acid code followed by the numerical position (<italic>e.g.</italic>, S315). To prioritize sites that could be mapped to human genes, protein names were transformed to gene symbols using the top human result from NCBI. After normalization, the model precision on the validation set for individual phosphosites in specific PMIDs was 0.58 with a recall of 0.81. This validation involves an additional component beyond the BioBERT classification step as both the correct substrate and site must be extracted and the correct gene symbol must be selected for the substrate. For example, in the sentence “Rsk was phosphorylated on Thr573 by ERK1,” majority voting by the 10 fine-tuned BioBERT models might correctly classify Thr573 as a phosphorylation site on the substrate Rsk. However, an error may occur when transforming Rsk to the gene symbol RPS6KA1 and Thr573 to T573. Indeed, most of the precision loss at this step was due to the incorrect selection of gene symbols from the originally identified terms. To improve the precision of the results, we used ProtMapper to map the identified phosphosite to human reference protein sequences. Any site that could not be mapped to the reference was discarded. This improved precision to 0.91 with a slight drop in recall to 0.77.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.3">
      <title>Data Statistics of the Extracted Substrate–Site Pairs</title>
      <p id="p0160">To systematically illuminate the dark phosphoproteome, we used our model, named IDPpub, to extract phosphorylation sites in all MEDLINE abstracts. We identified phosphorylation sites in 253,443 abstracts. After entity normalization and ProtMapper filtering, we extracted from 58,227 abstracts 18,458 unique phosphorylation sites that could be mapped to human proteins. These covered 46% of the human phosphorylation sites with low-throughput evidence in PhosphoSitePlus and 57% of the human sites with regulatory information (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). Importantly, we extracted sentences for 11,634 sites that did not have regulatory information in or were not linked to low-throughput publications by PhosphoSitePlus.<fig id="fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p><bold>Numbers of sites with annotated regulatory information from PhosphoSitePlus, low-throughput publications from PhosphoSitePlus, and extracted sentences from IDPpub</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p>
      <p id="p0165">The CPTAC studies on 10 cancer types have identified over 125,000 human phosphorylation sites using mass spectrometry (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Only 3% of these sites have annotated regulatory information in PhosphoSitePlus. The human phosphorylation sites extracted from abstracts by IDPpub included 4117 CPTAC phosphorylation sites, 1803 of which have no annotated regulatory information. In addition, extracted sentences may describe roles in disease that are not captured in PhosphoSitePlus. For example, DOCK1-Y1811 has no annotated regulatory information in PhosphoSitePlus but has a role in cell growth and invasion in glioblastoma according to the extracted publication (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). In addition, ING5-T152 is regulated by the cell cycle (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) and involved in tumor cell proliferation. This site was positively correlated with proliferation-related cell signatures across multiple cancer types (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). Some additional examples are found in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.<fig id="fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p><bold>Spearman’s correlation between ING5 T152 phosphorylation abundance and the HALLMARK E2F Target score in four CPTAC cancer studies.</bold> CPTAC, Clinical Proteomics Tumor Analysis Consortium.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Examples of extracted phosphorylation site evidence not curated in PhosphoSitePlus for phosphosites identified in CPTAC studies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Substrate</th><th>Site</th><th>PMID</th><th>Sentence</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>DOCK1</td><td>Y1811</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="22080864" id="intref0035">22080864</ext-link></td><td>Here, we report that PDGFRα signaling in glioblastomas leads to Src-dependent phosphorylation of the guanine nucleotide exchange factor <bold>Dock180</bold> at <bold>tyrosine 1811 (Dock180(Y1811))</bold> that results in activation of the GTPase Rac1 and subsequent cell growth and invasion</td></tr><tr><td>ING5</td><td>T152</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25860957" id="intref0040">25860957</ext-link></td><td>In summary we identified a phosphorylation site at <bold>threonine 152</bold> of I<bold>NG5</bold> that is cell cycle regulated, and we observed that <bold>ING5</bold> is necessary for tumor cell proliferation, without any apparent dependency on the tumor suppressor p53</td></tr><tr><td>ZNF148</td><td>S306</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32060966" id="intref0045">32060966</ext-link></td><td>The clinical analysis indicates that SDHB deficiency is associated with elevated <bold>ZNF148</bold> levels, and <bold>ZNF148-S306</bold> phosphorylation level displays a positive correlation with poor prognosis in GIST patients</td></tr><tr><td>PXN</td><td>S178</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32064167" id="intref0050">32064167</ext-link></td><td>Hepatitis B virus X protein promotes tumor invasion and poor prognosis in hepatocellular carcinoma <italic>via</italic> phosphorylation of <bold>paxillin</bold> at <bold>Serine 178</bold> by activation of the c-Jun NH2-terminal kinase</td></tr><tr><td>ITPRID2</td><td>S92</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="26947549" id="intref0055">26947549</ext-link></td><td>From these results, we demonstrate that phospho-<bold>SSFA2 (pS92)</bold> is related to the prognosis of early resected lung adenocarcinomas</td></tr><tr><td>TMIGD2</td><td>S220</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="27838321" id="intref0060">27838321</ext-link></td><td>Trans-homophilic dimerization of <bold>IGPR-1</bold> stimulates the phosphorylation of <bold>serine 220 (Ser220)</bold>, which is required for <bold>IGPR-1</bold> to regulate endothelial barrier function and angiogenesis</td></tr><tr><td>NES</td><td>T315</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="28002641" id="intref0065">28002641</ext-link></td><td><bold>Nestin</bold> phosphorylation at <bold>threonines 315</bold> and 1299 correlates with proliferation and metastasis of human pancreatic cancer</td></tr><tr><td>EPHA2</td><td>S897</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30412282" id="intref0070">30412282</ext-link></td><td><italic>In vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> experiments revealed that <bold>EPHA2</bold> mutations could lead to ligand independent phosphorylation of <bold>Ser897,</bold> and promote lymphatic metastasis of ICC, in which NOTCH1 signaling pathway played an important role</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Identified substrates and sites are noted in bold.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.4">
      <title>Extracted Sentences Support Conclusions From Phosphoproteomics Experiments</title>
      <p id="p0170">Phosphoproteomics data can be used as a readout of the activity of kinases and phosphatases, the enzymes responsible for adding or removing phosphate groups. We correlated all phosphorylation site abundances with AKT1 activity scores in the CPTAC pan-cancer datasets to identify potential substrates of AKT1 in cancer. Based on the meta <italic>p</italic> value of the association across 10 CPTAC cancer cohorts, the top associated site was AKT1S1 T246, which is a marker of AKT1 activity (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) and contributes to the activity score. The third best correlated site, AFDN S1799 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>), had no current annotation in relation to AKT1 in either PhosphositePlus (Cell Signaling Technology) or Signor. In contrast, IDPpub extracted a sentence from a study identifying AFDN S1799 as a target of AKT in breast cancer cells (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). There are many similar examples connecting a phosphorylation site identified in the CPTAC data to a regulatory kinase that has not been associated with the site in PhosphoSitePlus (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<fig id="fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p><bold>Spearman’s correlation between AFDN S1799 phosphorylation abundance and AKT1 kinase activity scores in four CPTAC cancer studies.</bold> CPTAC, Clinical Proteomics Tumor Analysis Consortium.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr6"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Examples of kinases for phosphorylation sites not curated in PhosphoSitePlus but extracted by IDPpub</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Kinase</th><th>Substrate</th><th>Site position</th><th>Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>AKT</td><td>AFDN</td><td>S1799</td><td align="char">24269953</td></tr><tr><td>IKKβ</td><td>MTDH</td><td>S298</td><td align="char">25849741</td></tr><tr><td>CDK1</td><td>PRC1</td><td>T470</td><td align="char">17438553</td></tr><tr><td>CDK5</td><td>PPP1R1B</td><td>T75</td><td align="char">1295672,<break/>1474424,<break/>1546412,<break/>22820052</td></tr><tr><td>ERK</td><td>ZNF148</td><td>S306</td><td align="char">32060966</td></tr><tr><td>GSK3β</td><td>KIF1A</td><td>S402</td><td align="char">33067366</td></tr><tr><td>PKA</td><td>NOS1</td><td>S1417</td><td align="char">23012472</td></tr><tr><td>CaMKII</td><td>NOS1</td><td>S852</td><td align="char">33121174</td></tr><tr><td>FYN</td><td>G6PD</td><td>Y401</td><td align="char">32863204</td></tr><tr><td>GSK3β</td><td>IKZF1</td><td>S391</td><td align="char">32807499</td></tr><tr><td>TrkB</td><td>APP</td><td>Y762</td><td align="char">32782380</td></tr><tr><td>GSK3β</td><td>NPM1</td><td>T95</td><td align="char">32686519</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
      <p id="p0175">To support the identification of regulatory information from sentences, we further annotated all kinases and phosphatases in the sentences. We identified 20,614 co-occurrences between a kinase and a phosphorylation site in 29,080 sentences. About 20% of the co-occurrences between kinases and phosphorylation sites represented known kinase–substrate relationships from PhosphoSitePlus. Furthermore, these co-occurrences covered 31% of the known human kinase–substrate relationships in PhosphoSitePlus.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.5">
      <title>Extension to Model Organisms</title>
      <p id="p0180">While human phosphorylation sites are the most widely studied, information on phosphorylation sites on model organisms is also important. We used PubTator to identify species information for the 253,443 abstracts with extracted phosphorylation sites. Over half (131,435) of the abstracts were annotated with human, whereas the second most common species was mouse (Taxonomy ID: 10090) with 59,719 abstracts. Fewer than 5% of the abstracts were annotated with other model species. We performed the post-processing steps for the abstracts annotated with mouse to identify mouse gene IDs and protein sequences. We filtered for any sites with an exact match between the site position extracted from the sentence and the mouse protein sequence for that gene. After filtering, we found 5918 phosphorylation sites in 14,610 abstracts.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.6">
      <title>Repository</title>
      <p id="p0185">We generated a searchable repository of all phosphorylation sites extracted from abstracts, which can be accessed at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://idppub.ptmax.org" id="PC_linkJilmGpIydx">http://idppub.ptmax.org</ext-link> (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>). We provide three versions of the extracted sites in the web portal. The first is the set of phosphorylation sites aligned to human proteins. The second is the set of phosphorylation sites that match mouse proteins. The third is the full results without gene normalization, and these results are annotated with taxonomy information from PubTator so that they can be filtered for specific species. For each version, a user can search for an individual gene, an individual single site on a gene, or a list of sites. The web portal provides a bar plot illustrating the number of sentences containing each site and a table of extracted sentences with links to the publications. The substrate, the phosphosite, and any co-occurring kinases and phosphatases are highlighted in each sentence. The sentences can be further searched for the exact match of terms, such as “apoptosis” or “tumor,” which could be used to filter for function or disease relations.<fig id="fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p><bold>Example of the IDPpub web portal results for MTDH</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr7"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec3">
    <title>Discussion</title>
    <p id="p0190">Mass spectrometry–based phosphoproteomics profiling offers tremendous potential for biological discoveries, but interpretation of phosphoproteomics sites identified from such studies is hampered by our limited knowledge on functions, biological contexts, or precipitating enzymes of the phosphosites. Extracting what is known from the literature is time consuming and often requires advanced biological knowledge. This study takes a hybrid approach combining deep learning–based NLP models and domain knowledge–based rules to automatically extract substrates, the positions of phosphorylated amino acids on these substrates, and corresponding evidence sentences from biomedical abstracts.</p>
    <p id="p0195">The evidence sentences extracted can quickly be assessed for potential biological context without scanning entire articles and can also point users to interesting articles for further reading. After identifying a set of phosphosites associated with a phenotype, scientists are currently limited to the functional information in manually curated databases such as PhosphoSitePlus. The literature must be searched for information not yet present in curated databases for all other sites individually. With IDPpub, users can quickly find additional evidence from all PubMed abstracts for phosphosites in bulk. Similarly, manually curated kinase–substrate information is poor in databases, with phosphatase–substrate information even more minimal. We have added annotations for kinases and phosphatases that co-occur in the same sentence as phosphorylation sites. While a co-occurrence does not necessarily indicate a true relationship, these annotations can help identify potential regulating enzymes.</p>
    <p id="p0200">We developed IDPpub to be as accurate as possible while also prioritizing high recall as sentences containing false-positive relationships can be easily discarded upon manual review. However, IDPpub could still be improved in future iterations. While the model is reasonably accurate in selecting the correct substrate for a phosphorylation site in a sentence, the normalization to a gene symbol is still challenging. This is partly because of nonunique names for proteins. For example, “PDK1” may refer to either 3-phosphoinositide-dependent protein kinase-1 (protein name PDK1, gene symbol <italic>PDPK1</italic>) or pyruvate dehydrogenase kinase 1 (gene symbol <italic>PDK1</italic>). In addition, accuracy of selecting the correct gene symbol is also diminished by inaccurate boundary detection of the NER step. For example, the model may identify “CRK” as the substrate instead of the full string “CRK-II.” This issue accounts for the drop in performance between the initial cross validation and validation of the BioBERT step on an additional 150 abstracts. For the training data, manual curation included setting the correct boundaries for both substrates and sites within a sentence to optimize the training of the relation extraction task. For the 150 test abstracts, we did not adjust the NER-defined boundaries as that would not be feasible to apply to the full database for prediction. In the future, correct boundary detection and identification of substrates in a sentence can be improved using new models (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>).</p>
    <p id="p0205">Improvements could also be made for extracting the correct site position. MESH terms could be used to filter biomedical articles to avoid false recognition of cell or chemical names, such as T-4 cells, that have a similar naming convention to the notations used for designating amino acid positions that are phosphosites. Also, normalizing the location of a site is still a major issue in the field of phosphoproteomics. Site localization is typically reported based on a reference protein sequence, which may come from one of several different sequence databases and can vary over time and between different protein isoforms. Manually searching the literature for a site identified in a phosphoproteomics experiment is a challenge because the manuscripts studying that site may list a completely different position that could even be over 100 amino acids away. For example, Bailey <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) described phosphorylation of tau on T149 and T153, which correspond to numbering on isoform 8 but are analogous to T466 and T470 on the canonical tau isoform. In IDPpub, we align the sites to the human UniProt sequences using ProtMapper. This improves consistency with PhosphoSitePlus but may not easily be applied to nonhuman studies or those where other human protein sequence databases are used as references. Indeed, identifying the species associated with phosphorylation sites mentioned in an abstract is a significant challenge, even from a manual reading. In our study, we aligned the sites to protein sequences from human and mouse, which were associated with 50% and 20% of the abstracts containing extracted phosphorylation sites, respectively. Furthermore, we provided a table that includes all sites extracted from sentences without alignment, along with the PubTator-annotated species information for the corresponding abstracts. This table can be valuable for filtering phosphosites in organisms beyond human and mouse.</p>
    <p id="p0210">The utility of IDPpub can be extended through the mining of full biomedical texts, which will increase the number of extracted sites and evidence sentences. Importantly, IDPpub can be automatically updated with newly published articles, providing continual utility to the community. Moreover, IDPpub can be modified with new regular expressions to capture additional post-translational modifications (PTMs). The ability to quickly filter primary literature for manual review enhances the usability of the data from high-throughput studies measuring various types of PTMs. Moving forward, we will also develop new models to identify and normalize other important elements from the sentences containing extracted PTM sites, such as the enzyme manipulating the PTM and the regulatory function of the modification. These enhancements will facilitate downstream analyses such as functional enrichment of a set of phosphorylation sites. Furthermore, with the accurate identification of enzyme–substrate relationships, we can further refine the analysis of binding motifs for regulatory enzymes.</p>
    <p id="p0215">In summary, the current implementation of IDPpub and its search tools are valuable complements to existing phosphorylation information portals. Ongoing improvements will further contribute to a deeper understanding of the phosphoproteome and other PTMomes.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec4">
    <title>Data Availability</title>
    <p id="p0220">All identified phosphosites and associated sentences can be searched and browsed at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://idppub.ptmax.org" id="PC_linkV5BPnkd2jB">http://idppub.ptmax.org</ext-link>. The whole dataset can also be downloaded from the website through the download link.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
    <title>Conflict of interest</title>
    <p id="p0225">The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ref-list id="cebib0010">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="bib1">
      <label>1</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sharma</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>D’Souza</surname>
            <given-names>R.C.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tyanova</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schaab</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wiśniewski</surname>
            <given-names>J.R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cox</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Ultradeep human phosphoproteome reveals a distinct regulatory nature of Tyr and Ser/Thr-based signaling</article-title>
        <source>Cell Rep.</source>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <year>2014</year>
        <fpage>1583</fpage>
        <lpage>1594</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25159151</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib2">
      <label>2</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <collab>UniProt Consortium</collab>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>UniProt: the universal protein knowledgebase in 2021</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>49</volume>
        <year>2021</year>
        <fpage>D480</fpage>
        <lpage>D489</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33237286</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib3">
      <label>3</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hornbeck</surname>
            <given-names>P.V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Murray</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kornhauser</surname>
            <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Latham</surname>
            <given-names>V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Skrzypek</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>PhosphoSitePlus, 2014: mutations, PTMs and recalibrations</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>43</volume>
        <year>2015</year>
        <fpage>D512</fpage>
        <lpage>D520</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25514926</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib4">
      <label>4</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Torii</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Arighi</surname>
            <given-names>C.N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Q.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>C.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vijay-Shanker</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>RLIMS-P 2.0: a generalizable rule-based information extraction system for literature mining of protein phosphorylation information</article-title>
        <source>IEEE/ACM Trans. Comput. Biol. Bioinform.</source>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <year>2015</year>
        <fpage>17</fpage>
        <lpage>29</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26357075</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib5">
      <label>5</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Raja</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Natarajan</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Mining protein phosphorylation information from biomedical literature using NLP parsing and support vector machines</article-title>
        <source>Comput. Methods Programs Biomed.</source>
        <volume>160</volume>
        <year>2018</year>
        <fpage>57</fpage>
        <lpage>64</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29728247</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib6">
      <label>6</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Elangovan</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pires</surname>
            <given-names>D.E.V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Davis</surname>
            <given-names>M.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Verspoor</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Large-scale protein-protein post-translational modification extraction with distant supervision and confidence calibrated BioBERT</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinform.</source>
        <volume>23</volume>
        <year>2022</year>
        <fpage>4</fpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib7">
      <label>7</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yoon</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>So</surname>
            <given-names>C.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>BioBERT: a pre-trained biomedical language representation model for biomedical text mining</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <volume>36</volume>
        <year>2020</year>
        <fpage>1234</fpage>
        <lpage>1240</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31501885</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib8">
      <label>8</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Soysal</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jiang</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pakhomov</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Clamp - a toolkit for efficiently building customized clinical natural language processing pipelines</article-title>
        <source>J. Am. Med. Inform. Assoc.</source>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <year>2018</year>
        <fpage>331</fpage>
        <lpage>336</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29186491</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib9">
      <label>9</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>So</surname>
            <given-names>C.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jeon</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jeong</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Choi</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A neural named entity recognition and multi-type normalization tool for biomedical text mining</article-title>
        <source>IEEE Access</source>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <year>2019</year>
        <fpage>73729</fpage>
        <lpage>73740</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib10">
      <label>10</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Licata</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lo Surdo</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Iannuccelli</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Palma</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Micarelli</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Perfetto</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>SIGNOR 2.0, the SIGnaling Network open resource 2.0: 2019 update</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>48</volume>
        <year>2020</year>
        <fpage>D504</fpage>
        <lpage>D510</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31665520</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib11">
      <label>11</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11">
        <comment>[preprint]</comment>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bachman</surname>
            <given-names>J.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sorger</surname>
            <given-names>P.K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gyori</surname>
            <given-names>B.M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Assembling a corpus of phosphoproteomic annotations using ProtMapper to normalize site information from databases and text mining</article-title>
        <source>bioRxiv</source>
        <year>2022</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/822668</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib12">
      <label>12</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wei</surname>
            <given-names>C.-H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Allot</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Leaman</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>Z.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>PubTator central: automated concept annotation for biomedical full text articles</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>47</volume>
        <year>2019</year>
        <fpage>W587</fpage>
        <lpage>W593</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31114887</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib13">
      <label>13</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pagès</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Carlson</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Falcon</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>AnnotationDbi: manipulation of SQLite-based annotations in bioconductor. R package version 1.62.2</article-title>
        <source>Bioconductor</source>
        <year>2023</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18129/B9.bioc.AnnotationDbi</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib14">
      <label>14</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Carlson</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>org.Mm.eg.db: genome wide annotation for mouse. R package version 3.8.2</article-title>
        <source>Bioconductor</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18129/B9.bioc.org.Mm.eg.db</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib15">
      <label>15</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Manning</surname>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Whyte</surname>
            <given-names>D.B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Martinez</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hunter</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sudarsanam</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The protein kinase complement of the human genome</article-title>
        <source>Science</source>
        <volume>298</volume>
        <year>2002</year>
        <fpage>1912</fpage>
        <lpage>1934</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12471243</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib16">
      <label>16</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Damle</surname>
            <given-names>N.P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Köhn</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The human DEPhOsphorylation Database DEPOD: 2019 update</article-title>
        <source>Database</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/database/baz133</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib17">
      <label>17</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17">
        <article-title>UniProt: the universal protein knowledgebase in 2023</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>51</volume>
        <year>2023</year>
        <fpage>D523</fpage>
        <lpage>D531</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36408920</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib18">
      <label>18</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dou</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Da Veiga Leprevost</surname>
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Geffen</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Calinawan</surname>
            <given-names>A.P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Aguet</surname>
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Proteogenomic data and resources for pan-cancer analysis</article-title>
        <source>Cancer Cell</source>
        <volume>41</volume>
        <year>2023</year>
        <fpage>1397</fpage>
        <lpage>1406</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37582339</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib19">
      <label>19</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liao</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Savage</surname>
            <given-names>S.R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dou</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shi</surname>
            <given-names>Z.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yi</surname>
            <given-names>X.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jiang</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A proteogenomics data-driven knowledge base of human cancer</article-title>
        <source>Cell Syst.</source>
        <volume>14</volume>
        <year>2023</year>
        <fpage>777</fpage>
        <lpage>787.e5</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37619559</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib20">
      <label>20</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Feng</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>K.-W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>X.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cheng</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Activation of Rac1 by Src-dependent phosphorylation of Dock180(Y1811) mediates PDGFRα-stimulated glioma tumorigenesis in mice and humans</article-title>
        <source>J. Clin. Invest.</source>
        <volume>121</volume>
        <year>2011</year>
        <fpage>4670</fpage>
        <lpage>4684</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22080864</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib21">
      <label>21</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Linzen</surname>
            <given-names>U.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lilischkis</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pandithage</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schilling</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ullius</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lüscher-Firzlaff</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>ING5 is phosphorylated by CDK2 and controls cell proliferation independently of p53</article-title>
        <source>PLoS One</source>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <year>2015</year>
        <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0123736</object-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib22">
      <label>22</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kovacina</surname>
            <given-names>K.S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>G.Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bae</surname>
            <given-names>S.S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Guzzetta</surname>
            <given-names>A.W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schaefer</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Birnbaum</surname>
            <given-names>M.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Identification of a proline-rich Akt substrate as a 14-3-3 binding partner</article-title>
        <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
        <volume>278</volume>
        <year>2003</year>
        <fpage>10189</fpage>
        <lpage>10194</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12524439</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib23">
      <label>23</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Elloul</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kedrin</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Knoblauch</surname>
            <given-names>N.W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Beck</surname>
            <given-names>A.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Toker</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The adherens junction protein afadin is an AKT substrate that regulates breast cancer cell migration</article-title>
        <source>Mol. Cancer Res.</source>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <year>2014</year>
        <fpage>464</fpage>
        <lpage>476</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24269953</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib24">
      <label>24</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Allot</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Peng</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wei</surname>
            <given-names>C.-H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Phan</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>Z.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>LitVar: a semantic search engine for linking genomic variant data in PubMed and PMC</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>46</volume>
        <year>2018</year>
        <fpage>W530</fpage>
        <lpage>W536</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29762787</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib25">
      <label>25</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bailey</surname>
            <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Covy</surname>
            <given-names>J.P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Melrose</surname>
            <given-names>H.L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rousseau</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Watkinson</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Knight</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>LRRK2 phosphorylates novel tau epitopes and promotes tauopathy</article-title>
        <source>Acta Neuropathol.</source>
        <volume>126</volume>
        <year>2013</year>
        <fpage>809</fpage>
        <lpage>827</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24113872</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
  <ack id="ack0010">
    <title>Acknowledgments</title>
    <p id="p0230">This work was supported by the <funding-source id="gs2"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000002</institution-id><institution>National Institutes of Health</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> grants from the <funding-source id="gs4"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000054</institution-id><institution>National Cancer Institute</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (grant nos.: U24 CA271076 and R01 CA245903, by <funding-source id="gs6"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100004917</institution-id><institution>Cancer Prevention &amp; Research Institute of Texas</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> Awards RR160027 and RP220050, and funding from the McNair Medical Institute at The <funding-source id="gs8"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100001234</institution-id><institution>Robert and Janice McNair Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>.</p>
    <sec id="sec5">
      <title>Funding and additional information</title>
      <p id="p0235">B. Z. is a <funding-source id="gs5"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100004917</institution-id><institution>Cancer Prevention &amp; Research Institute of Texas</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> scholar in cancer research and a McNair scholar.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec6">
      <title>Author contributions</title>
      <p id="p0240">S. R. S., E. J. J., and B. Z. conceptualization; Y. Z. and H. X. methodology; Y. Z., Y. L., Z. S., and H. A. P. software; S. R. S. and Y. Z. validation; S. R. S. and Y. Z. formal analysis; S. R. S. investigation; H. X. resources; S. R. S. and E. J. J. data curation; S. R. S. and Y. Z. writing–original draft; E. J. J., Y. L., Z. S., and B. Z. writing–review &amp; editing; S. R. S. visualization; H. X. and B. Z. supervision; B. Z. project administration; H. X. and B. Z. funding acquisition.</p>
    </sec>
  </ack>
</back>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?origin publisher?>
<?FILEmeta_MCPRO100682 xml ?>
<?FILEmain xml ?>
<?FILEmain pdf ?>
<?FILEgr1 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr2 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr3 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr4 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr5 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr6 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr7 jpg ?>
<?FILEga1 jpg ?>
<?properties open_access?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Cell Proteomics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol Cell Proteomics</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Molecular &amp; Cellular Proteomics : MCP</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1535-9476</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1535-9484</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">10716774</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S1535-9476(23)00193-7</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mcpro.2023.100682</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100682</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Technological Innovation and Resources</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>IDPpub: Illuminating the Dark Phosphoproteome Through PubMed Mining</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1">
        <name>
          <surname>Savage</surname>
          <given-names>Sara R.</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
        <xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">‡</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2">
        <name>
          <surname>Zhang</surname>
          <given-names>Yaoyun</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
        <xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">‡</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3">
        <name>
          <surname>Jaehnig</surname>
          <given-names>Eric J.</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4">
        <name>
          <surname>Liao</surname>
          <given-names>Yuxing</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5">
        <name>
          <surname>Shi</surname>
          <given-names>Zhiao</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6">
        <name>
          <surname>Pham</surname>
          <given-names>Huy Anh</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7">
        <name>
          <surname>Xu</surname>
          <given-names>Hua</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8">
        <name>
          <surname>Zhang</surname>
          <given-names>Bing</given-names>
        </name>
        <email>bing.zhang@bcm.edu</email>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
        <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Lester and Sue Smith Breast Center, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, Texas, USA</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Molecular and Human Genetics, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, Texas, USA</aff>
      <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Melax Technologies Inc, Houston, Texas, USA</aff>
      <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Section of Biomedical Informatics and Data Science, School of Medicine, Yale University, Connecticut, USA</aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>For correspondence: Bing Zhang <email>bing.zhang@bcm.edu</email></corresp>
      <fn id="fn1">
        <label>‡</label>
        <p id="ntpara0010">These authors contributed equally to this work.</p>
      </fn>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>21</day>
      <month>11</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <month>1</month>
      <year>2024</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>21</day>
      <month>11</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>23</volume>
    <issue>1</issue>
    <elocation-id>100682</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>17</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© 2023 The Authors</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract id="abs0010">
      <p>Global phosphoproteomics experiments quantify tens of thousands of phosphorylation sites. However, data interpretation is hampered by our limited knowledge on functions, biological contexts, or precipitating enzymes of the phosphosites. This study establishes a repository of phosphosites with associated evidence in biomedical abstracts, using deep learning–based natural language processing techniques. Our model for illuminating the dark phosphoproteome through PubMed mining (IDPpub) was generated by fine-tuning BioBERT, a deep learning tool for biomedical text mining. Trained using sentences containing protein substrates and phosphorylation site positions from 3000 abstracts, the IDPpub model was then used to extract phosphorylation sites from all MEDLINE abstracts. The extracted proteins were normalized to gene symbols using the National Center for Biotechnology Information gene query, and sites were mapped to human UniProt sequences using ProtMapper and mouse UniProt sequences by direct match. Precision and recall were calculated using 150 curated abstracts, and utility was assessed by analyzing the CPTAC (Clinical Proteomics Tumor Analysis Consortium) pan-cancer phosphoproteomics datasets and the PhosphoSitePlus database. Using 10-fold cross validation, pairs of correct substrates and phosphosite positions were extracted with an average precision of 0.93 and recall of 0.94. After entity normalization and site mapping to human reference sequences, an independent validation achieved a precision of 0.91 and recall of 0.77. The IDPpub repository contains 18,458 unique human phosphorylation sites with evidence sentences from 58,227 abstracts and 5918 mouse sites in 14,610 abstracts. This included evidence sentences for 1803 sites identified in CPTAC studies that are not covered by manually curated functional information in PhosphoSitePlus. Evaluation results demonstrate the potential of IDPpub as an effective biomedical text mining tool for collecting phosphosites. Moreover, the repository (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://idppub.ptmax.org" id="PC_linkwFgyMZUVzu">http://idppub.ptmax.org</ext-link>), which can be automatically updated, can serve as a powerful complement to existing resources.</p>
    </abstract>
    <abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0015">
      <title>Graphical Abstract</title>
      <fig id="undfig1" position="anchor">
        <graphic xlink:href="ga1"/>
      </fig>
    </abstract>
    <abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0020">
      <title>Highlights</title>
      <p>
        <list list-type="simple" id="ulist0010">
          <list-item id="u0010">
            <label>•</label>
            <p id="p0010">IDPpub utilizes BioBERT to extract phosphorylation sites.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item id="u0015">
            <label>•</label>
            <p id="p0015">Alignment of extracted phosphorylation sites to reference sequences.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item id="u0020">
            <label>•</label>
            <p id="p0020">Identified evidence sentences for tumor-associated sites.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item id="u0025">
            <label>•</label>
            <p id="p0025">Web portal to explore evidence sentences for phosphorylation sites.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </p>
    </abstract>
    <abstract abstract-type="teaser" id="abs0025">
      <title>In Brief</title>
      <p>Phosphorylation sites have important functions but are poorly annotated in public databases. We developed IDPpub, a pipeline that uses BioBERT to extract phosphorylation sites from biomedical abstracts. We align the sites to human and mouse reference sequences to facilitate computational applications and intersection with mass spectrometry experiments. The evidence sentences can be used to identify regulating enzymes and biological functions. All data are available in a web portal for easy search.</p>
    </abstract>
    <kwd-group id="kwrds0010">
      <title>Keywords</title>
      <kwd>phosphoproteomics</kwd>
      <kwd>text mining</kwd>
      <kwd>natural language processing</kwd>
      <kwd>deep learning</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
  </article-meta>
  <def-list>
    <title>Abbreviations</title>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0035">BERT</term>
      <def>
        <p>Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0045">CPTAC</term>
      <def>
        <p>Clinical Proteomics Tumor Analysis Consortium</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0055">NCBI</term>
      <def>
        <p>National Center for Biotechnology Information</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0065">NLP</term>
      <def>
        <p>natural language processing</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
    <def-item>
      <term id="kwrd0075">PTM</term>
      <def>
        <p>post-translational modification</p>
      </def>
    </def-item>
  </def-list>
</front>
<body>
  <p id="p0030">Phosphorylation, the addition of a phosphate group to a substrate protein, is an essential component of biological signaling. This process, which affects over 75% of all human proteins (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>), frequently modulates a protein’s stability or function. Advances in mass spectrometry and phosphopeptide enrichment methods, such as immobilized affinity chromatography, now enable the high-throughput identification of the phosphorylation events in cells and tissues. Phosphosites from these high-throughput experiments are frequently archived in databases such as UniProt (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>) and PhosphoSitePlus (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). The same databases that collect high-throughput sites often also provide manual curation of sites that have been well studied and have a known impact on the function of a protein from the scientific literature. Because manual curation is time consuming, it cannot keep pace with the explosion of reported biological research findings, and therefore, relatively few sites in these databases have annotated biological functions. In fact, only 4% of the sites in PhosphoSitePlus have been annotated with a function. The “dark” phosphoproteome makes determining how sites of interest identified in a high-throughput experiment contribute to a clinical or biological phenotype a challenge.</p>
  <p id="p0035">As a complement to manual curation, natural language processing (NLP) techniques can extract research findings from the literature text automatically. Previous works have built several information extraction systems to extract the protein substrate and phosphosite location of the phosphorylation event. Both rule-based (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) and machine learning–based approaches (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>) have been used. The rule-based RLIMS-P system utilized a comprehensive set of syntactic–semantic patterns for extraction of phosphorylation events (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Another system leveraged the patterns in RLIMS-P, trigger words such as “phosphorylation” and “autophosphorylated,” and other context features to build an automatic Support Vector Machine model (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). However, these systems were built to find specific subsets of phosphorylation sites, such as those mentioned with the phosphorylating kinase (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) or those involved in protein–protein interactions (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). In addition, the results from these models are not normalized for use in downstream computational analyses.</p>
  <p id="p0040">Because there are no open source methods for extracting phosphorylation sites with evidence sentences, we built a new NLP-based system to address the aforementioned challenges. The current state-of-art deep learning framework for NLP, Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers (BERT), provides a model that embeds linguistic and domain knowledge and that can be fine-tuned for downstream tasks, such as relation extraction. BioBERT (BERT for biomedical text mining) was initiated using the original model of BERT and was fine-tuned using biomedical abstracts in MEDLINE and full texts in PubMed Central (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>).</p>
  <p id="p0045">We used a gold standard training dataset of 3000 biomedical abstracts that were curated with substrate protein and corresponding site position pairs to fine-tune BioBERT models. Specific low-throughput sites studied through conventional targeted methods are more likely to be listed in the abstract of articles than are sites identified in high-throughput studies. As such, abstracts from low-throughput studies are more likely to mention functionally relevant phosphorylated sites.</p>
  <p id="p0050">This information extraction system was then applied to all abstracts in the entire NLM MEDLINE database. Mentions of protein substrates and site locations were normalized to standardized nomenclature using gene/protein synonyms and regular expressions. Thus, a repository of phosphosites on substrates mentioned in each abstract was generated, together with the evidence sentences. Finally, a web portal was constructed to provide a service to search phosphorylation information using substrates and site locations as queries.</p>
  <sec id="sec1">
    <title>Experimental Procedures</title>
    <sec id="sec1.1">
      <title>Abstract Processing</title>
      <p id="p0055">Titles and text of abstracts for both training and prediction were downloaded from the National Library of Medicine (MEDLINE version 2020-12-14) and prepared as follows.</p>
      <sec id="sec1.1.1">
        <title>Preprocessing</title>
        <p id="p0060">In the preprocessing step, abstracts were split into sentences by sentence boundary detection using the OpenNLP sentence detector in CLAMP (Melax Tech), version 1.6.6 (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Tokens were identified in the sentence and separated by the default tokenization tool based on lexicons and regular expressions, and parts of speech were tagged with the default OpenNLP tagger in CLAMP.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec1.1.2">
        <title>Named Entity Recognition</title>
        <p id="p0065">Named entity recognition (NER) was performed using CLAMP to classify tokens into two semantic types: gene/protein name and phosphosites.</p>
        <sec id="sec1.1.2.1">
          <title>Gene/Protein Name Recognition</title>
          <p id="p0070">Gene/protein names were recognized using a hybrid method. An API for the NER software BERN (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) was first used for deep learning–based gene/protein recognition. Next, the synonyms collected from PhosphoSitePlus were used as a complementary resource for dictionary lookup-based gene/protein recognition. A token was classified with the term “Substrate” if it was recognized by either BERN or the dictionary lookup.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec1.1.2.2">
          <title>Site Recognition</title>
          <p id="p0075">The amino acid positions of phosphosites were recognized by regular expressions consisting of cue words and numbers, such as serine-20, serine residues 20, S20, etc. (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). A token was classified with the term “Phosphosite” if it fit any of the regular expressions.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Keywords of different site expressions</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Serine</th><th>Threonine</th><th>Tyrosine</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>S</td><td>t</td><td>y</td></tr><tr><td>ser</td><td>thr</td><td>tyr</td></tr><tr><td>serines</td><td>threonines</td><td>tyrosines</td></tr><tr><td>serine</td><td>threonine</td><td>tyrosine</td></tr><tr><td>ps</td><td>pt</td><td>py</td></tr><tr><td>pser</td><td>pthr</td><td>ptyr</td></tr><tr><td>pserines</td><td>pthreonines</td><td>ptyrosines</td></tr><tr><td>pserine</td><td>pthreonine</td><td>ptyrosine</td></tr><tr><td>phosphos</td><td>phosphot</td><td>phosphoy</td></tr><tr><td>phosphoser</td><td>phosphothr</td><td>phosphotyr</td></tr><tr><td>phosphoserines</td><td>phosphothreonines</td><td>phosphotyrosines</td></tr><tr><td>phosphoserine</td><td>phosphothreonine</td><td>phosphotyrosine</td></tr><tr><td>phosphorusserines</td><td>phosphorusthreonines</td><td>phosphorustyrosines</td></tr><tr><td>phosphorusserine</td><td>phosphorusthreonine</td><td>phosphorustyrosine</td></tr><tr><td>serinesresidues</td><td>threoninesresidues</td><td>tyrosinesresidues</td></tr><tr><td>serineresidues</td><td>threonineresidues</td><td>tyrosineresidues</td></tr><tr><td>serinesresidue</td><td>threoninesresidue</td><td>tyrosinesresidue</td></tr><tr><td>serineresidue</td><td>threonineresidue</td><td>tyrosineresidue</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.2">
      <title>Training Data Annotation</title>
      <p id="p0080">Using the regulatory sites file from PhosphoSitePlus and the kinase–substrate relationships in Signor (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>) as a guide, we randomly selected 3000 biomedical abstracts that mentioned a phosphorylation site. To prepare a positive set of phosphosites on substrate proteins, a relationship between the correct “Substrate” and “Phosphosite” within the same sentence in an abstract was manually annotated using CLAMP. Token boundaries for the correct substrate and phosphosite were adjusted if the NER process did not correctly extract the token. A negative set was generated from all other tokens classified as “Substrate” within the same sentence as a token classified “Phosphosite.” If the candidate substrate and/or phosphosite were also mentioned in the abstract title, then the title was added to the end of the sentence. For each unique “Substrate” and “Phosphosite” pair in each sentence, the token labeled “Substrate” was replaced with the word “@SUBSTRATE$” and the token labeled “Phosphosite” was replaced with the word “@PHOSPHOSITE$”.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.3">
      <title>Fine-Tuning BioBERT for Relation Extraction</title>
      <p id="p0085">The set of sentences containing positive and negative substrate and phosphosite pairs was used to train BioBERT (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>) to classify a relationship between a potential substrate and a potential phosphosite. Ten-fold cross validation was used to fine tune BioBERT with a maximum length of 150, batch size of 32, 3 epochs, and a learning rate of 5 × 10<sup>−5</sup>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.4">
      <title>Model Validation</title>
      <p id="p0090">From the regulatory sites file from PhosphoSitePlus and the kinase–substrate relationships in Signor, we randomly selected an additional 150 biomedical abstracts that mentioned a phosphorylation site and were not used for training. These abstracts were processed with the same method as those used for training.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.5">
      <title>Concept Normalization and Postprocessing</title>
      <p id="p0095">The protein substrates and phosphosites were normalized to standard forms. Substrates were normalized to gene symbols by using the first result from the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) gene search API. First, common description words such as “human,” “mutant,” “wild type,” “recombinant,” and “endogenous” were removed from the identified term. Then the modified term AND “human [Organism]” was submitted to the gene search API. For the mouse search, “mouse” was also removed from any identified term. Then the modified term AND “10090[Taxonomy ID]” was submitted to the gene search API.</p>
      <p id="p0100">Phosphosites were normalized to the unified form of the single letter amino acid code followed by the number location. For example, both “serine-20” and “serine residue 20” were normalized to S20 using regular expressions. If an amino acid was not extracted as part of the phosphosite entity, all preceding words in the sentence were searched using regular expressions for any form of “serine,” “tyrosine,” or “threonine.” Phosphosites were discarded if no site position was identified or if an S, T, or Y was followed by a 0 (<italic>e.g</italic>., S003).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.6">
      <title>ProtMapper Filtering</title>
      <p id="p0105">Normalized phosphorylation sites were submitted to ProtMapper (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>) for mapping to human reference protein sequences using the default parameters. Sites were discarded if ProtMapper indicated “NO_MAPPING_FOUND” or if ProtMapper was unable to process the site. For comparison with PhosphoSitePlus, the site positions mapped to the human reference sequences were used.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.7">
      <title>Mouse site Filtering</title>
      <p id="p0110">PubTator (NCBI) (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) was used to identify abstracts with the mouse species annotation (taxonomy ID: 10090). Predicted protein substrates for these abstracts were submitted to the NCBI gene search for mouse gene IDs as described in the “<italic>Concept normalization and postprocessing</italic>” section. Mouse protein sequences were acquired from SwissProt in October 2023, and ID mapping was performed using the AnnotationDbi R package (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) and org.Mm.eg.db (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Mouse phosphorylation sites were filtered to those with an exact amino acid match in the protein sequence at the position identified in the sentence.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.8">
      <title>Kinase and Phosphatase Annotation</title>
      <p id="p0115">Human protein kinases were downloaded from KinBase (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://kinase.com/web/current/kinbase/genes/SpeciesID/9606/" id="intref0015">http://kinase.com/web/current/kinbase/genes/SpeciesID/9606/</ext-link>) (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) and SwissProt (keyword:“Kinase [KW-0418]” AND reviewed:yes AND organism:“<italic>Homo sapiens</italic> (Human) [9606]”) (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>) in November 2021. Human phosphatases were downloaded from DEPOD (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) and filtered to those with an “active” status and in a protein phosphatase family (AP, CDC25, DUSP, EYA, FCP, HP1, HP2, LMWPTP, NagD, PPM, PPP, PTP, RTR1, and SSU72) in November 2021. Mouse protein kinases were downloaded from KinBase (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://kinase.com/web/current/kinbase/genes/SpeciesID/10090/" id="intref0020">http://kinase.com/web/current/kinbase/genes/SpeciesID/10090/</ext-link>) in October 2023. Mouse protein phosphatases were downloaded from SwissProt (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) in October 2023 with the keyword KW-0904 (keyword:KW-0904 AND reviewed:true AND model_organism:10090). All extracted genes from sentences with a positive prediction for a phosphorylation site were submitted to the NCBI gene search as described in the “<italic>Concept normalization and postprocessing” section</italic>. Genes were annotated as kinases or phosphatases if the gene symbol after normalization matched a kinase or phosphatase gene symbol in the downloaded lists.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.9">
      <title>Comparison to PhosphoSitePlus</title>
      <p id="p0120">Phosphorylation site information and the regulatory site tables were downloaded from PhosphoSitePlus (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>) in January 2023. The kinase–substrate table was downloaded from PhosphoSitePlus in September 2023. All tables were filtered to the human organism and a “-p” modification. For kinase–substrate comparison, autophosphorylation events were excluded.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.10">
      <title>Comparison to Clinical Proteomics Tumor Analysis Consortium Phosphoproteomics Data</title>
      <p id="p0125">Clinical Proteomics Tumor Analysis Consortium (CPTAC) pan-cancer data were acquired from Ref. (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Spearman correlation between ING5-T152 phosphorylation abundance and HALLMARK activity scores and between AKT1 activity scores and all phosphorylation sites were performed using LinkedOmicsKB (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1.11">
      <title>Website Development</title>
      <p id="p0130">Finalized results were stored in an SQLite database (version 3.7.17). The website was developed with PHP (version 5.6) and Slim framework (version 3) on the backend. The frontend was based on Fomantic UI (version 2.8), and search results are displayed in a table with Bootstrap-table (version 1.21). The graph was built with D3.js (version 7).</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2">
    <title>Results</title>
    <sec id="sec2.1">
      <title>Deep Learning NLP Model Generation to Automatically Extract Phosphosites</title>
      <p id="p0135">The NLP pipeline (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>) to generate a model identifying phosphosites on proteins consists of multiple steps: (1) preprocessing abstracts to extract tokens from sentences, (2) named entity recognition (NER) to identify protein names and amino acid positions for corresponding sites, (3) manual corpus annotation to curate a gold standard positive training set, and (4) relation recognition and fine-tuning of a pretrained deep learning NLP method to automatically identify the substrate–phosphosite pairs.<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p><bold>Model pipeline to extract phosphorylation sites from abstracts.</bold> Abstract text was separated into sentences and tokenized, and named entity recognition was performed using regular expressions and BERN to label potential substrates and potential site positions. Substrate and site pairs were encoded in each sentence, which was then classified using BioBERT. BioBERT, Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers for biomedical text mining.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p>
      <p id="p0140">To create a gold standard list of phosphosites mentioned in abstracts to use for training and validation, we downloaded the Regulatory Sites file from PhosphoSitePlus and the sites with known kinases from Signor. We used only human sites and generated a list containing the amino acid location of the phosphosite, the gene symbol of its substrate protein, and the associated PubMed Manuscript ID. We randomly selected 3000 abstracts from this list to use for model training.</p>
      <p id="p0145">The abstracts were broken into sentences and tokens using CLAMP, and NER was used to label tokens as protein names or site positions. Regular expressions and dictionary look-up were used to identify site positions, whereas BERN was used to identify protein names. Manual annotation of the corpus was performed to identify which site position belonged to which protein within a single sentence. All other candidate site positions and candidate substrates were used as negative relationships. There were 16,729 sentences for positive relationships and 27,591 sentences for negative relationships. We used 10-fold cross validation to fine-tune BioBERT to generate 10 models that could classify a relationship between a potential substrate and potential site. The 10 models had an average precision of 92.7%, recall of 94.3%, specificity of 95.5%, and F1 score of 93.5% (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>).<fig id="fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p><bold>Model performance for identifying the correct substrate and site pairs in 10-fold cross validation.</bold><italic>Boxes</italic> indicate median and interquartile range for the results from 10 models.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p>
      <p id="p0150">We manually curated an additional 150 abstracts with phosphosites and used these for independent model validation. Majority voting of the 10 models performed slightly better than the individual model with the best cross F1 score (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). Unanimous voting of the 10 models had the best precision but worst recall (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>).<fig id="fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p><bold>Independent performance on correctly identifying phosphorylation sites from 150 abstracts.</bold> Three different methods were used to combine the results from 10 different models. A substrate and site in a sentence was classified as a positive if six or more models classified it as 1 (majority), all 10 models classified it as 1 (unanimous), or if the best performing model classified it as 1 (best).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.2">
      <title>Normalization of Phosphosite Representation to Human Sequences</title>
      <p id="p0155">After extracting phosphosites from the literature, the sites need to be normalized to have a consistent format for downstream analysis. Site positions were transformed using regular expressions to a single letter amino acid code followed by the numerical position (<italic>e.g.</italic>, S315). To prioritize sites that could be mapped to human genes, protein names were transformed to gene symbols using the top human result from NCBI. After normalization, the model precision on the validation set for individual phosphosites in specific PMIDs was 0.58 with a recall of 0.81. This validation involves an additional component beyond the BioBERT classification step as both the correct substrate and site must be extracted and the correct gene symbol must be selected for the substrate. For example, in the sentence “Rsk was phosphorylated on Thr573 by ERK1,” majority voting by the 10 fine-tuned BioBERT models might correctly classify Thr573 as a phosphorylation site on the substrate Rsk. However, an error may occur when transforming Rsk to the gene symbol RPS6KA1 and Thr573 to T573. Indeed, most of the precision loss at this step was due to the incorrect selection of gene symbols from the originally identified terms. To improve the precision of the results, we used ProtMapper to map the identified phosphosite to human reference protein sequences. Any site that could not be mapped to the reference was discarded. This improved precision to 0.91 with a slight drop in recall to 0.77.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.3">
      <title>Data Statistics of the Extracted Substrate–Site Pairs</title>
      <p id="p0160">To systematically illuminate the dark phosphoproteome, we used our model, named IDPpub, to extract phosphorylation sites in all MEDLINE abstracts. We identified phosphorylation sites in 253,443 abstracts. After entity normalization and ProtMapper filtering, we extracted from 58,227 abstracts 18,458 unique phosphorylation sites that could be mapped to human proteins. These covered 46% of the human phosphorylation sites with low-throughput evidence in PhosphoSitePlus and 57% of the human sites with regulatory information (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). Importantly, we extracted sentences for 11,634 sites that did not have regulatory information in or were not linked to low-throughput publications by PhosphoSitePlus.<fig id="fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p><bold>Numbers of sites with annotated regulatory information from PhosphoSitePlus, low-throughput publications from PhosphoSitePlus, and extracted sentences from IDPpub</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p>
      <p id="p0165">The CPTAC studies on 10 cancer types have identified over 125,000 human phosphorylation sites using mass spectrometry (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Only 3% of these sites have annotated regulatory information in PhosphoSitePlus. The human phosphorylation sites extracted from abstracts by IDPpub included 4117 CPTAC phosphorylation sites, 1803 of which have no annotated regulatory information. In addition, extracted sentences may describe roles in disease that are not captured in PhosphoSitePlus. For example, DOCK1-Y1811 has no annotated regulatory information in PhosphoSitePlus but has a role in cell growth and invasion in glioblastoma according to the extracted publication (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). In addition, ING5-T152 is regulated by the cell cycle (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) and involved in tumor cell proliferation. This site was positively correlated with proliferation-related cell signatures across multiple cancer types (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). Some additional examples are found in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.<fig id="fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p><bold>Spearman’s correlation between ING5 T152 phosphorylation abundance and the HALLMARK E2F Target score in four CPTAC cancer studies.</bold> CPTAC, Clinical Proteomics Tumor Analysis Consortium.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Examples of extracted phosphorylation site evidence not curated in PhosphoSitePlus for phosphosites identified in CPTAC studies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Substrate</th><th>Site</th><th>PMID</th><th>Sentence</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>DOCK1</td><td>Y1811</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="22080864" id="intref0035">22080864</ext-link></td><td>Here, we report that PDGFRα signaling in glioblastomas leads to Src-dependent phosphorylation of the guanine nucleotide exchange factor <bold>Dock180</bold> at <bold>tyrosine 1811 (Dock180(Y1811))</bold> that results in activation of the GTPase Rac1 and subsequent cell growth and invasion</td></tr><tr><td>ING5</td><td>T152</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25860957" id="intref0040">25860957</ext-link></td><td>In summary we identified a phosphorylation site at <bold>threonine 152</bold> of I<bold>NG5</bold> that is cell cycle regulated, and we observed that <bold>ING5</bold> is necessary for tumor cell proliferation, without any apparent dependency on the tumor suppressor p53</td></tr><tr><td>ZNF148</td><td>S306</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32060966" id="intref0045">32060966</ext-link></td><td>The clinical analysis indicates that SDHB deficiency is associated with elevated <bold>ZNF148</bold> levels, and <bold>ZNF148-S306</bold> phosphorylation level displays a positive correlation with poor prognosis in GIST patients</td></tr><tr><td>PXN</td><td>S178</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32064167" id="intref0050">32064167</ext-link></td><td>Hepatitis B virus X protein promotes tumor invasion and poor prognosis in hepatocellular carcinoma <italic>via</italic> phosphorylation of <bold>paxillin</bold> at <bold>Serine 178</bold> by activation of the c-Jun NH2-terminal kinase</td></tr><tr><td>ITPRID2</td><td>S92</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="26947549" id="intref0055">26947549</ext-link></td><td>From these results, we demonstrate that phospho-<bold>SSFA2 (pS92)</bold> is related to the prognosis of early resected lung adenocarcinomas</td></tr><tr><td>TMIGD2</td><td>S220</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="27838321" id="intref0060">27838321</ext-link></td><td>Trans-homophilic dimerization of <bold>IGPR-1</bold> stimulates the phosphorylation of <bold>serine 220 (Ser220)</bold>, which is required for <bold>IGPR-1</bold> to regulate endothelial barrier function and angiogenesis</td></tr><tr><td>NES</td><td>T315</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="28002641" id="intref0065">28002641</ext-link></td><td><bold>Nestin</bold> phosphorylation at <bold>threonines 315</bold> and 1299 correlates with proliferation and metastasis of human pancreatic cancer</td></tr><tr><td>EPHA2</td><td>S897</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30412282" id="intref0070">30412282</ext-link></td><td><italic>In vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> experiments revealed that <bold>EPHA2</bold> mutations could lead to ligand independent phosphorylation of <bold>Ser897,</bold> and promote lymphatic metastasis of ICC, in which NOTCH1 signaling pathway played an important role</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Identified substrates and sites are noted in bold.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.4">
      <title>Extracted Sentences Support Conclusions From Phosphoproteomics Experiments</title>
      <p id="p0170">Phosphoproteomics data can be used as a readout of the activity of kinases and phosphatases, the enzymes responsible for adding or removing phosphate groups. We correlated all phosphorylation site abundances with AKT1 activity scores in the CPTAC pan-cancer datasets to identify potential substrates of AKT1 in cancer. Based on the meta <italic>p</italic> value of the association across 10 CPTAC cancer cohorts, the top associated site was AKT1S1 T246, which is a marker of AKT1 activity (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) and contributes to the activity score. The third best correlated site, AFDN S1799 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>), had no current annotation in relation to AKT1 in either PhosphositePlus (Cell Signaling Technology) or Signor. In contrast, IDPpub extracted a sentence from a study identifying AFDN S1799 as a target of AKT in breast cancer cells (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). There are many similar examples connecting a phosphorylation site identified in the CPTAC data to a regulatory kinase that has not been associated with the site in PhosphoSitePlus (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<fig id="fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p><bold>Spearman’s correlation between AFDN S1799 phosphorylation abundance and AKT1 kinase activity scores in four CPTAC cancer studies.</bold> CPTAC, Clinical Proteomics Tumor Analysis Consortium.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr6"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Examples of kinases for phosphorylation sites not curated in PhosphoSitePlus but extracted by IDPpub</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Kinase</th><th>Substrate</th><th>Site position</th><th>Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>AKT</td><td>AFDN</td><td>S1799</td><td align="char">24269953</td></tr><tr><td>IKKβ</td><td>MTDH</td><td>S298</td><td align="char">25849741</td></tr><tr><td>CDK1</td><td>PRC1</td><td>T470</td><td align="char">17438553</td></tr><tr><td>CDK5</td><td>PPP1R1B</td><td>T75</td><td align="char">1295672,<break/>1474424,<break/>1546412,<break/>22820052</td></tr><tr><td>ERK</td><td>ZNF148</td><td>S306</td><td align="char">32060966</td></tr><tr><td>GSK3β</td><td>KIF1A</td><td>S402</td><td align="char">33067366</td></tr><tr><td>PKA</td><td>NOS1</td><td>S1417</td><td align="char">23012472</td></tr><tr><td>CaMKII</td><td>NOS1</td><td>S852</td><td align="char">33121174</td></tr><tr><td>FYN</td><td>G6PD</td><td>Y401</td><td align="char">32863204</td></tr><tr><td>GSK3β</td><td>IKZF1</td><td>S391</td><td align="char">32807499</td></tr><tr><td>TrkB</td><td>APP</td><td>Y762</td><td align="char">32782380</td></tr><tr><td>GSK3β</td><td>NPM1</td><td>T95</td><td align="char">32686519</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
      <p id="p0175">To support the identification of regulatory information from sentences, we further annotated all kinases and phosphatases in the sentences. We identified 20,614 co-occurrences between a kinase and a phosphorylation site in 29,080 sentences. About 20% of the co-occurrences between kinases and phosphorylation sites represented known kinase–substrate relationships from PhosphoSitePlus. Furthermore, these co-occurrences covered 31% of the known human kinase–substrate relationships in PhosphoSitePlus.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.5">
      <title>Extension to Model Organisms</title>
      <p id="p0180">While human phosphorylation sites are the most widely studied, information on phosphorylation sites on model organisms is also important. We used PubTator to identify species information for the 253,443 abstracts with extracted phosphorylation sites. Over half (131,435) of the abstracts were annotated with human, whereas the second most common species was mouse (Taxonomy ID: 10090) with 59,719 abstracts. Fewer than 5% of the abstracts were annotated with other model species. We performed the post-processing steps for the abstracts annotated with mouse to identify mouse gene IDs and protein sequences. We filtered for any sites with an exact match between the site position extracted from the sentence and the mouse protein sequence for that gene. After filtering, we found 5918 phosphorylation sites in 14,610 abstracts.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.6">
      <title>Repository</title>
      <p id="p0185">We generated a searchable repository of all phosphorylation sites extracted from abstracts, which can be accessed at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://idppub.ptmax.org" id="PC_linkJilmGpIydx">http://idppub.ptmax.org</ext-link> (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>). We provide three versions of the extracted sites in the web portal. The first is the set of phosphorylation sites aligned to human proteins. The second is the set of phosphorylation sites that match mouse proteins. The third is the full results without gene normalization, and these results are annotated with taxonomy information from PubTator so that they can be filtered for specific species. For each version, a user can search for an individual gene, an individual single site on a gene, or a list of sites. The web portal provides a bar plot illustrating the number of sentences containing each site and a table of extracted sentences with links to the publications. The substrate, the phosphosite, and any co-occurring kinases and phosphatases are highlighted in each sentence. The sentences can be further searched for the exact match of terms, such as “apoptosis” or “tumor,” which could be used to filter for function or disease relations.<fig id="fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p><bold>Example of the IDPpub web portal results for MTDH</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr7"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec3">
    <title>Discussion</title>
    <p id="p0190">Mass spectrometry–based phosphoproteomics profiling offers tremendous potential for biological discoveries, but interpretation of phosphoproteomics sites identified from such studies is hampered by our limited knowledge on functions, biological contexts, or precipitating enzymes of the phosphosites. Extracting what is known from the literature is time consuming and often requires advanced biological knowledge. This study takes a hybrid approach combining deep learning–based NLP models and domain knowledge–based rules to automatically extract substrates, the positions of phosphorylated amino acids on these substrates, and corresponding evidence sentences from biomedical abstracts.</p>
    <p id="p0195">The evidence sentences extracted can quickly be assessed for potential biological context without scanning entire articles and can also point users to interesting articles for further reading. After identifying a set of phosphosites associated with a phenotype, scientists are currently limited to the functional information in manually curated databases such as PhosphoSitePlus. The literature must be searched for information not yet present in curated databases for all other sites individually. With IDPpub, users can quickly find additional evidence from all PubMed abstracts for phosphosites in bulk. Similarly, manually curated kinase–substrate information is poor in databases, with phosphatase–substrate information even more minimal. We have added annotations for kinases and phosphatases that co-occur in the same sentence as phosphorylation sites. While a co-occurrence does not necessarily indicate a true relationship, these annotations can help identify potential regulating enzymes.</p>
    <p id="p0200">We developed IDPpub to be as accurate as possible while also prioritizing high recall as sentences containing false-positive relationships can be easily discarded upon manual review. However, IDPpub could still be improved in future iterations. While the model is reasonably accurate in selecting the correct substrate for a phosphorylation site in a sentence, the normalization to a gene symbol is still challenging. This is partly because of nonunique names for proteins. For example, “PDK1” may refer to either 3-phosphoinositide-dependent protein kinase-1 (protein name PDK1, gene symbol <italic>PDPK1</italic>) or pyruvate dehydrogenase kinase 1 (gene symbol <italic>PDK1</italic>). In addition, accuracy of selecting the correct gene symbol is also diminished by inaccurate boundary detection of the NER step. For example, the model may identify “CRK” as the substrate instead of the full string “CRK-II.” This issue accounts for the drop in performance between the initial cross validation and validation of the BioBERT step on an additional 150 abstracts. For the training data, manual curation included setting the correct boundaries for both substrates and sites within a sentence to optimize the training of the relation extraction task. For the 150 test abstracts, we did not adjust the NER-defined boundaries as that would not be feasible to apply to the full database for prediction. In the future, correct boundary detection and identification of substrates in a sentence can be improved using new models (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>).</p>
    <p id="p0205">Improvements could also be made for extracting the correct site position. MESH terms could be used to filter biomedical articles to avoid false recognition of cell or chemical names, such as T-4 cells, that have a similar naming convention to the notations used for designating amino acid positions that are phosphosites. Also, normalizing the location of a site is still a major issue in the field of phosphoproteomics. Site localization is typically reported based on a reference protein sequence, which may come from one of several different sequence databases and can vary over time and between different protein isoforms. Manually searching the literature for a site identified in a phosphoproteomics experiment is a challenge because the manuscripts studying that site may list a completely different position that could even be over 100 amino acids away. For example, Bailey <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) described phosphorylation of tau on T149 and T153, which correspond to numbering on isoform 8 but are analogous to T466 and T470 on the canonical tau isoform. In IDPpub, we align the sites to the human UniProt sequences using ProtMapper. This improves consistency with PhosphoSitePlus but may not easily be applied to nonhuman studies or those where other human protein sequence databases are used as references. Indeed, identifying the species associated with phosphorylation sites mentioned in an abstract is a significant challenge, even from a manual reading. In our study, we aligned the sites to protein sequences from human and mouse, which were associated with 50% and 20% of the abstracts containing extracted phosphorylation sites, respectively. Furthermore, we provided a table that includes all sites extracted from sentences without alignment, along with the PubTator-annotated species information for the corresponding abstracts. This table can be valuable for filtering phosphosites in organisms beyond human and mouse.</p>
    <p id="p0210">The utility of IDPpub can be extended through the mining of full biomedical texts, which will increase the number of extracted sites and evidence sentences. Importantly, IDPpub can be automatically updated with newly published articles, providing continual utility to the community. Moreover, IDPpub can be modified with new regular expressions to capture additional post-translational modifications (PTMs). The ability to quickly filter primary literature for manual review enhances the usability of the data from high-throughput studies measuring various types of PTMs. Moving forward, we will also develop new models to identify and normalize other important elements from the sentences containing extracted PTM sites, such as the enzyme manipulating the PTM and the regulatory function of the modification. These enhancements will facilitate downstream analyses such as functional enrichment of a set of phosphorylation sites. Furthermore, with the accurate identification of enzyme–substrate relationships, we can further refine the analysis of binding motifs for regulatory enzymes.</p>
    <p id="p0215">In summary, the current implementation of IDPpub and its search tools are valuable complements to existing phosphorylation information portals. Ongoing improvements will further contribute to a deeper understanding of the phosphoproteome and other PTMomes.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec4">
    <title>Data Availability</title>
    <p id="p0220">All identified phosphosites and associated sentences can be searched and browsed at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://idppub.ptmax.org" id="PC_linkV5BPnkd2jB">http://idppub.ptmax.org</ext-link>. The whole dataset can also be downloaded from the website through the download link.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
    <title>Conflict of interest</title>
    <p id="p0225">The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ref-list id="cebib0010">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="bib1">
      <label>1</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sharma</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>D’Souza</surname>
            <given-names>R.C.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tyanova</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schaab</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wiśniewski</surname>
            <given-names>J.R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cox</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Ultradeep human phosphoproteome reveals a distinct regulatory nature of Tyr and Ser/Thr-based signaling</article-title>
        <source>Cell Rep.</source>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <year>2014</year>
        <fpage>1583</fpage>
        <lpage>1594</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25159151</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib2">
      <label>2</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <collab>UniProt Consortium</collab>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>UniProt: the universal protein knowledgebase in 2021</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>49</volume>
        <year>2021</year>
        <fpage>D480</fpage>
        <lpage>D489</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33237286</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib3">
      <label>3</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hornbeck</surname>
            <given-names>P.V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Murray</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kornhauser</surname>
            <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Latham</surname>
            <given-names>V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Skrzypek</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>PhosphoSitePlus, 2014: mutations, PTMs and recalibrations</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>43</volume>
        <year>2015</year>
        <fpage>D512</fpage>
        <lpage>D520</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25514926</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib4">
      <label>4</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Torii</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Arighi</surname>
            <given-names>C.N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Q.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>C.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vijay-Shanker</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>RLIMS-P 2.0: a generalizable rule-based information extraction system for literature mining of protein phosphorylation information</article-title>
        <source>IEEE/ACM Trans. Comput. Biol. Bioinform.</source>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <year>2015</year>
        <fpage>17</fpage>
        <lpage>29</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26357075</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib5">
      <label>5</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Raja</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Natarajan</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Mining protein phosphorylation information from biomedical literature using NLP parsing and support vector machines</article-title>
        <source>Comput. Methods Programs Biomed.</source>
        <volume>160</volume>
        <year>2018</year>
        <fpage>57</fpage>
        <lpage>64</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29728247</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib6">
      <label>6</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Elangovan</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pires</surname>
            <given-names>D.E.V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Davis</surname>
            <given-names>M.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Verspoor</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Large-scale protein-protein post-translational modification extraction with distant supervision and confidence calibrated BioBERT</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinform.</source>
        <volume>23</volume>
        <year>2022</year>
        <fpage>4</fpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib7">
      <label>7</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yoon</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>So</surname>
            <given-names>C.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>BioBERT: a pre-trained biomedical language representation model for biomedical text mining</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <volume>36</volume>
        <year>2020</year>
        <fpage>1234</fpage>
        <lpage>1240</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31501885</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib8">
      <label>8</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Soysal</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jiang</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pakhomov</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Clamp - a toolkit for efficiently building customized clinical natural language processing pipelines</article-title>
        <source>J. Am. Med. Inform. Assoc.</source>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <year>2018</year>
        <fpage>331</fpage>
        <lpage>336</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29186491</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib9">
      <label>9</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>So</surname>
            <given-names>C.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jeon</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jeong</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Choi</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A neural named entity recognition and multi-type normalization tool for biomedical text mining</article-title>
        <source>IEEE Access</source>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <year>2019</year>
        <fpage>73729</fpage>
        <lpage>73740</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib10">
      <label>10</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Licata</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lo Surdo</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Iannuccelli</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Palma</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Micarelli</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Perfetto</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>SIGNOR 2.0, the SIGnaling Network open resource 2.0: 2019 update</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>48</volume>
        <year>2020</year>
        <fpage>D504</fpage>
        <lpage>D510</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31665520</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib11">
      <label>11</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11">
        <comment>[preprint]</comment>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bachman</surname>
            <given-names>J.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sorger</surname>
            <given-names>P.K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gyori</surname>
            <given-names>B.M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Assembling a corpus of phosphoproteomic annotations using ProtMapper to normalize site information from databases and text mining</article-title>
        <source>bioRxiv</source>
        <year>2022</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/822668</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib12">
      <label>12</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wei</surname>
            <given-names>C.-H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Allot</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Leaman</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>Z.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>PubTator central: automated concept annotation for biomedical full text articles</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>47</volume>
        <year>2019</year>
        <fpage>W587</fpage>
        <lpage>W593</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31114887</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib13">
      <label>13</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pagès</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Carlson</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Falcon</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>AnnotationDbi: manipulation of SQLite-based annotations in bioconductor. R package version 1.62.2</article-title>
        <source>Bioconductor</source>
        <year>2023</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18129/B9.bioc.AnnotationDbi</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib14">
      <label>14</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Carlson</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>org.Mm.eg.db: genome wide annotation for mouse. R package version 3.8.2</article-title>
        <source>Bioconductor</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18129/B9.bioc.org.Mm.eg.db</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib15">
      <label>15</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Manning</surname>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Whyte</surname>
            <given-names>D.B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Martinez</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hunter</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sudarsanam</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The protein kinase complement of the human genome</article-title>
        <source>Science</source>
        <volume>298</volume>
        <year>2002</year>
        <fpage>1912</fpage>
        <lpage>1934</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12471243</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib16">
      <label>16</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Damle</surname>
            <given-names>N.P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Köhn</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The human DEPhOsphorylation Database DEPOD: 2019 update</article-title>
        <source>Database</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/database/baz133</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib17">
      <label>17</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17">
        <article-title>UniProt: the universal protein knowledgebase in 2023</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>51</volume>
        <year>2023</year>
        <fpage>D523</fpage>
        <lpage>D531</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36408920</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib18">
      <label>18</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dou</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Da Veiga Leprevost</surname>
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Geffen</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Calinawan</surname>
            <given-names>A.P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Aguet</surname>
            <given-names>F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Proteogenomic data and resources for pan-cancer analysis</article-title>
        <source>Cancer Cell</source>
        <volume>41</volume>
        <year>2023</year>
        <fpage>1397</fpage>
        <lpage>1406</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37582339</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib19">
      <label>19</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liao</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Savage</surname>
            <given-names>S.R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dou</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shi</surname>
            <given-names>Z.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yi</surname>
            <given-names>X.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jiang</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A proteogenomics data-driven knowledge base of human cancer</article-title>
        <source>Cell Syst.</source>
        <volume>14</volume>
        <year>2023</year>
        <fpage>777</fpage>
        <lpage>787.e5</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37619559</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib20">
      <label>20</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Feng</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>K.-W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>X.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cheng</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Activation of Rac1 by Src-dependent phosphorylation of Dock180(Y1811) mediates PDGFRα-stimulated glioma tumorigenesis in mice and humans</article-title>
        <source>J. Clin. Invest.</source>
        <volume>121</volume>
        <year>2011</year>
        <fpage>4670</fpage>
        <lpage>4684</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22080864</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib21">
      <label>21</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Linzen</surname>
            <given-names>U.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lilischkis</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pandithage</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schilling</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ullius</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lüscher-Firzlaff</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>ING5 is phosphorylated by CDK2 and controls cell proliferation independently of p53</article-title>
        <source>PLoS One</source>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <year>2015</year>
        <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0123736</object-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib22">
      <label>22</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kovacina</surname>
            <given-names>K.S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>G.Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bae</surname>
            <given-names>S.S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Guzzetta</surname>
            <given-names>A.W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schaefer</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Birnbaum</surname>
            <given-names>M.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Identification of a proline-rich Akt substrate as a 14-3-3 binding partner</article-title>
        <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
        <volume>278</volume>
        <year>2003</year>
        <fpage>10189</fpage>
        <lpage>10194</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12524439</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib23">
      <label>23</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Elloul</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kedrin</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Knoblauch</surname>
            <given-names>N.W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Beck</surname>
            <given-names>A.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Toker</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The adherens junction protein afadin is an AKT substrate that regulates breast cancer cell migration</article-title>
        <source>Mol. Cancer Res.</source>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <year>2014</year>
        <fpage>464</fpage>
        <lpage>476</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24269953</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib24">
      <label>24</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Allot</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Peng</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wei</surname>
            <given-names>C.-H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Phan</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>Z.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>LitVar: a semantic search engine for linking genomic variant data in PubMed and PMC</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <volume>46</volume>
        <year>2018</year>
        <fpage>W530</fpage>
        <lpage>W536</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29762787</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib25">
      <label>25</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bailey</surname>
            <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Covy</surname>
            <given-names>J.P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Melrose</surname>
            <given-names>H.L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rousseau</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Watkinson</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Knight</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>LRRK2 phosphorylates novel tau epitopes and promotes tauopathy</article-title>
        <source>Acta Neuropathol.</source>
        <volume>126</volume>
        <year>2013</year>
        <fpage>809</fpage>
        <lpage>827</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24113872</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
  <ack id="ack0010">
    <title>Acknowledgments</title>
    <p id="p0230">This work was supported by the <funding-source id="gs2"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000002</institution-id><institution>National Institutes of Health</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> grants from the <funding-source id="gs4"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000054</institution-id><institution>National Cancer Institute</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (grant nos.: U24 CA271076 and R01 CA245903, by <funding-source id="gs6"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100004917</institution-id><institution>Cancer Prevention &amp; Research Institute of Texas</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> Awards RR160027 and RP220050, and funding from the McNair Medical Institute at The <funding-source id="gs8"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100001234</institution-id><institution>Robert and Janice McNair Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>.</p>
    <sec id="sec5">
      <title>Funding and additional information</title>
      <p id="p0235">B. Z. is a <funding-source id="gs5"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100004917</institution-id><institution>Cancer Prevention &amp; Research Institute of Texas</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> scholar in cancer research and a McNair scholar.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec6">
      <title>Author contributions</title>
      <p id="p0240">S. R. S., E. J. J., and B. Z. conceptualization; Y. Z. and H. X. methodology; Y. Z., Y. L., Z. S., and H. A. P. software; S. R. S. and Y. Z. validation; S. R. S. and Y. Z. formal analysis; S. R. S. investigation; H. X. resources; S. R. S. and E. J. J. data curation; S. R. S. and Y. Z. writing–original draft; E. J. J., Y. L., Z. S., and B. Z. writing–review &amp; editing; S. R. S. visualization; H. X. and B. Z. supervision; B. Z. project administration; H. X. and B. Z. funding acquisition.</p>
    </sec>
  </ack>
</back>
