<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?properties open_access?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1367-4803</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1367-4811</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">10017096</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36857576</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btad111</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">btad111</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Applications Note</subject>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading">
          <subject>Structural Bioinformatics</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01060</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>RSCanner: rapid assessment and visualization of RNA structure content</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Mahadeshwar</surname>
          <given-names>Gandhar</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Department of Molecular Biophysics and Biochemistry, Yale University</institution>, New Haven, CT 06511, <country country="US">United States</country></aff>
        <xref rid="btad111-FM1" ref-type="author-notes"/>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0278-1528</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Tavares</surname>
          <given-names>Rafael de Cesaris Araujo</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Department of Chemistry, Yale University</institution>, New Haven, CT 06511, <country country="US">United States</country></aff>
        <xref rid="btad111-FM1" ref-type="author-notes"/>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Wan</surname>
          <given-names>Han</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Department of Molecular, Cellular and Developmental Biology, Yale University</institution>, New Haven, CT 06511, <country country="US">United States</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8375-8436</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Perry</surname>
          <given-names>Zion R</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Department of Molecular Biophysics and Biochemistry, Yale University</institution>, New Haven, CT 06511, <country country="US">United States</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <name>
          <surname>Pyle</surname>
          <given-names>Anna Marie</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Department of Chemistry, Yale University</institution>, New Haven, CT 06511, <country country="US">United States</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>Department of Molecular, Cellular and Developmental Biology, Yale University</institution>, New Haven, CT 06511, <country country="US">United States</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>Howard Hughes Medical Institute</institution>, Chevy Chase, MD 20815, <country country="US">United States</country></aff>
        <xref rid="btad111-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
        <!--anna.pyle@yale.edu-->
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name>
          <surname>Ponty</surname>
          <given-names>Yann</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Associate Editor</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="btad111-cor1">Corresponding author. Department of Molecular, Cellular and Developmental Biology, Yale University, 266 Whitney Avenue, Yale Science Building Room 306, New Haven, CT, 06511, United States. E-mail: <email>anna.pyle@yale.edu</email></corresp>
      <fn id="btad111-FM1">
        <p>Gandhar Mahadeshwar and Rafael de Cesaris Araujo Tavares contributed equally to this work.</p>
      </fn>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <month>3</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2023-03-01">
      <day>01</day>
      <month>3</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>01</day>
      <month>3</month>
      <year>2023</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>39</volume>
    <issue>3</issue>
    <elocation-id>btad111</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>09</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>06</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="editorial-decision">
        <day>27</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>27</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="corrected-typeset">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2023. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xlink:href="btad111.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <sec id="s1">
        <title>Motivation</title>
        <p>The increasing availability of RNA structural information that spans many kilobases of transcript sequence imposes a need for tools that can rapidly screen, identify, and prioritize structural modules of interest.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2">
        <title>Results</title>
        <p>We describe <italic toggle="yes">R</italic>NA <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>tructural <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>ontent Sc<italic toggle="yes">anner</italic> (RSCanner), an automated tool that scans RNA transcripts for regions that contain high levels of secondary structure and then classifies each region for its relative propensity to adopt stable or dynamic structures. RSCanner then generates an intuitive heatmap enabling users to rapidly pinpoint regions likely to contain a high or low density of discrete RNA structures, thereby informing downstream functional or structural investigation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3">
        <title>Availability and implementation</title>
        <p>RSCanner is freely available as both R script and R Markdown files, along with full documentation and test data (<ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/pylelab/RSCanner" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/pylelab/RSCanner</ext-link>).</p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>National Human Genome Research Institute</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100000051</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>HG011868</award-id>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship Program</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>DGE-2139841</award-id>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="3"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec>
    <title>1 Introduction</title>
    <p>The advent of powerful platforms for RNA structure interrogation (<xref rid="btad111-B11" ref-type="bibr">Smola et al. 2015</xref>) has generated large amounts of structural data for individual RNAs and even whole transcriptomes (<xref rid="btad111-B14" ref-type="bibr">Zubradt et al. 2017</xref>). We can now visualize RNA secondary structure models, which can be used as roadmaps for planning downstream functional studies on individual transcripts. Given our enhanced ability to accurately model the structures of RNAs that are several kilobases in length (<xref rid="btad111-B4" ref-type="bibr">Huston et al. 2021</xref>), there is an increased need to prioritize structural features within new RNA targets and to identify stable regions of fixed base-pair content (BPC). RNA regions that sample a limited number of stable structural conformers are good candidates for structure–function studies and subsequent 3D elucidation (<xref rid="btad111-B1" ref-type="bibr">Akiyama et al. 2021</xref>). In contrast, unstructured and conformationally variable regions can also play important functional roles, and they may serve as useful probe hybridization sites (<xref rid="btad111-B7" ref-type="bibr">McHugh and Guttman 2018</xref>). Despite the availability of tools for detecting structured RNA regions derived from experimental data (<xref rid="btad111-B8" ref-type="bibr">Quarrier et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="btad111-B11" ref-type="bibr">Smola et al. 2015</xref>; <xref rid="btad111-B3" ref-type="bibr">Gilmore et al. 2017</xref>; <xref rid="btad111-B5" ref-type="bibr">Incarnato et al. 2018</xref>), there is currently no program that is able to quantify and rank the relative levels of RNA secondary structure <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>based on base-pairing probabilities.</p>
    <p>We previously introduced a strategy for computing stable BPC along the length of long RNA molecules such as viral genomes, thereby providing a means for selecting transcript modules for subsequent structural investigation (<xref rid="btad111-B2" ref-type="bibr">Tavares et al. 2021</xref>). In the current work, we present <italic toggle="yes">R</italic>NA <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>tructural <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>ontent Sc<italic toggle="yes">anner</italic> (RSCanner), an R package that automates and extends the previous methodology by including customized parameters and standardized outputs. RSCanner identifies and analyzes modules of high BPC across any RNA target of interest, regardless of length. RSCanner scans an RNA secondary structure model in windows, calculates relative BPC, and applies a Shannon entropy (SE) filter derived from base-pairing probabilities to identify regions where a high degree of secondary structure coincides with regions that are conformationally restricted or conformationally variable. In doing so, RSCanner enables the user to quickly pinpoint regions of high and low density of discrete RNA structures, which can significantly facilitate the choice of candidate regions for biochemical and structural analysis, as well as aid in downstream experimental design.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>2 Overview of RSCanner</title>
    <p>RSCanner is designed to evaluate the base-pairing content of an existing RNA secondary structure, regardless of its origin. The input secondary structure can be derived from an <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> calculation (<ext-link xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/?term=Tavares+RCA&amp;cauthor_id=33268519" ext-link-type="uri">Tavares</ext-link><xref rid="btad111-B2" ref-type="bibr">et al. 2021</xref>) or from an experimentally determined secondary structure, such as those derived from SHAPE experiments (<xref rid="btad111-B4" ref-type="bibr">Huston et al. 2021</xref>). During this process, RSCanner sequentially scans the input RNA secondary structure model, computes its relative BPC, and then assesses the conformational variability of the secondary structure across the RNA sequence. The program utilizes a secondary structure model that is expressed in connectivity table or dot-bracket format and a list of per-nucleotide SE values as inputs (<xref rid="btad111-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>, Step 1). Both inputs can be directly obtained from databases like Rfam (<xref rid="btad111-B6" ref-type="bibr">Kalvari et al. 2021</xref>) or computed through third-party RNA secondary structure prediction programs with or without experimental constraints, e.g. Superfold (<xref rid="btad111-B11" ref-type="bibr">Smola et al. 2015</xref>) and RNAstructure (<xref rid="btad111-B9" ref-type="bibr">Reuter and Mathews 2010</xref>). Here, we have used Superfold to obtain the initial inputs for all RSCanner calculations. The BPC, defined here as the percent of double-stranded RNA, is calculated in sliding windows centered at each nucleotide across the entire RNA. SE values are smoothed by calculating the local median using the same sliding window approach (<xref rid="btad111-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>, Step 2). SE is calculated from the probability of the formation of each base pair across all possible RNA conformations during structure prediction. High SE indicates that the RNA samples multiple conformations, while low SE suggests that it adopts one major conformation (<xref rid="btad111-B13" ref-type="bibr">Weeks 2021</xref>). Nucleotides with BPC values above (i.e. more structured than) and SE below (i.e. less conformationally dynamic than) a user-defined threshold are termed ‘structure counts’ (<xref rid="btad111-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>, Step 3). By default, the program uses the global median (50th percentile) of both BPC and SE datasets as thresholds, but the user can adjust the stringency of these parameters by independently setting each cut-off value to a desired percentile. Finally, the frequency of structure counts (% structure content) is calculated in non-overlapping bins tiling the entire RNA, which is represented as a line plot with a 1D heatmap overlay (<xref rid="btad111-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>, Step 4). In contrast, if a user wishes to identify conformationally variable regions with high BPC (e.g. interconverting secondary structures), one can visually examine the intermediate graphic outputs for regions where high BPC correlates with high SE (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S1</xref>).</p>
    <fig position="float" id="btad111-F1">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>RSCanner workflow and application to the HCV RNA genome. (A) Flowchart of RSCanner algorithmic steps. (B) Final graphic output of RSCanner analysis on the HCV RNA genome. Note that the HCV genomic secondary structure that was used as input (Step 1, A) was obtained experimentally, as described in <xref rid="btad111-B12" ref-type="bibr">Wan et al. (2022)</xref>. The boundaries of HCV coding regions are shown under the plot. The plot is colored based on the percentage of structure content. (C) Table showing RSCanner data output (first four columns) along with previously characterized structures that overlap with each bin (fifth column)</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="btad111f1" position="float"/>
    </fig>
    <sec>
      <title>2.1 Graphic and text outputs</title>
      <p>RSCanner produces several graphic outputs, illustrated here using a recently published Hepatitis C virus (HCV) genomic RNA structure (<xref rid="btad111-B12" ref-type="bibr">Wan et al. 2022</xref>). First, it outputs the calculated BPC and smoothed SE values for individual nucleotides in line plots (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S2A and B</xref>) and in accompanying text files. Second, it saves the nucleotides that pass both filtering thresholds (structure counts) into a text file and plots a histogram (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S2C</xref>). Last, RSCanner produces a line plot with 1D heatmap overlay (<xref rid="btad111-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>), along with the corresponding data text file with binning windows in descending ordered of ‘% structure content’. Here, we note the top-scoring regions (highest % structure content) flagged in the HCV genome along with known RNA structural elements that overlap with them (<xref rid="btad111-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1C</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>2.2 User-adjustable parameters</title>
      <p>RSCanner allows the user to define several parameters. The sliding window size for BPC and/or SE smoothing and the bin size for the histogram can be changed to generate graphs of varying granularity. The lower and upper nucleotide bounds for visualization can also be altered, allowing the user to zoom in on specific regions of interest on the RNA. Furthermore, the stringency for filtering structure counts can be adjusted by individually varying the cut-off values for BPC and SE. For example, to increase the stringency, the user could increase the BPC cut-off value from the 25th to the 75th percentile (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S3A–C</xref>) and/or decrease the SE cut-off value from the 75th to 25th percentile (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S3A, D, and E</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>3 Results</title>
    <p>In addition to the HCV structure, we also applied RSCanner to other structured RNAs to illustrate its applicability to cases with and without experimental constraints: the HIV RNA genome, the SARS-CoV-2 Spike subgenomic RNA (sg-Spike), and the GRS1 long noncoding RNA (lncRNA GRS-1) (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S4</xref>). The SHAPE-informed HIV RNA secondary structure was obtained from its primary study (<xref rid="btad111-B10" ref-type="bibr">Siegfried et al. 2014</xref>), while the secondary structures for the other two RNAs were predicted with SuperFold (<xref rid="btad111-B11" ref-type="bibr">Smola et al. 2015</xref>) in the absence of experimental constraints.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
      <label>btad111_Supplementary_Data</label>
      <media xlink:href="btad111_supplementary_data.pdf">
        <caption>
          <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
        </caption>
      </media>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <sec>
    <title>Supplementary data</title>
    <p><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary data</xref> is available at <italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic> online.</p>
    <p>Conflict of interest: none declared.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>Funding</title>
    <p>This work was supported by the Howard Hughes Medical Institute to A.M.P.; the National Human Genome Research Institute [HG011868 to A.M.P.]; and the National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship Program [DGE-2139841 to Z.P.].</p>
  </sec>
  <ref-list id="ref1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="btad111-B1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Akiyama</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O Donoghue</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Three-dimensional structure of a flavivirus dumbbell RNA reveals molecular details of an RNA regulator of replication</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>7122</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34133732</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad111-B3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gilmore</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hejna</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Visualization of conformational variability in the domains of long single-stranded RNA molecules</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>8493</fpage>–<lpage>507</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28591846</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad111-B4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Huston</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Strine</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Comprehensive in vivo secondary structure of the SARS-CoV-2 genome reveals novel regulatory motifs and mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>584</fpage>–<lpage>98 e585</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33444546</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad111-B5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Incarnato</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morandi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>RNA framework: an all-in-one toolkit for the analysis of RNA structures and post-transcriptional modifications</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>e97</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29893890</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad111-B6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kalvari</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nawrocki</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ontiveros-Palacios</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Rfam 14: expanded coverage of metagenomic, viral and microRNA families</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>D192</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33211869</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad111-B7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>McHugh</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guttman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>RAP-MS: a method to identify proteins that interact directly with a specific RNA molecule in cells</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol Biol</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>1649</volume>:<fpage>473</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29130217</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad111-B8">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Quarrier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davis-Neulander</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Evaluation of the information content of RNA structure mapping data for secondary structure prediction</article-title>. <source>RNA</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1108</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20413617</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad111-B9">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Reuter</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mathews</surname><given-names>DH.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>RNAstructure: software for RNA secondary structure prediction and analysis</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>129</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20230624</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad111-B10">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Siegfried</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Busan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>RNA motif discovery by SHAPE and mutational profiling (SHAPE-MaP)</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>959</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25028896</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad111-B11">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Smola</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Busan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Selective 2'-hydroxyl acylation analyzed by primer extension and mutational profiling (SHAPE-MaP) for direct, versatile and accurate RNA structure analysis</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1643</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26426499</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad111-B2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tavares</surname><given-names>RCA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mahadeshwar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>The global and local distribution of RNA structure throughout the SARS-CoV-2 genome</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source><year>2021</year>;95(5):<fpage>e02190</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33268519</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad111-B12">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lindenbach</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>The in vivo and in vitro architecture of the hepatitis C virus RNA genome uncovers functional RNA secondary and tertiary structures</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>e0194621</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35353000</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad111-B13">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Weeks</surname><given-names>KM.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>SHAPE directed discovery of new functions in large RNAs</article-title>. <source>Acc Chem Res</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>2502</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33960770</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btad111-B14">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zubradt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Persad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><article-title>DMS-MaPseq for genome-wide or targeted RNA structure probing in vivo</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27819661</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
