<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">bioinfo</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1367-4803</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1367-4811</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3694644</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt238</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">btt238</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Ismb/Eccb 2013 Proceedings Papers Committee July 21 to July 23, 2013, Berlin, Germany</subject>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Original Papers</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Population Genomics</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>Efficient network-guided multi-locus association mapping with graph cuts</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Azencott</surname>
          <given-names>Chloé-Agathe</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btt238-AFF1">
          <sup>1</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="btt238-COR1">*</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Grimm</surname>
          <given-names>Dominik</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btt238-AFF1">
          <sup>1</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Sugiyama</surname>
          <given-names>Mahito</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btt238-AFF1">
          <sup>1</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Kawahara</surname>
          <given-names>Yoshinobu</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btt238-AFF1">
          <sup>2</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <name>
          <surname>Borgwardt</surname>
          <given-names>Karsten M.</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btt238-AFF1">
          <sup>1</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btt238-AFF1">
          <sup>3</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <aff id="btt238-AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Machine Learning and Computational Biology Research Group, Max Planck Institute for Developmental Biology &amp; Max Planck Institute for Intelligent Systems Spemannstr. 38, 72076 Tübingen, Germany, <sup>2</sup>The Institute of Scientific and Industrial Research (ISIR) Osaka University 8-1 Mihogaoka, Ibaraki-shi, Osaka 567-0047, Japan and <sup>3</sup>Zentrum für Bioinformatik, Eberhard Karls Universität Tübingen, 72076 Tübingen, Germany</aff>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="btt238-COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed.</corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
      <day>1</day>
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2013</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>19</day>
      <month>6</month>
      <year>2013</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>19</day>
      <month>6</month>
      <year>2013</year>
    </pub-date>
    <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
    <volume>29</volume>
    <issue>13</issue>
    <fpage>i171</fpage>
    <lpage>i179</lpage>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
      <license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">
        <license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract>
      <p><bold>Motivation:</bold> As an increasing number of genome-wide association studies reveal the limitations of the attempt to explain phenotypic heritability by single genetic loci, there is a recent focus on associating complex phenotypes with sets of genetic loci. Although several methods for multi-locus mapping have been proposed, it is often unclear how to relate the detected loci to the growing knowledge about gene pathways and networks. The few methods that take biological pathways or networks into account are either restricted to investigating a limited number of predetermined sets of loci or do not scale to genome-wide settings.</p>
      <p><bold>Results:</bold> We present SConES, a new efficient method to discover sets of genetic loci that are maximally associated with a phenotype while being connected in an underlying network. Our approach is based on a minimum cut reformulation of the problem of selecting features under sparsity and connectivity constraints, which can be solved exactly and rapidly.</p>
      <p>SConES outperforms state-of-the-art competitors in terms of runtime, scales to hundreds of thousands of genetic loci and exhibits higher power in detecting causal SNPs in simulation studies than other methods. On flowering time phenotypes and genotypes from <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, SConES detects loci that enable accurate phenotype prediction and that are supported by the literature.</p>
      <p><bold>Availability:</bold> Code is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://webdav.tuebingen.mpg.de/u/karsten/Forschung/scones/">http://webdav.tuebingen.mpg.de/u/karsten/Forschung/scones/</ext-link>.</p>
      <p>
        <bold>Contact:</bold>
        <email>chloe-agathe.azencott@tuebingen.mpg.de</email>
      </p>
      <p><bold>Supplementary information:</bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btt238/-/DC1">Supplementary data</ext-link> are available at <italic>Bioinformatics</italic> online.</p>
    </abstract>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="9"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec id="SEC1">
    <title>1 INTRODUCTION</title>
    <p>Twin and family/pedigree studies make it possible to estimate the heritability of observed traits, that is to say the amount of their variability that can be attributed to genetic differences. In the past few years, genome-wide association studies (GWAS), in which several hundreds of thousands to millions of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) are assayed in up to thousands of individuals, have made it possible to identify hundreds of genetic variants associated with complex phenotypes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B37">Zuk <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Unfortunately, although studies associating single SNPs with phenotypic outcomes have become standard, they often fail to explain much of the heritability of complex traits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B24">Manolio <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Investigating the joint effects of multiple loci by mapping sets of genetic variants to the phenotype has the potential to help explain part of this missing heritability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B25">Marchini <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). Although efficient multiple linear regression approaches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B6">Cho <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B30">Rakitsch <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B35">Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>) make the detection of such multivariate associations possible, they often remain limited in power and hard to interpret. Incorporating biological knowledge into these approaches could help boosting their power and interpretability. However, current methods are limited to predefining a reasonable number of candidate sets to investigate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B5">Cantor <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B8">Fridley and Biernacka, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B36">Wu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), for instance by relying on gene pathways. They consequently run the risk of missing biologically relevant loci that have not been included in the candidate sets. This risk is made even likelier by the incomplete state of our current biological knowledge.</p>
    <p>For this reason, our goal here is to use prior knowledge in a more flexible way. We propose to use a biological network, defined between SNPs, to guide a multi-locus mapping approach that is both efficient to compute and biologically meaningful: <italic>We aim to find a set of SNPs that (i) are maximally associated with a given phenotype and (ii) tend to be connected in a given biological network. In addition, this set must be computed efficiently on genome-wide data</italic>. In this article, we assume an additive model to characterize multi-locus association. The network constraint stems from the assumption that SNPs influencing the same phenotype are biologically linked. However, the diversity of the type of relationships that this can encompass, together with the current incompleteness of biological knowledge, makes providing a network in which all the relevant connections are present unlikely. For this reason, although we want to encourage the SNPs to form a subnetwork of the network, we also do not want to enforce that they <italic>must</italic> form a single connected component. Finally, we stress that the method must scale to networks of hundreds of thousands or millions of nodes. Approaches by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B7">Chuang <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref> or <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B20">Li and Li (2008)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B27">Nacu <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref> developed to analyze gene networks containing hundreds of nodes do therefore not apply.</p>
    <p>Although our method can be applied to any network between genetic markers, we explore three special types of networks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="btt238-F1">Fig. 1</xref>):
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><italic>GS network</italic>: SNPs adjacent on the genomic sequence (GS) are linked together. In this setting, we aim at recovering sub-sequences of the genomic sequence that correlate with the phenotype.</p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>GM (gene membership) network</italic>: SNPs are connected as in the sequence network described earlier in the text; in addition, SNPs near the same gene are linked together as well. Usually, a SNP is considered to belong to a gene if it is either located inside said gene or within a predefined distance of this gene. In this setting, we aim more particularly at recovering genes that correlate with the phenotype.</p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>GI (gene interaction) network</italic>: SNPs are connected as in the GM network described earlier in the text. In addition, supposing we have a gene–gene interaction network (derived, for example, from protein–protein interaction data or gene expression correlations), SNPs belonging to two genes connected in the gene network are linked together. In this setting, we aim at recovering potential pathways that explain the phenotype.</p></list-item></list>
<fig id="btt238-F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Small examples of the three types of networks considered</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="btt238f1p"/></fig></p>
    <p>Our task is a feature selection problem in a graph-structured feature space, where the features are the SNPs, and the selection criterion should be related to their association with the phenotype considered. Our problem is different from subgraph selection problems such as those encountered in chemoinformatics, where each object is a graph and each feature is a subgraph of its own (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B34">Tsuda, 2011</xref>).</p>
    <p>Several approaches have already been developed for selecting graph-structured features. A number of them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B18">Le Saux and Bunke, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B15">Jie <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>) only use the graph over the features to build the learners evaluating their relevance, but do not enforce that the selected features should follow this underlying structure. Indeed, they can be applied to settings where the features connectivity varies across examples, whereas here, all individuals share the same network.</p>
    <p>The overlapping group Lasso (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B14">Jacob <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B22">Liu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>) is a sparse linear model designed to select features that belong to the union of a small number of predefined groups. If a graph over the features is given, defining those groups as all pairs of features connected by an edge or as all linear subgraphs of a given size yields the so-called graph Lasso. A similar approach is taken by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B13">Huang <italic>et al.</italic> (2009)</xref>: their structured sparsity penalty encourages selecting a small number of base blocks, where blocks are sets of features defined so as to match the structure of the problem. In the case of a graph-induced structure, blocks are defined as small connected components of that graph. As shown in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B23">Mairal and Yu (2011)</xref>, the overlapping group Lasso aforementioned is a relaxation of this binary problem. As the number of linear subgraphs or connected components of a given size grows exponentially with the number of nodes of the graph, which can reach millions in the case of whole-genome SNP data, only the edge-based version of the graph Lasso can be applied to our problem. It is however unclear whether it is sufficient to capture long-range connections between graph nodes.</p>
    <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B20">Li and Li (2008)</xref> propose a network-constrained version of the Lasso that imposes the type of graph connectivity we deem desirable. However, their approach has been developed with networks of genes (rather than of SNPs) in mind and does not scale easily to the datasets we envision. Indeed, the implementation they propose relies on a singular value decomposition of the Laplacian of the network, which is intensive to compute and cannot be stored in memory.</p>
    <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B7">Chuang <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref> also searched subnetworks of protein–protein interaction networks that are maximally associated with a phenotype; however, their greedy approach requires fixing beforehand a (necessarily small) upper-limit on the size of the subnetworks considered.</p>
    <p>In the case of directed acyclic graphs, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B23">Mairal and Yu (2011)</xref> propose a minimum flow formulation that makes it possible to use for groups (or blocks) the set of all paths of the network. Unfortunately, the generalization to undirected graphs with cycles, such as the SNP networks we consider, requires randomly assigning directions to edges and pruning those in cycles without any biological justification. Although this can work reasonably well in practice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B23">Mairal and Yu, 2011</xref>), this is akin to artificially removing more than half of the network connections without any biological justification.</p>
    <p>In what follows, we formulate the network-guided SNP selection problem as a minimum cut problem on a graph derived from the SNP network in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="SEC2">Section 2</xref> and evaluate the performance of our solution both in simulations and on actual <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> data in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="SEC3">Section 3</xref>.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="SEC2">
    <title>2 METHODS</title>
    <sec id="SEC2.1">
      <title>2.1 Problem formulation</title>
      <p>Let <italic>n</italic> be the number of SNPs and <italic>m</italic> the number of individuals. The SNP–SNP network is described by its adjacency matrix <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i1.jpg"/></inline-formula> of size <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i2.jpg"/></inline-formula>. A number of statistics based on covariance matrices, such as the Hilbert-Schmidt Independence Criterion (HSIC), (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B10">Gretton <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>) or the Sequence Kernel Association Test (SKAT) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B36">Wu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), can be used to compute a measure of dependence <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i3.jpg"/></inline-formula> between each single SNP and the phenotype. Under the common assumption that the joint effect of several SNPs is additive (which corresponds to using linear kernels in those methods), <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i4.jpg"/></inline-formula> is such that the association between a group of SNPs and the phenotype can be quantified as the sum of the scores of the SNPs belonging to this group. That is, given an indicator vector <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i5.jpg"/></inline-formula> such that, for any <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i6.jpg"/></inline-formula> is set to 1 if the <italic>p</italic>-th SNP is selected and 0 otherwise, the score of the selected SNPs is given by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i7.jpg"/></inline-formula>.</p>
      <p>We want to find the indicator vector <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i8.jpg"/></inline-formula> that maximizes <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i9.jpg"/></inline-formula> while ensuring that the solution is made of connected components of the SNP network. However, in general, it is difficult to find a subset of SNPs that satisfies the above two properties. Given a positive integer <italic>k</italic>, the problem of finding a connected subgraph with <italic>k</italic> vertices that maximize the sum of the weights on the vertices, which is equivalent to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i10.jpg"/></inline-formula> of our case, is known to be a strongly <bold>NP</bold>-complete problem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B19">Lee and Dooly, 1996</xref>). Therefore, this problem is often addressed based on enumeration-based algorithms, whose runtime grows exponentially with <italic>k</italic>. To cope with this problem, we consider an approach based on a graph-regularization scheme, which allows us to drastically reduce the runtime.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2.2">
      <title>2.2 Feature selection with graph regularization</title>
      <p>Rather than searching through all subgraphs of a given network, we reward the selection of adjacent features through graph regularization. As it is also desirable for biological interpretation, and to avoid selecting large numbers of SNPs in linkage disequilibrium, that the selected sub-networks are small in size, we reward sparse solutions. The first requirement can be addressed by means of a smoothness regularizer on the network (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B2">Ando and Zhang, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B32">Smola and Kondor, 2003</xref>), whereas the second one can be enforced with an <italic>l</italic><sub>0</sub> constraint:
<disp-formula id="btt238-M1"><label>(1)</label><graphic xlink:href="btt238m1"/></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i11.jpg"/></inline-formula> is the Laplacian of the SNP network. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i12.jpg"/></inline-formula> is defined as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i13.jpg"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i14.jpg"/></inline-formula> is the diagonal matrix where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i15.jpg"/></inline-formula> is the degree of node <italic>p</italic>. Here, we directly minimize the number of nonzero entries in <italic>f</italic> and do not require the proxy of an <italic>l</italic><sub>1</sub> constraint to achieve sparsity (of course in the case of binary indicators, <italic>l</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>l</italic><sub>0</sub> norms are equivalent). Positive parameters λ and η control the importance of the connectedness of selected features and the sparsity regularizer, respectively.</p>
      <p>As <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i16.jpg"/></inline-formula> if <italic>q</italic> is a neighbor of <italic>p</italic> (also written as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i17.jpg"/></inline-formula>), and 0 otherwise, if we denote by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i18.jpg"/></inline-formula> the neighborhood of <italic>p</italic>, then the degree of <italic>p</italic> can be rewritten <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i19.jpg"/></inline-formula>. The second term in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="btt238-M1">Equation (1)</xref> can therefore be rewritten as
<disp-formula id="btt238-M2"><label>(2)</label><graphic xlink:href="btt238m2"/></disp-formula>
and the problem in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="btt238-M1">Equation (1)</xref> is equivalent to
<disp-formula id="btt238-M3"><label>(3)</label><graphic xlink:href="btt238m3"/></disp-formula>
</p>
      <p>As <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i20.jpg"/></inline-formula> is 1 if <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i21.jpg"/></inline-formula> and 0 otherwise, it can be seen that the connectivity term in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="btt238-M1">Equation (1)</xref> penalizes the selection of SNPs not connected to one another, as well as the selection of only subnetworks of connected components of the SNP network. It does not prohibit the selection of several disconnected subnetworks. In particular, solutions may include individual SNPs fully disconnected from the other selected SNPs. Also, as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i22.jpg"/></inline-formula> in our case, the sparsity term in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="btt238-M1">Equation (1)</xref> is equivalent to reducing the individual SNP scores <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i23.jpg"/></inline-formula> by a constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i24.jpg"/></inline-formula>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2.3">
      <title>2.3 Min-Cut solution</title>
      <p>A <italic>cut</italic> on a weighted graph over vertices <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i25.jpg"/></inline-formula> is a partition of <italic>V</italic> in a nonempty set <italic>S</italic> and its complementary <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i26.jpg"/></inline-formula>. The <italic>cut-set</italic> of the cut is the set of edges whose end vertices belong to different sets of the partition. The <italic>minimum cut</italic> of the graph is the cut such that the sum of the weights of the edges belonging to its cut-set is minimum. If <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i27.jpg"/></inline-formula> is the adjacency matrix of the graph, finding the minimum cut is equivalent to finding <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i28.jpg"/></inline-formula> that minimizes the <italic>cut-function</italic>
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i29.jpg"/></inline-formula> where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i30.jpg"/></inline-formula> is 1 if <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i31.jpg"/></inline-formula> and 0 otherwise. Given two vertices <italic>s</italic> and <italic>t</italic>, an <italic>s/t-cut</italic> is a cut such that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i32.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i33.jpg"/></inline-formula>. According to the max-flow min-cut theorem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B28">Papadimitriou and Steiglitz, 1982</xref>), a minimum <italic>s</italic>/<italic>t</italic>-cut can be efficiently computed with the maximum flow algorithm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B9">Goldberg and Tarjan, 1988</xref>).
<statement><title>P<sc>roposition</sc> 1</title><p>Given a graph <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i34.jpg"/></inline-formula> of adjacency matrix <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i35.jpg"/></inline-formula>, solving the graph-regularized feature selection problem formalized in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="btt238-M1"><italic>Equation (1)</italic></xref> is equivalent to finding an s/t min-cut on the graph, depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="btt238-F2">Figure 2</xref>, whose vertices are that of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i36.jpg"/></inline-formula>, augmented by two additional nodes s and t, and whose edges are given by the adjacency matrix <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i37.jpg"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i38.jpg"/></inline-formula> for 1≤p,q≤n and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i40.jpg"/></inline-formula></p></statement>
<statement><title>P<sc>roof</sc></title><p>The problem in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="btt238-M1">Equation (1)</xref> is equivalent to
<disp-formula id="btt238-M4"><label>(4)</label><graphic xlink:href="btt238m4"/></disp-formula>
</p><p>The second term of the objective is a cut-function over <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i41.jpg"/></inline-formula>:
<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="btt238um1"/></disp-formula>
</p><p>The first term can also be encoded as a cut-function by introducing to artificial nodes <italic>s</italic> and <italic>t</italic>:
<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="btt238um2"/></disp-formula>
<italic>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i42.jpg"/></inline-formula> is a constant, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i43.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i44.jpg"/></inline-formula> is defined as aforementioned. As <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i45.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i46.jpg"/></inline-formula> enforce that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i47.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i48.jpg"/></inline-formula>, it follows that <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="btt238-M1">Equation (1)</xref> is an <italic>s</italic>/<italic>t</italic> min-cut problem on the transformed graph defined by the adjacency matrix <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i49.jpg"/></inline-formula> over the vertices of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i50.jpg"/></inline-formula> augmented by <italic>s</italic> and <italic>t</italic>. The aforementioned still holds if <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i51.jpg"/></inline-formula> is a weighted adjacency matrix, and therefore the min-cut reformulation can also be applied to a weighted network.</italic> ▪</p><p>It is therefore possible to use maximal flow algorithms to efficiently optimize the objective function defined in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="btt238-M1">Equation (1)</xref> and select a small number of connected SNPs maximally associated with a phenotype. In our implementation, we use the Boykov–Kolmogorov algorithm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B4">Boykov and Kolmogorov, 2004</xref>). Although its worst case complexity is in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i52.jpg"/></inline-formula>, where <italic>n<sub>E</sub></italic> is the number of edges of the graph and <italic>n<sub>C</sub></italic> the size of the minimum cut, it performs much better in practice, particularly when the graph is sparse. We refer to this method as SConES, for Selecting CONnected Explanatory SNPs.</p></statement>
</p>
      <fig id="btt238-F2" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Graph for the <italic>s</italic>/ <italic>t</italic>-min-cut formulation of the selection of networks of genetic markers</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="btt238f2p"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="SEC3">
    <title>3 RESULTS</title>
    <p>We evaluate the ability of SConES to detect networks of trait-associated SNPs on simulated datasets and on datasets from an association mapping study in <italic>A.thaliana</italic>.</p>
    <sec id="SEC3.1">
      <title>3.1 Experimental settings</title>
      <p>For all of our experiments, we consider the three SNP networks defined in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="SEC1">Section 1</xref>: the GS network, the GM network and the GI network. For SConES, the association term <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i53.jpg"/></inline-formula> is derived from Linear SKAT (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B36">Wu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), which makes it possible to correct for covariates (and therefore population structure). SKAT has been devised to address rare variants association problems by grouping SNPs to achieve statistical significance, but it can equally be applied to common variants.</p>
      <p><italic>Univariate linear regression</italic>: As a baseline for comparisons, we run a linear regression-based single-SNP search for association and select those SNPs that are significantly associated with the phenotype (Bonferroni-corrected <italic>P</italic>-value <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i54.jpg"/></inline-formula>).</p>
      <p><italic>Linear mixed model</italic>: Similarly, we run a linear mixed model (LMM) single-SNP search for association (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B21">Lippert <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>) and select those SNPs that are significantly associated with the phenotype (Bonferroni-corrected <italic>P</italic>-value <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i55.jpg"/></inline-formula>).</p>
      <p><italic>Lasso</italic>: To compare SConES to a method that also considers all additive effects of SNPs simultaneously with a sparsity constraint, but without any network regularization, we also run a Lasso regression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B33">Tibshirani, 1994</xref>), using the SLEP implementation (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.public.asu.edu/~jye02/Software/SLEP">http://www.public.asu.edu/∼jye02/Software/SLEP</ext-link>) of the Lasso.</p>
      <p><italic>ncLasso</italic>: In addition, we compare SConES to the network-constrained Lasso ncLasso (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B20">Li and Li, 2008</xref>), a version of the Lasso with sparsity and graph-smoothing constraints equivalent to that of SConES. Given a genotype matrix <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i56.jpg"/></inline-formula> and a phenotype <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i57.jpg"/></inline-formula>, ncLasso solves the following relaxed problem (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i58.jpg"/></inline-formula>):
<disp-formula id="btt238-M5"><label>(5)</label><graphic xlink:href="btt238m5"/></disp-formula>
</p>
      <p>The solution for ncLasso proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B20">Li and Li (2008)</xref> requires to compute and store a single value decomposition of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i59.jpg"/></inline-formula> and is therefore not applicable when its sizes exceeds <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i60.jpg"/></inline-formula> by far. However, a similar solution can be obtained by decomposing <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i61.jpg"/></inline-formula> as the product of the network’s incidence matrix with its transpose, an approach that is much faster (particularly when the network is sparse).</p>
      <p><italic>groupLasso and graphLasso</italic>: Eventually, we also compare our method to the nonoverlapping group Lasso (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B14">Jacob <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). The nonoverlapping group Lasso solves the following relaxed problem:
<disp-formula id="btt238-M6"><label>(6)</label><graphic xlink:href="btt238m6"/></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i62.jpg"/></inline-formula> is a set of (possibly overlapping) predefined groups of SNPs. We consider the following two versions:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>graphLasso, for which the groups are directly defined from the same networks as considered for SConES as all pairs of vertices connected by an edge;</p></list-item><list-item><p>groupLasso, for which the groups are defined sensibly as follows:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>GS groups: pairs of adjacent SNPs (this gives raise to the same groups as for graphLasso with the sequence network);</p></list-item><list-item><p>GM groups: SNPs near the same gene;</p></list-item><list-item><p>GI groups: SNPs near either member of two interacting genes. Here, SNPs near genes that are not in the interaction network get grouped by gene.</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item></list>
</p>
      <p>We use the SLEP implementation of the nonoverlapping group Lasso, combined with the trick described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B14">Jacob <italic>et al.</italic> (2009)</xref> to compute the overlapping group Lasso by replicating features in nonoverlapping groups.</p>
      <p><italic>Setting the parameters</italic>: All methods considered, except for the univariate linear regression, have parameters (e.g. λ and η in the case of SConES) that need to be optimized. In our experiments, we run 10-fold cross-validation grid-search experiments over ranges of values of the parameters: seven values of λ and η each for SConES and ncLasso and seven values of the parameter λ for the Lasso and the nonoverlapping group Lasso (ranging from <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i63.jpg"/></inline-formula> to 10<sup>3</sup>). We then pick as optimal the parameters leading to the most stable selection and report as finally selected the features selected in all folds. More specifically, we define stability according to a consistency index similar to that of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B17">Kuncheva (2007)</xref>. The consistency index between two feature sets <italic>S</italic> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i64.jpg"/></inline-formula> is defined as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i65.jpg"/></inline-formula> (Details can be found in the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btt238/-/DC1">Supplementary Materials</ext-link>). For an experiment with <italic>k</italic> folds, the consistency is computed as the average of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i66.jpg"/></inline-formula> pairwise consistencies between the sets of features selected over each fold.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC3.2">
      <title>3.2 Runtime</title>
      <p>We first compare the CPU runtime of SConES with that of the linear regression, ncLasso and graphLasso. To assess the performance of our methods, we simulate from 100 to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i67.jpg"/></inline-formula> SNPs for 200 individuals and generate exponential random networks with a density of 2% (chosen as an upper limit on the density of currently available gene-gene interaction networks) between those SNPs.</p>
      <p>We report the real CPU runtime of one cross-validation, for set parameters, over a single AMD Opteron CPU (2048 KB, 2600 MHz) with 512 GB of memory, running Ubuntu 12.04 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="btt238-F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Across a wide range of numbers of SNPs, SConES is at least two orders of magnitude faster than graphLasso and one order of magnitude faster than ncLasso.
<fig id="btt238-F3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Real CPU runtime comparison between univariate linear regression, ncLasso, nonoverlapping group Lasso and SConES, from 100 to 25 000 SNPs (left) and from 100 to 200 000 SNPs (right). ‘ncLasso’ refers to the original implementation suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B20">Li and Li (2008)</xref> and ‘ncLasso (accelerated)’ to the incidence-matrix-based implementation we use here. After 3 weeks, nonoverlapping group Lasso and ncLasso had not finished running for 50 000 SNPs. The accelerated version of ncLasso ran out of memory for ≥150 000 SNPs</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="btt238f3p"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC3.3">
      <title>3.3 Simulations</title>
      <p>To assess the performance of our methods, we simulate phenotypes for <italic>m</italic> = 500 real <italic>A.thaliana</italic> genotypes (214 051 SNPs), chosen at random among those made available by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B12">Horton <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref>, and the <italic>A.thaliana</italic> protein–protein interaction information from The Arabidopsis Internet Resource (TAIR, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.arabidopsis.org/portals/proteome/proteinInteract.jsp">http://www.arabidopsis.org/portals/proteome/proteinInteract.jsp</ext-link>, resulting in 55 584 646 SNP–SNP connections). We use a window size of 20 000 bp to define proximity of a SNP to a gene, in accordance with the threshold used for the interpretation of GWAS results in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B3">Atwell <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref>. Restricting ourselves to 1000 randomly chosen SNPs with minor allele frequency larger than 10%, we pick 20 of the SNPs to be causal, and generate phenotypes <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i68.jpg"/></inline-formula>, where both the support weights <italic>w</italic> and the noise <italic>ϵ</italic> are normally distributed. We consider the following scenarios: (a) the causal SNPs are randomly distributed in the network; (b) the causal SNPs are adjacent on the genomic sequence; (c) the causal SNPs are near the same gene; (d–f) the causal SNPs are near either of two, three and five interacting genes, respectively. We then select SNPs using univariate linear regression, Lasso, ncLasso, the two flavors of nonoverlapping group Lasso and SConES as described in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="SEC3.1">Section 3.1</xref>. We repeat each experiment 30 times and compare the selected SNPs of either approach with the true causal ones in terms of power (fraction of causal SNPs selected) or false discovery rate (FDR, fraction of selected SNPs that are not causal). We summarize the results with F-scores (harmonic mean of power and one minus FDR) in <xref ref-type="table" rid="btt238-T1">Table 1</xref>.
<table-wrap id="btt238-T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>F-scores of SConES, compared with state-of-the-art Lasso algorithms and a baseline univariate linear regression, in six different data simulation scenarios</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Method</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(a)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(b)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(c)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(d)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(e)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(f)</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Univariate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26 ± 0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29 ± 0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28 ± 0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27 ± 0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26 ± 0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 ± 0.08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0.32 ± 0.01</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36 ± 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0.33 ± 0.01</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lasso</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.35</bold> ± <bold>0.01</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32 ± 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32 ± 0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ncLasso</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">    GS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25 ± 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38 ± 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30 ± 0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">    GM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26 ± 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26 ± 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27 ± 0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">    GI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26 ± 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26 ± 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43 ± 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34 ± 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28 ± 0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">groupLasso</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">    GS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36 ± 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32 ± 0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">    GM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12 ± 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44 ± 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0.50 ± 0.01</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0.40 ± 0.01</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0.33 ± 0.01</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">    GI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09 ± 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26 ± 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.54</bold> ± <bold>0.01</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0.40 ± 0.01</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.34</bold> ± <bold>0.01</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">graphLasso</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">    GS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36 ± 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32 ± 0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">    GM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31 ± 0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">    GI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27 ± 0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SConES</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">    GS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0.55 ± 0.04</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57 ± 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0.50 ± 0.01</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.43</bold> ± <bold>0.02</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0.33 ± 0.02</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">    GM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19 ± 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.58</bold> ± <bold>0.03</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0.75 ± 0.03</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0.40 ± 0.02</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32 ± 0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">    GI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20 ± 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48 ± 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.78</bold> ± <bold>0.03</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39 ± 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.34</bold> ± <bold>0.02</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="btt238-TF1"><p><italic>Note:</italic> The true causal SNPs are (a) unconnected; (b) adjacent on the GS; (c) near the same gene; (d) near either of the same two connected genes; (e) near either of the same three connected genes; (f) near either of the same five connected genes. Best performance in bold and second best in italics.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p>As SConES returns a binary feature selection rather than a feature ranking, it is not possible to draw FDR curves or compare powers at same FDR as is often done when evaluating such methods. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="btt238-F4">Figure 4</xref> presents the average FDR and power of the different algorithms under three of the scenarios, depending on the network used. The closer the FDR power point representing an algorithm to the upper-left corner, the better this algorithm at maximizing power while minimizing FDR. As it is easy to get better power by selecting more SNPs, we also report on the same figure the number of SNPs selected by each algorithm and show that it remains reasonably close to the true value of 20 causal SNPs.
<fig id="btt238-F4" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>Power and FDR of SConES, compared with state-of-the-art Lasso algorithms and a baseline univariate linear regression, in three different data simulation scenarios. Best methods are closest to the upper-left corner. Numbers denote the number of SNPs selected by the method</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="btt238f4p"/></fig></p>
      <p>SConES is systematically better than its state-of-the-art comparison partners at leveraging structural information to retrieve the connected SNPs that were causal. Only when the groups perfectly match the causal structure [Scenario (d)] can groupLasso outperform SConES. Although the performance of SConES and ncLasso does depend on the network, the nonoverlapping group Lasso is much more sensitive to the definition of its groups. Furthermore, we observe that removing a small fraction (1–15%) of the edges between causal features does not harm the performance of SConES (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btt238/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link>). This means that SConES is robust to missing edges, an important point when the biological network used is likely to be incomplete. Nevertheless, the performance of SConES, as that of all other network-regularized approaches, is strongly negatively affected when the network is entirely inappropriate [Scenario (a)]. In addition, the decrease in performance from Scenario (c) to Scenario (f), when the number of interacting genes near which the causal SNPs are located increases from 1 to 5, indicates that SConES, like its structure-regularized comparison partners, performs better when the causal SNPs are less spread out in the network. Finally, ncLasso is both slower and less performing than SConES. This indicates that solving the feature selection problem we pose directly, rather than its relaxed version, allows for better recovery of true causal features.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC3.4">
      <title>3.4 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flowering time phenotypes</title>
      <p>We then apply our method to a large collection of 17 <italic>A.thaliana</italic> flowering times phenotypes from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B3">Atwell <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref> (up to 194 individuals, 214 051 SNPs). The groups and networks are again derived from the TAIR protein–protein interaction data. We filter out SNPs with a minor allele frequency lower than 10%, as is typical in <italic>A.thaliana</italic> GWAS studies. We use the first principal components of the genotypic data as covariates to correct for population structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B29">Price <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>): the number of principal components is chosen by adding them one by one until the genomic control is close to 1 (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btt238/-/DC1">Supplementary Figure S1</ext-link>).</p>
      <p>The direct competitors of SConES on this problem are the methods that also impose graph constraints on the SNPs they select, namely, graphLasso and ncLasso. However, graphLasso does not scale to datasets such as ours with &gt;200 k SNPs (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="btt238-F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Hence, we had to exclude it from our experiments. While even our accelerated implementation of ncLasso could not be run on &gt;125 000 SNPs in our simulations, the networks derived for <italic>A.thaliana</italic> are sparser than that used in the simulations, which makes it possible to run ncLasso on this data.</p>
      <p>Instead, we compare SConES to ncLasso and groupLasso, which uses pairs of neighboring SNPs, SNPs from the same gene or SNPs from interacting genes as predefined groups. The groupLasso on sequence-neighboring SNPs is identical to graphLasso on the sequence network, which is the only instance of graphLasso whose computation is practically feasible on this dataset. We run Lasso, ncLasso, groupLasso and SConES on the flowering time phenotypes as described in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="SEC3.1">Section 3.1</xref>. However, for many of the phenotypes, the Lasso approaches select large number of SNPs (&gt;10 000), which makes the results hard to interprete. Using cross-validated predictivity, as is generally done for Lasso, still does not entirely solve this issue, particularly for large group sizes (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btt238/-/DC1">Supplementary Tables S2</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btt238/-/DC1">S3</ext-link>). We therefore filter out solutions containing &gt;1% of the total number of SNPs before using consistency to select the optimal parameters.</p>
      <p>To evaluate the quality of the SNPs selected, we perform ridge regression on each phenotype in a cross-validation scheme that uses only the selected SNPs and report its average Pearson’s squared correlation coefficient in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="btt238-F5">Figure 5</xref>. We also report, as an additional baseline, the cross-validated predictivity of a standard best linear unbiased prediction (BLUP) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B11">Henderson, 1975</xref>). Although the features selected by groupLasso + GS achieve higher predictivity than SConES + GS on most phenotypes, the features selected by SConES + GM are at least as predictive as those selected by groupLasso + GM in two thirds of the phenotypes; the picture is the same for SConES + GI, whose selected SNPs are on average more predictive than those of groupLasso + GI. The superiority of groupLasso in that respect is to be expected, as predicitivity is directly optimized by the regression. Also in 80% of the cases, if any of the feature selection methods achieves high predictivity (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="btt238i159.jpg"/></inline-formula>), SConES outperforms all other methods including BLUP.
<fig id="btt238-F5" position="float"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p>Cross-validated predictivity (measured as Pearson’s squared correlation coefficient between actual phenotype and phenotype predicted by a ridge-regression over the selected SNPs) of SConES compared with that of Lasso, groupLasso and ncLasso. Horizontal bars indicate cross-validated BLUP predictivity</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="btt238f5p"/></fig></p>
      <p>Next, we checked whether the selected SNPs from the three methods coincide with flowering time genes from the literature. We report in <xref ref-type="table" rid="btt238-T2">Table 2</xref> the number of SNPs selected by each of the methods and the proportion of these SNPs that are near flowering time candidate genes listed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B31">Segura <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref>. Here, the picture is reversed: SConES + GS and groupLasso + GI retrieve the highest ratio of SNPs near candidate genes, whereas groupLasso + GS, SConES + GI and SConES + GM show lower ratios. At first sight, it seems surprising that the methods with highest predictive power retrieve the least SNPs near candidate genes.
<table-wrap id="btt238-T2" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Associations detected close to known candidate genes, for all flowering time phenotypes of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phenotype</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Univariate</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">LMM</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lasso</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">groupLasso<hr/></th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">ncLasso<hr/></th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">SConES<hr/></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GS</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GM</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GS</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GM</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GS</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GM</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GI</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 W</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33/288</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59/706</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">144/547</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40/1077</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14/318</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14/318</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>123/271</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/69</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 W GH LN</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13/205</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54/478</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>128/321</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31/981</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/320</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/320</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92/1251</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92/1252</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92/1253</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 W</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15/129</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48/1489</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>80/436</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/238</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/298</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/298</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104/1670</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66/1078</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42/859</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 W GH FT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/143</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5/16</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66/1470</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14/427</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/398</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/398</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26/322</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26/322</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26/319</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FLC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/101</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/214</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/135</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>115/1592</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FT GH</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7/46</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/106</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90/841</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">177/1417</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37/1434</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42/1709</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42/1709</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/626</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/59</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1/2</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14/437</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/177</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/177</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39/674</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86/1381</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54/1091</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LN16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/222</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">138/957</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89/1307</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22/1094</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33/1323</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33/1323</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>73/73</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36/569</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51/863</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84/721</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20/466</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/224</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/224</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7/59</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7/59</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7/59</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 W GH FT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1/3</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20/194</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49/654</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52/898</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">241/1258</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63/1597</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84/1997</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84/1997</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29/317</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29/317</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 W</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93/610</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>126/810</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28/1006</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43/1256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43/1256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76/756</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78/1185</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25/892</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 W GH LN</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/122</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13/168</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19/493</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21/501</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21/501</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>11/73</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75/776</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68/757</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FRI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>10/10</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101/1266</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101/1271</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101/1274</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FT Field</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51/221</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>52/72</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18/709</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/238</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/238</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LN10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>18/121</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/202</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/644</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/649</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/649</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">165/1921</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/91</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LN22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33/894</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81/1023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23/501</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26/506</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26/506</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>140/1378</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>140/1378</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">140/1378</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SDV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/208</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/721</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105/936</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14/379</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15/384</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15/384</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>53/454</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/8</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="btt238-TF2"><p><italic>Note:</italic> We report the number of selected SNPs near candidate genes, followed by the total number of selected SNPs. Largest ratio in bold.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p>To further investigate this phenomenon, we record how many distinct flowering time candidate genes are retrieved on average by the various methods. A gene is considered retrieved if the method selects a SNP near it. Our results are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="btt238-T3">Table 3</xref>. Methods retrieving a large fraction of SNPs near candidate genes do not necessarily retrieve the largest number of distinct candidate genes. Good predictive power, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="btt238-F5">Figure 5</xref>, however, seems to correlate with the number of distinct candidate genes selected by an algorithm, not with the percentage of selected SNPs near candidate genes. groupLasso + GI has the highest fraction of candidate gene SNPs among all methods but detects only three distinct candidate genes. This is probably due to groupLasso selecting entire genes or gene pairs; if groupLasso detects a candidate gene, it will pick most of the SNPs near that gene, which leads to its high candidate SNP ratio in <xref ref-type="table" rid="btt238-T2">Table 2</xref>.
<table-wrap id="btt238-T3" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Summary statistics, averaged over the <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> flowering time phenotypes: average total number of selected SNPs (‘No of SNPs’), average proportion of selected SNPs near candidate genes (‘near candidate genes’) and average number of different candidate genes recovered (‘candidate genes hit’)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Method</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No of SNPs</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Near candidate genes</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Candidate genes hit</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Univariate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lasso</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.82</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">groupLasso GS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">153</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">groupLasso GM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">611</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">groupLasso GI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">546</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.65</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ncLasso GS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">684</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.88</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ncLasso GM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">608</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.59</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ncLasso GI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">608</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.59</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SConES GS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">729</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.53</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SConES GM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">546</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.82</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SConES GI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">496</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.24</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
      <p>We also compare the selected SNPs to those deemed significant by a LMM ran on the full data (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btt238/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S4</ext-link>). SConES systematically recovers more of those SNPs than the Lasso approaches.</p>
      <p>To summarize, SConES is able to select SNPs that are highly predictive of the phenotype. Among all methods, SConES + GM discovers the largest number of distinct genes whose involvement in flowering time is supported by the literature.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="SEC4">
    <title>4 DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSIONS</title>
    <p>In this article, we defined SConES, a novel approach to multi-locus mapping that selects SNPs that tend to be connected in a given biological network without restricting the search to predefined sets of loci. As the optimization of SConES can be solved by maximum flow, our solution is computationally efficient and scales to whole-genome data. Our experiments show that our method is one to two orders of magnitude faster than the state-of-the-art Lasso-based comparison partners and can therefore easily scale to hundreds of thousands of SNPs. In simulations, SConES is better at leveraging the structure of the biological network to recover causal SNPs.</p>
    <p>On real GWAS data from <italic>A.thaliana</italic>, the predictive ability of the features selected by SConES is superior to that of groupLasso on two of the three network types we consider. When using more biological information (gene membership or interactions), SConES tends to recover more distinct explanatory genes than groupLasso, resulting in better phenotypic prediction.</p>
    <p>The constraints imposed by groupLasso and SConES are different: although the groups given to groupLasso and the networks passed to SConES come from the same information, the groups force many more SNPs to be selected simultaneously when they may not bring much more information. This gives SConES more flexibility and makes it less vulnerable to ill-defined groups or networks, which is especially desirable in the light of the current noisiness and incompleteness of biological networks. Our results on the GS network actually indicate that graphLasso, using pairs of network edges as groups, may achieve the same flexibility as SConES; unfortunately, it is too computationally demanding to be run on the most informative networks.</p>
    <p>We currently derive the SNP networks from neighborhood along the genome sequence, closeness to a same gene or proximity to interacting proteins. Refining those networks and exploring other types of networks as well as understanding the effects of their topology and density is one of our next projects.</p>
    <p>Although we do not explicitly consider linkage disequilibrium, the <italic>l</italic><sub>0</sub> sparsity constraint of SConES should enforce that when several correlated SNPs are associated with a phenotype, a single one of them is picked. On the other hand, if SConES is given a GS network such as the one we describe, the graph smoothness constraint will encourage nearby SNPs to be selected together, leading to the selection of subsequences that are likely to be haplotype blocks. Such a network should therefore only be used when the goal of the experiment is to detect consecutive sequences of associated SNPs.</p>
    <p>For now, SConES considers an additive model between genetic loci. Future work includes taking pairwise multiplicative effects into account. Replacing the association term in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="btt238-M1">Equation (1)</xref> by a sum over pairs of SNPs rather than over individual SNPs results in a maximum flow problem over a fully connected network of SNPs, which cannot be solved straightforwardly, if only because the resulting adjacency matrix is too large to fit in memory on a regular computer. It might be possible, however, to leverage some of the techniques used for two-locus GWAS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B1">Achlioptas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B16">Kam-Thong <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>) to help solve this problem.</p>
    <p>Extensions of SConES to other models include the use of mixed models to account for population structure and other confounders. This is currently a challenge, as it is unclear how to derive additive test statistics from such models.</p>
    <p>An interesting extension to study would replace the Laplacian by a random-walk-based matrix, derived from powers of the adjacency matrix, so as to treat disconnected SNPs that are close-by in the networks differently from those that are far apart. Although we already observe that SConES is robust to edge removal, this would likely make it more resistant to missing edges.</p>
    <p>Another important extension of SConES is to devise a way to evaluate the statistical significance of the set of selected SNPs. Regularized feature selection approaches such as SConES or its Lasso comparison partners do not lend themselves well to the computation of <italic>P</italic>-values. Permutation tests could be an option, but the number of permutations to run is difficult to evaluate as is that of hypotheses tested. Another possibility would be to implement the multiple-sample splitting approach proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="btt238-B26">Meinshausen <italic>et al.</italic> (2009)</xref>. However, the loss of power from performing selection on only subsets of the samples is too large, given the sizes of current genomic datasets, to make this feasible. Therefore, evaluating statistical significance and controlling FDRs of Lasso and SConES approaches alike remain a challenge for the future.</p>
    <p>Finally, further exciting research topics include applying SConES to larger datasets from human disease consortia (we estimate it would require less than a day to run on a million of SNPs) and extending it to the detection of shared networks of markers between multiple phenotypes.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
      <caption>
        <title>Supplementary Data</title>
      </caption>
      <media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_29_13_i171__index.html"/>
      <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_btt238_Azencott.312.supp.1.pdf"/>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack>
    <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
    <p>The authors thank Recep Colak, Barbara Rakitsch and Nino Shervashidze for fruitful discussions.</p>
    <p><italic>Funding</italic>: C.A. is funded by an <funding-source>Alexander von Humboldt fellowship</funding-source>. This work was partially funded by the DFG project Kernels for Large, Labeled Graphs (LaLa).</p>
    <p><italic>Conflict of Interest</italic>: none declared.</p>
  </ack>
  <ref-list>
    <title>REFERENCES</title>
    <ref id="btt238-B1">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Achlioptas</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <source>Two-Locus Association Mapping In Subquadratic Time. KDD ’11</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <publisher-loc>ACM, New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>
        <fpage>726</fpage>
        <lpage>734</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B2">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ando</surname>
            <given-names>RK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <person-group person-group-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Schölkopf</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hoffman</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Learning on graph with Laplacian regularization</article-title>
        <source>Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 19</source>
        <year>2007</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B3">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Atwell</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Genome-wide association study of 107 phenotypes in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> inbred lines</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>465</volume>
        <fpage>627</fpage>
        <lpage>631</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20336072</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B4">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Boykov</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kolmogorov</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>An experimental comparison of min-cut/max-flow algorithms for energy minimization in vision</article-title>
        <source>IEEE T. Pattern Anal.</source>
        <year>2004</year>
        <volume>26</volume>
        <fpage>1124</fpage>
        <lpage>1137</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B5">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cantor</surname>
            <given-names>RM</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Prioritizing GWAS results: a review of statistical methods and recommendations for their application</article-title>
        <source>Am. J. Hum. Genet.</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>86</volume>
        <fpage>6</fpage>
        <lpage>22</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20074509</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B6">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cho</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Joint identification of multiple genetic variants via elastic-net variable selection in a genome-wide association analysis</article-title>
        <source>Ann. Hum. Genet.</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>74</volume>
        <fpage>416</fpage>
        <lpage>428</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20642809</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B7">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chuang</surname>
            <given-names>HY</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Network-based classification of breast cancer metastasis</article-title>
        <source>Mol. Syst. Biol.</source>
        <year>2007</year>
        <volume>3</volume>
        <fpage>140</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17940530</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B8">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Fridley</surname>
            <given-names>BL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Biernacka</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Gene set analysis of SNP data: benefits, challenges, and future directions</article-title>
        <source>Eur. J. Hum. Genet.</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>19</volume>
        <fpage>837</fpage>
        <lpage>843</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21487444</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B9">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Goldberg</surname>
            <given-names>AV</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tarjan</surname>
            <given-names>RE</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A new approach to the maximum-flow problem</article-title>
        <source>J. ACM</source>
        <year>1988</year>
        <volume>35</volume>
        <fpage>921</fpage>
        <lpage>940</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B10">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gretton</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <person-group person-group-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Sanjay</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Measuring statistical dependence with Hilbert-Schmidt norms</article-title>
        <source>Algorithmic Learning Theory, 16th International Conference, ALT 2005, Singapore, October 8-11, 2005, Proceedings. Lecture Notes in Computer Science 3734 Springer 2005. ALT</source>
        <year>2005</year>
        <publisher-loc>Springer-Verlag</publisher-loc>
        <fpage>63</fpage>
        <lpage>77</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B11">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Henderson</surname>
            <given-names>CR</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Best linear unbiased estimation and prediction under a selection model</article-title>
        <source>Biometrics</source>
        <year>1975</year>
        <volume>31</volume>
        <fpage>423</fpage>
        <lpage>447</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1174616</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B12">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Horton</surname>
            <given-names>MW</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Genome-wide patterns of genetic variation in worldwide <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> accessions from the RegMap panel</article-title>
        <source>Nat. Genet.</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>44</volume>
        <fpage>212</fpage>
        <lpage>216</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22231484</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B13">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <person-group person-group-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Andrea</surname>
            <given-names>PD</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Learning with Structured Sparsity</article-title>
        <source>Proceedings of the 26th Annual International Conference on Machine Learning, ICML 2009, Montreal, Quebec, Canada, June 14-18, 2009</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <publisher-loc>ACM, New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>
        <fpage>417</fpage>
        <lpage>424</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B14">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jacob</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <person-group person-group-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Andrea</surname>
            <given-names>PD</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Group Lasso with Overlap and Graph Lasso</article-title>
        <source>Proceedings of the 26th Annual International Conference on Machine Learning, ICML 2009, Montreal, Quebec, Canada, June 14-18, 2009</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <publisher-loc>ACM, New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>
        <fpage>433</fpage>
        <lpage>440</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B15">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jie</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <person-group person-group-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Yap</surname>
            <given-names>PT</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Structural feature selection for connectivity network-based MCI diagnosis</article-title>
        <source>Multimodal Brain Image Analysis, Volume 7509 of Lecture Notes in Computer Science</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <publisher-loc>Springer, Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
        <fpage>175</fpage>
        <lpage>184</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B16">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kam-Thong</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>GLIDE: GPU-based linear regression for detection of epistasis</article-title>
        <source>Hum. Hered.</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>73</volume>
        <fpage>220</fpage>
        <lpage>236</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22965145</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B17">
      <element-citation publication-type="confproc">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kuncheva</surname>
            <given-names>LI</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <year>2007</year>
        <comment>A stability index for feature selection. In: Vladan,D. (ed.) <italic>Proceedings of the 25th IASTED International Multi-Conference: artificial intelligence and applications</italic>. IASTED/ACTA Press, Innsbruck, Austria</comment>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B18">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Le Saux</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bunke</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <person-group person-group-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Marques</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Feature selection for graph-based image classifiers</article-title>
        <source>Pattern Recognition and Image Analysis, Volume 3523 of Lecture Notes in Computer Science</source>
        <year>2005</year>
        <publisher-loc>Springer, Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
        <fpage>147</fpage>
        <lpage>154</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B19">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>HF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dooly</surname>
            <given-names>DR</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Algorithms for the constrained maximum-weight connected graph problem</article-title>
        <source>Nav. Res. Logist.</source>
        <year>1996</year>
        <volume>43</volume>
        <fpage>985</fpage>
        <lpage>1008</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B20">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Network-constrained regularization and variable selection for analysis of genomic data</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>24</volume>
        <fpage>1175</fpage>
        <lpage>1182</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18310618</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B21">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lippert</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>FaST linear mixed models for genome-wide association studies</article-title>
        <source>Nat. Meth.</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <fpage>833</fpage>
        <lpage>835</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B22">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Incorporating group correlations in genome-wide association studies using smoothed group lasso</article-title>
        <source>Biostatistics</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>14</volume>
        <fpage>205</fpage>
        <lpage>219</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22988281</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B23">
      <element-citation publication-type="confproc">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mairal</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <year>2011</year>
        <comment>Path coding penalties for directed acyclic graphs. In: <italic>Proceedings of the 4th NIPS Workshop on Optimization for Machine Learning (OPT’11)</italic></comment>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B24">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Manolio</surname>
            <given-names>TA</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Finding the missing heritability of complex diseases</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>461</volume>
        <fpage>747</fpage>
        <lpage>753</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19812666</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B25">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Marchini</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Genome-wide strategies for detecting multiple loci that influence complex diseases</article-title>
        <source>Nat. Genet.</source>
        <year>2005</year>
        <volume>37</volume>
        <fpage>413</fpage>
        <lpage>417</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15793588</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B26">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Meinshausen</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title><italic>P</italic>-values for high-dimensional regression</article-title>
        <source>J. Am. Stat. Assoc.</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>104</volume>
        <fpage>1671</fpage>
        <lpage>1681</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B27">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nacu</surname>
            <given-names>Ş</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Gene expression network analysis and applications to immunology</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2007</year>
        <volume>23</volume>
        <fpage>850</fpage>
        <lpage>858</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17267429</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B28">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Papadimitriou</surname>
            <given-names>CH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Steiglitz</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Combinatorial Optimization: Algorithms and Complexity</source>
        <year>1982</year>
        <publisher-loc>Englewood Cliffs, NJ, USA</publisher-loc>
        <publisher-name>Prentice-Hall Inc</publisher-name>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B29">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Price</surname>
            <given-names>AL</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Principal components analysis corrects for stratification in genome-wide association studies</article-title>
        <source>Nat. Genet.</source>
        <year>2006</year>
        <volume>38</volume>
        <fpage>904</fpage>
        <lpage>909</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16862161</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B30">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rakitsch</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A lasso multi-marker mixed model for association mapping with population structure correction</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics.</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>29</volume>
        <fpage>206</fpage>
        <lpage>214</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23175758</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B31">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Segura</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>An efficient multi-locus mixed-model approach for genome-wide association studies in structured populations</article-title>
        <source>Nat. Genet.</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>44</volume>
        <fpage>825</fpage>
        <lpage>830</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22706313</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B32">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Smola</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kondor</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <person-group person-group-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Schölkopf</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Warmuth</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Kernels and regularization on graphs</article-title>
        <source>Learning Theory and Kernel Machines, Volume 2777 of Lecture Notes in Computer Science</source>
        <year>2003</year>
        <publisher-loc>Springer, Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
        <fpage>144</fpage>
        <lpage>158</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B33">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tibshirani</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Regression shrinkage and selection via the lasso</article-title>
        <source>J. R. Stat. Soc. Series B</source>
        <year>1994</year>
        <volume>58</volume>
        <fpage>267</fpage>
        <lpage>288</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B34">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tsuda</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <person-group person-group-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>HHS</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Graph classification methods in chemoinformatics</article-title>
        <source>Handbook of Statistical Bioinformatics, Springer Handbooks of Computational Statistics</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <publisher-loc>Springer, Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
        <fpage>335</fpage>
        <lpage>351</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B35">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Identifying QTLs and epistasis in structured plant populations using adaptive mixed lasso</article-title>
        <source>J. Agric. Biol. Environ. Stat.</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>16</volume>
        <fpage>170</fpage>
        <lpage>184</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B36">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>MC</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Rare-variant association testing for sequencing data with the sequence kernel association test</article-title>
        <source>Am. J. Hum. Genet.</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>89</volume>
        <fpage>82</fpage>
        <lpage>93</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21737059</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt238-B37">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zuk</surname>
            <given-names>O</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The mystery of missing heritability: Genetic interactions create phantom heritability</article-title>
        <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>109</volume>
        <fpage>1193</fpage>
        <lpage>1198</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22223662</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
