<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">bioinfo</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1367-4803</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1367-4811</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3998129</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt772</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">btt772</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Applications Notes</subject>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Systems Biology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>Morpheus: a user-friendly modeling environment for multiscale and multicellular systems biology</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Starruß</surname>
          <given-names>Jörn</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="btt772-FN1">
          <sup>†</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>de Back</surname>
          <given-names>Walter</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="btt772-COR1">*</xref>
        <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="btt772-FN1">
          <sup>†</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Brusch</surname>
          <given-names>Lutz</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Deutsch</surname>
          <given-names>Andreas</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <aff>Center for Information Services and High Performance Computing, Technische Universität Dresden, 01062 Dresden, Germany</aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="btt772-COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed.</corresp>
      <fn id="btt772-FN2">
        <p>Associate Editor: Martin Bishop</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="btt772-FN1">
        <p><sup>†</sup>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as Joint First Authors.</p>
      </fn>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
      <day>1</day>
      <month>5</month>
      <year>2014</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>17</day>
      <month>1</month>
      <year>2014</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>17</day>
      <month>1</month>
      <year>2014</year>
    </pub-date>
    <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
    <volume>30</volume>
    <issue>9</issue>
    <fpage>1331</fpage>
    <lpage>1332</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>2</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>12</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
      <license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
        <license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract>
      <p><bold>Summary:</bold> Morpheus is a modeling environment for the simulation and integration of cell-based models with ordinary differential equations and reaction-diffusion systems. It allows rapid development of multiscale models in biological terms and mathematical expressions rather than programming code. Its graphical user interface supports the entire workflow from model construction and simulation to visualization, archiving and batch processing.</p>
      <p><bold>Availability and implementation:</bold> Binary packages are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://imc.zih.tu-dresden.de/wiki/morpheus">http://imc.zih.tu-dresden.de/wiki/morpheus</ext-link> for Linux, Mac OSX and MS Windows.</p>
      <p>
        <bold>Contact:</bold>
        <email>walter.deback@tu-dresden.de</email>
      </p>
      <p><bold>Supplementary information:</bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btt772/-/DC1">Supplementary data</ext-link> are available at <italic>Bioinformatics</italic> online.</p>
    </abstract>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="2"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec>
    <title>1 INTRODUCTION</title>
    <p>Systems biology is rapidly expanding its scope from the study of intracellular networks to the analysis of tissue- and organ-scale systems. This increases the need for computational methods and software that support the simulation and integration of cell-based models with models for intra- and extracellular dynamics. Currently available modeling environments typically require programming or scripting to account for dynamical feedback between submodels at different scales (<xref rid="btt772-B1" ref-type="bibr">Andasari <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="btt772-B8" ref-type="bibr">Mirams <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="btt772-B11" ref-type="bibr">Swat <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Yet, as models grow more complex, it becomes increasingly important to separate modeling from implementation, to automate multiscale model integration and to provide intuitive user interfaces (<xref rid="btt772-B10" ref-type="bibr">Sütterlin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>).</p>
    <p>Morpheus is a user-friendly application for the modeling, simulation and integration of cell-based models, ordinary differential equations and reaction-diffusion systems. It supports the construction of multiscale models using biological terminology and mathematical constructs, based on a novel domain-specific language. Its graphical user interface (GUI) supports the whole workflow from model development and simulation to visualization and data output and features tools for archiving and batch processing.</p>
    <p>Morpheus has hitherto been used in a variety of studies, including collective motion (<xref rid="btt772-B9" ref-type="bibr">Starruß <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), morphogenesis (<xref rid="btt772-B5" ref-type="bibr">Köhn-Luque <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>, <xref rid="btt772-B6" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) and cell fate decisions (<xref rid="btt772-B2" ref-type="bibr">de Back <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013a</xref>, <xref rid="btt772-B3" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="btt772-F1">Fig. 1</xref>A).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="SEC2">
    <title>2 SOFTWARE</title>
    <sec id="SEC2.1">
      <title>2.1 Model formalisms</title>
      <p>Modeling of multicellular systems requires methods that go beyond the standard repertoire of model formalisms in systems biology (<xref rid="btt772-B7" ref-type="bibr">Machado <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Cells must typically be modeled as discrete interacting entities, sometimes as motile objects, possibly even with articulated 3D cell shapes. Morpheus provides methods to define cell-based models of interactions between discrete cells, spatially represented as point-like objects or with explicit 2D/3D cell shapes. Cell motility, adhesion and biophysical constraints can be added using the cellular Potts model (CPM) framework (<xref rid="btt772-B4" ref-type="bibr">Graner <italic>et al.</italic>, 1992</xref>).</p>
      <p>Cells can be linked to models of intracellular biological pathways such as gene regulatory networks and signaling pathways. These can be specified in the form of ordinary, stochastic and delay differential equations or imported from SBML-based models. Morpheus also supports the simulation of reaction-diffusion systems. This can be used to couple cellular behavior to morphogen concentrations in the extracellular environment.</p>
      <p>Apart from these core formalisms, a range of auxiliary models can be constructed including coupled lattice ODEs, finite state machines, gradient-based models and cellular automata. All formalisms can be used as single-scale models or integrated into multiscale models. Example use cases are described on the Web site and are available in the GUI.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2.2">
      <title>2.2 Model description</title>
      <p>Morpheus separates modeling from numerical implementation by using a declarative domain-specific markup language. The model description language allows users to describe their models in biological and mathematical terms. Mathematical expressions such as functions, equations, events and systems of differential equations can be specified in common infix notation to describe the interactions and dynamics of cell-bound variables and molecular species in reaction-diffusion systems, based on symbolic identifiers.</p>
      <p>Multiscale interactions are described by linking symbolic identifiers associated with different spatiotemporal models. Internally, Morpheus automatically integrates these models by appropriately mapping data between spatial models and scheduling numerical updates according to the dependencies between symbols.</p>
      <p>Model descriptions also specify aspects related to the simulation of the model, such as time and spatial discretization, initial and boundary conditions as well as data output and visualization. The full model specification is stored in a single file in XML format, aiding archiving and model exchange. The same format is used to periodically store the simulation state during execution.</p>
      <p>The model description language and model integration is described in more detail in the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btt772/-/DC1">Supplementary Information</ext-link> and on the Web site.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2.3">
      <title>2.3 Graphical user interface</title>
      <p>GUI (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="btt772-F1">Fig. 1</xref>B) assists the user in the workflow from model development to data analysis. The model editor supports model construction by, for example, copy/pasting between models, disabling/enabling model components and providing context-sensitive documentation. It provides a job scheduler that supports multithreaded and parallel job execution. For parameter exploration and sensitivity analysis, ranges of values can be specified for batch processing of any set of model parameters. Simulation results are archived with their associated models in a folder structure that can be browsed from within the GUI. Archived models can be restored and resumed for further analysis.
<fig id="btt772-F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Morpheus supports the simulation and integration of diverse modeling approaches including (1) cell-based, (2) multiscale and (3) image-based modeling, see case studies in main text. (<bold>B</bold>) The user interface provides workflow tools for (1) model editing, (2) visualization, (3) archiving, (4) data analysis and (5) batch processing</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="btt772f1p"/></fig></p>
      <p>Output data can be analyzed at runtime, written to plain text files for <italic>post hoc</italic> analysis and visualized using the flexible gnuplot interface. For 3D data, the multichannel TIFF format is supported, providing an interface to image analysis software such as ImageJ.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>3 CASE STUDIES</title>
    <p>To date, the Morpheus modeling and simulation environment has been used in a diverse range of studies including the study of collective motion in <italic>Myxococcus xantus</italic> using an extension of the CPM (<xref rid="btt772-B9" ref-type="bibr">Starruß <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), the investigation of transdifferentiation and pattern formation in the pancreas using a coupled ODE lattice model (<xref rid="btt772-B2" ref-type="bibr">de Back <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013a</xref>, <xref rid="btt772-B3" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="btt772-F1">Fig. 1</xref>A1) and modeling of vascular morphogenesis using a coupled CPM/reaction-diffusion model (<xref rid="btt772-B5" ref-type="bibr">Köhn-Luque <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>, <xref rid="btt772-B6" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="btt772-F1">Fig. 1</xref>A2). Currently, the software is also being used for image-based modeling by integration of spatial information from microscopy images into simulation models (e.g. liver tissue, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="btt772-F1">Fig. 1</xref>A3). Morpheus has also proven to be useful in the classroom, for students in mathematics and physics as well as in biology.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
      <caption>
        <title>Supplementary Data</title>
      </caption>
      <media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_30_9_1331__index.html"/>
      <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_btt772_Morpheus_Supplement.pdf"/>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack>
    <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
    <p>The authors thank Fabian Rost, Robert Müller, Michael Seifert and Anja Voß-Böhme for discussions and contributions, and thank Marino Zerial and Yannis Kalaidzidis for providing the image data of liver tissue.</p>
    <p><italic>Funding</italic>: <funding-source>German Ministry for Education and Research (BMBF)</funding-source> (<award-id>0315734</award-id>, <award-id>0316169</award-id>).</p>
    <p><italic>Conflict of Interest</italic>: none declared.</p>
  </ack>
  <ref-list>
    <title>REFERENCES</title>
    <ref id="btt772-B1">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Andasari</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Integrating intracellular dynamics using CompuCell3D and BionetSolver: applications to multiscale modelling of cancer cell growth and invasion</article-title>
        <source>PLoS One</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <fpage>e33726</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22461894</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt772-B2">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>de Back</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>On the role of lateral stabilization during early patterning in the pancreas</article-title>
        <source>J. R. Soc. Interface</source>
        <year>2013a</year>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <fpage>20120766</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23193107</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt772-B3">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>de Back</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Transdifferentiation of pancreatic cells by loss of contact-mediated signals</article-title>
        <source>BMC Syst. Biol.</source>
        <year>2013b</year>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <fpage>77</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23938152</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt772-B4">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Graner</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Simulation of biological cell sorting using a two-dimensional extended Potts model</article-title>
        <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
        <year>1992</year>
        <volume>69</volume>
        <fpage>2013</fpage>
        <lpage>2016</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10046374</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt772-B5">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Köhn-Luque</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Early embryonic vascular patterning by matrix-mediated paracrine signalling: a mathematical model study</article-title>
        <source>PLoS One</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <fpage>e24175</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21949696</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt772-B6">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Köhn-Luque</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Dynamics of VEGF matrix-retention in vascular network patterning</article-title>
        <source>Phys. Biol.</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <fpage>066007</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24305433</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt772-B7">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Machado</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Modeling formalisms in systems biology</article-title>
        <source>AMB Express</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>1</volume>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <lpage>14</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21906327</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt772-B8">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mirams</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Chaste: an open source C++ library for computational physiology and biology</article-title>
        <source>PLoS Comput. Biol.</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <fpage>e1002970</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23516352</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt772-B9">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Starruß</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A new mechanism for collective migration in <italic>Myxococcus xanthus</italic></article-title>
        <source>J. Stat. Phys.</source>
        <year>2007</year>
        <volume>128</volume>
        <fpage>269</fpage>
        <lpage>286</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt772-B10">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sütterlin</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Bridging the scales: semantic integration of quantitative SBML in graphical multi-cellular models and simulations with EPISIM and COPASI</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>29</volume>
        <fpage>223</fpage>
        <lpage>229</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23162085</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btt772-B11">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Swat</surname>
            <given-names>MH</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Multi-scale modeling of tissues using CompuCell3D</article-title>
        <source>Methods Cell Biol.</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>110</volume>
        <fpage>325</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22482955</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
