<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.1 20050630//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 2.1?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformation</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformation</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Bioinformation</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Bioinformation</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">0973-8894</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">0973-2063</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Biomedical Informatics</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3819573</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">97320630009870</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6026/97320630009870</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Software</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>SNPAAMapper: An efficient genome-wide SNP variant analysis pipeline for next-generation sequencing data</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Bai</surname>
          <given-names>Yongsheng</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Cavalcoli</surname>
          <given-names>James</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Morgridge Institute for Research, University of Wisconsin-Madison, 330 N Orchard St, Madison, WI 53715, U.S.A</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Center for Computational Medicine and Bioinformatics, and Department of Computational Medicine and Bioinformatics, University of Michigan, 100 Washtenaw Ave., Ann Arbor, Michigan 48109, U.S.A</aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="COR1"><label>*</label>Yongsheng Bai: <email>yongshengbai@hotmail.com</email></corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <year>2013</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>16</day>
      <month>10</month>
      <year>2013</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>9</volume>
    <issue>17</issue>
    <fpage>870</fpage>
    <lpage>872</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>27</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© 2013 Biomedical Informatics</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
      <license license-type="open-access">
        <license-p>This is an open-access article, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium,
for non-commercial purposes, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract>
      <p>Many NGS analysis tools focusing on read alignment and variant calling functions for exome sequencing data have been 
developed in recent years. However, publicly available tools dealing with the downstream analysis of genome-wide variants are 
fewer and have limited functionality. We developed SNPAAMapper, a novel variant analysis pipeline that can effectively classify 
variants by region (e.g. CDS, UTRs, intron, upstream, downstream), predict amino acid change type (e.g. synonymous, non-synonymous 
mutation), and prioritize mutation effects (e.g. CDS versus UTRs). Additional functionality afforded by our pipeline includes: 
checking variants at exon/intron junctions, customized homozygosity and allele frequency cutoff parameters, and annotation of 
known variants with dbSNP information, listing original and mutated amino acid sequences containing variants. The final result is 
reported in a spreadsheet format table containing all variant associated information and prioritized amino acids effects for 
investigators to examine.</p>
      <sec id="sb1e">
        <title>Availability</title>
        <p>Perl scripts and required input files are available on the web at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ccmb.med.umich.edu/ccdu/SNPAAMapper">http://www.ccmb.med.umich.edu/ccdu /SNPAAMapper.</ext-link></p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <kwd-group>
      <kwd>SNP</kwd>
      <kwd>Next Generation Sequencing</kwd>
      <kwd>Downstream Analysis</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec id="s1">
    <title>Background</title>
    <p>Next-generation sequencing (NGS) technologies, such as exome 
and/or whole-genome re-sequencing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>], are increasingly 
assisting researchers in the identification of genetic mutations. 
The application of this technology has been helping researchers 
to identify novel mutations associated with both rare and 
common disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">2</xref>,
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>]. As the study of genetic mutation 
enters the NGS era, reliable and publicly available downstream 
analysis tools are becoming increasingly important to the field. 
We developed SNPAAMapper, a single nucleotide 
polymorphism (SNP) annotation and amino acid mapping 
pipeline.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="methods" id="s2">
    <title>Methodology</title>
    <p>Several initial data processing steps were used to annotate the 
variants. First, the short read sequences were aligned to the 
reference genome using BWA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>] and the SAMtools package 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>] 
was used to call variants (SNPs and INDELs). Second, 
depending on the biology questions being asked, several 
intermediate and filter steps/parameters could be applied to 
select and filter these variants before the algorithms were 
called. The filtered Variant Call Format (VCF) file was used as 
the input for further processing. The overall view of the 
SNPAAMapper is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>. There are two major 
algorithms involved in classifying variants by regions in our 
variant analysis pipeline. Algorithm 1 generates a new 
annotation table with “coding” and other information 
annotated for each exon. We followed the University of 
California, Santa Cruz (UCSC) internal database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06">6</xref>] annotation 
coordinates (zero-based start and one-based end) to populate 
and/or calculate the start and end of each feature (coding 
region sequences or CDS, upstream or downstream sequences, 
untranslated regions or UTRs, intron) for each exon. Features 
were annotated according to their “neighboring” or deriving 
feature’s annotation coordinates from the UCSC. For example, 
if the “intronStart” was calculated from its previous exonEnd 
which is one-based annotation from UCSC annotation, the 
“intronStart” will be one-based as well.</p>
    <p>This configure file generated by Algorithm 1 was read by 
Algorithm 2 to assign identified variants to the genomic 
locus/gene(s) and to classify the variants by regions. There are 
two sub-algorithms in Algorithm 2: Algorithm2-Sub1 generated 
a list of feature (CDS, upstream, downstream, UTRs, and 
intron,) annotation files only once for each genome/species. 
Specifically, two paired files (feature_start with feature_end 
and feature_start with UCSC Gene ID) for each feature and one 
main file (chromosome_number with feature_start) were 
produced as described below. All start coordinates on every 
chromosome for each feature’s main file were recorded and 
sorted for the purpose of quickly locating variant’s genomic 
coordinate in the genome. The “end coordinate” and associated 
UCSC gene IDs corresponding to every start annotation for 
each feature was stored in two separate files. Algorithm2-Sub2 
used above annotations/files to map identified variants onto 
the genomic location and report annotation classes. We 
downloaded all human (hg19) protein-coding genes’ full 
coding region sequences (CDS Exons) including introns 
between CDSs with the genomic coordinates annotated for the 
beginning and end of CDSs from the UCSC genome browser’s 
“Gene and Gene Prediction” data track [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07">7</xref>]. The downloaded 
output sequence type was set to “genomic” and we also 
stipulated downloaded sequences format as “Exons in upper 
case, everything else in lower case” for easy manipulation. We 
also downloaded UCSC annotation table “kgXref.txt” to 
convert the UCSC KnownGene ID to HUGO gene symbol for 
final report. The pipeline used genomic coordinate to 
automatically classify variants into regions: non-synonymous 
missense (NSM), non-synonymous nonsense (NSN), and 
synonymous (SYN) mutation if the hit falls into a CDS, 
upstream, downstream, the 5’ or 3’ UTR, and intron region. The 
UCSC “knownGene.txt” and “kgXref.txt” annotation files from 
UCSC genome browser were used to obtain the information 
relative to the genomic location and gene for detected variants. 
The final mutation effect was prioritized according to the 
category order listed above.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s3">
    <title>SNPAAMapper Input and Output</title>
    <p>The current SNPAAMapper pipeline accepts the VCF input file 
in tab-delimited format. The current final output file consists of 
the following columns: sample number, chromosome number, 
variant genomic position start, gene symbol, UCSC Gene ID, 
variant mapping strand, amino acid position for mutation (for 
CDS hit), variant type (SNP or INDEL), reference amino acid 
(and codon) → mutant amino acid (and codon), variant class 
(SYN, NSM, or NSN), reference amino acid sequence, mutated 
amino acid sequence, hit type (CDS, Upstream, Downstream, 
UTRs, or Intron hit), dbSNP ID [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>] if known, reference 
nucleotide, alternative or called nucleotide, quality, depth, 
allele frequency, read categories, and other useful information 
from variant calling results. A sample output from 
SNPAAMapper on a NGS dataset is shown in our additional 
illustration.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s4">
    <title>Caveats and Future Development</title>
    <p>Our pipeline provides a convenient tool that allows detected 
variants to be further elucidated. This pipeline facilitates the 
fast downstream analysis for detected variants. We believe our 
pipeline will supply researchers with a convenient downstream 
interpretation for identified variants. In comparing to snpEff 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R09">9</xref>], 
an open-source, state of the art variant effect predictor tool, 
although their performance are similar, SNPAAMapper has the 
functionality of annotating regulatory variants, and the 
mutation effect prioritization step in SNPAAMapper also 
greatly simplifies downstream analysis. SNPAAMapper 
provides maximum flexibility and allows analysis of NGS read 
data generated by any short, long, single-end and paired-end 
protocols from different NGS sequencing platforms. Current 
version of SNPAAMapper processes the VCF file generated by 
samtools-0.1.18 or its earlier version. It is also an easy-to-use 
pipeline for processing VCF input data. Researchers can easily 
run the pipeline commands by setting their customized 
parameters to prioritize the SNPs for wet-lab validation. The 
initial pipeline was written for human data, but it can be easily 
modified and/or extended for other species. Also, the current 
pipeline only reports detailed annotation information for the 
SNP variant class. We’ll extend our algorithms/pipeline to 
handle INDELs. The pipeline is also freely available for 
academic users to use. Users can download all input files onto 
their machines and run the pipeline as long as Perl is installed.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s5">
    <title>Funding</title>
    <p>This pipeline development was supported in part by 
funds from the Medical School at the University of Michigan.</p>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack>
    <p>We thank Jan Ching Chun Hu for providing the sequencing 
data. We greatly appreciate Ana Grant and Jun Li for their 
precious comments on the manuscript.</p>
  </ack>
  <fn-group>
    <fn id="FN1" fn-type="other">
      <p><bold>Citation:</bold>Bai &amp; Cavalcoli, Bioinformation 9(17): 870-872 (2013)</p>
    </fn>
  </fn-group>
  <ref-list>
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="R01">
      <label>1</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bentley</surname>
            <given-names>DR</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source>
        <year>2006</year>
        <volume>16</volume>
        <fpage>545</fpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 17055251?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17055251</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R02">
      <label>2</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Basiardes</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <source>Nature Methods</source>
        <year>2005</year>
        <volume>2</volume>
        <fpage>63</fpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 16152676?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16152676</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R03">
      <label>3</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ng</surname>
            <given-names>SB</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <source>Nat Genet</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>42</volume>
        <fpage>30</fpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 19915526?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19915526</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R04">
      <label>4</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Durbin</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <fpage>1754</fpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 19451168?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19451168</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R05">
      <label>5</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <fpage>2078</fpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 19505943?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505943</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R06">
      <label>6</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kent</surname>
            <given-names>WJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <source>Genome Res</source>
        <year>2002</year>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <fpage>996</fpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 12045153?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12045153</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R07">
      <label>7</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
        <comment>
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genome.ucsc.edu">http://genome.ucsc.edu</ext-link>
        </comment>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R08">
      <label>8</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
        <comment>
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/SNP/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/SNP/</ext-link>
        </comment>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R09">
      <label>9</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cingolani</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <source>Fly (Austin)</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <fpage>80</fpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 22728672?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22728672</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
<floats-group>
  <fig id="F1" position="float">
    <label>Figure 1</label>
    <caption>
      <p>The SNPAAMapper analysis pipeline workflow</p>
    </caption>
    <graphic xlink:href="97320630009870F1"/>
  </fig>
</floats-group>
