<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">bioinfo</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1367-4803</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1367-4811</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4824126</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv724</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">btv724</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Applications Notes</subject>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Databases and Ontologies</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>Sequence database versioning for command line and Galaxy bioinformatics servers</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Dooley</surname>
          <given-names>Damion M.</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btv724-aff1">
          <sup>1</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="btv724-cor1">*</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Petkau</surname>
          <given-names>Aaron J.</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btv724-aff2">
          <sup>2</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Van Domselaar</surname>
          <given-names>Gary</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btv724-aff2">
          <sup>2</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Hsiao</surname>
          <given-names>William W.L.</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btv724-aff1">
          <sup>1</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btv724-aff3">
          <sup>3</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="btv724-cor1">*</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="btv724-aff1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Pathology, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, BC, Canada</aff>
      <aff id="btv724-aff2"><sup>2</sup>National Microbiology Laboratory, Public Health Agency of Canada, Winnipeg, MB, Canada</aff>
      <aff id="btv724-aff3"><sup>3</sup>BC Public Health Microbiology and Reference Laboratory, Vancouver, BC, Canada</aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="btv724-cor1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed.</corresp>
      <fn id="btv724-FN1">
        <p>Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren</p>
      </fn>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
      <day>15</day>
      <month>4</month>
      <year>2016</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>12</day>
      <month>12</month>
      <year>2015</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>12</day>
      <month>12</month>
      <year>2015</year>
    </pub-date>
    <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
    <volume>32</volume>
    <issue>8</issue>
    <fpage>1275</fpage>
    <lpage>1277</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>12</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>01</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>06</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
      <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" license-type="creative-commons">
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract>
      <p><bold>Motivation:</bold> There are various reasons for rerunning bioinformatics tools and pipelines on sequencing data, including reproducing a past result, validation of a new tool or workflow using a known dataset, or tracking the impact of database changes. For identical results to be achieved, regularly updated reference sequence databases must be versioned and archived. Database administrators have tried to fill the requirements by supplying users with one-off versions of databases, but these are time consuming to set up and are inconsistent across resources. Disk storage and data backup performance has also discouraged maintaining multiple versions of databases since databases such as NCBI nr can consume 50 Gb or more disk space per version, with growth rates that parallel Moore's law.</p>
      <p><bold>Results:</bold> Our end-to-end solution combines our own Kipper software package—a simple key-value large file versioning system—with BioMAJ (software for downloading sequence databases), and Galaxy (a web-based bioinformatics data processing platform). Available versions of databases can be recalled and used by command-line and Galaxy users. The Kipper data store format makes publishing curated FASTA databases convenient since in most cases it can store a range of versions into a file marginally larger than the size of the latest version.</p>
      <p><bold>Availability and implementation:</bold> Kipper v1.0.0 and the Galaxy Versioned Data tool are written in Python and released as free and open source software available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/Public-Health-Bioinformatics/kipper">https://github.com/Public-Health-Bioinformatics/kipper</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/Public-Health-Bioinformatics/versioned_data">https://github.com/Public-Health-Bioinformatics/versioned_data</ext-link>, respectively; detailed setup instructions can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/Public-Health-Bioinformatics/versioned_data/blob/master/doc/setup.md">https://github.com/Public-Health-Bioinformatics/versioned_data/blob/master/doc/setup.md</ext-link></p>
      <p><bold>Contact</bold>: <email>Damion.Dooley@Bccdc.Ca</email> or <email>William.Hsiao@Bccdc.Ca</email></p>
      <p><bold>Supplementary information:</bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btv724/-/DC1">Supplementary data</ext-link> are available at <italic>Bioinformatics</italic> online.</p>
    </abstract>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="3"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec>
    <title>1 Introduction</title>
    <p>As outlined in motivation, the challenge is to efficiently archive versions of large FASTA format reference sequence databases which usually grow with many inserts but relatively few deletes or updates. These databases are suited to differential archiving (hereafter referred to as ‘diff’) in which the differences between consecutive version files are encoded as a set of instructions that enables their regeneration. With this in mind, we reviewed existing solutions for large text file versioning using the following criteria:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A choice of archiving engines tuned to file content.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An efficient differential versioning engine for large (&gt;30 Gb) key-value text files.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Handle scheduled import of reference databases.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Easy interface to Galaxy.</p></list-item></list></p>
    <p>We concluded that a large FASTA file differential archiving system would have to be developed. Some NCBI reference databases provide daily diff files spanning the most recent month (e.g. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ftp://ftp.ncbi.nih.gov/genbank/daily-nc/">ftp://ftp.ncbi.nih.gov/genbank/daily-nc/</ext-link>) but no publically available client-side system exists for version update and retrieval. Git (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://git-scm.com">http://git-scm.com</ext-link>), a file and code versioning tool, was evaluated as a possible solution but was found to be inefficient at versioning large FASTA files. As noted by <xref rid="btv724-B4" ref-type="bibr">Ram (2013)</xref> Git does not handle large datasets well, and must externalize them as separate files using tools like git-annex (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://git-annex.branchable.com">https://git-annex.branchable.com</ext-link>). Our review of popular key-value databases (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btv724/-/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link>) found that they lack a versioning system for key-value contents.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>2 Implementation</title>
    <p>Our end-to-end versioned Data System combines BioMAJ version 1.2.3 (<xref rid="btv724-B2" ref-type="bibr">Filangi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>) a flexible reference database download manager, with several versioning tool options and a user-friendly graphical interface (Galaxy). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="btv724-F1">Figure 1</xref> shows our proof-of-concept implementation of a Galaxy interface to the Kipper, git, file-folder and Biomaj systems.
<fig id="btv724-F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>End-to-end database versioning system: (<bold>a</bold>) BioMAJ on a schedule checks for and downloads new database versions. For a given database it can then trigger Kipper to add it to a volume. (<bold>b</bold>) One can also add new database versions directly via command line either to a Kipper or git archive or as a new sub-folder. (<bold>c</bold>) Galaxy can then provide these versions to users for retrieval</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="btv724f1p"/></fig>
</p>
    <p>BioMAJ places large multi-volume reference databases into a versioned folder structure, and can trigger download post-processes on them like Kipper diff transformation. Recently the BioMAJ team introduced a Galaxy tool that connects current BioMAJ downloads (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.e-biogenouest.org/resources/1397/download/AnthonyBretaudeau_Galaxy_Day_IFB_2014_BioMAJ2Galaxy.pdf">https://www.e-biogenouest.org/resources/1397/download/AnthonyBretaudeau_Galaxy_Day_IFB_2014_BioMAJ2Galaxy.pdf</ext-link>). This nicely addresses the end-to-end data synchronization problem for current databases, but database versions are stored in full, so the storage space problem remains, and recall functionality can still be enhanced.</p>
    <sec>
      <title>2.1 Kipper</title>
      <p>Kipper is a command-line file versioning solution we have created for key-value text records. It manages a simple key-value data store by keeping track of whether a given key is inserted, updated, or deleted for each version. It recalls versions by date or version id, and stores them in separate volume files when convenient. An additional JSON metadata file catalogs the data store’s name, data type, volume(s) and versions. Version metadata can be downloaded separately to determine if a new version is available. Kipper currently accepts text files having tab or space delimited key-value records, as well as the standard multi-line FASTA format. For FASTA data, the unique sequence identifier (text between ‘&gt;’and first space) is used for key text. The remaining FASTA description and sequence becomes the value.</p>
      <p>In a volume each key-value record is stored as a line containing the following tab-delimited fields (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="btv724-T1">Table 1</xref>): creation version id (Ins), deletion version id (Del), key (Key) and value (Value). As they are sorted by key and then creation version id, consecutive records track a key-value’s inserts, updates and deletes. <xref ref-type="table" rid="btv724-T1">Table 1</xref> shows an update to the description text for a FASTA RCSB Protein Database record with gene id 384482242. The first line shows the original record was inserted in (our) version 1. It is removed in version 3, and the following line re-inserts it with an additional associated gene id in version 3. The sequence is removed under this key in version 7 (elsewhere it actually lives on as a new gi|817598624|pdb|4D0C|C record).
<table-wrap id="btv724-T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>. Kipper record format example</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ins</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Del</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Key</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Value</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|384482242|pdb|2YF5|C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chain C, Complex Of A B21 Chicken Mhc Class I Molecule And A 10mer Chicken Peptide TAGQSNYDRL</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|384482242|pdb|2YF5|C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chain C, Complex Of A B21 Chicken Mhc Class I Molecule And A 10mer Chicken Peptide<bold>^Agi|817598624|pdb|4D0C|C Chain C, Complex Of A B21 Chicken Mhc Class I Molecule And A 10mer Chicken Peptide</bold> TAGQSNYDRL</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>2.2 Galaxy versioned data tool</title>
      <p>Like many labs, we are adopting Galaxy (<xref rid="btv724-B3" ref-type="bibr">Giardine <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>) for running bioinformatics tasks and workflows. Within this context, our Versioned Data tool provides an easy interface for retrieving multiple reference databases and derived products like NCBI-BLAST databases. This tool enables a user to select versioned datasets by name from a list (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="btv724-F1">Fig. 1c</xref>). In a special Galaxy data library called ‘Versioned Data’ a Galaxy admin can arrange versioned data first by data source (NCBI, EBI, etc.) or by type (viral, bacterial, etc.) Individual data stores are set up within this hierarchy and are listed in the tool. A user can then select the current version, or a particular retrieval date or version number. Requested datasets are fetched from a cache if they exist there, otherwise the cache is populated with newly extracted data. Folder and BioMAJ interfaces do not need caching—they merely return links to permanent folder content.</p>
      <p>A Galaxy admin can also set up a set of post-processing workflows, such as BLAST (<xref rid="btv724-B1" ref-type="bibr">Camacho <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>) indexing, that users can trigger directly on retrieved datasets. The results are cached for reuse by other users. A cache-cleaning script can be run periodically to remove all but the latest cached version of any dataset.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>3 Discussion</title>
    <p>We have found that Kipper can version 50 Gb+ text files that other archiving systems like git have no capacity for. There are a few operational issues we plan to address as detailed in the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btv724/-/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link> file (e.g. small changes in FASTA descriptions can lead to re-insertions of long sequences; also the prerequisite download of large input files can be unreliable.)</p>
    <p>The standardization of reference databases by date of publication is a key problem for experimental replication in the bioinformatics realm. The community needs to develop a basic metadata standard for reference database sharing. Towards this goal, our Kipper versioning and archiving system brings reference database reproducibility, ease of use and lower maintenance costs to existing server infrastructure. We welcome partnerships to extend the Kipper data store functionality, and we encourage reference database providers to consider Kipper for convenient version storage, recall and publishing.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
      <caption>
        <title>Supplementary Data</title>
      </caption>
      <media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_32_8_1275__index.html"/>
      <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword" xlink:href="supp_btv724_Kipper_Versioned_Data-Supplementary_WH_DD.docx"/>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack>
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <p>More information about the project can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.irida.ca">http://www.irida.ca</ext-link>.</p>
  </ack>
  <sec>
    <title>Funding</title>
    <p>This work was supported by the Genome Canada/Genome BC Grant 172PHM ‘A Federated Bioinformatics Platform for Public Health Microbial Genomics’ under Fiona Brinkman, Gary Van Domselaar and William Hsiao.</p>
    <p><italic>Conflict of Interest:</italic> none declared.</p>
  </sec>
  <ref-list>
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="btv724-B1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Camacho</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>BLAST+: architecture and applications</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>421</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20003500</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv724-B2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Filangi</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>BioMAJ: a flexible framework for databanks synchronization and processing</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>1823</fpage>–<lpage>1825</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18593718</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv724-B3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giardine</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Galaxy: a platform for interactive large-scale genome analysis</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>., <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>1451</fpage>–<lpage>1455</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16169926</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv724-B4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ram</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Git can facilitate greater reproducibility and increased transparency in science</article-title>. <source>Source Code Biol. Med</source>., <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>7</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23448176</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
