<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">gbe</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">gbe</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Genome Biology and Evolution</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1759-6653</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4524488</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26133389</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evv121</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">evv121</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Research Article</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>Quest for Orthologs Entails Quest for Tree of Life: In Search of the Gene Stream</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Boeckmann</surname>
          <given-names>Brigitte</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv121-AFF1">
          <sup>1</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="evv121-COR1">*</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Marcet-Houben</surname>
          <given-names>Marina</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv121-AFF2">
          <sup>2</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv121-AFF3">
          <sup>3</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Rees</surname>
          <given-names>Jonathan A.</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv121-AFF4">
          <sup>4</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Forslund</surname>
          <given-names>Kristoffer</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv121-AFF5">
          <sup>5</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Huerta-Cepas</surname>
          <given-names>Jaime</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv121-AFF5">
          <sup>5</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Muffato</surname>
          <given-names>Matthieu</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv121-AFF6">
          <sup>6</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Yilmaz</surname>
          <given-names>Pelin</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv121-AFF7">
          <sup>7</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Xenarios</surname>
          <given-names>Ioannis</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv121-AFF1">
          <sup>1</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv121-AFF8">
          <sup>8</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv121-AFF9">
          <sup>9</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Bork</surname>
          <given-names>Peer</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv121-AFF5">
          <sup>5</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv121-AFF10">
          <sup>10</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv121-AFF11">
          <sup>11</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Lewis</surname>
          <given-names>Suzanna E.</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv121-AFF12">
          <sup>12</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Gabaldón</surname>
          <given-names>Toni</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv121-AFF2">
          <sup>2</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv121-AFF3">
          <sup>3</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv121-AFF13">
          <sup>13</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <collab>the Quest for Orthologs Species Tree Working Group</collab>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="evv121-AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Swiss-Prot, Swiss Institute of Bioinformatics, Geneva, Switzerland</aff>
      <aff id="evv121-AFF2"><sup>2</sup>Bioinformatics and Genomics, Centre for Genomic Regulation, Barcelona, Spain</aff>
      <aff id="evv121-AFF3"><sup>3</sup>Universitat Pompeu Fabra, Barcelona, Spain</aff>
      <aff id="evv121-AFF4"><sup>4</sup>US National Evolutionary Synthesis Center, Duke University, Durham, NC</aff>
      <aff id="evv121-AFF5"><sup>5</sup>Structural and Computational Biology Unit, European Molecular Biology Laboratory, Heidelberg, Germany</aff>
      <aff id="evv121-AFF6"><sup>6</sup>European Molecular Biology Laboratory, European Bioinformatics Institute, Wellcome Trust Genome Campus, Hinxton, United Kingdom</aff>
      <aff id="evv121-AFF7"><sup>7</sup>Microbial Genomics and Bioinformatics Research Group, Max Planck Institute for Marine Microbiology, Bremen, Germany</aff>
      <aff id="evv121-AFF8"><sup>8</sup>Vital-IT, Swiss Institute of Bioinformatics, Lausanne, Switzerland</aff>
      <aff id="evv121-AFF9"><sup>9</sup>Center for Integrative Genomics, University of Lausanne, Lausanne, Switzerland</aff>
      <aff id="evv121-AFF10"><sup>10</sup>Germany Molecular Medicine Partnership Unit, University Hospital Heidelberg and European Molecular Biology Laboratory, Heidelberg, Germany</aff>
      <aff id="evv121-AFF11"><sup>11</sup>Max Delbrück Centre for Molecular Medicine, Berlin, Germany</aff>
      <aff id="evv121-AFF12"><sup>12</sup>Genomics Division, Lawrence Berkeley National Lab, Berkeley</aff>
      <aff id="evv121-AFF13"><sup>13</sup>Institució Catalana de Recerca I Estudis Avançats, Barcelona, Spain</aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="evv121-COR1">*Corresponding author: E-mail: <email>brigitte.boeckmann@isb-sib.ch</email>.</corresp>
      <fn id="FN100">
        <p><bold>Associate editor:</bold> Eugene Koonin</p>
      </fn>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2015</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>01</day>
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2015</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>01</day>
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2015</year>
    </pub-date>
    <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
    <volume>7</volume>
    <issue>7</issue>
    <fpage>1988</fpage>
    <lpage>1999</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>19</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2015. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
      <license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract>
      <p>Quest for Orthologs (QfO) is a community effort with the goal to improve and benchmark orthology predictions. As quality assessment assumes prior knowledge on species phylogenies, we investigated the congruency between existing species trees by comparing the relationships of 147 QfO reference organisms from six Tree of Life (ToL)/species tree projects: The National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) taxonomy, Opentree of Life, the sequenced species/species ToL, the 16S ribosomal RNA (rRNA) database, and trees published by Ciccarelli et al. (Ciccarelli FD, et al. 2006. Toward automatic reconstruction of a highly resolved tree of life. Science 311:1283–1287) and by Huerta-Cepas et al. (Huerta-Cepas J, Marcet-Houben M, Gabaldon T. 2014. A nested phylogenetic reconstruction approach provides scalable resolution in the eukaryotic Tree Of Life. PeerJ PrePrints 2:223) Our study reveals that each species tree suggests a different phylogeny: 87 of the 146 (60%) possible splits of a dichotomous and rooted tree are congruent, while all other splits are incongruent in at least one of the species trees. Topological differences are observed not only at deep speciation events, but also within younger clades, such as <italic>Hominidae</italic>, <italic>Rodentia</italic>, <italic>Laurasiatheria</italic>, <italic>or rosids</italic>. The evolutionary relationships of 27 archaea and bacteria are highly inconsistent. By assessing 458,108 gene trees from 65 genomes, we show that consistent species topologies are more often supported by gene phylogenies than contradicting ones. The largest concordant species tree includes 77 of the QfO reference organisms at the most. Results are summarized in the form of a consensus ToL (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://swisstree.vital-it.ch/species_tree">http://swisstree.vital-it.ch/species_tree</ext-link>) that can serve different benchmarking purposes.</p>
    </abstract>
    <kwd-group>
      <kwd>Tree of Life</kwd>
      <kwd>species tree</kwd>
      <kwd>gene tree support</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="12"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec sec-type="intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <p>Because important applications in the Life Sciences rely on orthology inference, scientists—among whom many authors of orthology databases—joined a community effort named “Quest for Orthologs (QfO),” one of whose goals is to compare and improve orthology predictions (<xref rid="evv121-B16" ref-type="bibr">Gabaldon et al. 2009</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B9" ref-type="bibr">Dessimoz et al. 2012</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B48" ref-type="bibr">Sonnhammer et al. 2014</xref>). The evaluation of such inference depends on the thorough understanding of the evolution of gene families and taxa. To generate reference gene trees (<xref rid="evv121-B51" ref-type="bibr">Trachana et al. 2011</xref>, <xref rid="evv121-B52" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B48" ref-type="bibr">Sonnhammer et al. 2014</xref>), it is crucial to find a core set of species whose relative histories are known to the best of our knowledge. After realizing the incongruence of Trees of Life (ToL) at the third Quest for Orthologs (QfO3) conference in Lausanne (Switzerland) in 2013 </p>
    <p>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://questfororthologs.org/meetings#quest_for_orthologs_3">http://questfororthologs.org/meetings#quest_for_orthologs_3</ext-link>, last accessed July 7, 2015), a QfO species tree working group was initiated to survey the status of species phylogenies as well as to establish contacts between experts of the ToL community. Within the same year, exchanges were initiated between the two research communities at the Biodiversity Information Standards conference (Taxonomic Databases Working Group) in 2013 in Florence, Italy (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.slideshare.net/suzi.lewis/q4-o-at-tdwg-2013">http://www.slideshare.net/suzi.lewis/q4-o-at-tdwg-2013</ext-link>, last accessed July 7, 2015).</p>
    <p>ToL links inferred species histories on a global level. Although there is an ongoing debate on tree or network-based evolution—particularly in prokaryotes where horizontal gene transfer (HGT) can be massive (<xref rid="evv121-B28" ref-type="bibr">Koonin et al. 2001</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B53" ref-type="bibr">Treangen and Rocha 2011</xref>)—the concept of a ToL is an important pillar in evolutionary biology. In the context of quality assessment for orthology predictions, species trees are key in reconciling species and gene histories and decoding discordance between the two trees. Yet, understanding to which extent species trees are robust recapitulations of the evolution of life and to which extent they depend on method and data set contingencies is challenging. Initially, morphological and anatomical observations led to the assumption that species are related to each other, and species were grouped and classified accordingly. Molecular phylogenetics revolutionized the inference of species phylogenies, thanks to its ability to trace the evolution of proteins, genes, and genomes. Be it for predicting species phylogenies or understanding the evolutionary relationships of genes, the underlying analyses are alike (<xref rid="evv121-B55" ref-type="bibr">Whelan et al. 2001</xref>). As a first step, genes related to each other (homologs) are identified, followed by in-depth analysis on how the genes are related, that is, whether they diverged following a speciation event (ortholog), gene duplication (paralog), or were laterally transferred between organisms (xenolog). In other words, the prediction of gene relationships is based on knowledge of the species tree, and the species tree can be inferred from the study of gene relationships. Hence, there is a risk of circularity when inferring orthology predictions from ortholog-derived species trees.</p>
    <p>In this study, we address the question of the current knowledge and reliability of species relationships by assessing the congruence among the most inclusive ToLs and species trees. To do this, we compared tree topologies for 147 species that were selected for the QfO reference data set 2013: 120 eukaryotes, 7 archaea, and 20 bacteria (hereafter named QfO reference organisms; taxa are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv121/-/DC1">supplementary table S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv121/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). The prediction of their evolutionary relationship differs in many ways which are all able to influence the tree topology (compare <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv121/-/DC1">supplementary table S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv121/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). To begin with, the size of the six analyzed species phylogenies ranges from 191 to 2,227,481 taxa. Taxon sampling has a strong impact on tree reconstruction. As an example, high species coverage has been shown to avoid systematic bias and long branch attraction (LBA) in phylogenetic analysis of molecular sequences (<xref rid="evv121-B41" ref-type="bibr">Philippe et al. 2000</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B20" ref-type="bibr">Heath et al. 2008</xref>). Of importance is also the type of data: In contrast to noncoding genes, coding genes can be analyzed at the level of both nucleotide sequences and amino acid sequences, which can lead to complementary resolution at different levels in the tree space. The analysis of a single gene presumes that the gene history reflects that of the species, as opposed to the study of multiple marker genes. The latter allows the comparison of all gene tree topologies with each other, which helps to identify topological incongruence such as nonvertical gene traffic, which is especially relevant to the study of prokaryotic relationships. Phylogenetic signals can also be obtained from domain occurrence in proteomes, and the analysis of the binary matrix constitutes a fast tree-building approach for regular revision. Another fundamental difference is that not all species trees are built from scratch: Some ToLs use an existing species classification as the initial tree, to which phylogenetic information is added or to guide a phylogenetic analysis. In this case, species trees are not independent, and are thus likely to share higher topological congruence. Last but not the least, some species trees are rooted, while others are not, thus influencing the analysis as well as the interpretation of the tree topology.</p>
    <p>The six species trees under comparison are the following: 1) The NCBI taxonomy is probably the most widely used species classification in molecular phylogenetics because it is the repository for standardized nomenclature and taxonomic identifiers for international sequence databases (<xref rid="evv121-B14" ref-type="bibr">Federhen 2011</xref>). As such, it is often implicitly used as the guide for classification. However, the NCBI taxonomy database is not an authoritative source for nomenclature or classification (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Taxonomy/Browser/wwwtax.cgi?mode=Root">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Taxonomy/Browser/wwwtax.cgi?mode=Root</ext-link>, last accessed July 7, 2015). It currently stores data from 971,052 species and 1,254,947 taxonomic nodes (NCBI taxonomy browser; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Taxonomy/taxonomyhome.html/index.cgi?chapter=statistics">www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Taxonomy/taxonomyhome.html/index.cgi?chapter=statistics</ext-link>, February 19, 2015). The species classification, based on expert knowledge, includes a large number of multifurcating nodes that represent yet unknown species phylogenies. 2) The Open Tree of Life (Opentree) strives to capture the spectrum of known biodiversity. Initially based on the NCBI taxonomy, published species phylogenies are stepwise mapped on the species classification (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biorxiv.org/content/early/2014/12/15/012260">http://biorxiv.org/content/early/2014/12/15/012260</ext-link>, last accessed July 7, 2015). With over 2.3 million taxa, it is the largest of the six species trees. 3) The sequenced species Tree of Life (sToL) is an NCBI taxonomy-guided, bifurcating likelihood tree based on the protein domain composition predicted for cellular organisms with complete proteomes (<xref rid="evv121-B13" ref-type="bibr">Fang et al. 2013</xref>). 4) <xref rid="evv121-B21" ref-type="bibr">Huerta-Cepas, Marcet-Houben, et al. (2014)</xref> developed a nested, hierarchical approach to maximize phylogenetic signals from the sequence data used for tree reconstruction (hereafter named Tree-HC). The species tree thus analyzed includes 216 eukaryotic species and no prokaryotes. 5) <xref rid="evv121-B6" ref-type="bibr">Cicarelli et al. (2006)</xref> published a species tree based on 31 concatenated universal proteins from 191 species, of which 23 are eukaryotes, 18 archaea, and 150 bacteria (hereafter named ToL-C). Although this tree has been updated, thanks to an improved HGT detection methodology (<xref rid="evv121-B7" ref-type="bibr">Creevey et al. 2011</xref>) and the possibility of careful data selection from a considerably increased collection of completely sequenced genomes, we decided to oppose this early version of a species tree—constructed by an automated procedure—to more recent and larger ToLs. 6) The 16S rRNA project is probably the greatest attempt for the detailed analysis of a gene history (<xref rid="evv121-B38" ref-type="bibr">Munoz et al. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B58" ref-type="bibr">Yilmaz et al. 2013</xref>). In 1977, the study of this gene by <xref rid="evv121-B56" ref-type="bibr">Woese and Fox (1977)</xref> resulted in the identification of Archaea as a third domain of life. Today, the expert-curated multiple sequence alignment of ribosomal RNA sequences consists of data from over 10,000 taxa, and the 16S rRNA has become an important marker gene for metagenomics. However, more than one copy of this gene has been observed in genomes (<xref rid="evv121-B5" ref-type="bibr">Case et al. 2007</xref>). As the gene could be subject to HGT, the gene tree can differ from the actual species phylogeny. Consequently, alternative markers have been proposed to determine bacterial biodiversity (<xref rid="evv121-B5" ref-type="bibr">Case et al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B31" ref-type="bibr">Lang et al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B36" ref-type="bibr">Mende et al. 2013</xref>).</p>
    <p>In this study, we show that—for the six species trees—the tree topology of the 147 QfO reference organisms is congruent at 87 of the 146 possible internal nodes of a rooted binary tree; all other nodes are incongruent in at least one of the species trees. In addition, we assessed the discordance of the different species trees with individual gene trees by using available phylomes for QfO species available at PhylomeDB (<xref rid="evv121-B21" ref-type="bibr">Huerta-Cepas, Capella-Gutierrez, et al. 2014</xref>). For benchmarking in the context of the QfO activities, we propose the use of an annotated consensus tree (ToL<sub>c</sub>-147) whose internal branches can be multifurcated at different levels of consistency. We provide a first version here.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="materials">
    <title>Material and Methods</title>
    <sec>
      <title>Terms</title>
      <p>The terms to describe tree relationships and properties have been used in different ways in publications. In this document, the general notion congruency (antonym: incongruency) refers to identical relationships of taxa in independent gene phylogenies or species phylogenies, as well as for splits obtained from these trees. The term concordance (antonym: discordance) is used to describe congruence between a gene tree and a species tree, likewise when trees were pruned to sets of common taxa. A tree topology—or part of it—is consistent, if identical relationships of taxa or clades have been reconstructed based on different data sets.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Species Tree Comparison</title>
      <p>The NCBI taxonomic classification tree was generated at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Taxonomy/CommonTree/wwwcmt.cgi">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Taxonomy/CommonTree/wwwcmt.cgi</ext-link> (July 14, 2014) based on the taxonomic identifiers for the species of the QfO reference proteomes. The sToL tree was constructed at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://supfam.org/SUPERFAMILY/cgi-bin/genome_names.cgi">http://supfam.org/SUPERFAMILY/cgi-bin/genome_names.cgi</ext-link> (July 8, 2014). Twenty-five species differed in their strain and could not be mapped based on the taxonomic identifiers. These species were mapped based on the species names (“relaxed species mapping”). Opentree provided a draft of the species tree (April 16, 2014) and the corresponding species mapping to taxonomic identifiers. The 216 eukaryotic species tree published by Huerta-Cepas (peerj.com/preprints/223/) was provided, including NCBI taxonomic identifiers and annotated branch support values (aLRT SH). Seventy-one species were mapped by taxonomic identifiers, 27 by species name. The ToL by Ciccarelli et al. (ToL-C) was copied from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://itol.embl.de/">http://itol.embl.de/</ext-link> (July 14, 2014). Forty-four QfO reference organisms were identified by their scientific names. The 16S rRNA-based species phylogeny of the all-species living tree project was obtained from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.arb-silva.de/projects/">http://www.arb-silva.de/projects/</ext-link> (LTPs115). Twenty-two archaea and bacteria were mapped to the QfO data set by the species name. Species not matching the QfO reference proteomes were pruned from the trees using the Newick utilities (<xref rid="evv121-B27" ref-type="bibr">Junier and Zdobnov 2010</xref>); species names were standardized using Perl scripts. Robinson–Foulds (RF) distances between pairs of species trees—except for the two complementing species trees that have no taxa in common—were calculated with ETE v2.2 (<xref rid="evv121-B23" ref-type="bibr">Huerta-Cepas et al. 2010</xref>).</p>
      <p>The species consensus tree (ToL<sub>c</sub>-147) was constructed manually and consistency levels annotated for multifurcation at different levels of topological congruence. As a first approach, consistency values were assigned for each node and each species tree, according to the following instances: +1, node is congruent with the ToL<sub>c</sub>-147 topology; +2, same as +1, with significant branch support; 0, multifurcating node; −1, alternative topology (incongruent with ToL<sub>c</sub>-147); −2, alternative topology with significant branch support (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv121/-/DC1">supplementary table S3</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv121/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). The average consistency value was calculated for each node, and results classified into four levels: Level L90 (&gt;1), level L70 (0.75–1), level L50 (&gt;0 to &lt;0.75), and level L10 (≤0). The assigned levels correspond to the annotated consistency values (90, 70, 50, 10) in ToL<sub>c</sub>-147, so nodes can be multifurcated at different levels with existing tree visualization tools. Further evidence for the evolutionary relationship of species was obtained from the literature, and levels adapted according to findings in a similar way as described above; for instance, when published clade-specific analyses significantly supported nodes of the consensus tree. Finally, a fifth level was introduced for practical reasons, for nodes with conflicting results which await further classification (L30).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Assessment of Gene Tree Support for Species Topologies</title>
      <p>For each phylome reconstructed for the QfO project (phyIDs 500–542), the trees were downloaded from phylogenomic database phylomeDB (<xref rid="evv121-B21" ref-type="bibr">Huerta-Cepas, Capella-Gutierrez, et al. 2014</xref>). These gene trees were constructed with a methodology similar to the one used to infer the species phylogeny of Tree-HC, although based on a different set of proteomes. Because gene tree reconstruction was not guided by a species tree and because this experiment is not a quality assessment, this collection of gene phylogenies is suitable to estimate gene tree support for our consensus tree and alternative topologies. Each tree in each phylome was first compared with a given species tree. If they overlapped in less than three species, the tree was discarded. Trees were then pruned so that they contained only species that were present in the species tree. Trees were then rooted by the species placed closest to the root according to the species tree. The tree was then split into orthologous trees following the methodology explained previously (<xref rid="evv121-B33" ref-type="bibr">Marcet-Houben and Gabaldon 2011</xref>) as implemented in ETE v2.2. Briefly, all duplication nodes were detected in the tree by using a species overlap algorithm (<xref rid="evv121-B22" ref-type="bibr">Huerta-Cepas et al. 2007</xref>). All the possible combinations of the duplicated parts of the tree were done and then the tree was pruned as many times as combinations of duplicated nodes were found. These pruned trees are called orthologous trees as all the leaves in them are orthologous to each other. Only trees with less than 100 associated orthologous trees were considered to reduce computing time. A support measure was then calculated as follows: Species trees and orthologous trees were pruned so that they contained exactly the same set of species. Then, for each node in the remaining species tree, we searched each orthologous tree for the presence of the node. The number of trees that contained the node was divided by the total amount of trees that contained the species derived from the node, whether they were monophyletic or not. If a tree resulted in more than one orthologous tree, then each orthologous tree was checked for the presence of the node and then divided by the number of orthologous trees that contained the species derived from the node. This was done to ensure that each tree contributed equally to the final result.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>Results and Discussion</title>
    <sec>
      <title>Species Supernetworks: Survey on the Topological Congruence of Species Trees</title>
      <p>Six well-known broad species phylogenies were compared: The NCBI taxonomic classification, the Opentree of Life, the sequenced sToL, the 16S rRNA-based species tree, and the species phylogenies published by Ciccarelli et al (ToL-C) and Huerta-Cepas et al (Tree-HC). All these trees were generated by applying different methodologies and using different databases, data sets, and sources of phylogenetic signals (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv121/-/DC1">supplementary table S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv121/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online), which makes the search for a consensus species tree especially meaningful. Nonrelevant taxa were pruned from all trees, resulting in cladograms of up to 147 QfO reference organisms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evv121-F1">fig. 1</xref><italic>A</italic> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv121/-/DC1">supplementary file S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv121/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Four of the trees cover species from all the three domains of life (ToLs), and the two complementing species trees consist of prokaryotes and eukaryotes, respectively. Thus, each species can be found in the analyzed data sets—at the most five times—and the average frequency was 4.1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evv121-F1">fig. 1</xref><italic>B</italic>).
<fig id="evv121-F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>F<sc>ig</sc>. 1.—</label><caption><p>Comparison of the six species trees. (<italic>A</italic>) Coverage of QfO species in the analyzed ToLs/species trees: Stacked bar chart of species from the Quest for Orthologs reference proteome set 2013 mapped to the species trees, color-coded by domains of life. The far left column presents the QfO reference organisms. (<italic>B</italic>) Frequency of QfO reference organisms in the analyzed ToLs/species trees. On average, each QfO reference organism occurred in the data set about 4.1 times; represented only twice are the amoeba <italic>Polysphondylium_pallidum</italic> (NCBI TaxId: 13642), the fungi <italic>Rhizopus delemar</italic> (TaxId: 246409) and <italic>Batrachochytrium_dendrobatidis</italic> (NCBI TaxId: 684364). Supernetwork of the eukaryote (<italic>C</italic>), bacterial (<italic>D</italic>), and archaeal (<italic>E</italic>) clade visualize topological congruence and incongruence between ToLs/species trees. (<italic>F</italic>) RF distances between ToLs/species trees: For each tree, the table shows the number of species in common with the species of the QfO reference data set (green cells), the number of QfO reference organisms shared by two trees (blue), and the average RF distances per node between trees (red).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evv121f1p"/></fig></p>
      <p>At first, the degree of incongruence between the predicted species phylogenies was explored through supernetworks for each of the three domains of life (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evv121-F1">fig. 1</xref><italic>C</italic>–<italic>E</italic>). In a phylogenetic supernetwork, identical topologies are merged into a tree structure and alternative topologies are combined into a network (<xref rid="evv121-B25" ref-type="bibr">Huson et al. 2004</xref>). Considerably higher topological congruence is observed in the eukaryotic clade compared with the two prokaryotic clades. One known major factor disturbing phylogenetic reconstruction in prokaryotes is the pervasiveness of HGT in these domains (<xref rid="evv121-B1" ref-type="bibr">Bapteste et al. 2004</xref>). Rates of HGT have been estimated to lie in the range of 1.6–32.6% (<xref rid="evv121-B28" ref-type="bibr">Koonin et al. 2001</xref>) and higher (<xref rid="evv121-B34" ref-type="bibr">McDaniel et al. 2010</xref>), and a constant rate of interspecies gene traffic was reported for universally single copy genes (<xref rid="evv121-B52" ref-type="bibr">Trachana et al. 2014</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Quantification of Topological Congruence between Species Trees</title>
      <p>There are basically two approaches for the quantification of differences in tree topologies: 1) Tree incompatibility, which is calculated from contradicting splits and does not take into account multifurcation, and 2) tree dissimilarity, which is determined from all nonidentical splits, thus measuring incongruent branching patterns including multifurcation. At first, the former sounds more suitable when aiming to identify a consensus, however it does not take into account unresolved (multifurcating) nodes, and thus equates a star-like tree with the perfect tree. This is why we decided to measure the dissimilarity between species phylogenies by applying the RF metric (<xref rid="evv121-B44" ref-type="bibr">Robinson and Foulds 1981</xref>) averaged over the number of nodes common to a tree pair (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evv121-F1">fig. 1</xref><italic>F</italic>). The resulting normalized RF distances between pairs of species trees range from 10% to 63%, thus confirming that none of the species phylogenies are congruent. Distances are shortest between trees which include a high fraction of eukaryotic species, while they increase according to the fraction of prokaryotic species. This result indicates once again high dissimilarity in bacterial and archaeal phylogenies and is thus in agreement with the above described supernetworks. The smallest distance between ToLs was calculated for the NCBI taxonomy and Opentree. This is not surprising, as Opentree is based on the NCBI taxonomic classification. Both trees still share a relatively large number of unresolved nodes, but Opentree synthesizes the taxonomic hierarchy with published species phylogenies, which results in a higher resolution in <italic>Homininae</italic> or early diverging metazoans (<italic>Amphimedon</italic>, <italic>Trichoplax</italic>, <italic>Bilateria</italic>) for instance. The RF distance is the most commonly used dissimilarity measure for pairs of tree topologies, regardless of its high susceptibility to certain topological differences which can result in maximum distance values, even for the interchange of a single leaf (<xref rid="evv121-B32" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al. 2011</xref>). Thus one needs to exercise caution and avoid overinterpreting the results. It should also be recalled that—at this stage—it is not possible to assess the quality of inferred species trees for many reasons, most important of all the lack of knowledge on the true tree. Thus, low distances do not indicate high accuracy nor do high distances indicate failure. The goal of this study is to identify topological incongruence between species phylogenies and, to this end, we summarize node consistency based on the comparison of all six species phylogenies: 87 of the 146 possible splits of a bifurcating, rooted tree are congruent in the compared species trees; all other splits are incongruent in at least one of the six trees (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv121/-/DC1">supplementary table S3</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv121/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Noteworthy, NCBI reflects well topological incongruence in the form of multifurcating nodes, but misses some of the highly supported nodes, such as the consistent node for Diptera/<italic>Bombyx mori</italic>, Metazoa/Monosiga, or Opisthokonta.</p>
      <p>In eukaryotes, 67% (80/119) of the internal nodes of a rooted binary tree are congruent, 79% (94/119) are congruent or compatible (multifurcating), and alternative phylogenies are suggested for 21% (25/119) of the internal nodes. Various reasons can be given for the topological differences within the eukaryotic clade. Tree reconstruction artifacts are frequently explained by the lack of a phylogenetic signal or the failing to discriminate a phylogenetic signal from noise. The former is commonly observed in closely related species, species which diverged in a short interval from a common lineage (short common branch length) or in genes under strong structural and functional constraints, thus evolving at a low rate and lacking shared traits. When homoplasy prevails synapomorphy in genes of fast-evolving species, taxa tend to be grouped by mistake—an artifact known as LBA (<xref rid="evv121-B45" ref-type="bibr">Schulmeister 2004</xref>). For the 147 QfO reference organisms, such knowledge can, for instance, help explain topological incongruence observed for discrete representatives of invertebrate clades sampled along the human lineage as well as for species which diverged early from major clades such as ecdysozoans. Differing phylogenies are not only observed at deep nodes, but also at recent speciation events (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evv121-F2">figs. 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evv121-F3">3</xref><italic>A</italic>). The phylogeny of <italic>Homininae</italic> is an example: The topology is unresolved in the NCBI classification, and a monophyletic origin of chimp and gorilla is suggested by sToL. Opentree implemented a resolved but differing species history—human being more closely related to chimp than to gorilla—based on relevant published phylogenies. One of the underlying studies is a recent phylogenetic analysis of complete mitochondrial primate genomes that provides significant support for a common ancestor of human and chimp after the divergence of gorilla, which is in agreement with many other clade-specific analyses (<xref rid="evv121-B42" ref-type="bibr">Pozzi et al. 2014</xref>). Within the mammalian branch, we note two further clades with contradicting phylogenies: <italic>Glires</italic> and <italic>Laurasiatheria</italic>. Within the first group, the rodents <italic>Cavia porcellus</italic> and <italic>Spermophilus tridecemlineatus</italic> show an interchanged divergence order, and each of the two topologies is suggested by two of the four species trees that include the relevant QfO reference organisms. Tree-HC provides significant branch support for a monophyletic origin of <italic>Murinae</italic> and <italic>C</italic><italic>. porcellus</italic>, and Opentree has implemented supporting results for the same topology. For <italic>Laurasiatheria</italic>, none of the species trees suggest the same phylogeny. For the same clades, incongruence is also observed in various published phylogenies, thus indicating that phylogenetic signals which are derived from the different data sets are ambiguous.
<fig id="evv121-F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>F<sc>ig</sc>. 2.—</label><caption><p>Overview of critical spots in reconstructed species phylogenies. For lack of space, all species trees were pruned to include only species which illustrate yet unresolved phylogenies and contradicting topologies. Color codes: Light green = topologies supporting the consensus tree (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evv121-F3">fig. 3</xref>); dark green = topologies supporting the consensus tree with significant support; red = topologies differ from the consensus tree; dark red = topologies with significant support differ from the consensus tree; light gray = unresolved and/or unknown topologies.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evv121f2p"/></fig>
<fig id="evv121-F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>F<sc>ig</sc>. 3.—</label><caption><p>Consensus tree. (<italic>A</italic>) Consensus phylogeny of the 147 QfO reference organisms. Green branches highlight congruent and bifurcating topologies, grey branches indicate topologies that are either multifurcating or incongruent in at least one of the species trees. Red triangles mark nodes that are supported by at least 75% of the gene trees (see also <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv121/-/DC1">supplementary file S4</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv121/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). (<italic>B</italic>) Eukaryotic clade of the consensus tree at highest (bifurcating, left handed) and lowest (L90, right handed) resolution, pruned to the species set as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evv121-F2">figure 2</xref>. Bifurcation is not yet possible for most internal nodes in the archaeal and bacterial clades; the topologies are thus identical for both trees.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evv121f3p"/></fig></p>
      <p>In nonvertebrate eukaryotes, differing bifurcating tree topologies are observed within chordates for species of the genus <italic>Ciona</italic> and <italic>Branchiostoma floridae</italic>, for the platyhelminth <italic>Schistosoma mansoni</italic>, for early divergence groups within ecdysozoans, for the metazoans <italic>Trichoplax adhaerens</italic> and <italic>Amphimedon queenslandica</italic>; within fungi for the ascomycetes <italic>Ashbya gossypii</italic>, <italic>Candida albicans</italic>, and <italic>Phaeosphaeria nodorum</italic>, and for the basidiomycete <italic>Puccinia graminis</italic>; within <italic>Viridiplantae</italic> for the <italic>rosids Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>, and within the genus <italic>Plasmodium</italic> for <italic>Plasmodium berghei</italic>. At deep nodes, incongruent phylogenies concern the groups <italic>Halvaria</italic>, <italic>AH/SAR</italic>, the recently suggested clade <italic>Neozoa</italic> (<italic>Unikonta</italic> and <italic>AH/SAR</italic>; <xref rid="evv121-B19" ref-type="bibr">He et al. 2014</xref>), and <italic>Excavata</italic>.</p>
      <p>As for prokaryotes, 27% (7/26, archaea: 50% [3/6], bacteria: 21% [4/19]) of the internal nodes are congruent, 38% (10/26, archaea: 50% [3/6], bacteria: 37% [7/19]) are congruent or compatible (multifurcating), and 62% (16/26, archaea: 50% [3/6], bacteria 63% [12/19]) are incongruent. At the deepest nodes in the ToL, all relevant species trees agree on the monophyly of bacteria, and that of archaea when rooted with bacteria. The representative group of archaeal QfO reference organisms include both crenarchaeotes and euryarchaeotes, and their monophyly is still disputed (<xref rid="evv121-B57" ref-type="bibr">Wolf et al. 2001</xref>). Noteworthy, the tree topology for five archaeal species common to Tol-C and the 16S rRNA species tree is congruent and in agreement with a recently published archaeal phylogeny based on over 200 marker genes (<xref rid="evv121-B40" ref-type="bibr">Petitjean et al. 2015</xref>). Consistent clades are observed within <italic>Archaea</italic> for the class <italic>Thermoprotei</italic> (<italic>Pyrobaculum aerophilum</italic>, <italic>Sulfolobus solfataricus</italic>) and the phylum <italic>Euryarchaeota</italic> (<italic>Halobacterium salinarum</italic>, <italic>Methanosarcina acetivorans</italic>, <italic>Methanocaldococcus jannaschii</italic>, <italic>Thermococcus kodakaraensis</italic>), within bacteria for the phylum <italic>Cyanobacteria</italic> (<italic>Gloeobacter violaceus</italic>, <italic>Synechocystis</italic> sp.), the order <italic>Actinomycetales</italic> (Mycobacterium tuberculosis, Streptomyces coelicolor), the class <italic>Gammaproteobacteria</italic> (<italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>), and the phylum <italic>Proteobacteria</italic> (<italic>Bradyrhizobium diazoefficiens</italic>, <italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens</italic>, and <italic>Gammaproteobacteria</italic>). Other nodes within prokaryotes are unresolved or conflicting.</p>
      <p>In summary, for the QfO reference organisms the topological congruence between species trees is more than 3-fold higher in the eukaryotic clade than in the bacterial clade. Discrepancies can be explained with tree reconstruction artifacts and differences in genome evolution. As HGT is prevalent in prokaryotes, inclusion of species or genes prominently subjected to it will heavily affect phylogeny (<xref rid="evv121-B52" ref-type="bibr">Trachana et al. 2014</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Consequences for Orthology Prediction and Benchmarking</title>
      <p>Needless to say, a resolved evolutionary species history would be preferable for orthology prediction and benchmarking. The largest nonconflicting and bifurcating tree generated from the six species trees would, however, only include 77 species at the most (ToL<sub>c</sub>-77; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv121/-/DC1">supplementary file S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv121/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Thus, we constructed a consensus tree composed of all 147 QfO reference organisms (ToL<sub>c</sub>-147) taking into consideration both the degree of topological incongruence and the branch support, if available. A large fraction of consistent nodes of the eukaryotic clade present in Tree-HC was significantly supported. For yet unresolved and inconsistent nodes, high quality phylogenetic studies were conducted from the literature, because clade-specific analyses commonly possess a higher species density, more marker genes, and less ambiguous or missing characters that originate from distantly related species. So far, all studies that have been taken into account concern eukaryotic clades: Primates (<xref rid="evv121-B12" ref-type="bibr">Fabre et al. 2009</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B42" ref-type="bibr">Pozzi et al. 2014</xref>), laurasiatherians (<xref rid="evv121-B60" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B42" ref-type="bibr">Pozzi et al. 2014</xref>), chordates (<xref rid="evv121-B8" ref-type="bibr">Delsuc et al. 2006</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B43" ref-type="bibr">Putnam et al. 2008</xref>), nonchordate metazoans (<xref rid="evv121-B17" ref-type="bibr">Halanych et al. 1995</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B50" ref-type="bibr">Telford et al. 2005</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B8" ref-type="bibr">Delsuc et al. 2006</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B10" ref-type="bibr">Dunn et al. 2008</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B49" ref-type="bibr">Srivastava et al. 2008</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B39" ref-type="bibr">Nosenko et al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B37" ref-type="bibr">Misof et al. 2014</xref>), choanozoans (<xref rid="evv121-B46" ref-type="bibr">Shalchian-Tabrizi et al. 2008</xref>), fungi (<xref rid="evv121-B11" ref-type="bibr">Ebersberger et al. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B35" ref-type="bibr">Medina et al. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B4" ref-type="bibr">Capella-Gutierrez et al. 2012</xref>), amoebozoans (<xref rid="evv121-B30" ref-type="bibr">Lahr et al. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B15" ref-type="bibr">Fiz-Palacios et al. 2013</xref>), plants (<xref rid="evv121-B54" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al. 2009</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B3" ref-type="bibr">Burleigh et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B59" ref-type="bibr">Zeng et al. 2014</xref>), halvarians (<xref rid="evv121-B47" ref-type="bibr">Simpson et al. 2006</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B29" ref-type="bibr">Krief et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B2" ref-type="bibr">Burki et al. 2012</xref>), and deep branches in eukaryotes (<xref rid="evv121-B47" ref-type="bibr">Simpson et al. 2006</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B18" ref-type="bibr">Hampl et al. 2009</xref>; <xref rid="evv121-B3" ref-type="bibr">Burleigh et al. 2010</xref>). In contrast to eukaryotes, the predicted evolutionary relationships for bacteria and archaea are too divergent to generate a possible bifurcating tree. Consequently, for the time being we retain the polytomy of the NCBI taxonomic classification. As a result, orthology prediction for these domains of life has to be complemented with non–tree-based methods for HGT prediction such as the analysis of codon usage or oligonucleotide profiles. The proposed species consensus tree ToL<sub>c</sub>-147 is presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evv121-F3">figure 3</xref> and available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://swisstree.vital-it.ch/species_tree">http://swisstree.vital-it.ch/species_tree</ext-link> (last accessed July 7, 2015). The assigned consistency values are annotated and can be used to multifurcate nodes at different levels of topological congruence between species trees.</p>
      <p>However, even if there were a bifurcating, resolved species tree, there could be a risk in oversimplifying the view on genome evolution. Assuming that the main gene stream—inherited genes with full-length orthology—reflects species evolution, each genome is likely to contain a fraction of genes which is discordant with any species tree. This can be because of horizontal/endosymbiont gene transfer and pseudo-orthologs in accurate gene trees, but it can also be because of the lack of phylogenetic signal and noise resulting from incomplete lineage sorting, gene conversion, changes in domain architectures, wrong gene models, sequence errors, and so on. As an illustration, a recent analysis of the evolution of 48 bird species and the genes encoded in their genomes revealed that no single gene tree was fully congruent with the reconstructed species phylogeny (<xref rid="evv121-B26" ref-type="bibr">Jarvis et al. 2014</xref>). In a group of closely related vertebrate species where the role of HGT is negligible, such a result indicates that both incomplete lineage sorting and stochastic noise can create widespread discordance between gene trees and species trees. The intentional exploration of this nonsupporting gene fraction might provide advanced insight into genome and species evolution. Consequently, it is worthwhile reflecting the reliability of predicted gene relationships by means of confidence scores which allow experiment-specific data selection by database users. In addition, confidence scores could be used for improved orthology benchmarking, accounting for the sensitivity/specificity trade-off.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Assessment of Gene Tree Support for Species Tree Topologies</title>
      <p>To assess the level of discordance between the different species trees and the individual gene trees, we compared each species tree node with 458,108 gene phylogenies built for proteins encoded in 65 QfO reference species (<xref rid="evv121-B21" ref-type="bibr">Huerta-Cepas, Capella-Gutierrez, et al. 2014</xref>). This analysis was performed on ToL<sub>c</sub>-147 as well as on each species tree. By analyzing results according to the assigned consistency levels, we show that gene tree topologies coincide more often with consistent nodes (consistency levels L90 and L70) in species trees than with conflicting ones (consistency levels L10, L30, and L50) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evv121-F4">fig. 4</xref>). This trend is also observed in the individual box plots for each project (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv121/-/DC1">supplementary file S3</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv121/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Interestingly, species trees which differ from the consensus tree (hereafter named “alternative species topologies” and assigned category “AT” for practical reasons) occur as the most dispersed group. The range of its gene tree support values corresponds to that determined for incongruent nodes. In fact, category AT includes many prokaryotic speciation nodes which are still polytomous in ToL<sub>c</sub>-147 because of incongruent topologies in the species trees, thus explaining the comparatively tall box plot. Even when assuming ToL<sub>c</sub>-147 to present the true tree, gene trees congruent with alternative species topologies can be correct, for instance, when containing xenologs or pseudo-orthologs. ToL<sub>c</sub>-147 with annotated gene tree support is presented in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv121/-/DC1">supplementary file S4</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv121/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online.
<fig id="evv121-F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>F<sc>ig</sc>. 4.—</label><caption><p>Box plot of gene tree fractions supporting species tree topologies at different consistency levels. Consistent species tree topologies with (L90) and without (L70) significant branch support are generally in compliance with the analyzed gene trees. The fraction of supporting gene trees drops considerably when species tree topologies are incongruent, once or more, between the species trees (L10, L30, L50). Consistency categories “L30” and AT were assigned for practical reasons. Level L30 is the default value for conflicting nodes prior to evaluation, and the two remaining nodes (<italic>Excavata</italic>, <italic>Proteobacteria</italic>) show on the one hand conflicting species topologies, on the other hand significant branch support in at least one of the species trees. Only a low fraction of our gene trees supports these speciation nodes. Category AT indicates alternative topologies suggested by the species trees, and results cover the range of conflicting levels (L10, L50); this makes sense because alternative topologies are incongruent with the consensus tree and between species trees. For each box plot, bottom of the box is the first quartile (Q1), top of the box is the third quartile (Q3), the middle bar is the median, whiskers represent the 1.5 interquartile range (IQR).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evv121f4p"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="conclusions">
    <title>Conclusions</title>
    <p>This study sheds light on the current resolution of the species phylogeny for the 147 QfO reference proteomes. Open questions concern not only the true species tree, but likewise which type of phylogenetic signal is most informative for tree reconstruction at a particular level of depth and taxonomic range. As for sequence-based phylogenetic analysis, the selection of good marker genes and a higher and balanced species density in the tree space may help to stabilize the tree topology. A comparison of species trees obtained from the analysis of different types of characters, including morphological ones, can help to identify strengths and weakness of each approach in order to optimize species tree inference. Other issues worthwhile discussing between expert communities include taxon sampling and visualization of annotated evolutionary changes which result in the characteristics of extant species at any level of organization. We hope that this work will contribute to a lively exchange between the QfO and ToL communities.</p>
    <p>For orthology benchmarking, we propose a species consensus tree with conservation values associated to each node for multifurcation at the desired consistency level. We provide here the first version of one such reference tree covering the QfO reference species.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv121/-/DC1">Supplementary tables S1–S3</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv121/-/DC1">supplementary files S1–S4</ext-link> are available at Genome Biology and Evolution online (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gbe.oxfordjournals.org/">http://www.gbe.oxfordjournals.org/</ext-link>).</p>
    <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
      <caption>
        <title>Supplementary Data</title>
      </caption>
      <media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_7_7_1988__index.html"/>
      <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="x-zip-compressed" xlink:href="supp_evv121_suppl_data.zip"/>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack>
    <title>Acknowledgments</title>
    <p>The authors wish to thank Vivienne Baillie Gerritsen for proofreading. This work was supported by the <funding-source>Swiss Federal Government through the Federal Office of Education and Science (B.B.)</funding-source>. Funding for open access charge: <funding-source>Swiss Institute of Bioinformatics</funding-source>. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. T.G. group research is funded in part by a grant from the Spanish ministry of Economy and Competitiveness (BIO2012-37161), a Grant from the <funding-source>Qatar National Research Fund</funding-source> (<award-id>NPRP 5-298-3-086</award-id>), and a grant from the <funding-source>European Research Council under the European Union’s Seventh Framework Programme</funding-source> (<award-id>FP/2007-2013</award-id>)/ERC (grant agreement no. <award-id>ERC-2012-StG-310325</award-id>). M.M. acknowledges support from the Wellcome Trust (grant number <award-id>WT095908</award-id>) and the <funding-source>European Molecular Biology Laboratory</funding-source>.</p>
  </ack>
  <ref-list>
    <title>Literature Cited</title>
    <ref id="evv121-B1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bapteste</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Boucher</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Leigh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Doolittle</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Phylogenetic reconstruction and lateral gene transfer</article-title>. <source>Trends Microbiol.</source><volume>12</volume>:<fpage>406</fpage>–<lpage>411</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15337161</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burki</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pombert</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>The evolutionary history of haptophytes and cryptophytes: phylogenomic evidence for separate origins</article-title>. <source>Proc Biol Sci.</source><volume>279</volume>:<fpage>2246</fpage>–<lpage>2254</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22298847</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burleigh</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Genome-scale phylogenetics: inferring the plant tree of life from 18,896 gene trees</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol.</source><volume>60</volume>:<fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21186249</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Capella-Gutierrez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcet-Houben</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabaldon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Phylogenomics supports microsporidia as the earliest diverging clade of sequenced fungi</article-title>. <source>BMC Biol.</source><volume>10</volume>:<fpage>47</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22651672</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Case</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Use of 16S rRNA and rpoB genes as molecular markers for microbial ecology studies</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol.</source><volume>73</volume>:<fpage>278</fpage>–<lpage>288</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17071787</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ciccarelli</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Toward automatic reconstruction of a highly resolved tree of life</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>311</volume>:<fpage>1283</fpage>–<lpage>1287</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16513982</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Creevey</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Doerks</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Raes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Universally distributed single-copy genes indicate a constant rate of horizontal transfer</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e22099</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21850220</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B8">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delsuc</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Brinkmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chourrout</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Philippe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Tunicates and not cephalochordates are the closest living relatives of vertebrates</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>439</volume>:<fpage>965</fpage>–<lpage>968</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16495997</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B9">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dessimoz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabaldon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonnhammer</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrero</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Toward community standards in the quest for orthologs</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>28</volume>:<fpage>900</fpage>–<lpage>904</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22332236</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B10">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Broad phylogenomic sampling improves resolution of the animal tree of life</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>452</volume>:<fpage>745</fpage>–<lpage>749</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18322464</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B11">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ebersberger</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>A consistent phylogenetic backbone for the fungi</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol.</source><volume>29</volume>:<fpage>1319</fpage>–<lpage>1334</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22114356</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B12">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fabre</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Douzery</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Patterns of macroevolution among Primates inferred from a supermatrix of mitochondrial and nuclear DNA</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol.</source><volume>53</volume>:<fpage>808</fpage>–<lpage>825</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19682589</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B13">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>A daily-updated tree of (sequenced) life as a reference for genome research</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep.</source><volume>3</volume>:<fpage>2015</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23778980</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B14">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Federhen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>The NCBI taxonomy database</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>40</volume>:<fpage>D136</fpage>–<lpage>D143</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22139910</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B15">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fiz-Palacios</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>Did terrestrial diversification of amoebas (amoebozoa) occur in synchrony with land plants?</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e74374</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24040233</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B16">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gabaldon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Joining forces in the quest for orthologs</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol.</source><volume>10</volume>:<fpage>403</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19785718</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B17">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halanych</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Evidence from 18S ribosomal DNA that the lophophorates are protostome animals</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>267</volume>:<fpage>1641</fpage>–<lpage>1643</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7886451</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B18">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hampl</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Phylogenomic analyses support the monophyly of Excavata and resolve relationships among eukaryotic “supergroups”</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</source><volume>106</volume>:<fpage>3859</fpage>–<lpage>3864</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19237557</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B19">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>An alternative root for the eukaryote tree of life</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol.</source><volume>24</volume>:<fpage>465</fpage>–<lpage>470</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24508168</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B20">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedtke</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillis</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Taxon sampling and the accuracy of phylogenetic analyses</article-title>. <source>J Syst Evol.</source><volume>46</volume>:<fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>257</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B21">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huerta-Cepas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Capella-Gutierrez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pryszcz</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcet-Houben</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabaldon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>PhylomeDB v4: zooming into the plurality of evolutionary histories of a genome</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>42</volume>:<fpage>D897</fpage>–<lpage>D902</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24275491</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B22">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huerta-Cepas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dopazo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dopazo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabaldon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>The human phylome</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol.</source><volume>8</volume>:<fpage>R109</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17567924</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B23">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huerta-Cepas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dopazo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabaldon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>ETE: a python Environment for Tree Exploration</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><volume>11</volume>:<fpage>24</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20070885</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B24">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huerta-Cepas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcet-Houben</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabaldon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>A nested phylogenetic reconstruction approach provides scalable resolution in the eukaryotic Tree Of Life</article-title>. <source>PeerJ PrePrints</source><volume>2</volume>:<fpage>223</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B25">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huson</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Dezulian</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Klopper</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Steel</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Phylogenetic super-networks from partial trees</article-title>. <source>IEEE/ACM Trans Comput Biol Bioinform</source><volume>1</volume>:<fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>158</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17051697</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B26">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Whole-genome analyses resolve early branches in the tree of life of modern birds</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>346</volume>:<fpage>1320</fpage>–<lpage>1331</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25504713</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B27">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Junier</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zdobnov</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>The Newick utilities: high-throughput phylogenetic tree processing in the UNIX shell</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>26</volume>:<fpage>1669</fpage>–<lpage>1670</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20472542</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B28">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koonin</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Makarova</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Aravind</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Horizontal gene transfer in prokaryotes: quantification and classification</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Microbiol.</source><volume>55</volume>:<fpage>709</fpage>–<lpage>742</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11544372</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B29">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krief</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>On the diversity of malaria parasites in African apes and the origin of <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> from Bonobos</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog.</source><volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e1000765</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20169187</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B30">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lahr</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Comprehensive phylogenetic reconstruction of amoebozoa based on concatenated analyses of SSU-rDNA and actin genes</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e22780</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21829512</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B31">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Darling</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>Phylogeny of bacterial and archaeal genomes using conserved genes: supertrees and supermatrices</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e62510</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23638103</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B32">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Moret</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>A metric for phylogenetic trees based on matching</article-title>. <source>IEEE/ACM Trans Comput Biol Bioinform.</source><volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1014</fpage>–<lpage>1022</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22184263</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B33">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marcet-Houben</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabaldon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>TreeKO: a duplication-aware algorithm for the comparison of phylogenetic trees</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>39</volume>:<fpage>e66</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21335609</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B34">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McDaniel</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>High frequency of horizontal gene transfer in the oceans</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>330</volume>:<fpage>50</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20929803</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B35">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Reconstructing the fungal tree of life using phylogenomics and a preliminary investigation of the distribution of yeast prion-like proteins in the fungal kingdom</article-title>. <source>J Mol Evol.</source><volume>73</volume>:<fpage>116</fpage>–<lpage>133</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21938499</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B36">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mende</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunagawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeller</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>Accurate and universal delineation of prokaryotic species</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods.</source><volume>10</volume>:<fpage>881</fpage>–<lpage>884</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23892899</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B37">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Misof</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Phylogenomics resolves the timing and pattern of insect evolution</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>346</volume>:<fpage>763</fpage>–<lpage>767</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25378627</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B38">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Munoz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Release LTPs104 of the All-Species Living Tree</article-title>. <source>Syst Appl Microbiol.</source><volume>34</volume>:<fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>170</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21497273</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B39">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nosenko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>Deep metazoan phylogeny: when different genes tell different stories</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol.</source><volume>67</volume>:<fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>233</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23353073</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B40">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petitjean</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Deschamps</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez-Garcia</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Brochier-Armanet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>Extending the conserved phylogenetic core of archaea disentangles the evolution of the third domain of life</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol.</source><volume>32</volume>:<fpage>1242</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25660375</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B41">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Philippe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Early-branching or fast-evolving eukaryotes? An answer based on slowly evolving positions</article-title>. <source>Proc Biol Sci.</source><volume>267</volume>:<fpage>1213</fpage>–<lpage>1221</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10902687</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B42">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pozzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Primate phylogenetic relationships and divergence dates inferred from complete mitochondrial genomes</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol.</source><volume>75</volume>:<fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>183</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24583291</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B43">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Putnam</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>The amphioxus genome and the evolution of the chordate karyotype</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>453</volume>:<fpage>1064</fpage>–<lpage>1071</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18563158</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B44">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Foulds</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name></person-group><year>1981</year><article-title>Comparison of phylogenetic trees</article-title>. <source>Math Biosci.</source><volume>53</volume>:<fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>147</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B45">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schulmeister</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Inconsistency of maximum parsimony revisited</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol.</source><volume>53</volume>:<fpage>521</fpage>–<lpage>528</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15371243</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B46">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shalchian-Tabrizi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Multigene phylogeny of choanozoa and the origin of animals</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>3</volume>:<fpage>e2098</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18461162</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B47">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Inagaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Roger</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Comprehensive multigene phylogenies of excavate protists reveal the evolutionary positions of “primitive” eukaryotes</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol.</source><volume>23</volume>:<fpage>615</fpage>–<lpage>625</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16308337</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B48">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sonnhammer</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Big data and other challenges in the quest for orthologs</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>30</volume>:<fpage>2993</fpage>–<lpage>2998</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25064571</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B49">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>The Trichoplax genome and the nature of placozoans</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>454</volume>:<fpage>955</fpage>–<lpage>960</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18719581</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B50">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Telford</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gowri-Shankar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Consideration of RNA secondary structure significantly improves likelihood-based estimates of phylogeny: examples from the bilateria</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol.</source><volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1129</fpage>–<lpage>1136</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15689526</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B51">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trachana</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Orthology prediction methods: a quality assessment using curated protein families</article-title>. <source>Bioessays</source><volume>33</volume>:<fpage>769</fpage>–<lpage>780</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21853451</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B52">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trachana</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>A phylogeny-based benchmarking test for orthology inference reveals the limitations of function-based validation</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e111122</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25369365</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B53">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Treangen</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Horizontal transfer, not duplication, drives the expansion of protein families in prokaryotes</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet.</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e1001284</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21298028</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B54">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Rosid radiation and the rapid rise of angiosperm-dominated forests</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</source><volume>106</volume>:<fpage>3853</fpage>–<lpage>3858</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19223592</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B55">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Molecular phylogenetics: state-of-the-art methods for looking into the past</article-title>. <source>Trends Genet.</source><volume>17</volume>:<fpage>262</fpage>–<lpage>272</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11335036</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B56">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woese</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group><year>1977</year><article-title>Phylogenetic structure of the prokaryotic domain: the primary kingdoms</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</source><volume>74</volume>:<fpage>5088</fpage>–<lpage>5090</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">270744</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B57">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogozin</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name><name><surname>Grishin</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatusov</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Koonin</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Genome trees constructed using five different approaches suggest new major bacterial clades</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol.</source><volume>1</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11734060</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B58">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>The SILVA and “All-species Living Tree Project (LTP)” taxonomic frameworks</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>42</volume>:<fpage>D643</fpage>–<lpage>D648</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24293649</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B59">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Resolution of deep angiosperm phylogeny using conserved nuclear genes and estimates of early divergence times</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun.</source><volume>5</volume>:<fpage>4956</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25249442</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="evv121-B60">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Phylogenomic analysis resolves the interordinal relationships and rapid diversification of the laurasiatherian mammals</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol.</source><volume>61</volume>:<fpage>150</fpage>–<lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21900649</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
