<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">bioinfo</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1367-4803</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1367-4811</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4542784</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26072512</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv262</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">btv262</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Ismb/Eccb 2015 Proceedings Papers Committee July 10 to July 14, 2015, Dublin, Ireland</subject>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Genes</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>Misassembly detection using paired-end sequence reads and optical mapping data</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Muggli</surname>
          <given-names>Martin D.</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btv262-AFF1">
          <sup>1</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="btv262-COR1">*</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Puglisi</surname>
          <given-names>Simon J.</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btv262-AFF1">
          <sup>2</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Ronen</surname>
          <given-names>Roy</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btv262-AFF1">
          <sup>3</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Boucher</surname>
          <given-names>Christina</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btv262-AFF1">
          <sup>1</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="btv262-AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Computer Science, Colorado State University, Fort Collins, CO 80526, USA, <sup>2</sup>Department of Computer Science, University of Helsinki, Finland and <sup>3</sup>Bioinformatics Graduate Program, University of California, San Diego, La Jolla, CA 92093, USA</aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="btv262-COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed.</corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
      <day>15</day>
      <month>6</month>
      <year>2015</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>10</day>
      <month>6</month>
      <year>2015</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>10</day>
      <month>6</month>
      <year>2015</year>
    </pub-date>
    <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
    <volume>31</volume>
    <issue>12</issue>
    <fpage>i80</fpage>
    <lpage>i88</lpage>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
      <license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License(<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</uri>),which permits non-commercial reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract>
      <p><bold>Motivation:</bold> A crucial problem in genome assembly is the discovery and correction of misassembly errors in draft genomes. We develop a method called <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> that enhances the quality of draft genomes by identifying misassembly errors and their breakpoints using paired-end sequence reads and optical mapping data. Our method also fulfills the critical need for open source computational methods for analyzing optical mapping data. We apply our method to various assemblies of the loblolly pine, <italic>Francisella tularensis</italic>, rice and budgerigar genomes. We generated and used stimulated optical mapping data for loblolly pine and <italic>F.tularensis</italic> and used real optical mapping data for rice and budgerigar.</p>
      <p><bold>Results:</bold> Our results demonstrate that we detect more than 54% of extensively misassembled contigs and more than 60% of locally misassembled contigs in assemblies of <italic>F.tularensis</italic> and between 31% and 100% of extensively misassembled contigs and between 57% and 73% of locally misassembled contigs in assemblies of loblolly pine. Using the real optical mapping data, we correctly identified 75% of extensively misassembled contigs and 100% of locally misassembled contigs in rice, and 77% of extensively misassembled contigs and 80% of locally misassembled contigs in budgerigar.</p>
      <p><bold>Availability and implementation:</bold><sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> can be used as a post-processing step in combination with any genome assembler and is freely available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cs.colostate.edu/seq/">http://www.cs.colostate.edu/seq/</ext-link>.</p>
      <p>
        <bold>Contact:</bold>
        <email>muggli@cs.colostate.edu</email>
      </p>
      <p><bold>Supplementary information:</bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btv262/-/DC1">Supplementary data</ext-link> are available at <italic>Bioinformatics</italic> online.</p>
    </abstract>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="9"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec>
    <title>1 Introduction</title>
    <p>Comparing genetic variation between and within a species is a fundamental activity in biological research. For example, there is currently a major effort to sequence entire genomes of agriculturally important plant species to identify parts of the genome variable in a given breeding program and, ultimately, create superior plant varieties. Robust genome assembly methods are imperative to these large sequencing initiatives and other scientific projects (<xref rid="btv262-B17" ref-type="bibr">Haussler <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref rid="btv262-B37" ref-type="bibr">Ossowski <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref rid="btv262-B44" ref-type="bibr">Robinson <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref rid="btv262-B53" ref-type="bibr">Turnbaugh <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>) because scientific analyses frequently use those genomes to determine genetic variation and associated biological traits.</p>
    <p>At present, the majority of assembly programs are based on the Eulerian assembly paradigm (<xref rid="btv262-B21" ref-type="bibr">Idury and Waterman 1995</xref>; <xref rid="btv262-B39" ref-type="bibr">Pevzner <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>), where a de Bruijn graph is constructed with a vertex <italic>v</italic> for every <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM1"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>-mer present in a set of reads and an edge <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM2"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for every observed <italic>k</italic>-mer in the reads with <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM3"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>-mer prefix <italic>v</italic> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM4"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>-mer suffix <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM5"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. A contig corresponds to a non-branching path through this graph. We refer the reader to <xref rid="btv262-B10" ref-type="bibr">Compeau <italic>et al.</italic> (2011)</xref> for a more thorough explanation of de Bruijn graphs and their use in assembly. SPAdes (<xref rid="btv262-B3" ref-type="bibr">Bankevich <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>), IDBA (<xref rid="btv262-B38" ref-type="bibr">Peng <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>), Euler-SR (<xref rid="btv262-B6" ref-type="bibr">Chaisson and Pevzner 2008</xref>), Velvet (<xref rid="btv262-B56" ref-type="bibr">Zerbino and Birney 2008</xref>), SOAPdenovo (<xref rid="btv262-B29" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>), ABySS (<xref rid="btv262-B49" ref-type="bibr">Simpson <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>) and ALLPATHS (<xref rid="btv262-B5" ref-type="bibr">Butler <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>) all use this paradigm and follow the same general outline: extract <italic>k</italic>-mers from the reads, construct a de Bruijn graph from the set <italic>k</italic>-mers, simplify the graph and construct contigs.</p>
    <p>One crucial problem that persists in Eulerian assembly (and genome assembly, in general) is the discovery and correction of misassembly errors in draft genomes. We define a <italic>misassembly error</italic> as an assembled region that contains a significantly large insertion, deletion, inversion, or rearrangement that is the result of decisions made by the assembly program. Identification of misassembly errors is important because true biological variations manifest in similar ways, and thus, these errors can be easily misconstrued as true genetic variation (<xref rid="btv262-B46" ref-type="bibr">Salzberg 2005</xref>). This can mislead a range of genomic analyses. We note that the exact definition of a misassembly error can vary and adopt the standard definition used by QUAST (<xref rid="btv262-B16" ref-type="bibr">Gurevich <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>) and other tools. See Section 3.1 for this exact definition. Once the existence and location of a misassembly are identified, it can be removed by segmenting the contig at that location.</p>
    <p>We present a computational method for identifying misassembly errors using a combination of short reads and optical mapping data. Optical mapping is a system developed in 1993 (<xref rid="btv262-B48" ref-type="bibr">Schwartz <italic>et al.</italic> 1993</xref>) that can construct ordered, genome-wide, high-resolution restriction maps. The system works as follows (<xref rid="btv262-B2" ref-type="bibr">Aston and Schwartz 2006</xref>; <xref rid="btv262-B11" ref-type="bibr">Dimalanta <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>): an ensemble of DNA molecules adhered to a charged glass plate is elongated by fluid flow. An enzyme is then used to cleave them into fragments at loci where the corresponding recognition sequence occurs. Next, the fragments are highlighted with fluorescent dye and imaged under a microscope. Finally, these images are analyzed to estimate the fragment sizes, producing a molecular map. Since the fragments stay relatively stationary during the aforementioned process, the images capture their relative order and size (<xref rid="btv262-B36" ref-type="bibr">Neely <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Multiple copies of the genome undergo this process, and a consensus map is formed that consists of an ordered sequence of fragment sizes, each indicating the approximate number of bases between occurrences of the recognition sequence in the genome (<xref rid="btv262-B1" ref-type="bibr">Anantharaman and Mishra 2001</xref>).</p>
    <p>Although optical mapping data have been used for discerning structural variation in the human genome (<xref rid="btv262-B50" ref-type="bibr">Teague <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>) and for scaffolding and validating contigs for several large sequencing projects—including those for various prokaryote species (<xref rid="btv262-B42" ref-type="bibr">Reslewic <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref rid="btv262-B57" ref-type="bibr">Zhou <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>, <xref rid="btv262-B58" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>), rice (<xref rid="btv262-B59" ref-type="bibr">Zhou <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>), maize (<xref rid="btv262-B60" ref-type="bibr">Zhou <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>), mouse (<xref rid="btv262-B9" ref-type="bibr">Church <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>), goat (<xref rid="btv262-B12" ref-type="bibr">Dong <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>), parrot (<xref rid="btv262-B18" ref-type="bibr">Howard <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>) and <italic>Amborella trichopoda</italic> (<xref rid="btv262-B7" ref-type="bibr">Chamala <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>)—there are no publicly available tools for using this data for misassembly detection using short read and optical mapping data. In 2014, <xref rid="btv262-B31" ref-type="bibr">Mendelowitz and Pop (2014)</xref> further this point stating that ‘There is, thus, a critical need for the continued development and public release of software tools for processing optical mapping data, mirroring the tremendous advances made in analytical methods for second- and third-generation sequencing data’.</p>
    <p>Our tool, which we call sc&gt;/sc&gt;, predicts which contigs are misassembled and the approximate locations of the errors in the contigs. It takes as input the paired-end sequence read data, contigs, an ensemble of optical maps and the restriction enzymes used to construct the optical maps. <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> first uses the paired-end read data to divide the contigs into two sets: those that are predicted to be correctly assembled and those that are not. Then the set of contigs that are candidates for containing misassembly errors are further divided into misassembled contigs and correctly assembled contigs using optical mapping data. Fundamental to the first step is the concept of a <italic>red</italic><italic>–</italic><italic>black positional de Bruijn graph</italic>, which encapsulates recurring artifacts in the alignment of the sequence read data to the contigs and their position in the contig. The red vertices in this graph indicate if a contig is likely to be misassembled and also flag the location where the misassembly error occurs. These locations are called <italic>misassembly breakpoints</italic>.</p>
    <p>In the second stage of <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> where optical mapping data are used, the contigs conjectured to be misassembled are <italic>in silico</italic> digested with the set of input restriction enzymes and aligned to the optical map using Twin (<xref rid="btv262-B33" ref-type="bibr">Muggli <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). Based on the presence or absence of alignment, a prediction of misassembly is made. The <italic>in silico</italic> digestion process computationally mimics how each restriction enzyme would cleave the segment of DNA defined by the contig, returning ‘mini-optical maps’ that can be aligned to the optical map for the whole genome. An important aspect of our work is that it highlights the need to use another source of information, which is independent of the sequence data but representative of the same genome, to identify misassembly errors. We show that optical mapping data can be used as this information source.</p>
    <p>We give results for the <italic>Francisella tularensis</italic>, loblolly pine, rice and budgerigar genomes. Each genome was assembled using various de Bruijn graph assemblers, and then misassembly errors were predicted. We present results for both real and simulated optical mapping data; simulated data were generated for the <italic>F</italic><italic>.</italic><italic>tularensis</italic> and loblolly pine genomes, and real optical mapping data for the rice and budgerigar genomes. Our results on <italic>F</italic><italic>.</italic><italic>tularensis</italic> show that <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> correctly identifies (on average) 86% and 80% of locally and extensively misassembled contigs, respectively. This is a considerable improvement on existing methods, which identified (on average) 26% and 16% of locally and extensively misassembled contigs, respectively, in the same assemblies. The results on the loblolly pine genome assemblies show similar improvement. Out of the 499 extensively and 3 locally misassembled contigs in the SOAPdenovo assembly of rice, <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> correctly identified 374 (75%) and 3 (100%) of them, respectively. Competing methods identified between 25% and 30% of these extensively misassembled contigs, and none of these locally misassembled contigs. Lastly, we downloaded the latest Illumina-454 hybrid assembly of budgerigar that was released by <xref rid="btv262-B18" ref-type="bibr">Ganapathy <italic>et al.</italic> (2014)</xref>, and predicted misassembly errors using the accompanied Illumina paired-end data and optical mapping data. <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> correctly identified 10 777 of the 13 996 extensively misassembled contigs (77%) and 2350 (out of 2937) locally misassembled contigs (80%). Hence, we tested our method across four different genomes, which all vary in size and GC content.</p>
    <p>Our conclusions, based on these experimental results, are that the specificity of <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> significantly increases by incorporating optical mapping data into the prediction of misassembly errors, and the sensitivity of <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> is substantially better in comparison to competing methods that just use paired-end data. Therefore, we show evidence that optical mapping data can be a powerful tool for misassembly identification.</p>
    <sec id="SEC1.1">
      <title>1.1 Related work</title>
      <p>Amosvalidate (<xref rid="btv262-B41" ref-type="bibr">Phillippy <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>), REAPR (<xref rid="btv262-B20" ref-type="bibr">Hunt <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>) and Pilon (<xref rid="btv262-B54" ref-type="bibr">Walker <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>) are capable of identifying and correcting misassembly errors. REAPR is designed to use both short insert and long insert paired-end sequencing libraries; however, it can operate with only one of these types of sequencing data. Amosvalidate, which is included as part of the AMOS assembly package (<xref rid="btv262-B52" ref-type="bibr">Treangen <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), was developed specifically for first generation sequencing libraries (<xref rid="btv262-B41" ref-type="bibr">Phillippy <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). iMetAMOS (<xref rid="btv262-B27" ref-type="bibr">Koren <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>) is an automated assembly pipeline that provides error correction and validation of the assembly. It packages several open-source tools and provides annotated assemblies that result from an ensemble of tools and assemblers. Currently, it uses REAPR for misassembly error correction. Pilon (<xref rid="btv262-B54" ref-type="bibr">Walker <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>) detects a variety (including misassembly) of errors in draft genomes and variant detection. Similar to REAPR, Pilon is specifically designed to use short insert and long insert libraries but unlike REAPR and amosvalidate, it is specifically designed for microbial genomes.</p>
      <p>Many optical mapping tools exist and deserve mentioning, including AGORA (<xref rid="btv262-B30" ref-type="bibr">Lin <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>), SOMA (<xref rid="btv262-B34" ref-type="bibr">Nagarajan <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>) and Twin (<xref rid="btv262-B33" ref-type="bibr">Muggli <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). AGORA (<xref rid="btv262-B30" ref-type="bibr">Lin <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>) uses the optical map information to constrain de Bruijn graph construction with the aim of improving the resulting assembly. SOMA (<xref rid="btv262-B34" ref-type="bibr">Nagarajan <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>) uses dynamic programming to align <italic>in silico</italic><italic>-</italic>digested contigs to an optical map. Twin (<xref rid="btv262-B33" ref-type="bibr">Muggli <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>) is an index-based method for aligning contigs to an optical map. Because of its use of an index data structure, it is capable of aligning <italic>in silico</italic>-digested contigs orders of magnitude faster than competing methods. <xref rid="btv262-B55" ref-type="bibr">Xavier <italic>et al.</italic> (2014)</xref> demonstrated misassembly errors in bacterial genomes can be detected using proprietary software.</p>
      <p>Lastly, there are special purpose tools that have some relation to <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> in their algorithmic approach. Numerous assembly tools use a finishing process after assembly, including Hapsembler (<xref rid="btv262-B13" ref-type="bibr">Donmez and Brudno 2011</xref>), LOCAS (<xref rid="btv262-B26" ref-type="bibr">Klein <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), Meraculous (<xref rid="btv262-B8" ref-type="bibr">Chapman <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>) and the ‘assisted assembly’ algorithm (<xref rid="btv262-B15" ref-type="bibr">Gnerre <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Hapsembler (<xref rid="btv262-B13" ref-type="bibr">Donmez and Brudno 2011</xref>) is a haplotype-specific genome assembly toolkit that is designed for genomes that are highly polymorphic. RACA (<xref rid="btv262-B25" ref-type="bibr">Kim <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>) and SCARPA (<xref rid="btv262-B14" ref-type="bibr">Donmez and Brudno 2013</xref>) are two scaffolding algorithms that perform paired-end alignment to the contigs as an initial step and, thus, are similar to our algorithm in that respect.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>2 Methods</title>
    <p><sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> can be broken down into four main steps: recruitment of reads to contigs, construction of the red–black positional de Bruijn graph, misassembly error prediction and misassembly verification using optical mapping data. We explain each of these steps in detail in the following subsections.</p>
    <sec id="SEC2.1">
      <title>2.1 Recruitment of reads and threshold calculation</title>
      <p><sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> first aligns reads to contigs to identify regions that contain abnormal read alignments. Collapsed or expanded repeats will present as the read coverage being greater or lower than the expected genome coverage in the region that has been misassembled. Similarly, inversion and rearrangement errors will present as the alignment of the mate-pairs being rearranged. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="btv262-F1">Figure 1</xref> illustrates these concordant and discordant read alignments. More specifically, this step consists of aligning all the (paired-end) reads to all the contigs and then calculating three thresholds, Δ<italic><sub>L</sub></italic>, Δ<italic><sub>U</sub></italic> and Γ. The range <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM6"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> defines the acceptable read depth, and Γ defines the maximum allowable number of reads whose mate-pair aligns in an inverted orientation. To calculate these thresholds, we consider all alignments of each read as opposed to just the best alignment of each read since misassembly errors frequently occur within repetitive regions where the reads will align to multiple locations. <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> performs this step using BWA (version 0.5.9) in paired-end mode with default parameters (<xref rid="btv262-B28" ref-type="bibr">Li and Durbin 2009</xref>). Subsequently, after alignment, each contig is treated as a series of consecutive 200-bp regions. These are sampled uniformly at random <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM7"><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> times, and the mean (µ<italic><sub>d</sub></italic>) and the standard deviation (σ<italic><sub>d</sub></italic>) of the read depth and the mean (µ<italic><sub>i</sub></italic>) and the standard deviation (σ<italic><sub>i</sub></italic>) of the number of alignments where a discordant mate-pair orientation is witnessed are calculated from these sampled regions. Δ<italic><sub>L</sub></italic> is set to the maximum of <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM8"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>µ</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, Δ<italic><sub>U</sub></italic> is set to <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM9"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>µ</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and Γ is set to <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM10"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo>µ</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The default for <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM11"><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM12"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mn>20</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>th of the contig length, and this parameter can be changed in the input to <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc>.
<fig id="btv262-F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>An illustration about the systematic alterations that occur with rearrangements, inversions, collapsed repeats and expanded repeats. (<bold>a</bold>) Proper read alignment where mate-pair reads have the correct orientation and distance from each other. A rearrangement or inversion will present itself by the orientation of the reads being incorrect and/or the distance of the mate-pairs being significantly smaller or significantly larger than the expected insert size. This is shown in (<bold>b</bold>) and (<bold>c</bold>), respectively. (<bold>d</bold>) The proper read depth, which is uniform across the genome. (<bold>e</bold>) A collapsed repeat, which results in the read depth being greater than expected. (<bold>f</bold>) A expanded repeat, which results in the read depth being lower than expected</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="btv262f1p"/></fig>
<fig id="btv262-F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>An example illustrating the red black positional de Bruijn graph (<inline-formula><mml:math id="MM13"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), the positional de Bruijn graph and the de Bruijn graph on a set of aligned reads, with their corresponding sets of <italic>k</italic>-mers and positional <italic>k</italic>-mers. There exists a region in the genome that extremely high coverage, which would suggest a possible misassembly error. Namely, the positional <italic>k</italic>-mers (GCCA, 111), (CCAT, 112) and (CATT, 113) have multiplicity 10, whereas all other positional <italic>k</italic>-mers have multiplicity 5. In the de Bruijn graph where the position is not taken into account, all <italic>k</italic>-mers have multiplicity of 10 and there is no evidence of a misassembled region. We note that in this example no vertex gluing operations occur but in more complex instances, vertex gluing will occur when equal <italic>k</italic>-mers align at adjacent positions</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="btv262f2p"/></fig>
</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2.2">
      <title>2.2 Construction of the red–black positional de Bruijn graph</title>
      <p>After threshold calculation, the red–black positional de Bruijn graph is constructed. For clarity, we begin by describing the <italic>positional de Bruijn graph</italic>, given by <xref rid="btv262-B45" ref-type="bibr">Ronen <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref> and then define the red–black positional de Bruijn graph. Although the edges in the traditional de Bruijn graph correspond to <italic>k</italic>-mers, the edges in the positional de Bruijn graph correspond to <italic>k</italic>-mers and their inferred positions on the contigs (<italic>positional k-mers</italic>). Hence, the positional de Bruijn graph <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM14"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>Φ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is defined for a multiset of positional <italic>k</italic>-mers and parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM15"><mml:mi>Φ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and is constructed in a similar manner to the traditional de Bruijn graph using an A-Bruijn graph framework from (<xref rid="btv262-B40" ref-type="bibr">Pevzner <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). Given a <italic>k</italic>-mer <italic>s<sub>k</sub></italic>, let <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM16"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">prefix</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> be the first <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM17"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> nucleotides of <italic>s<sub>k</sub></italic>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM18"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">suffix</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> be the last <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM19"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> nucleotides of <italic>s<sub>k</sub></italic>. Each positional <italic>k</italic>-mer <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM20"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in the input multiset corresponds to a directed edge in the graph between two positional <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM21"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>-mers, <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM22"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">prefix</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM23"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">suffix</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. After all edges are formed, the graph undergoes a gluing operation. A pair of positional <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM24"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>-mers, <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM25"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM26"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, are glued together into a single vertex if <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM27"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM28"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>Φ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>Φ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Two positional <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM29"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>-mers are glued together if their sequences are the same and their positions are within <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM30"><mml:mi>Φ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> from each other. We refer to the <italic>multiplicity</italic> of a positional <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM31"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>-mer <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM32"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as the number of occurrences where <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM33"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> clustered at position <italic>p</italic>.</p>
      <p><sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> constructs the red–black positional de Bruijn graph from the alignment of the reads to the contigs. The red–black positional de Bruijn graph contains positional <italic>k</italic>-mers and is constructed in an identical way as the positional de Bruijn graph with the addition that each vertex (<inline-formula><mml:math id="MM34"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>-mer) has an associated red or black color attributed to it that is defined using Δ<italic><sub>L</sub></italic>, Δ<italic><sub>U</sub></italic> and Γ. In addition to the multiplicity of each positional <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM35"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>-mer, the number of positional <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM36"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>-mers that originated from a read whose mate-pair did not align in the conventional direction is stored at each vertex. When the multiplicity is less than Δ<italic><sub>L</sub></italic> or greater than Δ<italic><sub>U</sub></italic> or if the observed frequency of discordant mate-pair orientation is greater than Γ, then the vertex is <italic>red</italic>; otherwise it is <italic>black</italic>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2.3">
      <title>2.3 Misassembly conjecture and breakpoint estimation</title>
      <p>A red–black positional de Bruijn graph is constructed for each contig, and misassembly errors in each contig are detected by searching for consecutive red vertices in the corresponding graph. Depth-first search is used for the graph traversal. If there are greater than 50 consecutive red vertices, then the contig is conjectured to be misassembled. The breakpoint in the contig can be determined by recovering the position of the corresponding red vertices (e.g. the positional <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM37"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>-mers). The number of consecutive red vertices needed to consider it misassembled can be changed via a command line parameter in <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc>. Our experiments were performed with the default (e.g. 50), which corresponds to a region in the contig that has length <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM38"><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>50 bp. After this stage of the algorithm, we take contigs having regions exceeding that threshold as a set of contigs that are conjectured to be misassembled and their transitions in and out of those regions as breakpoints.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2.4">
      <title>2.4 Misassembly verification</title>
      <p>Lastly, we use optical mapping data to verify whether a contig that is conjectured to be misassembled indeed is. Verification is based on the expectation that, after <italic>in silico</italic> digestion, a correctly assembled contig has a sequence of fragment sizes that is similar to that in the optical map at the corresponding locus in the genome. In other words, an <italic>in silico</italic>-digested contig should align to some region of the optical map since both are derived from the same region in the genome. Conversely, as misassembled contigs are not faithful reconstructions of any part of the genome, when <italic>in silico</italic> digested, their sequence of fragments will likewise not have a corresponding locus in the optical map to which it aligns.</p>
      <p>Optical maps contain measurement error at each fragment size, so some criteria is needed to decide whether variation in fragment size of an <italic>in silico</italic><italic>-</italic>digested contig and that of an optical map at a particular locus is due to variation in the size of the physical fragments or a consequence of optical measurement error. Because of this ambiguity, and the necessary tolerances to ensure correctly assembled contigs align to the locus in the optical map, misassembled contigs may also align to loci in the optical map, which by coincidence have a fragment sequence similar to the contig within the threshold margin of error. Although there are various sophisticated approaches to determining statistical significance of an alignment, such as by <xref rid="btv262-B47" ref-type="bibr">Sarkar <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref>, we use a <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM39"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>χ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> model discussed by <xref rid="btv262-B34" ref-type="bibr">Nagarajan <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref> and take the cumulative density function <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM40"><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>0.85 as evidence of alignment, which we found to work well empirically.</p>
      <p>In addition, a misassembled contig only fails to align to the optical map if the enzyme recognition sequence, and thus the cleavage sites, exist in the contig in a manner that disrupts a good alignment (e.g. a misassembled contig with an inverted segment may still align if cleavage sites flank the inverted segment). This implies that (i) some enzymes produce optical maps that have greater performance in identifying misassembly errors and (ii) alignment to the optical map is not as strong evidence for correct assembly as non-alignment to the optical map is for misassembly. This leads to the conclusion that an ensemble of optical maps (each made with a different enzyme) has a greater chance at revealing misassembly errors than a single optical map. As acquiring three optical maps for one genome is reasonably accessible for many sequencing projects, the process of <italic>in silico</italic> digestion and alignment is repeated for three enzymes. A contig is deemed to be misassembled if it fails to align to any one of the three optical maps. The alignment is performed using Twin (<xref rid="btv262-B33" ref-type="bibr">Muggli <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>) (with default parameters) and then these results are filtered according to the <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM41"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>χ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> model mentioned above. For our experiments, optical maps were simulated by <italic>in silico</italic> digesting reference genomes, adding normally distributed noise with a 150 bp standard deviation and discarding fragments smaller than 700 bp.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="SEC3">
    <title>3 Analyses</title>
    <sec id="SEC3.1">
      <title>3.1 Datasets using simulated optical mapping data</title>
      <p>Our first dataset consisted of approximately 6.9 million paired-end 101 bp reads from the prokaryote genome <italic>F.</italic><italic>tularensis</italic>, generated by Illumina Genome Analyzer (GA) IIx platform. It was obtained from the NCBI Short Read Archive [accession number (SRA:SRR063416)]. The reference genome was also downloaded from the NCBI website [Reference genome (RefSeq:NC_006570.2)]. The <italic>F.</italic><italic>tularensis</italic> genome is 1 892 775 bp in length with a GC content of 32%. As a measure of quality assurance, we aligned the reads to the <italic>F.</italic><italic>tularensis</italic> genome using BWA (version 0.5.9) (<xref rid="btv262-B28" ref-type="bibr">Li and Durbin 2009</xref>) with default parameters. We call a read <italic>mapped</italic> if BWA outputs an alignment for it and <italic>unmapped</italic> otherwise. Analysis of the alignments revealed that 97% of the reads mapped to the reference genome representing an average depth of approximately <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM42"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>367</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
      <p>Our second dataset consisted of approximately 31.3 million paired-end 100 bp reads from the loblolly pine (<italic>Pinus taeda</italic>) genome (<xref rid="btv262-B35" ref-type="bibr">Neale <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>), which has GC contact of 38%. We downloaded the reference genome from the pine genome website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pinegenome.org/pinerefseq">http://pinegenome.org/pinerefseq</ext-link>) and simulated reads from the largest five hundred scaffolds from the reference using ART (<xref rid="btv262-B19" ref-type="bibr">Huang <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>) (‘art illumina’). ART was ran with parameters that simulated 100 bp paired end reads with 200 bp insert size and 50x coverage. The data for this experiment are available on the <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> website. We simulated an optical map using the reference genome for <italic>F.</italic><italic>tularensis</italic> and loblolly pine since there is no publicly available one for these genomes.</p>
      <p>We assembled both sets of reads with a wide variety of state-of-the-art assemblers. The versions used were those that were publicly available before or on September 1, 2014: SPAdes (version 3.1) (<xref rid="btv262-B3" ref-type="bibr">Bankevich <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>); Velvet (version 1.2.10) (<xref rid="btv262-B56" ref-type="bibr">Zerbino and Birney 2008</xref>); SOAPdenovo (version 2.04) (<xref rid="btv262-B29" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>); ABySS (version 1.5.2) (<xref rid="btv262-B49" ref-type="bibr">Simpson <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>) and IDBA-UD (version 1.1.1) (<xref rid="btv262-B38" ref-type="bibr">Peng <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). SPAdes outputs two assemblies: before repeat resolution and after repeat resolution—we report both. Some of the assemblers emitted both contigs and scaffolds. We considered contigs only but note that all scaffolds had a greater number of misassembly errors. We emphasize that our purpose here is not to compare the various assemblers, but instead it is to demonstrate that all assemblers produce misassembly errors, which are in need of consideration and correction.</p>
      <p>We used QUAST (<xref rid="btv262-B16" ref-type="bibr">Gurevich <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>) in default mode to evaluate the assemblies. Hence, our experiments use the published reference genomes as being ground truth and use the published references to identify misassembly errors in the other assemblies through QUAST. We note that this is imperfect since the reference genomes are likely not error-free. QUAST defines misassembly error as being <italic>extensive</italic> or <italic>local</italic>. An extensively misassembled contig is defined as one that satisfies one following conditions: (i) the left flanking sequence aligns over 1 kb away from the right flanking sequence on the reference; (ii) flanking sequences overlap on more than 1 kb and (iii) flanking sequences align to different strands or different chromosomes, whereas a local misassembled contig is one that satisfies the following conditions: (i) two or more distinct alignments cover the breakpoint; (ii) the gap between left and right flanking sequences is less than 1 kb and the left and right flanking sequences both are on the same strand of the same chromosome of the reference genome. We made a minor alteration to QUAST to output which contigs contain local misassembly errors. A contig can contain both extensive and local misassembly errors. Any correctly assembled contig is one that does not contain either type of error.</p>
      <sec id="SEC3.1.1">
        <title>3.1.1 Detection of misassembly errors in <italic>F.</italic>tularensis</title>
        <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="btv262-T1">Table 1</xref> gives the assembly statistics corresponding to this experiment. Comparable assembly results on this data were reported by <xref rid="btv262-B22" ref-type="bibr">Ilie <italic>et al.</italic> (2014)</xref>, though in some cases we used more recent software releases (e.g. for SPAdes). Note that the number of locally misassembled contigs and the number of extensively misassembled contigs is not disjoint. A contig can be locally and extensively misassembled. Thus, <xref ref-type="table" rid="btv262-T1">Table 1</xref> gives the number of contigs having at least one extensive misassembly error and the number of contigs having at least one local misassembly error.
<table-wrap id="btv262-T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>The performance comparison between major assembly tools on the <italic>F.tularensis</italic> dataset, which has a genome length of 1 892 775 bp and 6 907 220 number of 101 bp reads, using QUAST in default mode (<xref rid="btv262-B16" ref-type="bibr">Gurevich <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Assembler</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. contigs (no. unaligned)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">N50</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Largest (bp)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (bp)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">local MA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MA (bp)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GF (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Velvet</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">358 (3 + 35 part)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7377</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 381</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 762 202</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">84 965</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOAPdenovo</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">307 (3 + 31 part)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8767</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 989</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 018 158</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">96 258</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABySS</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96 (1 part)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 975</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">88 275</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 875 628</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 330 684</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.87</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPAdes (−rr)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102 (2 + 11 part)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 148</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 449</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 788 634</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">258 309</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.81</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPAdes (+rr)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 (2 + 17 part)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 876</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 891</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 797 197</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">497 356</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.75</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IDBA</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109 (1 + 10 part)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 223</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 437</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 768 958</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">221 087</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.64</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="btv262-TF1"><p>All statistics are based on contigs no shorter than 500 bp. N50 is defined as the length for which the collection of all contigs of that length or longer contains at least half of the sum of the lengths of all contigs and for which the collection of all contigs of that length or shorter also contains at least half of the sum of the lengths of all contigs. The no. unaligned is the number of contigs that did not align to the reference genome, or they were only partially aligned (part). Total is sum of the length of all contigs. MA is the number of (extensively) misassembled contigs. Local MA is the total number of contigs that had local misassemblies. MA (bp) is the total length of the MA contigs. GF is the genome fraction percentage, which is the fraction of genome bases that are covered by the assembly. −rr and ++rr denotes before and after repeat resolution, respectively.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="btv262-T2" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>The performance comparison of our method on the <italic>F.tularensis</italic> dataset</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Correction method</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Assembler</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MA TPR</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">local MA TPR</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FPR</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="6" colspan="1">misSEQuel (paired-end data only)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Velvet</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% (11/11)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% (36/36)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58% (180/312)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOAPdenovo</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% (10/10)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% (35/35)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63% (165/263)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABySS</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% (64/64)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% (32/32)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87% (20/23)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPAdes (−rr)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% (11/11)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% (30/30)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83% (52/63)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPAdes (++rr)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% (23/23)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% (31/31)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86% (49/57)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IDBA</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% (10/10)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% (31/31)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38% (57/149)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6" colspan="1">misSEQuel (optical mapping data only)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Velvet</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55% (6/11)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69% (25/36)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24% (76/312)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOAPdenovo</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80% (8/10)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63% (22/35)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29% (77/263)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABySS</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69% (44/64)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88% (28/32)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13% (3/23)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPAdes (−rr)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91% (10/11)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87% (26/30)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21% (13/63)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPAdes (++rr)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87% (20/23)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81% (25/31)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16% (9/57)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IDBA</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90% (9/10)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77% (24/31)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10% (15/149)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6" colspan="1"><bold>misSEQuel (paired-end and optical mapping data)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Velvet</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>55% (6</bold>/<bold>11)</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>100% (36</bold>/<bold>36)</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>22% (68</bold>/<bold>312)</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SOAPdenovo</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>80% (8</bold>/<bold>10)</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>84% (21</bold>/<bold>35)</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>20% (53</bold>/<bold>263)</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ABySS</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>69% (44</bold>/<bold>64)</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>88% (28</bold>/<bold>32)</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>13% (3</bold>/<bold>23)</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SPAdes (−rr)</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>91% (10</bold>/<bold>11)</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>87% (26</bold>/<bold>30)</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>19% (12</bold>/<bold>63)</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SPAdes (++rr)</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>97% (20</bold>/<bold>23)</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>81% (25</bold>/<bold>31)</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>16% (9</bold>/<bold>57)</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>IDBA</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>90% (9</bold>/<bold>10)</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>77% (24</bold>/<bold>31)</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>9% (14</bold>/<bold>149)</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6" colspan="1">REAPR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Velvet</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55% (6/11)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11% (4/36)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 1% (2/312)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOAPdenovo</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20% (2/10)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14% (5/35)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2% (6/263)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABySS</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13% (8/64)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13% (4/32)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4% (1/23)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPAdes (−rr)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27% (3/11)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27% (8/30)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5% (3/63)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPAdes (++rr)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0% (0/23)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19% (6/31)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11% (6/57)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IDBA</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40% (4/10)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13% (4/31)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4% (6/149)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6" colspan="1">Pilon</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Velvet</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27% (3/11)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3% (1/36)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 1% (3/312)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOAPdenovo</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10% (1/10)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9% (3/35)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2% (5/263)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABySS</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3% (2/64)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6% (2/32)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4% (3/23)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPAdes (−rr)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0% (0/11)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3% (1/30)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5% (5/63)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPAdes (++rr)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0% (0/23)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10% (3/31)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12% (7/57)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IDBA</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0% (0/10)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10% (3/31)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4% (5/149)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="btv262-TF2"><p>The TPR in this context is a contig that is misassembled and is predicted to be so. The FPR is a correctly assembled contig that was predicted to be misassembled. The TPR and FPR are given as percentages with the raw values given in brackets. Bold values emphasize the benefit of using both data sources.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="btv262-T3" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>The performance comparison between major assembly tools on Loblolly pine genome dataset (62 647 324 bp, 31.3 million reads, 100 bp) using QUAST in default mode (<xref rid="btv262-B16" ref-type="bibr">Gurevich <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Assembler</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. contigs (no. unaligned)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">N50</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Largest (bp)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (bp)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">local MA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MA (bp)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GF (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Velvet</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 327 (0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1740</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 823</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 851 131</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.21</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOAPdenovo</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 126 (0 + 1 part)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7950</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 004</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 205 817</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABySS</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4586 (16 + 89 part)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 089</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">201 382</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 349 408</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">127</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">715</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 391 565</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.17</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPAdes (−rr)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 671 (4 + 10 part)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4809</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 993</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 079 764</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 079</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.30</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPAdes (+rr)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8607 (7 + 102 part)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 957</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">108 442</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 730 939</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">299</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 734 609</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.57</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IDBA</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 409 (3 + 31 part)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3990</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 213</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 765 854</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">200</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">292 769</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.03</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
        <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="btv262-T2">Table 2</xref> shows the results for (i) <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> with paired-end data only; (ii) <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> with optical mapping data only and (iii) <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> with both optical mapping and paired-end data to demonstrate the benefit of combining both types of data. As demonstrated by these results, using short paired-end data alone produced a high false-positive rate (FPR) due to ambiguous read mapping in locations that contain repetitive regions. This is an inherent shortcoming of short paired-end data and demonstrates that to decrease the FPR, another source of information must be used in combination. Optical mapping data have a much lower FPR and when used in combination with paired-end data, produces optimal results. The lowest FPR was witnessed when both optical mapping and paired-end data were used. In some cases, the reduction in the FPR was dramatic: from 87% (ABySS, paired-end data) to 13% (ABySS, paired-end and optical mapping data). The true-positive rate (TPR) of locally misassembled contigs was between 77% and 100% when both paired-end and optical mapping data were used. Lastly, TPR of extensively misassembled contigs was between 55% and 100% when both paired-end and optical mapping data were used.</p>
        <p>In our experiments, we iterate through combinations of three enzymes from the REBASE enzyme database (<xref rid="btv262-B43" ref-type="bibr">Roberts <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>) and use the set of enzymes that performed best. Our results demonstrate that with a good enzyme choice over half of all extensively misassembled contigs and over 75% of locally misassembled contigs can be identified with only a 9–22% false discovery rate.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="SEC3.1.2">
        <title>3.1.2 Detection of misassembly errors in loblolly pine</title>
        <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="btv262-T3">Table 3</xref> gives the assembly statistics corresponding to this experiment. The results for the loblolly pine are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="btv262-T4">Table 4</xref>. Both Velvet and SOAPdenovo produced zero misassembled contigs on this dataset, so we do not include them in <xref ref-type="table" rid="btv262-T4">Table 4</xref>. <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> correctly identifies between 31% and 100% of extensively misassembled contigs and between 57% and 73% of locally misassembled contigs. The FPR was between 0.6% and 43%. Although REAPR has a lower FPR (between 3% and 11%), it is only capable of identifying a small number of extensively misassembled contigs (between 2% and 14%) and a small number of locally misassembled contigs (between 2% and 27%). Similar to the results of <italic>F.</italic><italic>tularensis</italic>, Pilon had a lower FPR but also lower TPRs than REAPR. This is unsurprising since ‘it is optimized to use both fragment (or small) and long (or large) insert libraries’ and was created for microbial genomes (<xref rid="btv262-B54" ref-type="bibr">Walker <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>).
<table-wrap id="btv262-T4" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>The performance comparison of our method on the loblolly pine dataset</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Correction method</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Assembler</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MA TPR</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">local MA TPR</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FPR</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1"><bold>misSEQuel</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ABySS</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>31% (40</bold>/<bold>127)</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>57% (405</bold>/<bold>715)</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>43% (1604</bold>/<bold>3754)</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SPAdes (−rr)</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>100% (7</bold>/<bold>7)</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>73% (8</bold>/<bold>11)</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;1% (135</bold>/<bold>20 653)</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SPAdes (+rr)</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>67% (199</bold>/<bold>299)</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>67% (38</bold>/<bold>57)</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>38% (3117</bold>/<bold>8254)</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>IDBA</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>52% (32</bold>/<bold>61)</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>73% (145</bold>/<bold>200)</bold></td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>19% (4258</bold>/<bold>22 150)</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">REAPR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABySS</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7% (9/127)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2% (12/715)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3% (112/3754)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPAdes (−rr)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14% (1/7)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27% (3/11)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6% (1323/20 653)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPAdes (+rr)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7% (21/299)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5% (3/57)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5% (424/8254)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IDBA</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2% (1/61)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6% (12/200)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11% (2354/22 150)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Pilon</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABySS</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7% (8/127)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2% (11/715)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2% (70/3754)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPAdes (−rr)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14% (1/7)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18% (2/11)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4% (923/20 653)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPAdes (+rr)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5% (16/299)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5% (3/57)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5% (388/8254)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IDBA</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2% (1/61)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5% (12/200)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8% (1823/22 150)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="btv262-TF3"><p>Again, a true positive in this context is a contig that is misassembled and is predicted to be so. A false positive is a correctly assembled contig that was predicted to be misassembled. Bold values highlight MISSEQUEL results.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <p>Again, the restriction enzymes used in our experiments were chosen to be optimal by considering the set of all possible enzymes in the aforementioned database. Nonetheless, we note that if the enzyme combination was chosen at random, then the expected FPR and TPR would decrease by a small fraction for majority of the assemblies considered. The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btv262/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> shows prototypical ROC curves and heat-maps illustrating the density of enzyme combinations at various detection rates.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC3.2">
      <title>3.2 Datasets using real optical mapping data</title>
      <p>We evaluated the performance of <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> on rice and budgerigar. These genomes were chosen because they have available sequence and optical mapping data, are diverse in size and have undergone a significant level of verification. Rice and budgerigar have genome sizes of 430 Mb and 1.58 Gbp, respectively (<xref rid="btv262-B24" ref-type="bibr">Kawahara <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="btv262-B51" ref-type="bibr">Tiersch and Wachtel 1991</xref>). The size of budgerigar is only predicted (<xref rid="btv262-B51" ref-type="bibr">Tiersch and Wachtel 1991</xref>). The validated genomic regions will allow us to use QUAST to determine FPR and TPR, as in Subsection 3.1.</p>
      <sec id="SEC3.2.1">
        <title>3.2.1 Performance on rice genome</title>
        <p>The sequence dataset consists of approximately 134 million 76-bp paired-end reads for rice from the <italic>japonica</italic> cultivar Nipponbare, generated by Illumina, Inc. on the Genome Analyzer (GA) IIx platform (<xref rid="btv262-B24" ref-type="bibr">Kawahara <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). These reads were obtained from the NCBI Short Read Archive (accession SRX032913). The optical map for this same cultivar of rice was constructed by <xref rid="btv262-B59" ref-type="bibr">Zhou <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref> using SwaI as the restriction enzyme. This optical map was assembled from single molecule restriction maps into 14 optical map contigs, labeled as 12 chromosomes, with chromosome labels 6 and 11 both containing two optical map contigs. Both the sequence and optical mapping data were generated as part of a larger project that produced a ‘revised, error-corrected, and validated assembly of the Nipponbare cultivar of rice’ (<xref rid="btv262-B24" ref-type="bibr">Kawahara <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). This reference genome, termed Os-Nipponbare-Reference-IRGSP-1.0 is publicly available on the Rice Annotation Project (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rice.plantbiology.msu.edu/annotation_pseudo_current.shtml">http://rice.plantbiology.msu.edu/annotation_pseudo_current.shtml</ext-link>)</p>
        <p>The paired-end data were assembled using SOAPdenovo using default parameters. This assembly consists of 11 440 contigs larger than 500 bp, cove 81.3% of the reference genome (22 317 126 in size, 43.7% GC content). It has an N50 statistic of 1 680 499 extensively misassembled contigs and 3 locally misassembled contigs. We ran <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> with default parameters and the SOAPdenovo assembly, optical map and paired-end data as input. Similarly, we ran REAPR with default parameters, and the SOAPdenovo assembly, and paired-end data as input. Out of the 499 extensively misassembled contigs, <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> identified 374 of them (75%), whereas REAPR identified 30 (6%) and Pilon identified 25 (5%). Out of the three locally misassembled contigs, <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> identified all three, but REAPR and Pilon identified none. Lastly, <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> deemed that 821 of the correctly assembled contigs were misassembled (&lt;1% FPR), whereas REAPR and Pilon deemed that 800 and 522 were deemed misassembled (&lt;1% FPR), respectively. We further note that both <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> and REAPR agreed on 472 of these correctly assembled contigs; i.e. both REAPR and <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> predicted that 472 correctly assembled contigs are misassembled. This could suggest that a broadened definition of misassembly by QUAST would also deem these contigs to be misassembled.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="SEC3.2.2">
        <title>3.2.2 Misassembly errors in the draft genome of budgerigar</title>
        <p>A concerted effort has been in understanding the biodiversity of many bird species (<xref rid="btv262-B23" ref-type="bibr">Jarvis <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>)—including the budgerigar genome—and thus, a significant amount of data have been generated for budgerigar. Pacific Biosciences (PacBio) data, short read Illumina data, 454 and optical mapping data have been generated and used for the assembly of this genome. The sequence and optical map data for the budgerigar genome were generated for the Assemblathon 2 project of <xref rid="btv262-B4" ref-type="bibr">Bradnam <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref>. Budgerigar has a GC content of approximately 43.8% (<xref rid="btv262-B23" ref-type="bibr">Jarvis <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>) and contains GC-rich (<inline-formula><mml:math id="MM43"><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> 75%) regions (<xref rid="btv262-B18" ref-type="bibr">Howard <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). Sequence data consist of a combination of Roche 454, Illumina and PacBio reads, providing 16×, 285× and 10× coverage, respectively, of the genome. All sequence reads are available at the NCBI Short Read Archive (accession ERP002324). For our analysis, we consider the assembly generated using CABOG (<xref rid="btv262-B32" ref-type="bibr">Miller <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>), which was completed by the CBCB team (Koren and Phillippy) as part of Assemblathon 2 (<xref rid="btv262-B4" ref-type="bibr">Bradnam <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). The optical mapping data were created by Zhou, Goldstein, Place, Schwartz and Bechner using the SwaI restriction enzyme and consists of 92 separate pieces.</p>
        <p><xref rid="btv262-B18" ref-type="bibr">Ganapathy <italic>et al.</italic>(2014)</xref> released three hybrid assemblies; namely, (i) budgerigar 454-Illumina hybrid v6.3 using the CABOG (<xref rid="btv262-B32" ref-type="bibr">Miller <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>) assembler; (ii) budgerigar PacBio corrected reads (PBcR) hybrid using the CABOG assembler and (iii) budgerigar Illumina-454 hybrid using the SOAPdenovo (version 2.04) (<xref rid="btv262-B29" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>) assembler. We downloaded the PBcR assembly (ii), the Illumina-454 hybrid assembly (iii), in addition to the optical mapping data and pair-end data. The Illumina-454 assembly has 212 203 contigs (54 829 contigs <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM44"><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> 500 bp), N50 of 51 034 and largest contig of 500 974 (<xref rid="btv262-B18" ref-type="bibr">Howard <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). The PBcR assembly has 77 556 contigs, average, N50 of 102 885 and largest contig of 849 044 (<xref rid="btv262-B18" ref-type="bibr">Howard <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). We ran QUAST to evaluate the Illumina-454 hybrid assembly (all contigs <inline-formula><mml:math id="MM45"><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> 500 bp), using the PBcR assembly as the reference genome. It reported 13 996 extensively misassembled contigs and 2937 locally misassembled contigs. Thus, there are 39 394 contigs that contain no misassembly error. We ran <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> on the Illumina-454 hybrid assembly on this using the paired-end and optical mapping. <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> correctly identified 10 777 (out of 13 996) extensively misassembled contigs (77% MA TPR) and 2350 (out of 2937) locally misassembled contigs (80% local MA TPR); however, it incorrectly identified 4023 (out of the 39 394) as being misassembled (10%).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC3.3">
      <title>3.3 Practical considerations: memory and time</title>
      <p>We evaluated the memory and time requirements of <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc>. Since <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> is a multi-threaded application, its wall-clock time depends on the computing resources available to the user. <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> required a maximum of 8 threads, 16 GB and 1.5 h on all assemblies of <italic>F.</italic><italic>tularensis</italic> and a maximum of 20 GB and 2.5 h to complete on all assemblies of loblolly pine. Most genome assemblers require an incomparably greater amount of time and memory and thus, from a practical perspective, the requirements of <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> are not a significant increase. The difference in the resource requirements of <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> in comparison to modern assemblers is since it operates contig-wise rather than genome-wise and therefore, only deals with a significantly smaller portion of the data at a single time. We conclude by mentioning that <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> is not optimized for memory and time and both could be further reduced but reimplementing the red–black positional de Bruijn graph using memory- and time-succinct data structures.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>4 Discussion and conclusions</title>
    <p>This article describes the first non-proprietary computational method for identifying misassembly errors using short read sequence data and optical mapping data. Our results demonstrate (i) a substantial number of misassembly errors can be identified in draft genomes of prokaryote and eukaryote species; (ii) our method works on genomes that vary by GC-content and size; (iii) it can be used in combination with any assembler and thus, making it a viable post-processing step for any assembly and (iv) addresses the need for methods to analyze optical mapping data.</p>
    <p>One of our main contributions is the demonstration that optical mapping can have significant benefit for misassembly error detection. A high FPR will result using paired-end data alone because of ambiguous read mapping. Furthermore, superior results were always witnessed using paired-end data and optical mapping data. In some cases, the improvement of using both datasets over a single dataset was substantial. For example, the Velvet assembly of <italic>F.</italic><italic>tularensis</italic> had 312 correctly assembled contigs; 76 of these 312 were deemed to be misassembled when <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> was ran with optical mapping data alone, whereas this improved to 68 out of 312 when both paired-end and optical mapping data were used. Similarly, when <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> was ran on this same assembly, 69% (25/36) of locally misassembled contigs were identified, whereas this improved to 100% (36/36) when both datasets were used.</p>
    <p>Lastly, we point out two areas that warrant future work. One area that merits investigation is to develop methods that will distinguish between structural variation heterozygosity and paralogous variation and misassembly errors. <sc>mis</sc>SEQ<sc>uel</sc> is not able to detect the difference between structural variation and misassembly errors—and in fact, the high FPR might be due to this type of variation—however, methods that do so could be very valuable for finishing draft genomes. Lastly, we conclude by suggesting that efficient algorithmic selection of enzymes that will yield such informative optical maps in a <italic>de novo</italic> scenario is an area for interesting and important future work.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
      <caption>
        <title>Supplementary Data</title>
      </caption>
      <media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_31_12_i80__index.html"/>
      <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_btv262_Muggli_217_sup.pdf"/>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack>
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <p>The authors would like to thank Pavel Pevzner from the University of California, San Diego, and Anton Korobeynikov from Saint Petersburg State University for many insightful discussions. The authors thank Alexey Gurevich from Saint Petersburg State University for clarifications and support with QUAST. They thank Ganeshkumar Ganapathy, Erich Jarvis and Jason Howard from Duke University for assistance with the budgerigar experiments. Lastly, they thank David C. Schwartz and Shiguo Zhou from the University of Wisconsin-Madison, and Mihai Pop and Lee Mendelowitz from the University of Maryland for helping us get access to the rice data.</p>
    <sec>
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p>M.D.M. and C.B. were supported by the <funding-source>Colorado Clinical and Translational Sciences Institute</funding-source>, which is funded by <funding-source>National Institutes of Health</funding-source> (NIH-NCATS, <award-id>UL1TR001082</award-id>, <award-id>TL1TR001081</award-id>, <award-id>KL2TR001080</award-id>). S.J.P. was supported by the <funding-source>Helsinki Institute of Information Technology (HIIT)</funding-source> and by <funding-source>Academy of Finland through</funding-source> grants <award-id>258308</award-id> and <award-id>250345</award-id> (CoECGR).</p>
      <p><italic>Conflict of Interest</italic>: none declared.</p>
    </sec>
  </ack>
  <ref-list>
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="btv262-B1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anantharaman</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) 
<article-title>False positives in genomic map assembly and sequence validation</article-title>. In: <source>Proceedings of the First International Workshop on Algorithms in Bioinformatics</source>, <comment>WABI ’01</comment>, 
<publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aston</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) 
<article-title>Optical mapping in genomic analysis</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Meyers</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (eds) <source>Encyclopedia of Analytical Chemistry</source>. 
<publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>, 
<publisher-loc>Hoboken, NJ</publisher-loc>, pp. <fpage>5105</fpage>–<lpage>5121</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bankevich</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>SPAdes: a new genome assembly algorithm and its applications to single-cell sequencing</article-title>. <source>J. Comput. Biol.</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>455</fpage>–<lpage>477</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22506599</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradnam</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) 
<article-title>Assemblathon 2: evaluating <italic>de novo</italic> methods of genome assembly in three vertebrate species</article-title>. <source>GigaScience</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23587291</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) 
<article-title>ALLPATHS: <italic>de novo</italic> assembly of whole-genome shotgun microreads</article-title>. <source>Genome Res.</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>810</fpage>–<lpage>820</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18340039</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaisson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pevzner</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) 
<article-title>Short read fragment assembly of bacterial genomes</article-title>. <source>Genome Res.</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>324</fpage>–<lpage>330</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18083777</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chamala</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) 
<article-title>Assembly and validation of the genome of the nonmodel basal angiosperm <italic>Amborella</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source>, <volume>342</volume>, <fpage>1516</fpage>–<lpage>1517</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24357320</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B8">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) 
<article-title>Meraculous: <italic>de novo</italic> genome assembly with short paired-end reads</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>e23501</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21876754</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B9">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Church</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) 
<article-title>Lineage-specific biology revealed by a finished genome assembly of the mouse</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol.</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>e1000112</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19468303</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B10">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Compeau</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) 
<article-title>How to apply de Bruijn graphs to genome assembly</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>987</fpage>–<lpage>991</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22068540</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B11">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dimalanta</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) 
<article-title>Microfluidic system for large DNA molecule arrays</article-title>. <source>Anal. Chem.</source>, <volume>76</volume>, <fpage>5293</fpage>–<lpage>5301</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15362885</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B12">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) 
<article-title>Sequencing and automated whole-genome optical mapping of the genome of a domestic goat</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>136</fpage>–<lpage>141</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B13">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donmez</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brudno</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) 
<article-title>Hapsembler: an assembler for highly polymorphic genomes</article-title>. In: <source>Proceedings of RECOMB</source>, pp. <fpage>38</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B14">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donmez</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brudno</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) 
<article-title>SCARPA: scaffolding reads with practical algorithms</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>428</fpage>–<lpage>434</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23274213</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B18">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ganapathy</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) 
<article-title><italic>De novo</italic> high-coverage sequencing and annotated assemblies of the budgerigar genome</article-title>. <source>GigaScience</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>11</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25061512</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B15">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gnerre</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) 
<article-title>Assisted assembly: how to improve a <italic>de novo</italic> genome assembly by using related species</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol.</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>R88</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19712469</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B16">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gurevich</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) 
<article-title>QUAST: quality assessment tool for genome assemblies</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>1072</fpage>–<lpage>1075</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23422339</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B17">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haussler</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) 
<article-title>Genome 10K: a proposal to obtain whole-genome sequence for 10,000 vertebrate species</article-title>. <source>J. Hered.</source>, <volume>100</volume>, <fpage>659</fpage>–<lpage>674</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B19">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>ART: a next-generation sequencing read simulator</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>593</fpage>–<lpage>594</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22199392</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B20">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) 
<article-title>REAPR: a universal tool for genome assembly evaluation</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol.</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>R47</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23710727</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B21">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Idury</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) 
<article-title>A new algorithm for DNA sequence assembly</article-title>. <source>J. Comput. Biol.</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>291</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7497130</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B22">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ilie</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) 
<article-title>SAGE: string-overlap assembly of genomes</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>302</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25225118</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B23">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) 
<article-title>Whole-genome analyses resolve early branches in the tree of life of modern birds</article-title>. <source>Science</source>, <volume>346</volume>, <fpage>1320</fpage>–<lpage>1331</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25504713</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B24">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawahara</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) 
<article-title>Improvement of the <italic>Oryza sativa nipponbare</italic> reference genome using next generation sequence and optical map data</article-title>. <source>Rice</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24280096</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B25">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) 
<article-title>Reference-assisted chromosome assembly</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>110</volume>, <fpage>1785</fpage>–<lpage>1790</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23307812</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B26">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) 
<article-title>LOCAS–a low coverage assembly tool for resequencing projects</article-title>. <source>PloS One</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>e23455</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21858125</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B27">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koren</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) 
<article-title>Automated ensemble assembly and validation of microbial genomes</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>126</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24884846</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B28">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) 
<article-title>Fast and accurate short read alignment with Burrows–Wheeler transform</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>1754</fpage>–<lpage>1760</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19451168</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B29">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) 
<article-title><italic>De novo</italic> assembly of human genomes with massively parallel short read sequencing</article-title>. <source>Genome Res.</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>265</fpage>–<lpage>272</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20019144</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B30">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>AGORA: assembly guided by optical restriction alignment</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>189</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22856673</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B31">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mendelowitz</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pop</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) 
<article-title>Computational methods for optical mapping</article-title>. <source>GigaScience</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>33</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25671093</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B32">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) 
<article-title>Aggressive assembly of pyrosequencing reads with mates</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>2818</fpage>–<lpage>2824</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18952627</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B33">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muggli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) 
<article-title>Efficient indexed alignment of contigs to optical maps</article-title>. In: <source>Proceedings of WABI</source>, pp. <fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B34">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagarajan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) 
<article-title>Scaffolding and validation of bacterial genome assemblies using optical restriction maps</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>1229</fpage>–<lpage>1235</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18356192</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B35">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neale</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) 
<article-title>Decoding the massive genome of loblolly pine using haploid DNA and novel assembly strategies</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol.</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>R59</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24647006</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B36">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neely</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) 
<article-title>Optical mapping of DNA: single-molecule-based methods for mapping genome</article-title>. <source>Biopolymers</source>, <volume>95</volume>, <fpage>298</fpage>–<lpage>311</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21207457</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B37">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ossowski</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) 
<article-title>Sequencing of natural strains of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> with short reads</article-title>. <source>Genome Res.</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>2024</fpage>–<lpage>2033</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18818371</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B38">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>IDBA-UD: a <italic>de novo</italic> assembler for single-cell and metagenomic sequencing data with highly uneven depth</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>1420</fpage>–<lpage>1428</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22495754</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B39">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pevzner</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) 
<article-title>An Eulerian path approach to DNA fragment assembly</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>98</volume>, <fpage>9748</fpage>–<lpage>9753</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11504945</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B40">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pevzner</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) 
<article-title><italic>De Novo</italic> repeat classification and fragment assembly</article-title>. <source>Genome Res.</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>1786</fpage>–<lpage>1796</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15342561</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B41">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phillippy</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) 
<article-title>Genome assembly forensics: finding the elusive mis-assembly</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol.</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>R55</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18341692</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B42">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reslewic</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) 
<article-title>Whole-genome shotgun optical mapping of <italic>Rhodospirillum rubrum</italic></article-title>. <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>, <volume>71</volume>, <fpage>5511</fpage>–<lpage>5522</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16151144</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B43">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) 
<article-title>REBASE–a database for DNA restriction and modification: enzymes, genes and genomes</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>D234</fpage>–<lpage>D236</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19846593</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B44">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>G.E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). 
<article-title>Creating a buzz about insect genomes</article-title>. <source>Science</source>, <volume>331</volume>, <fpage>1386</fpage>–<lpage>1386</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21415334</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B45">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ronen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>SEQuel: improving the accuracy of genome assemblies</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>i188</fpage>–<lpage>i196</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22689760</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B46">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) 
<article-title>Beware of mis-assembled genomes</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>4320</fpage>–<lpage>4321</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16332717</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B47">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>Statistical significance of optical map alignments</article-title>. <source>J. Comput. Biol.</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>478</fpage>–<lpage>492</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22506568</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B48">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) 
<article-title>Ordered restriction maps of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> chromosomes constructed by optical mapping</article-title>. <source>Science</source>, <volume>262</volume>, <fpage>110</fpage>–<lpage>114</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8211116</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B49">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) 
<article-title>ABySS: a parallel assembler for short read sequence data</article-title>. <source>Genome Res.</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>1117</fpage>–<lpage>1123</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19251739</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B50">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teague</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) 
<article-title>High-resolution human genome structure by single-molecule analysis</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>107</volume>, <fpage>10848</fpage>–<lpage>10853</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20534489</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B51">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tiersch</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wachtel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>) 
<article-title>On the evolution of genome size of birds</article-title>. <source>J. Hered.</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>368</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1940280</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B52">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Treangen</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Next Generation Sequence Assembly with AMOS</source>, <volume>Vol. 11</volume>
<publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>, 
<publisher-loc>Hoboken, NJ</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B53">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turnbaugh</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) 
<article-title>The human microbiome project: exploring the microbial part of ourselves in a changing world</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>449</volume>, <fpage>804</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17943116</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B54">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) 
<article-title>Pilon: an integrated tool for comprehensive microbial variant detection and genome assembly improvement</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>e112963</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25409509</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B55">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xavier</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) 
<article-title>Employing whole genome mapping for optimal <italic>de novo</italic> assembly of bacterial genomes</article-title>. <source>BMC Res. Notes</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>484</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25077983</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B56">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zerbino</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Birney</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) 
<article-title>Velvet: algorithms for <italic>de novo</italic> short read assembly using de Bruijn graphs</article-title>. <source>Genome Res.</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>821</fpage>–<lpage>829</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18349386</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B57">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) 
<article-title>A whole-genome shotgun optical map of <italic>Yersinia pestis</italic> strain KIM</article-title>. <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>, <volume>68</volume>, <fpage>6321</fpage>–<lpage>6331</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12450857</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B58">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) 
<article-title>Shotgun optical mapping of the entire <italic>Leishmania major</italic> Friedlin genome</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biochem. Parasitol.</source>, <volume>138</volume>, <fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15500921</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B59">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) 
<article-title>Validation of rice genome sequence by optical mapping</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>278</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17697381</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv262-B60">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) 
<article-title>A single molecule scaffold for the maize genome</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet.</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>e1000711</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19936062</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
