<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BioData Min</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BioData Min</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>BioData Mining</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1756-0381</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4676895</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26692900</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">72</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13040-015-0072-2</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Methodology</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>Network construction and structure detection with metagenomic count data</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <name>
          <surname>Liu</surname>
          <given-names>Zhenqiu</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>zhenqiu.liu@cshs.org</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Lin</surname>
          <given-names>Shili</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>shili@stat.osu.edu</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Piantadosi</surname>
          <given-names>Steven</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>Steven.Piantadosi@csmc.edu</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Samuel Oschin Comprehensive Cancer Institute, Cedars-Sinai Medical Center, Los Angeles, 90048 CA USA </aff>
      <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Statistics, The Ohio State University, Columbus, 43210 OH USA </aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>12</day>
      <month>12</month>
      <year>2015</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>12</day>
      <month>12</month>
      <year>2015</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <year>2015</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>8</volume>
    <elocation-id>40</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>5</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>18</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© Liu et al. 2015</copyright-statement>
      <license license-type="OpenAccess">
        <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract id="Abs1">
      <sec>
        <title>Background</title>
        <p>The human microbiome plays a critical role in human health. Massive amounts of metagenomic data have been generated with advances in next-generation sequencing technologies that characterize microbial communities via direct isolation and sequencing. How to extract, analyze, and transform these vast amounts of data into useful knowledge is a great challenge to bioinformaticians. Microbial biodiversity research has focused primarily on taxa composition and abundance and less on the co-occurrences among different taxa. However, taxa co-occurrences and their relationships to environmental and clinical conditions are important because network structure may help to understand how microbial taxa function together.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Results</title>
        <p>We propose a systematic robust approach for bacteria network construction and structure detection using metagenomic count data. Pairwise similarity/distance measures between taxa are proposed by adapting distance measures for samples in ecology. We also extend the sparse inverse covariance approach to a sparse inverse of a similarity matrix from count data for network construction. Our approach is efficient for large metagenomic count data with thousands of bacterial taxa. We evaluate our method with real and simulated data. Our method identifies true and biologically significant network structures efficiently.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Conclusions</title>
        <p>Network analysis is crucial for detecting subnetwork structures with metagenomic count data. We developed a software tool in MATLAB for network construction and biologically significant module detection. Software MetaNet can be downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biostatistics.csmc.edu/MetaNet/">http://biostatistics.csmc.edu/MetaNet/</ext-link>.</p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
      <title>Keywords</title>
      <kwd>Metagenomics data</kwd>
      <kwd>Networks analysis</kwd>
      <kwd>Modules</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
        <meta-value>© The Author(s) 2015</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec id="Sec1">
    <title>Background</title>
    <p>Our human body is a host to various of microbes. Over 90 % of the cells in human body are bacterial or other non-human cells. These microbes have great influence on human physiology and nutrition, and are crucial for our health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Metagenomics, which is the study of genetic material recovered directly from uncultured microorganisms, has accelerated the analysis of functional biodiversity relevant to its ecology. The objectives of human microbiome research are to explore the host-microbiota interactions, associate differences in microbial communities with differences in metabolic functions and diseases, and understand how microbiota changes may affect human health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Massive amounts of metagenomic sequencing data have been generated with advances in next-generation sequencing (NGS) technologies. There are two NGS methods for metagenomics: whole metagenomic shotgun sequencing (WMGSS) and 16S rRNA gene sequencing. 16S rRNA sequencing is an amplicon sequencing method for identifying and comparing bacteria present within a given sample, while WMGSS comprehensively sample all genes in all organisms present in a given complex sample. The two techniques are quite different and intend for answer different biological questions. It has been shown that 16S rRNA sequencing contains hundreds of thousands of 16S RNAs fragments and is an efficient tool to infer bacterial communities, while WMGSS is mainly used for functional delineation and it is generally not deep enough to detect rare species in complex communities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. In this paper, we infer network structures and taxa co-occurrence with 16S rRNA sequencing. By examining the relationship of genome structure and function across many different taxa with NGS data, the scope of microbiology and of microbial evolution studies has been greatly broadened, and the field of systems biology has emerged [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p>
    <p>There have been great strides in determining the taxonomical and functional contents of a sample in the last several years. Many software packages including MOTHUR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], UniFrac [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], QIIME [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], and SILVAngs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] have been designed primarily for the analysis of 16S rRNA sequencing data, while the other software packages including MEGAN [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], Phymm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], NBC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] were developed mainly for shotgun metagenomic sequencing data. Those tools provide different approaches for the comparison of microbial communities with metagenomic sequence data. One output from some of the software is the abundance counts (sequence reads) for each taxa. These taxa abundance counts can be further analyzed to identify taxa and microbial communities that are associated with human diseases by comparing taxa counts from two or more groups with different disease status. Study of the link between characteristics of a microbiome and human disease is a active area of research. Current approaches such as MetaStats [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] and MetaDistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] mainly focus on variations in abundance across different clinical conditions, ignoring the interactions and structural variations among taxa. However, bacteria taxa do not act alone, rather they form part of large interacting (co-occurrence) networks and may function together. Variations in network structures and taxon interactions may be associated with disease status and clinical phenotypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Therefore network methods specifically designed for metagenomic count need to be developed.</p>
    <p>Networks methods and graph theory have been widely applied to gene regulatory network construction with expression data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Network analysis has also proved powerful for studying the characteristics of metabolic networks and their impact on various functional and evolutionary properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. RNA-Seq is a NGS approach to transcriptome profiling. It provides a far more precise measurement of levels of transcripts and their isoforms than other methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Local Poisson graphical (log-linear) model and Bayesian generalized graphical model for network construction have been developed with RNA-seq data recently [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. However, the log-linear model is not valid when there are zero counts or measures in the data, which is common in metagenomics. Also, the Bayesian Poisson graphical model is slow when the network size is large. It usually takes hours to construct a network with hundreds of nodes. Those parametric methods can not be applied to metagenomic count data without modification. Moreover, even though there are a few methods available for network construction with microbiome data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>], most methods for network analysis are based on pairwise correlations (or distance) and ignore high-order correlations. However, high-order (partial) correlation has the advantage over pairwise correlation, because it measures the conditional dependency between two taxa given the effect of other taxa being removed or fixed, and reflects direct correlation between taxa and excludes the between-taxon dependency due to other taxa. In addition, variance heterogeneity and non-normality of metagenomic count data make standard correlations invalid (e.g. Pearson correlation). One way to deal with the problem is to use proportion and log-ratio transformations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. However the log-ratio is not defined when there are zeros in the data and approximation methods have to be used.</p>
    <p>In this paper, we propose a nonparametric approach for co-occurrence network construction and subnetwork structure detection. We propose similarity (or distance) measures between taxa derived by adapting distance measures between samples with abundance counts defined in ecology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. We also expand the sparse inverse covariance method to sparse inverse of general similarity matrices for high-order correlation. The performance of our methods are evaluated through simulation and publicly available metagenomic data sets. The proposed methods are efficient for detecting true network structures. Even though the co-occurrence network is just a description analysis from temporal snapshots, it may be informative regarding how microbial taxa function together.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec2">
    <title>Methods</title>
    <p>Given samples with or without associated phenotypes, our goal is to study the connectivity and subnetwork structures of bacteria taxa with human microbiome. The final output from 16S rRNA sequencing of the host’s microflora is an integral, non-negative number of sequencing reads for each taxon. Such reads are the metagenomic counts represented as <disp-formula id="Equ1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ X =\left[ \begin{array}{llll} x_{11} &amp; x_{12} &amp; \ldots &amp; x_{1m} \\ x_{21} &amp; x_{22} &amp; \ldots &amp; x_{2m} \\ \vdots &amp; \vdots &amp; \ddots &amp; \vdots \\ x_{n1} &amp; x_{n2} &amp; \ldots &amp; x_{nm} \end{array} \right]  $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="]" open="[" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>…</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>21</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>…</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>⋱</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>…</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">nm</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
    <p>where X is the count matrix with n samples and m taxa, and <italic>x</italic><sub><italic>ij</italic></sub> denotes the total number of reads of taxon <italic>j</italic> in sample <italic>i</italic>. In case there have been known disease status or clinical conditions (<bold>y</bold>) available, we will also discuss methods for detecting structural variations across clinical conditions. Constructing a human metagenomic network requires several sequential steps: (i) estimating pairwise similarity (or distance) measures between different taxa, (ii) adjacency matrix construction, (iii) network structure (module) detection and differentiated networks. We will discuss each of these steps.</p>
    <sec id="Sec3">
      <title>Pairwise similarity measures</title>
      <p>Correlation coefficients are one type of similarity measures that describe the magnitude and direction of association between two variables. Because metagenomic count data typically have variances that are a function of the mean and are not normally distributed, the usual pairwise correlation (e.g. Pearson correlation coefficient)is not appropriate for network analysis. We use two distribution-free nonparametric correlations for count data. Given two n-dimensional vectors <bold>x</bold> and <bold>y</bold> and their corresponding ranks <bold>R</bold><sub><italic>x</italic></sub> and <bold>R</bold><sub><italic>y</italic></sub>, we have <list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Spearman rank-order correlation: <disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$R (\mathbf{x}, \mathbf{y}) = 1 - \frac{6\sum_{i=1}^{n} (\mathbf{R}_{xi} -\mathbf{R}_{yi})^{2}}{n(n^{2}-1)} $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:munderover accent="false" accentunder="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">xi</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">yi</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula> We will take the average of the scores when multiple elements have the tied ranks.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Kendall’s <italic>τ</italic> rank correlation: <disp-formula id="Equb"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\tau(\mathbf{x}, \mathbf{y})= \frac{\sum_{i&lt; j} \text{sgn}(x_{i} &lt; x_{j}) \text{sgn}(y_{i} &lt; y_{j})}{\sqrt{(T_{0} -T_{1})(T_{0} -T_{2})}}, $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mtext>sgn</mml:mtext><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mtext>sgn</mml:mtext><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_Equb.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula> where <italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub>=<italic>n</italic>(<italic>n</italic>−1)/2, <inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$T_{1} = \sum _{k} t_{k} (t_{k} -1)/2$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$T_{2} = \sum _{l} u_{l} (u_{l}-1)/2$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq2.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. The <italic>t</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> is the number of tied <bold>x</bold> values in the <italic>k</italic>th group of the tied <bold>x</bold> values, <italic>u</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub> is the number of tied <bold>y</bold> values in the <italic>l</italic>th group of tied <bold>y</bold> values, and sign (<italic>z</italic>) is defined as: <disp-formula id="Equc"><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\text{sgn}(z) = \left\{ \begin{array}{rl} 1 &amp; \text{if} \,x_{i} &lt; x_{j}, \\ 0 &amp; \text{if} \,x_{i} = x_{j}, \\ -1 &amp; \text{if} \,x_{i} &gt; x_{j}. \end{array} \right. $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M12"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>sgn</mml:mtext><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="" open="{" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>if</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>if</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>if</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_Equc.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p></list-item></list></p>
      <p>Our similarity matrix <italic>S</italic> can be defined with either <inline-formula id="IEq3"><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$S = \left [\sin \left (\frac {\pi }{2}R\left (\mathbf {x}_{i}, \mathbf {x}_{j}\right)\right)\right ]_{m\times m}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M14"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="]" open="[" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mo>sin</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq3.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> or <inline-formula id="IEq4"><alternatives><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$S = \left [\sin (\frac {\pi }{2}\tau (\mathbf {x}_{i}, \mathbf {x}_{j}))\right ]_{m\times m}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M16"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="]" open="[" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mo>sin</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq4.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Those distribution-free correlations only utilize rank information, and are more robust than the parametric approach. Even though they are slight less efficiency than Pearson correlation under normal distribution, both Spearman and Kendall correlation coefficients provide a good compromise between robustness and efficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>].</p>
      <p>Distance measures are commonly used for quantifying the dissimilarities between samples and visualizing the samples in 2D and 3D [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. They have been modified to measure pairwise similarity between taxa and construct phylogenetic tree recently [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Given two n-dimensional column vectors <bold>x</bold><sub>1</sub> and <bold>x</bold><sub>2</sub> of two taxa, distance measures between taxa can be defined as <list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Hellinger distance: <disp-formula id="Equd"><alternatives><tex-math id="M17">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$D(\mathbf{x}_{1}, \mathbf{x}_{2}) =\sqrt{\sum_{i=1}^{n}\left(\sqrt{\frac{x_{i1}}{\mathbf{x}_{+1}}} -\sqrt{\frac{x_{i2}}{\mathbf{x}_{+2}}}\right)^{2}}, $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M18"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:munderover accent="false" accentunder="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_Equd.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula> where <inline-formula id="IEq5"><alternatives><tex-math id="M19">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\mathbf {x}_{+1} = \sum _{i=1}^{n} x_{i1}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M20"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq5.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula id="IEq6"><alternatives><tex-math id="M21">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\mathbf {x}_{+2} = \sum _{i=1}^{n} x_{i2}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M22"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq6.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The <italic>χ</italic><sup>2</sup> distance: <disp-formula id="Eque"><alternatives><tex-math id="M23">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$D\left(\mathbf{x}_{1}, \mathbf{x}_{2}\right) = \sqrt{\sum_{i=1}^{n} \frac{\left(\mathbf{x}_{+1} + \mathbf{x}_{+2}\right)}{(x_{i1} + x_{i2})} \left(\sqrt{\frac{x_{i1}}{\mathbf{x}_{+1}}} - \sqrt{\frac{x_{i2}}{\mathbf{x}_{+2}}}\right)^{2}}. $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M24"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:munderover accent="false" accentunder="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_Eque.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p></list-item><list-item><p>Bray-Curtis dissimilarity: <disp-formula id="Equf"><alternatives><tex-math id="M25">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$D(\mathbf{x}_{1}, \mathbf{x}_{2}) = 1 - 2 \frac{\sum_{i=1}^{n}\min(x_{i1}, x_{i2}) }{\sum_{i=1}^{n}(x_{i1} + x_{i2})} = 1-2\sum_{i=1}^{n} \frac{\min(x_{i1}, x_{i2}) }{(\mathbf{x}_{+1} + \mathbf{x}_{+2})}. $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M26"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:munderover accent="false" accentunder="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mo>min</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:munderover accent="false" accentunder="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:munderover accent="false" accentunder="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>min</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_Equf.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p></list-item></list></p>
      <p>These distances can be calculated with either raw or relative abundance reads. Even though there is no great difference, we suggest to use relative abundance for sequencing depth adjustment. The relative abundance matrix <italic>P</italic> is computed from the count matrix <italic>X</italic> with <italic>P</italic>= [ <italic>p</italic><sub><italic>ij</italic></sub>]<sub><italic>n</italic>×<italic>m</italic></sub>, where <inline-formula id="IEq7"><alternatives><tex-math id="M27">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$p_{\textit {ij}} = \frac {x_{\textit {ij}}}{\sum _{j=1}^{m} x_{\textit {ij}}}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M28"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq7.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. Based on the distance measures, we define a similarity measure with the popular Gaussion kernel as <disp-formula id="Equg"><alternatives><tex-math id="M29">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$S =\, [\!S_{ij}]_{m\times m}, \qquad \text{where} \qquad S_{ij} = S(\mathbf{x}_{i}, \mathbf{x}_{j}) = e^{-\frac{D^{2}(\mathbf{x}_{i}, \mathbf{x}_{j})}{{\sigma}}}, $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M30"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="2em"/><mml:mtext>where</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="2em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_Equg.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula> where the free parameter <italic>σ</italic> can be estimated by resampling. We set <italic>σ</italic>=1 for all computations in this paper. This distance based similarity matrix <italic>S</italic> is a positive (semi)-definite kernel matrix well studied in machine learning and bioinformatics. The kernel function <inline-formula id="IEq8"><alternatives><tex-math id="M31">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$e^{-\frac {D^{2}(\mathbf {x}_{i}, \mathbf {x}_{j})}{{\sigma }}}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M32"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq8.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> can be treated as an inner product in the high-dimensional feature space, so <italic>S</italic> can be regarded as the covariance matrix in the feature space.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4">
      <title>Similarity to adjacency matrix</title>
      <p>To compensate for noise and measure error, we propose two efficient approaches to determine statistically significant nonzero similarities. Unlike most methods in the literature determining the network structure with an arbitrary threshold of pairwise correlation, we are more interested in studying high order correlations. i.e., how <bold>x</bold><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and <bold>x</bold><sub><italic>j</italic></sub> associate with each other when information about other variables is taken into consideration. Sparse inverse covariance for graph construction was originally proposed for continuous data with the assumption that the observations are from a multivariate Gaussian distribution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. This approach can handle large network efficiently. We extend this method to study the sparse inverse of a general similarity matrix <italic>S</italic><sup>−1</sup>, and evaluate its efficiency using simulation. Unlike <italic>S</italic>, a value zero in any cell of <italic>S</italic><sup>−1</sup> implies conditional independence among those variables. Mathematically <inline-formula id="IEq9"><alternatives><tex-math id="M33">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$S_{\textit {ij}}^{-1} = 0 \Rightarrow P(\mathbf {x}_{i},\mathbf {x}_{j}|\mathbf {x}_{-i, -j}) = 0$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M34"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>⇒</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq9.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, where <bold>x</bold><sub>−<italic>i</italic>,−<italic>j</italic></sub> denotes all the variables other than <bold>x</bold><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and <bold>x</bold><sub><italic>j</italic></sub>. The likelihood estimate of <italic>A</italic>=<italic>S</italic><sup>−1</sup> is <disp-formula id="Equh"><alternatives><tex-math id="M35">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\max_{A\succ 0} L = \log\det A - tr(SA), $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M36"><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>max</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>≻</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:mo>det</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">tr</mml:mtext><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">SA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_Equh.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula> where <italic>t</italic><italic>r</italic>(<italic>S</italic><italic>A</italic>) is the trace of <italic>SA</italic>. Assuming <italic>S</italic> is nonsingular, and taking the first order derivative, we have <italic>A</italic><sup>−1</sup>=<italic>S</italic>. However, it is common that <italic>n</italic>&lt;<italic>m</italic> in metagenomic data, so <italic>S</italic> can be singular. In such case, the following <italic>l</italic><sub>1</sub> penalized error function can be minimized to obtain maximal likelihood estimates: <disp-formula id="Equi"><alternatives><tex-math id="M37">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ \min_{A\succ 0} E = -\log\det A + tr(SA) + {\lambda} ||A||_{1}, $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M38"><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>min</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>≻</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:mo>det</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">tr</mml:mtext><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">SA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_Equi.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula> where <inline-formula id="IEq10"><alternatives><tex-math id="M39">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$||A||_{1} = \sum _{\textit {ij}} |a_{\textit {ij}}|$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M40"><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq10.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the elementwise <italic>l</italic><sub>1</sub> norm for matrix <italic>A</italic>. The sparse structure of A can be estimated directly. This approach follows the framework of block coordinate descent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Mathematically, we partition the matrices <italic>S</italic> and <italic>A</italic> into the following block form: <disp-formula id="Equj"><alternatives><tex-math id="M41">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$S =\left[ \begin{array}{ll} S_{11} &amp; \mathbf{s}_{12} \\ \mathbf{s}_{12}^{T} &amp; s_{22} \end{array}\right]; \qquad \qquad A =\left[ \begin{array}{ll} A_{11} &amp; \mathbf{a}_{12} \\ \mathbf{a}_{12} &amp; a_{22} \end{array}\right], $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M42"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="]" open="[" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="2em"/><mml:mspace width="2em"/><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="]" open="[" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_Equj.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula> where <inline-formula id="IEq11"><alternatives><tex-math id="M43">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$S_{11}, A_{11} \in \mathbb {R}^{(m-1)\times (m-1)}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M44"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℝ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq11.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq12"><alternatives><tex-math id="M45">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\mathbf {s}_{12}, \mathbf {a}_{12} \in \mathbb {R}^{m-1}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M46"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℝ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq12.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula id="IEq13"><alternatives><tex-math id="M47">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$s_{22}. a_{22} \in \mathbb {R}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M48"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>.</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>ℝ</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq13.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. Then we have <disp-formula id="Equk"><alternatives><tex-math id="M49">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{array}{@{}rcl@{}} \log\det A = \log\det \left[A_{11}\left(a_{22} - \mathbf{a}_{12}^{T}A_{11}^{-1}\mathbf{a}_{12}\right)\right] = \log\det A_{11}\, +\, \log \left(a_{22} - \mathbf{a}_{12}^{T}A_{11}^{-1}\mathbf{a}_{12}\right). \end{array} $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M50"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left center right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:mo>det</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:mo>det</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="]" open="[" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:mo>det</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"/><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_Equk.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>So <disp-formula id="Equl"><alternatives><tex-math id="M51">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\min_{A\succ 0} E = -\log\det A_{11} - \log (a_{22} - \mathbf{a}_{12}^{T}A_{11}^{-1}\mathbf{a}_{12}) + tr(SA) + {\lambda} ||A||_{1}. $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M52"><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>min</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>≻</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:mo>det</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:munderover accent="false" accentunder="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:munderover accent="false" accentunder="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">tr</mml:mtext><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">SA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_Equl.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>Assuming <italic>A</italic><sub>11</sub> is fixed and taking the first order derivative for <bold>a</bold><sub>12</sub> and <italic>a</italic><sub>22</sub>, we have the sub-differential of E with respect to <bold>a</bold><sub>12</sub>: <disp-formula id="Equm"><alternatives><tex-math id="M53">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\frac{\partial E}{\partial \mathbf{a}_{12}} = \frac{2}{a_{22} - \mathbf{a}_{12}^{T}A_{11}^{-1}\mathbf{a}_{12}}A_{11}^{-1}\mathbf{a}_{12} + 2\mathbf{s}_{12} + 2{\lambda}\text{sgn}(\mathbf{a}_{12}), $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M54"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mtext>sgn</mml:mtext><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_Equm.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula> where <inline-formula id="IEq14"><alternatives><tex-math id="M55">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\text {sgn}(x) = \frac {\partial |x|}{\partial x}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M56"><mml:mtext>sgn</mml:mtext><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq14.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> for <inline-formula id="IEq15"><alternatives><tex-math id="M57">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$x\in \mathbb {R}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M58"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>ℝ</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq15.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is defined as sgn(<italic>x</italic>)={1 <italic>x</italic>&gt;0,[−1,1] <italic>x</italic>=0,−1 <italic>x</italic>&lt;0.Similarly, since <italic>a</italic><sub>22</sub>&gt;0, the partial derivative of <italic>E</italic> with respect to <italic>a</italic><sub>22</sub>: <disp-formula id="Equn"><alternatives><tex-math id="M59">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\frac{\partial E}{\partial a_{22}}= -\frac{1}{a_{22} - \mathbf{a}_{12}^{T} A_{11}^{-1}\mathbf{a}_{12}} + s_{22} + {\lambda}. $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M60"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ.</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_Equn.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>After finding the derivative, we initialize <italic>A</italic><sup>0</sup>=(<italic>S</italic>+<italic>λ</italic><italic>I</italic>)<sup>−1</sup>, and then use the standard decent gradient algorithm to update each row/column repeatedly until the algorithm converges. After obtaining the sparse A and taking the absolute value <italic>A</italic>=|<italic>A</italic>|, we set the diagonal value of A to zero with <italic>A</italic>=<italic>A</italic>−diag(<italic>A</italic>) to get the final adjacency matrix A. The adjacency matrix <italic>A</italic> is a representation of a graph, where the value of <italic>a</italic><sub><italic>ij</italic></sub> represents the connectivity between taxa <italic>i</italic> and <italic>j</italic>.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec5">
    <title><italic>λ</italic> Determination</title>
    <p>The regularization parameter <italic>λ</italic> controls the number of nonzero estimated links between nodes and the sparsity of the network. The larger the <italic>λ</italic>, the sparser the network. A common approach for determining <italic>λ</italic> is stability selection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. This approach seeks the <italic>λ</italic> leading to the most stable sets of edges. Given data <italic>X</italic>, stability selection first draws <italic>p</italic> sub-samples <italic>X</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>X</italic><sub>2</sub>,…,<italic>X</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub> of size q (1&lt;<italic>q</italic>&lt;<italic>n</italic>), where <inline-formula id="IEq16"><alternatives><tex-math id="M61">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$q =\frac {2}{3}n$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M62"><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq16.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> in this paper, and then estimates one separate network <italic>A</italic><sup><italic>i</italic></sup>(<italic>λ</italic>) for each sub-sample <italic>X</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and a fixed regularization parameter <italic>λ</italic>. Stability selection then defines the average fraction of disagreements over all edges of the sub-sampled graphs as <disp-formula id="Equo"><alternatives><tex-math id="M63">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ D({\lambda}) = \frac{\sum_{j&lt;k}\bar{a}_{jk}({\lambda})(1-\bar{a}_{jk}({\lambda}))}{{p\choose2}}, \;\; \textrm{where }\;\; \bar{a}_{jk} = \frac{1}{p}\sum_{i=1}^{p} a_{jk}^{i}({\lambda}). $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M64"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ā</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">jk</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ā</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">jk</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mfrac linethickness="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="2.77626pt"/><mml:mspace width="2.77626pt"/><mml:mtext>where</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="2.77626pt"/><mml:mspace width="2.77626pt"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ā</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">jk</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munderover accent="false" accentunder="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">jk</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_Equo.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
    <p>The optimal <inline-formula id="IEq17"><alternatives><tex-math id="M65">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\hat {{\lambda }}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M66"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq17.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is then chosen as: <disp-formula id="Equp"><alternatives><tex-math id="M67">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\hat{{\lambda}} = \min\left\{{\lambda}: \max_{0 &lt; t &lt; {\lambda}}D(t) \le \alpha\right\}, \;\;\; \text{where}\;\;\; \alpha = 0.05. $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M68"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>min</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="}" open="{" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>max</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="2.77626pt"/><mml:mspace width="2.77626pt"/><mml:mspace width="2.77626pt"/><mml:mtext>where</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="2.77626pt"/><mml:mspace width="2.77626pt"/><mml:mspace width="2.77626pt"/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.05</mml:mn><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_Equp.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
    <p>Final network is constructed using whole data <italic>X</italic> and <inline-formula id="IEq18"><alternatives><tex-math id="M69">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\hat {{\lambda }}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M70"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq18.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p>
    <sec id="Sec6">
      <title>Network structure detection and differentiated networks</title>
      <p>The problem of subnetwork structure detection requires the partition of a network into communities (subnetworks/modules) of densely connected nodes, while nodes belonging to different communities are sparsely (weakly) connected. Bacterial subnetwork structure detection is very important because we want to know which taxa coexist and function together. One simple approach to accomplish this is modularity function maximization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. The modularity function also measures the quality of a partition and can be used to compare the performance of different partition methods. Given a weighted network with adjacency matrix <italic>A</italic>, to attribute each node to a module <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>, a modularity function can be defined as follows: <disp-formula id="Equq"><alternatives><tex-math id="M71">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ Q = \frac{1}{2w}\sum_{i,j}\left[a_{ij} -\frac{k_{i} k_{j}}{2w}\right ]\delta(c_{i}, c_{j}), $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M72"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mfenced close="]" open="[" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_Equq.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula> where <italic>a</italic><sub><italic>ij</italic></sub> is the weight of an edge between taxa (node) <italic>i</italic> and <italic>j</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq19"><alternatives><tex-math id="M73">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$k_{i} = \sum _{j} a_{\textit {ij}}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M74"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq19.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the sum of the weights of edges attached to taxon i, and <inline-formula id="IEq20"><alternatives><tex-math id="M75">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$w = \frac {1}{2}\sum _{i,j} a_{\textit {ij}}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M76"><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq20.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the total weight. In addition, <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> is the subnetwork (module) to which taxon i is assigned, and the <italic>δ</italic> function <italic>δ</italic>(<italic>u</italic>,<italic>v</italic>)=1 if <italic>u</italic>=<italic>v</italic> and 0 otherwise. Obviously, −1≤<italic>Q</italic>≤1 and the larger Q indicates better separation in subnetworks. The subnetwork partition algorithms are designed for maximizing Q. We adopt the two-step iterative local greedy approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>] in this paper. Unlike K-means or hierarchical clustering, this two-step algorithm automatically determines the number of network modules (clusters) without predefining.</p>
      <p>Given metagenomic data from different clinical conditions or different times, we construct a network with similarity <italic>S</italic><sup><italic>i</italic></sup> and adjacency matrix <italic>A</italic><sup><italic>i</italic></sup> for clinical condition or time i. We are interested in knowing wether the network structures of a subset of taxa have changed from one clinical condition (time) to another. We may define network statistics to measure the network structure changes either with the similarity matrix <italic>S</italic> or the adjacency matrix <italic>A</italic>. Given two networks <italic>A</italic><sup>1</sup> (<italic>S</italic><sup>1</sup>) and <italic>A</italic><sup>2</sup> (<italic>S</italic><sup>2</sup>), our first network statistic is defined by the following mean absolute distance (MAD): <disp-formula id="Equr"><alternatives><tex-math id="M77">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\Delta(A) = \frac{1}{m(m-1)}\sum_{i&lt;j&lt;m}|a^{1}_{ij} - a^{2}_{ij}|, \; \text{or} \; \Delta(S) = \frac{1}{m(m-1)}\sum_{i&lt;j&lt;m}|s^{1}_{ij} - s^{2}_{ij}|, $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M78"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="2.77626pt"/><mml:mtext>or</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="2.77626pt"/><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_Equr.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula> where <inline-formula id="IEq21"><alternatives><tex-math id="M79">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$a^{1}_{\textit {ij}}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M80"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq21.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq22"><alternatives><tex-math id="M81">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$a_{\textit {ij}}^{2}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M82"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq22.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> are the interaction score between taxa <italic>i</italic> and <italic>j</italic> in network 1 and 2. The networks are considered to be significantly different if the value of <italic>Δ</italic>(<italic>A</italic>) or <italic>Δ</italic>(<italic>S</italic>) is large. Permutation tests can be used to estimate the <italic>P</italic>-value. Exact permutation test will be used when the sample size is small (&lt;100), otherwise, the number of permutations used will be <italic>L</italic>=100, 000. We first permutate the original data <italic>L</italic> times and compute the <italic>Δ</italic>(<italic>A</italic>,<italic>π</italic>) or <italic>Δ</italic>(<italic>S</italic>,<italic>π</italic>) for each permutation <italic>π</italic>, the <italic>P</italic>-value corresponding to <italic>Δ</italic>(<italic>A</italic>) or <italic>Δ</italic>(<italic>S</italic>) can be computed as: <disp-formula id="Equs"><alternatives><tex-math id="M83">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$P(\Delta(A)) = \frac{1}{L} \sum_{\pi}I(\Delta(A,\pi)\ge \Delta(A)), \textrm{or }\, P(\Delta(S)) = \frac{1}{L} \sum_{\pi}I(\Delta(S,\pi)\ge \Delta(S)), $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M84"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>or</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_Equs.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula> where <italic>I</italic>(<italic>x</italic>)=1 if <italic>x</italic> is true and 0 otherwise, and <disp-formula id="Equt"><alternatives><tex-math id="M85">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\Delta(A, \pi) = \frac{1}{m(m-1)}\sum_{i&lt;j&lt; m}\left|a^{\pi, 1}_{ij} - a^{\pi, 2}_{ij}\right|, \text{or} \, \Delta(S, \pi) = \frac{1}{m(m-1)}\sum_{i&lt;j&lt; m}\left|s^{\pi, 1}_{ij} - s^{\pi, 2}_{ij}\right|. $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M86"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>or</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_Equt.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec7">
      <title>MetaNet package</title>
      <p>MetaNet toolbox in MATLAB was implemented to construct sparse network from metagenomic count data. The toolbox was tested under MATLAB 2013a, but should also work on the later versions of MATLAB. Implemented functions in this toolbox include several similarity (distance) measures, simulated distributions and network models, sparse inverse covariance estimation, network structure detection and differential networks, and network visualization. The goal of this distribution is to provide an easy-to-use tool for network construction and analysis. Although the package is till under development, the users can construct, analyze, and visualize a network from their own data without much difficulty. MetaNet is provided as is without warranty of any kind. More information and the toolbox can be downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biostatistics.csmc.edu/MetaNet/">http://biostatistics.csmc.edu/MetaNet/</ext-link>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec8">
      <title>Data sets</title>
      <sec id="Sec9">
        <title>Simulated data</title>
        <p>Simulated count data with different numbers of nodes and sample sizes are generated from a negative binomial (NB) distribution. More specifically, the data sets are generated from a NB distribution <italic>X</italic><sub><italic>ij</italic></sub>∼<italic>N</italic><italic>B</italic>(<italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>ij</italic></sub>,<italic>γ</italic>) with mean <italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>ij</italic></sub> and dispersion parameter <italic>γ</italic>, and <inline-formula id="IEq23"><alternatives><tex-math id="M87">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\log ({\lambda }_{i})$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M88"><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq23.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is from a multivariate distribution <inline-formula id="IEq24"><alternatives><tex-math id="M89">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\log ({\lambda }_{i}) \sim N(\mu, \Sigma)$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M90"><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∼</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>Σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq24.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> with mean <italic>μ</italic> and covariance matrix <italic>Σ</italic>. The graphical structures are constructed through <italic>A</italic>=<italic>Σ</italic><sup>−1</sup>, where A is an adjacency matrix with additional diagonal elements <inline-formula id="IEq25"><alternatives><tex-math id="M91">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$a_{\textit {ii}}=\sum _{j, i\neq j} a_{\textit {ij}}+1$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M92"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ii</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>≠</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq25.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <italic>i</italic>=1,…,<italic>n</italic>. The adjacency matrices are generated using three different models include small world, scale free, and range dependent networks. The small world network we use only allows a node to connect with its neighborhood node, while the scale-free network has the number of nodes of degree 2 following a power law, and the range dependent network has an edge between nodes <italic>i</italic> and <italic>j</italic> with probability 0.9.0.3<sup>|<italic>j</italic>−<italic>i</italic>|−1</sup>. These three networks are known to mimic the behavior of real biological networks. All count data sets in this paper are generated by setting <italic>μ</italic>=3 and the overdispersion parameter <italic>γ</italic>=2.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec10">
        <title>Real metagenomic data from body habitats</title>
        <p>The real data was collected from six body habitats including external auditory canal (EAC), gut, hair, nostril, oral cavity, and skin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. The objective of the original study was to estimate the microbial community composition and detect the differentiation in abundance among body habitats. A total of 815 samples were collected for 6 categories of habitat. Networks were constructed from gut, oral cavity (OC), and skin samples with the sample sizes of 45, 54, and 612 respectively. There were total 1713 taxa at the genus level.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec11" sec-type="results">
    <title>Results</title>
    <sec id="Sec12">
      <title>Results with simulation data</title>
      <p>The proposed approaches were first evaluated using simulated count data. Given the number of nodes <italic>n</italic>=20 and sample sizes of <italic>m</italic>=500, we simulated the count data with known network structures. The predicted adjacency matrix was then estimated with the inverse of similarity matrix. The regularized parameter <italic>λ</italic> was chosen via stability selection. Computational results with different similarity measures and graphic models are given in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Simulated networks. Results from simulation data with three network structures: <italic>Top</italic> panel: three different network structures; <italic>Bottom</italic> panel: predicted AUCs for each simulated network</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_72_Fig1_HTML" id="d30e4484"/></fig></p>
      <p>The proposed similarity or dissimilarity measures including Spearman correlation coefficients, Hellinger, and Bray-Curtis performed well to detect the true structures as shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. The area under ROC curves (AUC) was used to evaluate the performance of detecting proposed network structures, where the specificity for a network measures the proportion of no edges that are correctly detected, while the sensitivity for a network is the proportion of edges that are correctly identified. With the optimal <italic>λ</italic><sup>∗</sup>=0.2,0.55, and 0.65 for Spearman, Hellinger, and Bray-Curtis, we have the predicted AUCs of 0.91, 0.96, and 0.92 respectively with the small world network. The Bay-Curtis distance performed the best, while the other two measures also performed well (≥0.91). Similarly, our proposed approach also performed reasonable well with both scale-free and range dependent networks. We achieved the best predicted AUC of 0.851 and 0.902 with Hellinger distance and <italic>λ</italic><sup>∗</sup>=0.6 and 0.45 respectively for scale-free and range dependent networks. Overall Spearman has the lowest predicted AUCs for all models with the negative binomial simulated data as shown on the bottom of Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, but the differences among all measures are not very significant.</p>
      <p>To further evaluate the performance of the method for large networks with small sample sizes and different similarity measures, Small world, scale free, and range dependent networks with 500 nodes and the sample size of 50,100, and 200 respectively are used for data simulation. The count data are generated from Poisson distribution with <italic>μ</italic>=3. We repeated the computational experiments 50 times, the average AUC and their standard deviations with different similarity measures are reported in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Predicted AUCs with different network structures and sample sizes for large networks with 500 nodes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th><th align="left">Similarity</th><th align="left">Small world</th><th align="left">Scale-free</th><th align="left">Range-dependent</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">Spearman</td><td align="center">0.909 (±.015)</td><td align="center">0.930 (±.035)</td><td align="center">0.730 (±.021)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"/><td align="center">Bray-Curtis</td><td align="center">0.894 (±.014)</td><td align="center">0.786 (±.017)</td><td align="center">0.693 (±.016)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"/><td align="center">Hellinger</td><td align="center">0.936 (±.018)</td><td align="center">0.844 (±.019)</td><td align="center">0.709 (±.015)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">100</td><td align="center">Spearman</td><td align="center">0.982 (±.009)</td><td align="center">0.972 (±.020)</td><td align="center">0.849 (±.014)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"/><td align="center">Bray-Curtis</td><td align="center">0.975 (±.011)</td><td align="center">0.820 (±.016)</td><td align="center">0.794 (±.019)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"/><td align="center">Hellinger</td><td align="center">0.986 (±.016)</td><td align="center">0.883 (±.013)</td><td align="center">0.812 (±.011)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">200</td><td align="center">Spearman</td><td align="center">0.999 (±.012)</td><td align="center">0.994 (±.015)</td><td align="center">0.872 (±.015)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"/><td align="center">Bray-Curtis</td><td align="center">0.996 (±.009)</td><td align="center">0.864 (±0.014)</td><td align="center">0.828 (±.018)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"/><td align="center">Hellinger</td><td align="center">0.998 (±.006)</td><td align="center">0.944 (±.012)</td><td align="center">0.846 (±.015)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
      <p>Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> indicates that the predicted AUCs increase and the performance gets better as the sample size increases. The proposed method performs reasonable well for different network structures. While Hellinger distance achieves the best result in small-world network, Spearman’s rank correlation has the best performance with scale-free and range dependent networks. Therefore, Spearman’s rank correlation is more robust with large networks generated from Poisson distribution, even though differences among different similarity measures are not always statistically significant.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec13">
      <title>Results with real body habitats data</title>
      <p>There were 59 genera left for network construction after discarding genera with average abundance of less than two reads. We first calculated the similarity matrices from Spearman correlation coefficient, Hellinger, and Bray-Curtis distances respectively, and then determined the adjacency matrices with sparse inverse of the similarity matrices. The optimal <italic>λ</italic>s for Spearman, Hellinger, and Bray-Curtis were then determined with stability selection. To further reduce the false-positive rate, the final adjacency matrix <italic>A</italic> was determined by the common edges of three different adjacency matrices. For comparison purpose, we also constructed a common network with all the samples from different habitats. Exact permutation test was used to compare networks constructed from gut, oral cavity, and skin with the common network. The differentiated network structures for skin, gut, and oral cavity were detected with a permutation <italic>P</italic> value of 0.05. Subnetwork structures were then identified with modularity maximization. Bacteria networks unique for skin, gut, and oral cavity are shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Differentiated networks for Skin (I), Gut (II), and OC (III)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_72_Fig2_HTML" id="d30e4707"/></fig></p>
      <p>Different colors of the nodes indicate different network modules, and the node size represents relative abundance: The larger the nodes, the higher the relative abundance of a genera. The edges indicate the direct coexistence (co-occurrence) between two genera. The skin subnetwork on the top panel of Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> has 4 modules colored in green, blue, orange, and red with 6, 6, 2, and 2 genera respectively. Several genera on the network are known to cause skin infections. For instance, <italic>Streptococcus</italic> on the green module is a well-known bacteria directly related to several skin infections including Impetigo, Cellulitis, and Erysipelas. <italic>Actinomcyes</italic> genus causes a chronic (slowly progressive) infection named Actinomycosis, and Fusobacterium genus has been known to cause tropical phagedenic ulcer (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dermnetnz.org/bacterial/">http://dermnetnz.org/bacterial/</ext-link>). More interestingly, the direct association of <italic>Actinomcyes</italic> and <italic>Fusobacterium</italic> on the green module was verified by a recent study experimentally [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. The mixture and co-infection of two bacteria genera cause mastoiditis. In addition, <italic>Pasteurella</italic> genus has also been shown to cause skin disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Other genera directly connected to <italic>Pasteurella</italic> including <italic>Rothia, Granulicatella, Gemella</italic>, and <italic>Haemophilus</italic> may function together biologically and clinically through ‘guilt by association’. Even though the co-occurrences among genera are only verified statistically, their biological and medical implications need to be further validated in a wet lab, our methods provide a guidance for investigators in their research.</p>
      <p>The gut network constructed with 45 samples is shown in the bottom left panel (II) of Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. Two modules colored with green and yellow respectively are identified, each of them with 4 genera. All 4 high abundance genera and their interactions on the green module are associated with gut related diseases. <italic>Faecalibacterium</italic> and <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic> genera are both associated with type 2 diabetics and obeisity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Another recently study also indicates that <italic>Blautia</italic> and <italic>Faecalibacterium</italic> vary together during antibiotic therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>], and it has been shown that both <italic>Roseburia</italic> and <italic>Faecalibacterium</italic> have lower abundance in patients with Crohn’s Disease compared with their healthy siblings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. All these studies support our results that <italic>Faecalibacterium, Blautia, Roseburia</italic>, and <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic> interact with each other. However, interactions among the 4 genera (<italic>Subdoligranulum, Coprococcus, Anaerotruncus</italic>, and <italic>Oscillibacter</italic>) with lower abundance in the yellow module have not been well studied, even though individual genus has been reported in recent literature.</p>
      <p>Bacteria genera in oral cavity (OC) play a key role in mouth infections and periodontal diseases. Oral cavity network built with genera from 54 oral cavity samples is shown in the bottom right panel (III) of Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. Three modules colored with green, red, and yellow were identified with 2, 2, and 3 genera on each subnetwork. Interactions and co-occurrences are identified among both high abundance genera (<italic>Fusobacterium, Veillonella</italic>, Neisseria, Prevotella) and low abundance genera (Atopobium, and Megasphaera) in OC. Genera such as Fusobacterium, Neisseria, Porphyromonas, and <italic>Prevotella</italic> have been known to be significantly different in abundance with different clinical conditions and disease status [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. The co-occurrences between <italic>Porphyromonas</italic> and <italic>Fusobacterium</italic> on the yellow module has been verified through a mouse model experimentally [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. However, co-occurrences among <italic>Fusobacterium, Porphyromonas</italic>, and <italic>Neisseria</italic> together have not been explored. One interesting finding is the common interactions between <italic>Prevotella</italic> and <italic>Veillonella</italic> and between <italic>Megasphaera</italic> and <italic>Atopobium</italic> in the oral cavity and skin, indicating that some interactions and co-occurrences may be shared at different body habitats. Therefore, co-occurrence network analysis with proposed approach is useful for determining novel biological interactions that may help to decipher the structure of complex microbial communities. It is also useful for systematically exploring co-existence patterns in big metegenomics data that standard tools may fail to detect.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec14" sec-type="conclusion">
    <title>Conclusions</title>
    <p>We have developed a systematic approach for constructing networks and detecting subnetwork structures with metagenomic count data. Our contributions are in two areas: (1) we adapt distance measures between samples from ecology to compute similarity between taxa, and (2) we extend sparse inverse covariance methods for Gaussian models to determine high-order interactions with general similarity matrices. Based on both simulated and real data, our method can identify true and biologically important interactions and associations with limited computational experiments. One advantage of our approach is that it detects the partial (high-order) correlations among the taxa. Unlike pairwise correlation, partial correlation measures the conditional dependency between two taxa given the effect of rest taxa being removed or fixed. Therefore, networks constructed from partial correlation usually have lower false positive connections than those from pairwise correlation. In addition, modularity function maximization for structure detection in MetaNet automatically determines the number of network clusters, while other popular approaches such as K-means and hierarchical clustering require the number of clusters or a cutoff point to be predefined. Even though MetaNet is slightly computational intensive when comparing to the popular pairwise approach, it only takes minutes to construct a network with thousands of nodes. While our method has been developed for 16S rRNA sequencing data from human body, it can be applied to 16S sequencing data from other organisms. It may also be used to analyze whole metagenomic shotgun sequencing or RNA-seq, as long as the sequences are properly aligned. Note that our method constructs networks solely based on their statistical similarity or dissimilarity among taxa, the biological significance of the results has to be further validated in a web lab. Future works wledge and pathway information into our network constructions.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec15">
    <title>Appendix: network statistics</title>
    <p>Given the adjacency matrix <italic>A</italic> and the their subnetworks, different statistics has been defined to describe the network and taxa. The most important network statistics are [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]: <list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Degree: number of links connected to a taxon (node) i, <inline-formula id="IEq26"><alternatives><tex-math id="M93">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$k_{i} = \sum _{j} a_{\textit {ij}}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M94"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq26.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Number of triangles around a taxon i: <inline-formula id="IEq27"><alternatives><tex-math id="M95">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$T_{i} = \frac {1}{2} \sum _{j,k}a_{\textit {ij}}a_{\textit {ik}}a_{\textit {jk}}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M96"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ik</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">jk</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq27.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Clustering coefficient: Measuring the segregation of a network, <inline-formula id="IEq28"><alternatives><tex-math id="M97">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$C = \frac {1}{m}\sum _{i}C_{i} = \frac {1}{m}\sum _{i}\frac {2T_{i}}{K_{i}(K_{i}-1)}.$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M98"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq28.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></p></list-item><list-item><p>Participation coefficient of taxon i, <inline-formula id="IEq29"><alternatives><tex-math id="M99">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$Y_{i} = 1 - \sum _{m\in M}\left (\frac {K_{i}(m)}{K_{i}}\right)^{2}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M100"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13040_2015_Article_72_TeX2GIF_IEq29.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, where <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>(<italic>m</italic>) is the within-module degree of taxon i in module <italic>m</italic>.</p></list-item></list></p>
    <p>We will apply network statistics to rank the bacteria taxa. The larger the network statistics, the stronger connectivity the taxa, and the more important the taxa statistically. The biological importance of those taxa with larger network statistics can be further validated in the lab.</p>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <fn-group>
    <fn>
      <p>
        <bold>Competing interests</bold>
      </p>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
    </fn>
    <fn>
      <p>
        <bold>Authors’ contributions</bold>
      </p>
      <p>ZL conceptualized and designed method, developed the software, and wrote the manuscript. SL and SP helped in method design and manuscript writing and revised the manuscript critically. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
    </fn>
  </fn-group>
  <ack>
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <p>We thank the Associate Editor and anonymous referees for their constructive comments. This work was partially supported by the National Science Foundation (NSF) grants DMS-222381 (ZL) and DMS-1220772 (SL).</p>
  </ack>
  <ref-list id="Bib1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="CR1">
      <label>1</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Turnbaugh</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ley</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hamady</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fraser-Liggett</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Knight</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gordon</surname>
            <given-names>JI</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The human microbiome project</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <year>2007</year>
        <volume>449</volume>
        <fpage>804</fpage>
        <lpage>10</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature06244</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 17943116?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17943116</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR2">
      <label>2</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mande</surname>
            <given-names>SS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mohammed</surname>
            <given-names>MH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ghosh</surname>
            <given-names>TS</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Classification of metagenomic sequences: methods and challenges</article-title>
        <source>Brief Bioinform</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>13</volume>
        <issue>6</issue>
        <fpage>669</fpage>
        <lpage>81</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bib/bbs054</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 22962338?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22962338</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR3">
      <label>3</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Keller</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Horn</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Förster</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schultz</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Computational integration of genomic traits into 16S rDNA microbiota sequencing studies</article-title>
        <source>Gene</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>549</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>186</fpage>
        <lpage>91</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2014.07.066</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25084126?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25084126</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR4">
      <label>4</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wooley</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Godzik</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Friedberg</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A primer on metagenomics</article-title>
        <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <fpage>e1000667</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000667</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 20195499?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20195499</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR5">
      <label>5</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Huson</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Auch</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Qi</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schuster</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Megan analysis of metagenomic data</article-title>
        <source>Genome Res</source>
        <year>2007</year>
        <volume>17</volume>
        <fpage>377</fpage>
        <lpage>86</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.5969107</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 17255551?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17255551</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR6">
      <label>6</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Schloss</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Westcott</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ryabin</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hall</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hartmann</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hollister</surname>
            <given-names>EB</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Introducing mothur: opensource, platform-independent, community-supported software for describing and comparing microbial communities</article-title>
        <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>75</volume>
        <fpage>7537</fpage>
        <lpage>41</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.01541-09</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 19801464?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19801464</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR7">
      <label>7</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lozupone</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lladser</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Knights</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stombaugh</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Knight</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Unifrac: an effective distance metric for microbial community comparison</article-title>
        <source>ISME J</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>5</volume>
        <fpage>169172</fpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR8">
      <label>8</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Caporaso</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kuczynski</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stombaugh</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bittinger</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bushman</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Costello</surname>
            <given-names>EK</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Qiime allows analysis of high-throughput community sequencing data</article-title>
        <source>Nat Methods</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <fpage>335</fpage>
        <lpage>36</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.f.303</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 20383131?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20383131</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR9">
      <label>9</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Quast</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pruesse</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yilmaz</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gerken</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schweer</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yarza</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The SILVA ribosomal RNA gene data base project: improved data processing and web-based tools</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>41</volume>
        <issue>D1</issue>
        <fpage>D590</fpage>
        <lpage>96</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gks1219</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 23193283?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23193283</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR10">
      <label>10</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Huson</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mitra</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Weber</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ruscheweyh</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schuster</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Integrative analysis of environmental sequences using megan4</article-title>
        <source>Genome Res</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>21</volume>
        <fpage>1552</fpage>
        <lpage>60</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.120618.111</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 21690186?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21690186</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR11">
      <label>11</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Brady</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Salzberg</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Phymm and phymmbl: metagenomic phylogenetic classification with interpolated markov models</article-title>
        <source>Nat Methods</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <fpage>673</fpage>
        <lpage>76</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1358</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 19648916?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19648916</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR12">
      <label>12</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rosen</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Reichenberger</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rosenfeld</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Nbc: the naive bayes classification tool webserver for taxonomic classification of metagenomic reads</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>27</volume>
        <fpage>127</fpage>
        <lpage>29</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq619</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 21062764?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21062764</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR13">
      <label>13</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>White</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nagarajan</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pop</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Statistical methods for detecting differentially abundant features in clinical metagenomic samples</article-title>
        <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>5</volume>
        <fpage>1000352</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000352</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR14">
      <label>14</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hsiao</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cantarel</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Drbek</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fraser-Liggett</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Sparse distance-based learning for simultaneous multiclass classification and feature selection of metagenomic data</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>27</volume>
        <issue>23</issue>
        <fpage>3242</fpage>
        <lpage>49</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr547</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 21984758?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21984758</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR15">
      <label>15</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gevers</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kugathasan</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Denson</surname>
            <given-names>LA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vázquez-Baeza</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Van Treuren</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ren</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The treatment-naive microbiome in new-onset Crohn’s disease</article-title>
        <source>Cell Host Microbe</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>15</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <fpage>382</fpage>
        <lpage>92</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2014.02.005</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24629344?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24629344</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR16">
      <label>16</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Boutin</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bernatchez</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Audet</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Derôme</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Network analysis highlights complex interactions between pathogen, host and commensal microbiota</article-title>
        <source>PLoS One</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <issue>12</issue>
        <fpage>e84772</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0084772</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24376845?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24376845</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR17">
      <label>17</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hurwitz</surname>
            <given-names>BL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Westveld</surname>
            <given-names>AH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Brum</surname>
            <given-names>JR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sullivan</surname>
            <given-names>MB</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Modeling ecological drivers in marine viral communities using comparative metagenomics and network analyses</article-title>
        <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>111</volume>
        <issue>29</issue>
        <fpage>10714</fpage>
        <lpage>9</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1319778111</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25002514?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25002514</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR18">
      <label>18</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Braun</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McGovern</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Piantadosi</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Multilevel Regularized Regression for Simultaneous Taxa Selection and Network Construction with Metagenomic Count Data</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>31</volume>
        <issue>7</issue>
        <fpage>1067</fpage>
        <lpage>74</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu778</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25416747?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25416747</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR19">
      <label>19</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Horvath</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dong</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Geometric interpretation of gene coexpression network analysis</article-title>
        <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <issue>8</issue>
        <fpage>e1000117</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000117</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 18704157?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18704157</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR20">
      <label>20</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Barabási</surname>
            <given-names>AL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Oltvai</surname>
            <given-names>ZN</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Network biology: understanding the cell’s functional organization</article-title>
        <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>
        <year>2004</year>
        <volume>5</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <fpage>101</fpage>
        <lpage>13</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg1272</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 14735121?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14735121</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR21">
      <label>21</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Krämer</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schäfer</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Boulesteix</surname>
            <given-names>AL</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Regularized estimation of large-scale gene association networks using graphical Gaussian models</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <fpage>384</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-10-384</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 19930695?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19930695</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR22">
      <label>22</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Stelling</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Klamt</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bettenbrock</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schuster</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gilles</surname>
            <given-names>ED</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Metabolic network structure determines key aspects of functionality and regulation</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <year>2002</year>
        <volume>420</volume>
        <issue>6912</issue>
        <fpage>190</fpage>
        <lpage>3</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature01166</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 12432396?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12432396</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR23">
      <label>23</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Guimera</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nunes Amaral</surname>
            <given-names>LA</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Functional cartography of complex metabolic networks</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <year>2005</year>
        <volume>433</volume>
        <issue>7028</issue>
        <fpage>895</fpage>
        <lpage>900</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature03288</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 15729348?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15729348</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR24">
      <label>24</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kreimer</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Borenstein</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gophna</surname>
            <given-names>U</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ruppin</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The evolution of modularity in bacterial metabolic networks</article-title>
        <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>105</volume>
        <issue>19</issue>
        <fpage>6976</fpage>
        <lpage>81</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0712149105</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 18460604?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18460604</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR25">
      <label>25</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gerstein</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Snyder</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>RNA-Seq: a revolutionary tool for transcriptomics</article-title>
        <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>57</fpage>
        <lpage>63</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg2484</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 19015660?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19015660</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR26">
      <label>26</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Allen</surname>
            <given-names>GI</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A Local Poisson Graphical Model for inferring networks from sequencing data</article-title>
        <source>IEEE Trans Nanobioscience</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <fpage>189</fpage>
        <lpage>98</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TNB.2013.2263838</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 23955777?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23955777</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR27">
      <label>27</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mallick</surname>
            <given-names>BK</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Inferring gene networks from discrete expression data</article-title>
        <source>Biostatistics</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>14</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <fpage>708</fpage>
        <lpage>22</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/biostatistics/kxt021</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 23873894?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23873894</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR28">
      <label>28</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Faust</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Raes</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Microbial interactions: from networks to models</article-title>
        <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <issue>8</issue>
        <fpage>538</fpage>
        <lpage>50</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro2832</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 22796884?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22796884</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR29">
      <label>29</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Barberán</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bates</surname>
            <given-names>ST</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Casamayor</surname>
            <given-names>EO</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fierer</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Using network analysis to explore co-occurrence patterns in soil microbial communities</article-title>
        <source>ISME J</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <fpage>343</fpage>
        <lpage>51</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ismej.2011.119</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 21900968?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21900968</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR30">
      <label>30</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>McMurdie</surname>
            <given-names>PJ</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Holmes S. phyloseq: an R package for reproducible interactive analysis and graphics of microbiome census data</article-title>
        <source>PLoS One</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <fpage>e61217</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061217</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 23630581?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23630581</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR31">
      <label>31</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Oberauner</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zachow</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lackner</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Högenauer</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Smolle</surname>
            <given-names>KH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Berg</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The ignored diversity: complex bacterial communities in intensive care units revealed by 16S pyrosequencing</article-title>
        <source>Sci Rep</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>3</volume>
        <fpage>1413</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep01413</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 23475210?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23475210</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR32">
      <label>32</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lozupone</surname>
            <given-names>CA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stombaugh</surname>
            <given-names>JI</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gordon</surname>
            <given-names>JI</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jansson</surname>
            <given-names>JK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Knight</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Diversity, stability and resilience of the human gut microbiota</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>489</volume>
        <issue>7415</issue>
        <fpage>220</fpage>
        <lpage>30</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11550</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22972295</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR33">
      <label>33</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Friedman</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Alm</surname>
            <given-names>EJ</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Inferring correlation networks from genomic survey data</article-title>
        <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <issue>9</issue>
        <fpage>e1002687</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002687</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 23028285?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23028285</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR34">
      <label>34</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Clarke</surname>
            <given-names>KR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Somerfield</surname>
            <given-names>PJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chapman</surname>
            <given-names>MG</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>On resemblance measures for ecological studies, including taxonomic dissimilarities and a zero-adjusted Bray-Curtis coefficient for denuded assemblages</article-title>
        <source>J Exp Mar Biol Ecol</source>
        <year>2006</year>
        <volume>330</volume>
        <fpage>55</fpage>
        <lpage>80</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jembe.2005.12.017</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR35">
      <label>35</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Liu H, Han F, Yuan M, Lafferty J, Wasserman L. High dimensional semiparametric gaussian copula graphical models. 2012. Technical report, Johns Hopkins University.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR36">
      <label>36</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Croux</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dehon</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Influence functions of the Spearman and Kendall Correlation measures</article-title>
        <source>Stat Methods Appl</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>19</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <fpage>497</fpage>
        <lpage>515</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10260-010-0142-z</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR37">
      <label>37</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Legendre</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gallagher</surname>
            <given-names>ED</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Ecologically meaningful transformations for ordination of species data</article-title>
        <source>Oecologia</source>
        <year>2001</year>
        <volume>129</volume>
        <fpage>271</fpage>
        <lpage>80</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004420100716</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR38">
      <label>38</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mitra</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gilbert</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Field</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huson</surname>
            <given-names>DH</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Comparison of multiple metagenomes using phylogenetic networks based on ecological indices</article-title>
        <source>ISME J</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <fpage>1236</fpage>
        <lpage>42</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ismej.2010.51</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 20428222?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20428222</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR39">
      <label>39</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Parks</surname>
            <given-names>DH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Beiko</surname>
            <given-names>RG</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Measuring community similarity with phylogenetic networks</article-title>
        <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>29</volume>
        <issue>12</issue>
        <fpage>3947</fpage>
        <lpage>58</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/mss200</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 22915830?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22915830</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR40">
      <label>40</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Friedman</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hastie</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tibshirani</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Sparse inverse covariance estimation with the graphical lasso</article-title>
        <source>Biostatistics</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <fpage>432</fpage>
        <lpage>41</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/biostatistics/kxm045</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 18079126?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18079126</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR41">
      <label>41</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Banerjee</surname>
            <given-names>O</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>El Ghaoui</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Model selection through sparse maximum likelihood estimation for multivariate gaussian or binary data</article-title>
        <source>J. Mach. Learn. Res</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <fpage>485</fpage>
        <lpage>516</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR42">
      <label>42</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Liu H, Roeder K, Wasserman L. Stability approach to regularization selection for high dimensional graphical models. Advances Neural Inf Process Syst. 2010;:1432–1440.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR43">
      <label>43</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Meinshausen</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bühlmann</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Stability selection</article-title>
        <source>JR Stat Soc Series B Stat Methodol</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>72</volume>
        <fpage>417</fpage>
        <lpage>73</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-9868.2010.00740.x</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR44">
      <label>44</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Blondel</surname>
            <given-names>VD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Guillaume</surname>
            <given-names>JL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lambiotte</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lefebvre</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Fast unfolding of communities in large networks</article-title>
        <source>J Stat Mech Theory Exp</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <fpage>P10008</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1742-5468/2008/10/P10008</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR45">
      <label>45</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Newman</surname>
            <given-names>ME</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Finding community structure in networks using the eigenvectors of matrices</article-title>
        <source>Phys Rev E Stat Nonlin Soft Matter Phys</source>
        <year>2006</year>
        <volume>74</volume>
        <issue>3 Pt 2</issue>
        <fpage>036104</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevE.74.036104</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 17025705?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17025705</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR46">
      <label>46</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Costello</surname>
            <given-names>EK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lauber</surname>
            <given-names>CL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hamady</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fierer</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gordon</surname>
            <given-names>JI</given-names>
          </name>
          <collab>Knight R</collab>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Bacterial community variation in human body habitats across space and time</article-title>
        <source>Science</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>326</volume>
        <fpage>1694</fpage>
        <lpage>97</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1177486</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 19892944?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19892944</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR47">
      <label>47</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Salipante</surname>
            <given-names>SJ1</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hoogestraat</surname>
            <given-names>DR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Abbott</surname>
            <given-names>AN</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sengupta</surname>
            <given-names>DJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cummings</surname>
            <given-names>LA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Butler-Wu</surname>
            <given-names>SM</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Co-infection of Fusobacterium nucleatum and Actinomyces israelii in mastoiditis diagnosed by next-generation DNA sequencing</article-title>
        <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>52</volume>
        <issue>5</issue>
        <fpage>1789</fpage>
        <lpage>92</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.03133-13</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24574281?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24574281</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR48">
      <label>48</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hazelton</surname>
            <given-names>BJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Axt</surname>
            <given-names>MW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jones</surname>
            <given-names>CA</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Pasteurella canis osteoarticular infections in childhood: review of bone and joint infections due to pasteurella species over 10 years at a tertiary pediatric hospital and in the literature</article-title>
        <source>J Pediatr Orthop</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>33</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <fpage>e34</fpage>
        <lpage>8</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/BPO.0b013e318287ffe6</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 23482278?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23482278</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR49">
      <label>49</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Remely</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Aumueller</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jahn</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hippe</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Brath</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Haslberger</surname>
            <given-names>AG</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Microbiota and epigenetic regulation of inflammatory mediators in type 2 diabetes and obesity</article-title>
        <source>Benef Microbes</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>5</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>33</fpage>
        <lpage>43</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3920/BM2013.006</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24533976?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24533976</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR50">
      <label>50</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ferrer</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Martins Dos</surname>
            <given-names>Santos</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ott</surname>
            <given-names>SJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Moya</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Gut microbiota disturbance during antibiotic therapy: A multi-omic approach</article-title>
        <source>Gut Microbes</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>5</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>64</fpage>
        <lpage>70</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/gmic.27128</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24418972?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24418972</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR51">
      <label>51</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hedin CR, McCarthy NE, Louis P, Farquharson FM, McCartney S, Taylor K, et al. Altered intestinal microbiota and blood T cell phenotype are shared by patients with Crohn’s disease and their unaffected siblings. Gut. 2014. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/gutjnl-2013-306226">10.1136/gutjnl-2013-306226</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR52">
      <label>52</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sassone</surname>
            <given-names>LM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fidel</surname>
            <given-names>RA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Faveri</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Figueiredo</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fidel</surname>
            <given-names>SR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Feres</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A microbiological profile of unexposed and exposed pulp space of primary endodontic infections by checkerboard DNA-DNA hybridization</article-title>
        <source>J Endod</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>38</volume>
        <issue>7</issue>
        <fpage>889</fpage>
        <lpage>93</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joen.2012.03.021</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 22703649?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22703649</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR53">
      <label>53</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nascimento</surname>
            <given-names>Cd</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pita</surname>
            <given-names>MS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fernandes</surname>
            <given-names>FH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pedrazzi</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>de Albuquerque Junior RF, Ribeiro RF. Bacterial adhesion on the titanium and zirconia abutment surfaces</article-title>
        <source>Clin Oral Implants Res</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <fpage>337</fpage>
        <lpage>43</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/clr.12093</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 23316996?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23316996</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR54">
      <label>54</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Metzger</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>YY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dimeo</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ambrose</surname>
            <given-names>WW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Trope</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Arnold</surname>
            <given-names>RR</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Synergistic pathogenicity of Porphyromonas gingivalis and Fusobacterium nucleatum in the mouse subcutaneous chamber model</article-title>
        <source>J Endod</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>35</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>86</fpage>
        <lpage>94</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joen.2008.10.015</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 19084132?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19084132</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR55">
      <label>55</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rubinov</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sporns</surname>
            <given-names>O</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Complex network measures of brain connectivity: uses and interpretations</article-title>
        <source>Neuroimage</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>52</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <fpage>1059</fpage>
        <lpage>69</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2009.10.003</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 19819337?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19819337</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
