<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">bioinfo</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1367-4803</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1367-4811</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4565029</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv305</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">btv305</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Applications Notes</subject>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Systems Biology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>C<sc>o</sc>R<sc>eg</sc>N<sc>et</sc>: reconstruction and integrated analysis of co-regulatory networks</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Nicolle</surname>
          <given-names>Rémy</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btv305-AFF1">
          <sup>1</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btv305-AFF1">
          <sup>2</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btv305-AFF1">
          <sup>3</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="btv305-COR1">*</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Radvanyi</surname>
          <given-names>François</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btv305-AFF1">
          <sup>2</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btv305-AFF1">
          <sup>3</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Elati</surname>
          <given-names>Mohamed</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btv305-AFF1">
          <sup>1</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="btv305-COR1">*</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="btv305-AFF1"><sup>1</sup>iSSB, CNRS, University of Evry, Genopole, 91030 Evry Cedex, France, <sup>2</sup>Institut Curie, PSL Research University, 75248 Cedex 05, France and <sup>2</sup>CNRS UMR144, 75248 Cedex 05, France</aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="btv305-COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed</corresp>
      <fn id="btv305-FN1">
        <p>Associate Editor: Jonathan Wren</p>
      </fn>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
      <day>15</day>
      <month>9</month>
      <year>2015</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>14</day>
      <month>5</month>
      <year>2015</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>14</day>
      <month>5</month>
      <year>2015</year>
    </pub-date>
    <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
    <volume>31</volume>
    <issue>18</issue>
    <fpage>3066</fpage>
    <lpage>3068</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>21</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>22</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>8</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
      <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" license-type="creative-commons">
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract>
      <p>C<sc>o</sc>R<sc>eg</sc>N<sc>et</sc> is an R/Bioconductor package to analyze large-scale transcriptomic data by highlighting sets of co-regulators. Based on a transcriptomic dataset, C<sc>o</sc>R<sc>eg</sc>N<sc>et</sc> can be used to: reconstruct a large-scale co-regulatory network, integrate regulation evidences such as transcription factor binding sites and ChIP data, estimate sample-specific regulator activity, identify cooperative transcription factors and analyze the sample-specific combinations of active regulators through an interactive visualization tool. In this study C<sc>o</sc>R<sc>eg</sc>N<sc>et</sc> was used to identify driver regulators of bladder cancer.</p>
      <p><bold>Availability:</bold> C<sc>o</sc>R<sc>eg</sc>N<sc>et</sc> is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioconductor.org/packages/CoRegNet">http://bioconductor.org/packages/CoRegNet</ext-link></p>
      <p><bold>Contact:</bold><email>remy.nicolle@issb.genopole.fr</email> or <email>mohamed.elati@issb.genopole.fr</email></p>
      <p><bold>Supplementary inform</bold><bold>a</bold><bold>tion:</bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btv305/-/DC1">Supplementary data</ext-link> are available at <italic>Bioinformatics</italic> online.</p>
    </abstract>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="3"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec>
    <title>1 Introduction</title>
    <p>Recent advances in genomics enabled the profiling of thousands of tumors by large consortia and individual laboratories. While the amount of data holds great promise for our understanding of tumorigenesis, these datasets necessitate efficient methodologies to extract valuable knowledge from them.</p>
    <p>Transcriptomics is the most commonly available type of tumor large-scale data. The transcriptome reflects the genetic, epigenetic and environmental states of a tumor tissue and determines a great extent the phenotype of cells. Therefore, one of the first step towards the construction of a mechanistic model underlying cancer is the identification of the sets of transcription factors (TF) that actively maintain a malignant phenotype. This requires methodologies to model the tissue specificity of gene regulation by inferring trustful context-specific networks. More importantly, these models must take into account the complexity of mammalian gene regulation often involving the coordinated action of several TF (<xref rid="btv305-B8" ref-type="bibr">Panne, 2008</xref>).</p>
    <p>To identify tumor-driving active regulatory circuits, we propose a Bioconductor (<xref rid="btv305-B11" ref-type="bibr">Huber <italic>et al</italic>., 2015</xref>) package named C<sc>o</sc>R<sc>eg</sc>N<sc>et</sc> to (i) reconstruct a large-scale co-regulatory network from gene expression data and by integrating additional regulatory evidences such as TF Binding site and ChIP data, (ii) estimate the activity of each TF of the network in any given sample, (iii) predict sets of cooperative TF and (iv) identify sample-specific combination of active and driver TF using an interactive visualization tool integrating genomic aberrations. The proposed methods can be used as independent modules with alternative inputs such as networks inferred by other methods, experimentally defined networks or a different transcriptomic data for TF activity prediction and visualization (e.g. cell lines of same tissue). The following sections outline the functions of the C<sc>o</sc>R<sc>eg</sc>N<sc>et</sc> package and its application to the characterization of the driver regulators of bladder cancer subtypes.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>2 The C<sc>o</sc>R<sc>eg</sc>N<sc>et</sc> application</title>
    <p>Each following sections are detailed in the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btv305/-/DC1">Supplementary Information file</ext-link> and the workflow is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="btv305-F1">Figure 1</xref>.
<fig id="btv305-F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Analysis using the C<sc>o</sc>R<sc>eg</sc>N<sc>et</sc> package. <bold>(a)</bold> A set of methods can be used to construct a network of cooperative TF from transcriptomic data using the <sc>h</sc>-L<sc>icorn</sc> algorithm and by integrating regulatory evidences. <bold>(b)</bold> A Shiny/Cytoscape web application is available to visually analyze the network and the datasets. <bold>(c)</bold> A dynamic heatmap shows the influence of all or only a selection of TF in all samples. <bold>(d)</bold> The view of the co-regulation network reflects the activity of each TF in the selected samples or sample subtype. <bold>(e)</bold> Copy number aberration (CNA) of TF can be integrated and will first display as a pie graph showing the proportion of each alteration status in either all samples or in the selected subtype. The selection of a single TF will display a multi-layer heatmap to visualize the relationship between sample phenotype and TF expression, activity and CNA</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="btv305f1p"/></fig>
</p>
    <sec>
      <title>2.1 Regulatory network inference and refinement</title>
      <p>To reconstruct a large-scale regulatory network from gene expression data, the C<sc>o</sc>R<sc>eg</sc>N<sc>et</sc> package implements the <sc>h</sc>-L<sc>icorn</sc> algorithm (<xref rid="btv305-B2" ref-type="bibr">Chebil <italic>et</italic>
<italic>al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="btv305-B4" ref-type="bibr">Elati <italic>et</italic>
<italic>al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Compared to current methods, <sc>h</sc>-L<sc>icorn</sc> focuses on the identification of cooperative regulators of genes. It was proven to have comparable TF-gene pairs prediction performance with state of the art methods in synthetic and Human datasets (<xref rid="btv305-B2" ref-type="bibr">Chebil <italic>et</italic>
<italic>al.</italic>, 2014</xref>) and to retrieve more plausible cooperative TF pairs in yeast (<xref rid="btv305-B4" ref-type="bibr">Elati <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>, <xref rid="btv305-B12" ref-type="bibr">Lai <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>) and Human datasets (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btv305/-/DC1">Supplementary Information</ext-link>). To obtain a trustful network, regulatory and co-regulatory interactions can be integrated as additional evidences. These can include any type of TF–gene interaction data to support regulatory interactions (e.g. ChIP-seq, TF binding site) and TF–TF interaction data to support cooperative interactions (e.g. protein interactions). The inferred network can then be refined by selecting a subset of the network that is enriched in these external regulatory and co-regulatory evidences using an integrative selection algorithm (<xref rid="btv305-B6" ref-type="bibr">Marbach <italic>et</italic>
<italic>al.</italic>, 2012</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>2.2 Transcription factor influence</title>
      <p>C<sc>o</sc>R<sc>eg</sc>N<sc>et</sc> implements a function to estimate the activity of a TF in a given sample. This is based on a measure of transcriptional <italic>influence</italic>, which was shown to provide a transformed view of the transcriptome in which classification algorithms are more robust (<xref rid="btv305-B7" ref-type="bibr">Nicolle <italic>et</italic>
<italic>al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Based on a comparison of the expression of the activated and the repressed targets of a regulator, the <italic>influence</italic> is computed in a sample-specific manner (details in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btv305/-/DC1">Supplementary Information</ext-link>). Robustness of the measure was tested by correlating for each TF the <italic>influence</italic> using the original network and using a partially permuted version of the network with increasing levels of noise. The same was done by correlating the <italic>influence</italic> on the sub-parts of the network that are validated by regulatory evidences. In all comparisons, the <italic>influence</italic> was significantly more robust and consistent with the validated network (e.g. 97% correlation with 20% of noise, 96% for the ChIP validated network) than the other measures of TF activity that were tested (e.g. 75% with 20% of noise and 72% ChIP validation for network component analysis, details and reference in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btv305/-/DC1">Supplementary Information</ext-link>). Furthermore, the <italic>influence</italic> predicts well the activity of a TF in samples in which it was activated at the protein level by a chemical agonist (details in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btv305/-/DC1">Supplementary Information</ext-link>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>2.3 Constructing a network of cooperative TF</title>
      <p>To model the active transcriptional programs, a co-regulation network is built by setting an edge between two significantly cooperative TF (details in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btv305/-/DC1">Supplementary Information</ext-link>). The relevance of using the <sc>h</sc>-L<sc>icorn</sc> algorithm to directly infer a cooperative network is shown by the higher enrichment of the predicted co-regulators in experimentally validated and independently predicted protein interactions (AUPR: 14% for C<sc>o</sc>R<sc>eg</sc>N<sc>et</sc>, 6% max. among the four tested algorithms, see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btv305/-/DC1">Supplementary Information</ext-link>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>2.4 Integrative visualization of transcriptional activity</title>
      <p>Transcriptomes are summarized by the <italic>influence</italic> of the regulators on the expression of their target genes in the analyzed samples. This abstraction of the transcriptomes through TF activity reduces the number of features thereby simplifying the visualization of the dataset. Moreover, the co-regulation network unravels the combination of TF at work in the studied samples. Thus, an interactive visualization tool is embedded in the C<sc>o</sc>R<sc>eg</sc>N<sc>et</sc> package to analyze several layers of information through the sets of active co-regulators. The co-regulation network is accessible through a Cytoscape (<xref rid="btv305-B13" ref-type="bibr">Shannon <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>) widget with functionalities to display sets of active co-regulators in particular samples or subtypes (examples in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="btv305-F1">Fig. 1</xref> and in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btv305/-/DC1">Supplementary Information</ext-link>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>2.5 Implementation and availability</title>
      <p>C<sc>o</sc>R<sc>eg</sc>N<sc>et</sc> is an R package implementing a Shiny (<xref rid="btv305-B10" ref-type="bibr">Winston <italic>et</italic>
<italic>al.</italic>, 2015</xref>) and Cytoscape javascript applet for visualization. The network inference method is implemented in C and can be parallelized. The package is available as a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btv305/-/DC1">Supplementary File</ext-link> or through the Bioconductor repository.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>3 Case study</title>
    <p>The C<sc>o</sc>R<sc>eg</sc>N<sc>et</sc> package was used to analyze a set of bladder cancer samples for which both transcriptome and genomic alterations were available (<xref rid="btv305-B1" ref-type="bibr">Biton <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>, <xref rid="btv305-B14" ref-type="bibr">Rebouissou <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). The inferred network was used to estimate the influence of regulators and the visualization tool to identify active sets of master regulators for each bladder cancer subtype. In line with previous studies (<xref rid="btv305-B1" ref-type="bibr">Biton <italic>et</italic>
<italic>al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="btv305-B3" ref-type="bibr">Choi <italic>et</italic>
<italic>al.</italic>, 2014</xref>), PPAR<italic>γ</italic> was found to be the most active TF in the luminal bladder cancer TCGA subgroup I. Association with genomic alteration suggesting PPAR<italic>γ</italic> to be a major driver of these tumors (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btv305/-/DC1">Supplementary Information</ext-link>), which has been recently validated experimentally (<xref rid="btv305-B1" ref-type="bibr">Biton <italic>et</italic>
<italic>al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). Moreover, FOXA1, an effector of PPAR<italic>γ</italic> (<xref rid="btv305-B9" ref-type="bibr">Varley <italic>et</italic>
<italic>al.</italic>, 2008</xref>) and a co-factor of GATA3 in luminal breast cancer (<xref rid="btv305-B5" ref-type="bibr">Kong <italic>et</italic>
<italic>al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), is a significant co-regulator of both GATA3 and PPAR<italic>γ</italic> in the inferred network.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>Funding</title>
    <p>This work is supported by the <funding-source>INCa (French National Cancer Institute)</funding-source> through the INCa_2960 [<award-id>PLBIO10</award-id>] project and the <funding-source>European Union/Framework Programme</funding-source>
<award-id>7/2009</award-id> (“SYSCILIA” consortium, grant <award-id>241955</award-id>). R.N. was supported by a fellowship from the <funding-source>French Ministry of Education and Research</funding-source>. Funding for open access charge: SYSCILIA.</p>
    <p><italic>Conflict of Interest</italic>: none declared.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
      <caption>
        <title>Supplementary Data</title>
      </caption>
      <media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_31_18_3066__index.html"/>
      <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_btv305_SupplementaryInformation.pdf"/>
      <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="x-zip-compressed" xlink:href="supp_btv305_CoRegNet_1_2_0_tar.gz"/>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ref-list>
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="btv305-B1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biton</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Independent component analysis uncovers the landscape of the bladder tumor transcriptome and reveals insights into luminal and basal subtypes</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep.</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>1235</fpage>–<lpage>1245</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25456126</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv305-B2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chebil</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Hybrid method inference for the construction of cooperative regulatory network in human</article-title>. <source>IEEE Trans. NanoBioscience</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24771593</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv305-B3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Identification of distinct basal and luminal subtypes of muscle-invasive bladder cancer with different sensitivities to frontline chemotherapy</article-title>. <source>Cancer Cell</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>152</fpage>–<lpage>165</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24525232</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv305-B4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elati</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>LICORN: learning cooperative regulation networks from gene expression data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>2407</fpage>–<lpage>2414</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17720703</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv305-B11">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Orchestrating high-throughput genomic analysis with bioconductor</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>121</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25633503</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv305-B5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Cellular reprogramming by the conjoint action of ERalpha;, FOXA1, and GATA3 to a ligand-inducible growth state</article-title>. <source>Mol. Syst. Biol.</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv305-B12">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>A comprehensive performance evaluation on the prediction results of existing cooperative transcription factors identification algorithms</article-title>. <source>BMC Syst. Biol.</source>, <volume>8(Suppl 4)</volume>, <fpage>S9</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25521604</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv305-B6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marbach</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Predictive regulatory models in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> by integrative inference of transcriptional networks</article-title>. <source>Genome Res.</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>1334</fpage>–<lpage>1349</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22456606</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv305-B7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicolle</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Network transformation of gene expression for feature extraction</article-title>. In: <conf-name>ICMLA</conf-name>, <comment>pp. 108–113. IEEE</comment>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv305-B8">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Panne</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The enhanceosome</article-title>. <source>Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol.</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>236</fpage>–<lpage>242</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18206362</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv305-B14">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rebouissou</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>EGFR as a potential therapeutic target for a subset of muscle-invasive bladder cancers presenting a basal-like phenotype</article-title>. <source>Sci. Transl. Med.</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>244ra91</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv305-B13">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Cytoscape: a software environment for integrated models of biomolecular interaction networks</article-title>. <source>Genome Res.</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>2498</fpage>–<lpage>2504</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14597658</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv305-B9">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Varley</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>FOXA1 and IRF-1 intermediary transcriptional regulators of PPAR<italic>γ</italic>-induced urothelial cytodifferentiation</article-title>. <source>Cell Death Differ.</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>114</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18688264</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btv305-B10">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winston</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <comment><italic>shiny: Web Application Framework for R. R</italic> package version 0.11.1</comment>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
