<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName NPG_XML_Article.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 2.7.10?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nature2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4941544</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pii">srep29251</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep29251</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Article</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>Overcoming the matched-sample bottleneck: an orthogonal approach to integrate omic data</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Nguyen</surname>
          <given-names>Tin</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Diaz</surname>
          <given-names>Diana</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Tagett</surname>
          <given-names>Rebecca</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Draghici</surname>
          <given-names>Sorin</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>Wayne State University, Department of Computer Science</institution>, Detroit, 48202, Michigan, <country>USA</country></aff>
      <aff id="a2"><label>2</label><institution>Wayne State University, Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology</institution>, Detroit, 48202, Michigan, <country>USA</country></aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="c1">
        <label>a</label>
        <email>sorin@wayne.edu</email>
      </corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>12</day>
      <month>07</month>
      <year>2016</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <year>2016</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>6</volume>
    <elocation-id>29251</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>02</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>14</day>
        <month>06</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2016, Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
      <copyright-holder>Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-holder>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
        <!--author-paid-->
        <license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link></license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract>
      <p>MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are small non-coding RNA molecules whose primary function is to regulate the expression of gene products via hybridization to mRNA transcripts, resulting in suppression of translation or mRNA degradation. Although miRNAs have been implicated in complex diseases, including cancer, their impact on distinct biological pathways and phenotypes is largely unknown. Current integration approaches require sample-matched miRNA/mRNA datasets, resulting in limited applicability in practice. Since these approaches cannot integrate heterogeneous information available across independent experiments, they neither account for bias inherent in individual studies, nor do they benefit from increased sample size. Here we present a novel framework able to integrate miRNA and mRNA data (vertical data integration) available in independent studies (horizontal meta-analysis) allowing for a comprehensive analysis of the given phenotypes. To demonstrate the utility of our method, we conducted a meta-analysis of pancreatic and colorectal cancer, using 1,471 samples from 15 mRNA and 14 miRNA expression datasets. Our two-dimensional data integration approach greatly increases the power of statistical analysis and correctly identifies pathways known to be implicated in the phenotypes. The proposed framework is sufficiently general to integrate other types of data obtained from high-throughput assays.</p>
    </abstract>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <p>High-throughput technologies for gene expression profiling, such as DNA microarray or RNA-Seq, have transformed biomedical research by allowing for comprehensive monitoring of biological processes. A typical comparative analysis of expression data, e.g. patients versus healthy samples, generally yields a set of genes that are differentially expressed (DE) between the conditions. These sets of DE genes contains the genes that are likely to be involved in the biological processes responsible for the disease. However, such sets of genes are usually insufficient to reveal the underlying biological mechanisms. In addition, due to inherent bias and batch effects present in individual studies, independent experiments studying the same disease often yield completely different lists of DE genes, making interpretation extremely difficult<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>.</p>
  <p>In order to translate these lists of DE genes into a better understanding of biological phenomena, researchers have developed a variety of knowledge bases that map genes to functional modules. Depending on the amount of information that one wishes to include, these modules can be described as simple gene sets based on a function, process or component (e.g., the Molecular Signatures Database MSigDB<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>), organized in a hierarchical structure that contains information about the relationship between the various modules, as found in the Gene Ontology<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>, or organized into pathways that describe in details all known interactions between the various genes that are involved in a certain phenomenon. Pathway databases include: the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>, Reactome<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>, and Biocarta (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biocarta.com">www.biocarta.com</ext-link>).</p>
  <p>Analysis techniques have been developed to help interpret such sets of DE genes. The earliest approaches use Over-Representation Analysis (ORA)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref> to identify gene sets that have more DE genes than expected by chance. The drawbacks of this type of approach include that: (i) it only considers the number of DE genes and completely ignores expression changes; (ii) it assumes that genes are independent, which they are not; and (iii) it ignores the interactions between various modules. Functional Class Scoring (FCS) approaches, such as Gene Set Enrichment Analysis (GSEA)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref> and Gene Set Analysis (GSA)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>, have been developed to address some of the issues raised by ORA approaches. The main improvement of FCS is the observation that small but coordinated changes in expression of functionally related genes can have significant impact on pathways. Both FCS and ORA approaches can be used with gene sets, ontologies, or pathways. However, these approaches do not account for the hierarchical structure of pathways or interactions between genes. Topology-based approaches, which fully exploit all the knowledge about how gene interact as described by pathways, have been developed more recently. The first such techniques were ScorePAGE<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref> for metabolic pathways and the Impact Analysis<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref> for signaling pathways.</p>
  <p>Non-coding RNAs, especially microRNAs (miRNAs) have come into the spotlight more recently. Data describing observed and predicted interactions between miRNA and mRNA is accumulating rapidly in several databases, such as miRTarBase<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>, miRWalk<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>, starBase<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>, and TargetScan<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>. In addition, miRNA expression platforms, datasets and analysis tools<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref> have become more and more prevalent.</p>
  <p>Two of the most widely used approaches to include miRNA expression data for the purpose of pathway analysis are Micrographite<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref> and PARADIGM<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>. Micrographite<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref> is a topology-aware pathway analysis approach that is able to integrate sample-matched miRNA and mRNA expression. PARADIGM<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref> uses a probabilistic graphical model (PGM) to integrate information of different data types, which may include mRNA and miRNA.</p>
  <p>The first drawback of these tools for integrating miRNA and mRNA is that they need sample-matched data. In other words, these tools require both data types to be available for each individual patient. This reduces their practical availability since sample-matched data is relatively rare and difficult or expensive to obtain. Therefore, the vast amount of available expression data, both mRNA and miRNA, is not fully utilized.</p>
  <p>The second drawback is that these methods are unable to exploit heterogeneous information available across independent studies. Therefore, they are not able to address the inevitable bias inherent in individual studies. It would be tremendously beneficial if all datasets associated with a given condition could be analyzed together because of the increased power expected to be associated with the much larger number of measurements in the combined dataset. Large public repositories such as Gene Expression Omnibus<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>, The Cancer Genome Atlas (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cancergenome.nih.gov">cancergenome.nih.gov</ext-link>), ArrayExpress<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>, and Therapeutically Applicable Research to Generate Effective Treatments (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ocg.cancer.gov/programs/target">ocg.cancer.gov/programs/target</ext-link>) store thousands of datasets, within which there are independent experimental series with similar patient cohorts and experiment design. Expression data, mRNA as well as miRNA, are particularly prevalent in public databases, such that some disease conditions are represented by half a dozen studies or more.</p>
  <p>The process of combining sample-matched data of different types is referred to as <italic>vertical</italic> integrative analysis, while that of combining multiple unmatched studies using the same data type is referred as <italic>horizontal</italic> meta-analysis<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>. Thus, they are considered <italic>orthogonal</italic> classes of data integration. For microarray data, the method proposed by Rhodes <italic>et. al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref> was one of the earliest <italic>horizontal</italic> approaches to combine multiple microarray datasets, using Fisher’s method. Since then, other sophisticated approaches have been proposed for the integration of multiple gene expression datasets, on both the gene and pathway levels<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref>. The majority of these meta-analysis approaches work by combining the p-values obtained from individual gene expression datasets. However, they typically do not try to account for the data heterogeneity, attributed to batch effects, patient heterogeneity, and disease complexity, responsible for expression changes across different sources.</p>
  <p>Here we propose a framework that is able to integrate unmatched miRNA and mRNA data obtained from many independent laboratories. While validated in the context of pathway analysis, the framework can be modified to adapt to other domains or applications. This framework is not meant to compete with any existing approach, but to serve as a bridge between <italic>horizontal</italic> and <italic>vertical</italic> data integration. Each building block or technique of our pipeline can be easily substituted for by any other similar technique to suit the purpose of future analysis.</p>
  <p>We illustrate the new framework using 15 mRNA and 14 miRNA datasets related to two human diseases, colorectal cancer and pancreatic cancer. They were generated by independent labs, for different sets of patients. For both conditions, the new framework is able to identify pathways relevant to the phenotypes. We demonstrate that the accuracy is obtained only by integrating the data in both directions (horizontal and vertical).</p>
  <p>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first article that describes an orthogonal meta-analysis. Our results suggest that orthogonal classes of integrative techniques can be further combined to unravel the underlying mechanisms of complex diseases. With vast databases of various data types being made available, this framework is expected to be widely applicable because of its relaxed restrictions on the data being integrated.</p>
  <sec disp-level="1">
    <title>Methods</title>
    <p>The classical pathway analysis begins by considering a comparison between two conditions, e.g. disease versus healthy. Evidence for differential gene expression can be provided by any technique such as fold change, t-statistic, Kolmogorov-Smirnov statistic, or perturbation factor. These statistics are then compared against the null distribution to determine how unlikely it is for the observed differences between the two conditions to occur by chance, thereby producing a ranked list of DE genes. After this hypothesis testing is done at the gene level, the next step is hypothesis testing at the pathway level producing a ranked list of impacted pathways. In summary, the input of a classical pathway analysis method includes: (i) a pathway database, and (ii) a gene expression dataset. The output is a list of pathways ranked according to their p-values.</p>
    <p>Similarly, the input of the new approach includes: (i) a pathway database, (ii) a database of miRNA-mRNA interactions, (iii) multiple gene expression datasets, and (iv) multiple miRNA expression datasets. Each dataset is obtained from an independent study of the same disease. Here we describe a framework that transforms the new problem into the classical pathway analysis problem.</p>
    <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref> illustrates the pipeline of our framework, for the case of colorectal cancer. Panel (a) represents the biological knowledge obtained from public databases: pathway information and miRNA targets. Panel (b) shows a set of gene expression datasets obtained from independent studies, coming from different laboratories. For this example, we have 7 datasets (GSE4107, GSE9348, GSE15781, GSE21510, GSE23878, GSE41657, and GSE62322), all related to the same disease, colorectal cancer. Each dataset consists of two groups of samples: disease (group D) and control/healthy (group C). Panel (c) represents a set of miRNA expression datasets (GSE33125, GSE35834, GSE39814, GSE39833, GSE41655, GSE49246, GSE54632, and GSE73487), also from colorectal cancer. Similar to gene expression datasets, each miRNA dataset consists of disease and control samples. The data provided in panels (a,b,c) serve as the input for our framework.</p>
    <p>Pathways in public databases are typically described as graphs, where nodes are genes and edges are interactions between genes. In the first step, we extend the existing pathways with additional interactions between miRNAs and mRNAs. Panel (d) shows a part of the pathway <italic>Colorectal cancer</italic>, where blue nodes are genes and red nodes are miRNAs. The black arrow-headed lines represent activation while the red bar-headed lines represent inhibition. For example, <italic>hsa-miR-483-5p</italic> is known to suppress the expression of <italic>MAPK3</italic> and therefore an inhibition relationship is added between the two nodes in the pathway. All pathways are extended to include the known miRNA-mRNA interactions. The next step is to estimate the expression changes of each node (gene, miRNA) under the effects of the disease.</p>
    <p>Panel (e) shows the expression changes and the p-values for one gene in the mRNA data, across several datasets. In this case, the <italic>MAPK3</italic> gene is used as an example. In the forest plot shown in this panel, each horizontal line represents the expression change in each study. The small black box in each line shows the standardized mean difference (SMD) and the segment shows the confidence interval of SMD. We use the standardized mean difference instead of the raw difference because the independent studies measure the expression in a variety of ways (different platforms, sample preparation, etc.). The number on the right side of each line is the p-value of the test for differential expression, using the modified t-test provided in the limma package<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>.</p>
    <p>As shown in the figure, the SMD and p-value of a gene vary from study to study. We use the REstricted Maximum Likelihood (REML) algorithm<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">33</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref> to estimate the central tendency of SMD. We also use the add-CLT method<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref> to combine the independent p-values. Likewise, we compute the estimated SMDs and p-values for miRNA datasets (panel f).</p>
    <p>The augmented pathways, the combined p-value, together with the estimated size effect then serve as input for classical pathway analysis. In this work, we use Impact Analysis, which is a topology-aware pathway analysis method, to calculate the p-value for each augmented pathway (panel g).</p>
    <sec disp-level="2">
      <title>Standardized mean difference for each gene</title>
      <p>Consider a study composed of two independent groups, and suppose we wish to compare their means for a given gene. Let <inline-formula id="d33e291"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e292" xlink:href="srep29251-m1.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="d33e294"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e295" xlink:href="srep29251-m2.jpg"/></inline-formula> represent the sample means for that gene in the two groups, <italic>n</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>n</italic><sub>2</sub> the number of samples in each group, and <italic>S</italic><sub><italic>pooled</italic></sub> the pooled standard deviation of the two groups. The pooled standard deviation and the standardized mean difference (SMD) can be estimated as:</p>
      <p>
        <disp-formula id="eq3">
          <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e316" xlink:href="srep29251-m3.jpg"/>
        </disp-formula>
      </p>
      <p>
        <disp-formula id="eq4">
          <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e319" xlink:href="srep29251-m4.jpg"/>
        </disp-formula>
      </p>
      <p>The estimation of the standardized mean difference described in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq18">Equation (2)</xref> is often called Cohen’s <italic>d</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">37</xref>. The variance of Cohen’s <italic>d</italic> is given as follows:</p>
      <p>
        <disp-formula id="eq5">
          <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e334" xlink:href="srep29251-m5.jpg"/>
        </disp-formula>
      </p>
      <p>In the above equation, the first term reflects uncertainty in the estimate of the mean difference, and the second term reflects uncertainty in the estimate of <italic>S</italic><sub><italic>pooled</italic></sub>. The standard error of <italic>d</italic> is the square root of <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>d</italic></sub>. We note that Cohen’s <italic>d</italic>, which is based on sample averages, tends to overestimate the population effect size for small samples. Let <italic>n</italic> be the degrees of freedom used to estimate <italic>S</italic><sub><italic>pooled</italic></sub>, i.e. <italic>n</italic> = <italic>n</italic><sub>1</sub> + <italic>n</italic><sub>2</sub> − 2. The corrected effect size, or Hedges’ <italic>g</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">38</xref>, can be computed as follows:</p>
      <p>
        <disp-formula id="eq6">
          <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e385" xlink:href="srep29251-m6.jpg"/>
        </disp-formula>
      </p>
      <p>
        <disp-formula id="eq7">
          <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e388" xlink:href="srep29251-m7.jpg"/>
        </disp-formula>
      </p>
      <p>where Γ is the gamma function. In this work, we use Hedge’ <italic>g</italic> as the standardized mean difference (SMD) between disease and control groups for each gene/miRNA.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="2">
      <title>Random-effects model and REML</title>
      <p>Consider a collection of <italic>m</italic> studies where the effect size estimates, <italic>y</italic><sub>1</sub>, …, <italic>y</italic><sub><italic>m</italic></sub> have been derived from a set of studies, each of them modeled as in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq10">Equation (5)</xref>. A fixed-effects model would assume that there is one true effect size which underlies all of the studies in the analysis, such that all differences in observed effects are due to sampling error. However, this assumption is implausible since it cannot account for heterogeneity between studies<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">33</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref>.</p>
      <p>In contrast, the random-effects model allows for variability of the true effect. For example, the effect size might be higher (or lower) in studies where the participants are older, or have a healthier lifestyle compared to others. The random-effects model assumes that each effect size estimate can be decomposed into two variance components by a two-stage hierarchical process<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">33</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">39</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40">40</xref>. The first variance represents the variability of the effect size across studies, and the second variance represents the sampling error within each study. We can write the random-effects model as:</p>
      <p>
        <disp-formula id="eq8">
          <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e425" xlink:href="srep29251-m8.jpg"/>
        </disp-formula>
      </p>
      <p>where <italic>μ</italic> is the central tendency of the effect size, <italic>N</italic>(0, <italic>σ</italic><sup>2</sup>) represents the error term by which the effect size in the <italic>i</italic><sup><italic>th</italic></sup> study differs from the central tendency <italic>μ</italic>, and <inline-formula id="d33e449"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e450" xlink:href="srep29251-m9.jpg"/></inline-formula> represents the sampling error.</p>
      <p>The derivation and formulation of the REstricted Maximum Likelihood (REML) algorithm has been described in the literature<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">33</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">41</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42">42</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43">43</xref>. The log-likelihood function for <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq18">Equation (6)</xref> is given by:</p>
      <p>
        <disp-formula id="eq10">
          <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e461" xlink:href="srep29251-m10.jpg"/>
        </disp-formula>
      </p>
      <p>The REML estimators of <inline-formula id="d33e464"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e465" xlink:href="srep29251-m11.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="d33e467"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e468" xlink:href="srep29251-m12.jpg"/></inline-formula> are then computed by iteratively maximizing the log-likelihood. In our framework, we calculate <inline-formula id="d33e470"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e471" xlink:href="srep29251-m13.jpg"/></inline-formula> for each node (mRNA and miRNA) of the extended pathways. The estimated <italic>overall effect size</italic>
<inline-formula id="d33e476"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e477" xlink:href="srep29251-m14.jpg"/></inline-formula> and the <italic>combined p-value</italic> of individual genes and miRNAs serve as the input for Impact Analysis.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="2">
      <title>Combining independent p-values</title>
      <p>We first briefly recap some classical methods for combining independent p-values. Next, we describe the additive method<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44">44</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45">45</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46">46</xref> that is used to combine p-values for each mRNA and miRNA molecule in our framework.</p>
      <p>Fisher’s method<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47">47</xref> is the most widely used method for combining independent p-values. Considering a set of <italic>m</italic> independent significance tests, the resulting p-values <italic>P</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>P</italic><sub>2</sub>, …, <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>m</italic></sub> are independent and uniformly distributed on the interval [0, 1] under the null hypothesis. The random variables <italic>X</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> = −2ln<italic>P</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> (<italic>i</italic> ∈ {1, 2, …, <italic>m</italic>}) follow a chi-squared distribution with two degrees of freedom (<inline-formula id="d33e533"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e534" xlink:href="srep29251-m15.jpg"/></inline-formula>). Consequently, the log product of <italic>m</italic> independent p-values follows a chi-squared distribution with 2<italic>m</italic> degrees of freedom. We note that if one of the individual p-values approaches zero, which is often the case for empirical p-values, then the combined p-value approaches zero as well, regardless of other individual p-values. For example, if <italic>P</italic><sub>1</sub> → 0, then <italic>X</italic> → ∞ and therefore, <italic>Pr</italic>(<italic>X</italic>) → 0 regardless of <italic>P</italic><sub>2</sub>, <italic>P</italic><sub>3</sub>, …, <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>m</italic></sub>.</p>
      <p>Stouffer’s method<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b48">48</xref> is another classical method that is closely related to Fisher’s. The test statistic of Stouffer’s method is the sum of p-values transformed into standard normal variables, divided by the square root of <italic>m</italic>. Denoting <italic>ϕ</italic> as the standard normal cumulative distribution function, and <italic>p</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> (<italic>i</italic> ∈ [1..<italic>m</italic>]) the individual p-values that are independently and uniformly distributed under the null, the z-scores are calculated as <italic>z</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> = <italic>ϕ</italic><sup>−1</sup> (1 − <italic>p</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>). By definition, these z-scores follow the standard normal distribution. The summary statistic of Stouffer’s method <inline-formula id="d33e615"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e616" xlink:href="srep29251-m16.jpg"/></inline-formula> also follows the standard normal distribution under the null hypothesis. Similar to Fisher’s method, the combined p-values approach zero when one of the individual p-values approaches zero.</p>
      <p>The additive method<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44">44</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45">45</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46">46</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b49">49</xref> uses the sum of the p-values as the test statistic, instead of the log product. Consider the p-values resulting from <italic>m</italic> independent significance tests, <italic>P</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>P</italic><sub>2</sub>, …, <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>m</italic></sub>. Let the sum of these p-values, <inline-formula id="d33e642"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e643" xlink:href="srep29251-m17.jpg"/></inline-formula> (<italic>X</italic> ∈ [0, <italic>m</italic>]), be the new random variable. <italic>X</italic> is known to follow the Irwin-Hall distribution<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45">45</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46">46</xref> with the following probability density function (pdf):</p>
      <p>
        <disp-formula id="eq18">
          <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e659" xlink:href="srep29251-m18.jpg"/>
        </disp-formula>
      </p>
      <p>when <italic>m</italic> is large, some addends will be too small or too large to be stored in the memory. This leads to a totally inaccurate calculation when <italic>m</italic> passes a certain threshold, depending on the number of bits used to store numbers on the computer. For this reason, a modified version of the additive method, named add-CLT, was proposed<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref>.</p>
      <p>Let <italic>Y</italic> represent the average of p-values: <inline-formula id="d33e675"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e676" xlink:href="srep29251-m19.jpg"/></inline-formula> (<italic>Y</italic> ∈ [0, 1]). Since <inline-formula id="d33e681"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e682" xlink:href="srep29251-m20.jpg"/></inline-formula> the probability density function (pdf) and the corresponding cumulative distribution function (cdf) of <italic>Y</italic> can be derived using a linear transformation of <italic>X</italic> as follows:</p>
      <p>
        <disp-formula id="eq21">
          <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e693" xlink:href="srep29251-m21.jpg"/>
        </disp-formula>
      </p>
      <p>The variable <italic>Y</italic> is the mean of <italic>m</italic> independent and identically distributed (i.i.d.) random variables (the p-values from each individual experiment), that follow a uniform distribution with a mean of <inline-formula id="d33e702"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e703" xlink:href="srep29251-m22.jpg"/></inline-formula> and a variance of <inline-formula id="d33e705"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e706" xlink:href="srep29251-m23.jpg"/></inline-formula>. From the Central Limit Theorem<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50">50</xref>, the average of such <italic>m</italic> i.i.d. variables follows a normal distribution with mean <inline-formula id="d33e714"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e715" xlink:href="srep29251-m24.jpg"/></inline-formula> and variance <inline-formula id="d33e717"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e718" xlink:href="srep29251-m25.jpg"/></inline-formula>, i.e. <inline-formula id="d33e720"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e721" xlink:href="srep29251-m26.jpg"/></inline-formula> for sufficiently large values of <italic>m</italic>. The transition from the additive method to the Central Limit Theorem takes place at the <italic>m</italic> ≥ 20 threshold.</p>
      <p>In this work, we use the add-CLT method described above to combine the p-values calculated from the modified t-test (limma package).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="2">
      <title>Graphical representation of augmented pathways</title>
      <p>Here we give the formal description of the pathway augmentation process. Let <italic>P</italic> = (<italic>V, E</italic>) be the graphical representation of the pathway we want to extend with miRNA-mRNA interactions. <italic>V</italic> is the set of vertices (genes) while the directed edges in <italic>E</italic> represent the interactions between genes in the pathway. Each interaction consists of an ordered pair of vertices and the type of interaction between the pair, i.e. <italic>E</italic> = {(<italic>x</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>, <italic>y</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>), <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>} where <italic>x</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>, <italic>y</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> ∈ <italic>G</italic> (gene set) and <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> is the type of relation between <italic>x</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and <italic>y</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>, such as <italic>activation, repression, phosphorylation, etc</italic>. Topology-based pathway analysis methods, such as Impact Analysis, use interaction types to weigh the edges or to set the strength of signal propagation along the paths in a pathway.</p>
      <p>From the miRNA database, we get a set of miRNAs and their targets. Let us denote <italic>Z</italic> as the set of known miRNAs, <italic>ζ</italic> ∈ <italic>Z</italic> is one miRNA, and <italic>t</italic>(<italic>ζ</italic>) is the set of known targets for the miRNA <italic>ζ</italic>. The augmented pathway of <italic>P</italic> = (<italic>V, E</italic>) is denoted as <italic>P</italic>* = (<italic>V</italic>*, <italic>E</italic>*) and is constructed as follows:</p>
      <p>
        <disp-formula id="eq27">
          <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e847" xlink:href="srep29251-m27.jpg"/>
        </disp-formula>
      </p>
      <p>In other words, if a miRNA <italic>ζ</italic> targets a gene <italic>g</italic> that belongs to the pathway, we add <italic>ζ</italic> to the pathway and then connect <italic>ζ</italic> with its targets in the pathway. By default, the interaction type of new edges is <italic>repression</italic>, which represents the translation blockage of miRNAs to mRNA. The interaction type can be changed to suit the interaction between the miRNA molecule and its targets. We extend all pathways in the pathway database using the formulation described in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq27">Equation (10)</xref>. The R package mirIntegrator<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b51">51</xref> for pathway augmentation is available on Bioconductor website (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bioconductor.org">www.bioconductor.org</ext-link>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="2">
      <title>Impact analysis of augmented pathways</title>
      <p>The Impact Analysis method<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b52">52</xref> combines two types of evidence: (i) the over-representation of DE genes in a given pathway<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>, and (ii) the perturbation of that pathway, caused by disease, as measured by propagating expression changes through the pathway topology. These two aspects are captured, respectively, by the independent probability values, <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>NDE</italic></sub> and <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>PERT</italic></sub>. Here we review the Impact Analysis formulation.</p>
      <p>The first p-value, <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>NDE</italic></sub>, is obtained using the hypergeometric model<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>, which is the probability of obtaining at least the observed number of differentially expressed genes. The second p-value, <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>PERT</italic></sub>, depends on the identity of the specific genes that are differentially expressed as well as on the interactions described by the pathway. It is calculated based on the perturbation factor in each pathway. The perturbation factor of a gene, <italic>PF</italic>(<italic>g</italic>), is calculated as follows:</p>
      <p>
        <disp-formula id="eq28">
          <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e920" xlink:href="srep29251-m28.jpg"/>
        </disp-formula>
      </p>
      <p>The first term represents the signed normalized expression change of the gene <italic>g</italic>, i.e. log standardized mean difference as shown in panels (e,f) of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref>. The second term is the sum of perturbation factors of upstream genes, normalized by the number of downstream genes of each such upstream gene. The value of <italic>β</italic><sub><italic>ug</italic></sub> quantifies the strength of interaction between <italic>u</italic> and <italic>g</italic>. Here, <italic>β</italic><sub><italic>ug</italic></sub> = 1 for <italic>activation</italic> and <italic>β</italic><sub><italic>ug</italic></sub> = −1 for <italic>repression</italic>.</p>
      <p>The above equation essentially describes the perturbation factor PF for a gene as a linear function of the perturbation factors of all genes in a given pathway. In the stable state of the system, all relationships must hold, so the set of all equations defining the impact factors for all genes form a system of simultaneous equations whose solution will provide the values for the gene perturbation factors <italic>PF</italic><sub><italic>g</italic></sub>. The net perturbation accumulation at the level of each gene, <italic>Acc</italic>(<italic>g</italic>), is calculated by subtracting the observed expression change from the perturbation factor.</p>
      <p>
        <disp-formula id="eq29">
          <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e976" xlink:href="srep29251-m29.jpg"/>
        </disp-formula>
      </p>
      <p>The total accumulated perturbation in the pathway is then computed as:</p>
      <p>
        <disp-formula id="eq30">
          <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e981" xlink:href="srep29251-m30.jpg"/>
        </disp-formula>
      </p>
      <p>The null distribution of <italic>Acc</italic>(<italic>P</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>) is built by permutation of expression change. The p-value, <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>PERT</italic></sub>, is then calculated by the probability of having values more extreme than the actually observed <italic>Acc</italic>(<italic>P</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>).</p>
      <p>To compute <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>NDE</italic></sub> and <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>PERT</italic></sub>, the following input is required: the graphical representation of the pathway, the combined p-value of each node of the graph, and the estimated overall standardized mean difference. In short, the graphical representation of the augmented pathways is provided in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq27">Equation (10)</xref>, the p-value for each node of the augmented pathways is computed using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq21">Equation (9)</xref>, and the expression change, Δ<italic>E</italic>(<italic>g</italic>), is estimated by iteratively maximizing the log-likelihood function in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq10">Equation (7)</xref>. These two p-values, <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>NDE</italic></sub> and <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>PERT</italic></sub>, are then combined to get a single p-value that represents how likely the pathway is impacted under the effect of the disease.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec disp-level="1">
    <title>Experimental Results</title>
    <p>We analyzed a total of 1,471 samples from 29 public datasets for two human diseases, colorectal and pancreatic cancer. The datasets were generated in independent laboratories, from different individual tissue samples, and were run on different high-throughput platforms. The diseases were selected based on two criteria: (i) there are many publicly available miRNA and mRNA datasets, and (ii) there is a pathway specific to the disease (target pathway). The colorectal data consists of 7 mRNA and 8 miRNA datasets while the pancreatic data consists of 8 mRNA and 6 miRNA datasets. The processed data sets were downloaded directly from the Gene Expression Omnibus using the GEOquery package<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b53">53</xref>. The data were rescaled using a log transformation if they were not already in log scale (base 2). The details of each dataset, such as the number of samples, tissues, and platforms, are reported in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>.</p>
    <p>The databases used in our data analysis are KEGG for pathways, and miRTarBase for miRNAs. We downloaded 182 signaling pathways from KEGG version 76 (Dec-04-2015) by means of the R package ROntoTools<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b54">54</xref>. We augmented these pathways with known miRNAs and their target interactions, downloaded from miRTarBase. For each mRNA/miRNA, we use the <italic>modified t-test</italic>, available in the limma package<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>, to test for differential expression of mRNA/miRNAs. We use <italic>add-CLT</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref> as the method to combine independent p-values. We then adjust the combined p-values for multiple comparisons using False Discovery Rate (FDR)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b55">55</xref>. For expression change, we use <italic>Hedges’ g</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">38</xref> as effect size, and the <italic>REML</italic> method<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b56">56</xref> to estimate the central tendency of effect sizes. Following convention, we only take into consideration mRNA/miRNAs having FDR-corrected combined p-values less than 5%. Among these significant genes, we choose mRNA/miRNAs that have the highest estimated SMD as differentially expressed, up to 10% of total measured mRNA/miRNAs. All the R scripts used for data processing, pathway augmentation, and analysis are available on demand from the authors.</p>
    <p>For both diseases, we compare the orthogonal approach (ImpactAnalysis_I) with 5 other approaches: pathway-level meta-analysis (ImpactAnalysis_P), gene-level meta-analysis (ImpactAnalysis_G), plus the 3 meta-analysis approaches available in MetaPath package<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref>. Since the input data sets consist of multiple studies, none of which are sample-matched, we are unable to perform pathway analysis using approaches that integrate matched mRNA and miRNA expression.</p>
    <p>For pathway-level meta-analysis (ImpactAnalysis_P), we perform Impact Analysis on each mRNA expression dataset and then combine the independent p-values for each pathway. For example, if we have 7 mRNA datasets, we have 7 nominal p-values per pathway–one for each study. These 7 p-values are independent and thus can be combined using the add-CLT method to get one combined p-value. The final result is a list of 182 p-values for 182 signaling pathways. We then adjust the combined p-values for multiple comparisons using FDR.</p>
    <p>For gene-level meta-analysis (ImpactAnalysis_G), we perform the modified t-test<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref> for each mRNA dataset and then combine the p-values. With 7 mRNA datasets, for example, each gene will have 7 independent p-values, which will be combined into one p-value. We also calculate the SMD and standard error of each gene in each study, then use the REML algorithm to calculate the overall effect size across the 7 studies. Finally, pathway analysis is performed on 182 KEGG pathways using the combined p-values and the estimated effect sizes, resulting in a list of pathways ranked according to their p-values. We then adjust the p-values of pathways for multiple comparisons using FDR.</p>
    <p>The integrative approach (ImpactAnalysis_I) is similar to ImpactAnalysis_G, with the exception that ImpactAnalysis_I uses both mRNA and miRNA data. The meta-analysis is done on the mRNA/miRNA level and then the combined p-values and estimated effect sizes of mRNA/miRNAs serve as the input to the ImpactAnalysis.</p>
    <p>MetaPath<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref> is a dedicated approach that performs meta-analysis at both gene (MetaPath_G) and pathway levels (MetaPath_P) with a GSEA-like approach, and then combines the results (MetaPath_I) to give the final p-value and ranking of pathways. MetaPath first calculates the t-statistic for each gene in each study. In MetaPath_G, these statistics are combined for each gene using maxP<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b57">57</xref>. The combined statistics are then used to calculate enrichment scores for each pathway using a Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. In MetaPath_P, the pathway enrichment analysis is done first before meta-analysis. In MetaPath_I, the p-values of MetaPath_G and MetaPath_P are combined using minP<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b58">58</xref>.</p>
    <p>For each of the two diseases, we have a <italic>target</italic> KEGG pathway, which is the pathway created to describe the main phenomena involved in the respective disease. The augmented pathway for <italic>Colorectal cancer</italic> is displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2</xref>. The green rectangle nodes show the KEGG genes and the black arrows show the interactions between the genes. The green nodes and the red arrows show the miRNA molecules and their interactions with the genes, where the bar-headed arrow represents the “repression” activity. In each augmented node, we display two types of information: i) the total number of miRNAs that are known to target the corresponding gene, and ii) the miRNAs that were actually measured in the 8 miRNA colorectal datasets. The former is displayed in blue circles while the later is listed in blue rectangles. For example, the gene TGF<italic>β</italic> (in the far left of the figure) has 9 miRNAs that are known to target the gene but only two miRNAs (hsa:miR-375 and hsa:miR-633) were included in the miRNA data. Similarly, the augmented pathway for <italic>Pancreatic cancer</italic> is displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3</xref>. The graphs show that both <italic>target pathways</italic> are heavily regulated by miRNA molecules.</p>
    <p>In this experimental study, we expect that a good pathway analysis approach would be able to identify the very pathway that describes the disease phenomena as the most significant in each particular disease. Hence, we will compare the various methods based on this criterion.</p>
    <sec disp-level="2">
      <title>Colorectal cancer</title>
      <p>We obtained 8 miRNA (GSE33125, GSE35834, GSE39814, GSE39833, GSE41655, GSE49246, GSE54632, and GSE73487) and 7 mRNA (GSE4107, GSE9348, GSE15781, GSE21510, GSE23878, GSE41657, and GSE62322) datasets from the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO), as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>.</p>
      <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref> shows the results of the 6 approaches. The horizontal line across each list marks the cutoff <italic>FDR</italic> = 0.01. The pathway highlighted in green is the target pathway <italic>Colorectal cancer</italic>. MetaPath_P (pathway-level meta-analysis) identifies no significant pathway at the 1% cutoff, and ranks the target pathway at position 16<sup><italic>th</italic></sup>. Similarly, MetaPath_G (gene-level meta-analysis) and MetaPath_I (combination of gene- and pathway-level) identify no significant pathways. They rank the target pathway at positions 9<sup><italic>th</italic></sup> and 15<sup><italic>th</italic></sup>, respectively.</p>
      <p>The ImpactAnalysis_P approach identifies 12 pathways, among which there are many pathways that are related to cancer. However, the target pathway <italic>Colorectal cancer</italic> is not significant and is ranked 61<sup><italic>st</italic></sup> with adjusted <italic>p</italic> = 0.99. The gene-level meta-analysis (ImpactAnalysis_G) offers some improvement over ImpactAnalysis_P by improving the ranking (10<sup><italic>th</italic></sup>) and adjusted p-value (<italic>p</italic> = 0.1) of the target pathway <italic>Colorectal cancer</italic>. However, the target pathway is still not significant with the given threshold. The orthogonal meta-analysis, ImpactAnalysis_I, is able to further boost the power of the gene-level meta-analysis. It identifies 5 significant pathways, with the target pathway <italic>Colorectal cancer</italic> ranked at the very top. This is very likely due to the additional information provided by miRNA expression and prior knowledge accumulated in miRTarBase.</p>
      <p>Three of the other 4 pathways that are identified by ImpactAnalysis_I appear to be true positives. The <italic>Cell Cycle</italic> and <italic>Ribosome Biogenesis</italic> pathways are implicated in the proliferation aspect of cancer tissue. <italic>PPAR signaling</italic> has a role in colorectal cancer, although it is not fully understood<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b59">59</xref>. <italic>Progesterone-mediated oocyte maturation</italic> is clearly a false positive which may have appeared due to the presence of several cell cycle genes in that pathway.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="2">
      <title>Pancreatic cancer</title>
      <p>We obtained 8 mRNA (GSE15471, GSE19279, GSE27890, GSE32676, GSE36076, GSE43288, GSE45757, and GSE60601) and 6 miRNA datasets (GSE24279, GSE25820, GSE32678, GSE34052, GSE43796, and GSE60978) from Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO), as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>. Again, we compare our approach (ImpactAnalysis_I) with 5 other approaches: pathway-level meta-analysis, gene-level meta-analysis using only mRNA data, plus 3 meta-analysis approaches available in the MetaPath package<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref> as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t3">Table 3</xref>.</p>
      <p>MetaPath_P identifies no significant pathway and <italic>Graft-versus-host disease</italic> is ranked on top with adjusted p-value 0.4782. The target pathway <italic>Pancreatic cancer</italic> is ranked 17<sup><italic>th</italic></sup> with adjusted <italic>p</italic> = 0.89. MetaPath_G identifies 7 significant pathways. The target pathway is not significant (adjusted <italic>p</italic> = 0.22) and is ranked 91<sup><italic>st</italic></sup>. In consequence, the combination of these two methods, MetaPath_I, also fails to identify the target pathway as significant (adjusted <italic>p</italic> = 0.34 with ranking 91<sup><italic>st</italic></sup>).</p>
      <p>The pathway-level meta-analysis (ImpactAnalysis_P) identifies the <italic>PI3K-Akt signaling pathway</italic> and <italic>MicroRNAs in cancer</italic> as significant. The significance of <italic>MicroRNAs in cancer</italic> may indicate the importance of miRNA in pancreatic cancer, and <italic>PI3K-Akt signaling</italic> alteration is known to be involved in many cancers. However, the target pathway is not significant (adjusted <italic>p</italic> = 0.95 with ranking 32<sup><italic>nd</italic></sup>). The gene-level meta-analysis (ImpactAnalysis_G) improves the ranking of the target pathway (8<sup><italic>th</italic></sup>) but the p-value of the target pathway is still not significant. The orthogonal approach, ImpactAnalysis_I, identifies 7 pathways as significant. The target pathway <italic>Pancreatic cancer</italic> is ranked on top with FDR-corrected p-value 0.0017.</p>
      <p>Of the 6 significant non-target pathways found by ImpactAnalysis_I, three are cancer-related by name (<italic>Small cell lung cancer, Pathways in cancer, Proteoglycans in cancer</italic>). The breakdown of cell matrix adhesions, such as <italic>Focal Adhesion</italic> is an important property of metastasis - most pancreatic cancers are discovered when they are already high grade.</p>
      <p>In contrast to the 3 variations of the existing method, MetaPath, the proposed method ImpactAnalysis_I was able to effectively combine both independent datasets, as well as the two different types of data (mRNA and miRNA), and correctly report the target pathway as the most significantly impacted pathway in both meta-analysis studies. The results demonstrate that the correct pathways are identified only when the data are integrated both horizontally (combining multiple studies using the same data type) and vertically (combining miRNA with mRNA expression). This orthogonal meta-analysis uses three different kinds of data integration: integration of mRNA and miRNA, combining p-values and combining SMDs for genes and miRNA molecules.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="2">
      <title>Time complexity</title>
      <p>The data analysis was done on a personal MacBook Pro that has 8 GB 1600 MHz DDR3 RAM, 2.9 GHz Intel Core i7. Since MetaPath cannot exploit multiple processors, we run all the analysis using a single core. The time needed to run MetaPath was 39 minutes for Colorectal cancer and 47 minutes for Pancreatic cancer.</p>
      <p>For ImpactAnalysis_I, we first calculate the p-value for each gene/miRNA in each dataset using the limma package<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>. We then combine the p-values to get one combined p-value per gene/miRNA. Next, we calculate the standardized mean difference (SMD) for each dataset and then apply the REML algorithm to estimate to overall SMD, using the metafor package<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b56">56</xref>. The estimated SMDs and the combined p-values are processed by ROntoTools to produce the p-value for each pathway. ImpactAnalysis_I performes the analysis using the pathways augmented with the relevant miRNAs. The running time for ImpactAnalysis_I is 4 minutes for each of Colorectal and Pancreatic. The running time of each approach is reported in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t4">Table 4</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec disp-level="1">
    <title>Discussion</title>
    <p>One straightforward <italic>horizontal</italic> integration is to combine individual p-values provided by each study. In this way, one can apply any pathway analysis approach (such as GSEA<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref> or GSA<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>) to the collected mRNA datasets in order to calculate a p-value for each pathway in each study, and then combine these independent p-values. The advantage of this approach is its flexibility. MetaPath<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref> combines p-values in this way, but with the slight difference that the p-values are combined on both gene and pathway levels. The drawback is that each of these methods is designed to work with one single matrix of expression values, i.e. one data type. One can forcefully extend this matrix to include other data types as well but in order to do this, the data must be sample-matched. In other words, one must perform all types of assays on every single sample. In addition, since different data types are assayed on different platforms, the data need to be normalized together, for these approaches to function properly. However, the correct way to do such a cross-platform normalization is still an open problem<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b60">60</xref>. The same limitations apply to analysis tools dedicated to miRNA and mRNA integration<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b61">61</xref>. For meta-analysis, these approaches would require multiple sets of sample-matched data. Performing different assays on one set of samples is already expensive; asking for many sets of matched samples for the same disease is even more impractical.</p>
    <p>Although primarily designed to overcome the matched-sample bottleneck discussed above, our proposed framework also aims to address a well-known limitation of p-value-based meta-analyses. Classical approaches often rely on hypothesis testing to identify differential expression. This results in critical information loss. While the p-value is partly a function of effect size, it is also partly a function of sample size<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b62">62</xref>. For example, with large sample size, a statistical test will tend to find differences as significant, unless the effect size is exactly zero. In reality, any individual study will include some degree of batch effects, such as sampling/study bias, noise, and measurement errors. Simply combining individual p-values would not correct such problems. On the contrary, meta-analysis of effect sizes across all studies would definitely compensate for and eliminate such random effects. This point is illustrated in the results included here, in particular in the difference between ImpactAnalysis_P and ImpactAnalysis_G for both colorectal and pancreatic cancer (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Tables 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="t3">3</xref>). The former simply combines the p-values, while the latter takes into consideration both p-values and effect sizes across different studies. ImpactAnalysis_G offers a great improvement over ImpactAnalysis_P using the same sets of mRNA data.</p>
    <p>However, the approach proposed here is not without limitations. One such limitation is the computational complexity at both gene and pathway levels. For individual genes and miRNA molecules, the framework not only calculates p-values, but also iteratively estimates the effect sizes and variances. In principle, the iterative algorithm requires more computation than meta-analyses that use closed-form expressions. At pathway-level, Impact Analysis is a non-parametric approach that constructs an empirical distribution of all measured values for each pathway. This requires more computation and storage than parametric approaches, such as the hypergeometric test or Fisher’s exact test. However, this is mitigated by the power of modern computers which are able to perform all needed computations in less than 10 minutes, even for datasets with more than 1,000 samples (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t4">Table 4</xref>). In addition, our framework allows for parallel computing at the gene-level to reduce the time complexity. However, the time values reported here (in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t4">Table 4</xref>) do not take advantage of the ability to parallelize the computation in order to be comparable with the results obtained with MetaPath. All values reported in this table are obtained on a single core for both approaches.</p>
    <p>The biological results presented here could be further validated by investigating the other pathways reported as significant, and identifying the putative mechanisms that could explain all measured changes. A tool such as iPathway-Guide<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b63">63</xref>, could be used to provide more in depth functional analysis, including identification of drugs that are known to act on the observed signaling cascades. Follow-up experiments in which tumor cell lines, or samples from xenografts, are treated with those drugs would validate (or not) both the putative mechanisms investigated, as well as the other significant pathways. If many or all significant pathways were mechanistically implicated in the respective conditions, the proposed orthogonal meta-analysis approach would be further validated.</p>
    <p>Another direct application of the orthogonal framework is to infer condition-specific miRNA activity. The proposed gene-level meta-analysis basically identifies genes and miRNAs that are differentially expressed (DE) under the studied condition. This list of DE genes/miRNAs is obtained from a large number of studies and therefore it is expected to be more reliable than any individual study taken alone. From the list of DE genes/miRNAs and the computed statistics (effect sizes and variances), we can identify new putative targets of miRNAs using casual inference techniques<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b61">61</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b64">64</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b65">65</xref>. The predicted interactions between miRNA and mRNA can be further verified by established gene-specific experimental validation, such as qRT-PCR, luciferase reporter assays, and western blot<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b66">66</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b67">67</xref>.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec disp-level="1">
    <title>Conclusion</title>
    <p>In this article, we present a two-dimensional data integration that is able to combine mRNA and miRNA expression data obtained from many independent experiments. The framework first augments pathway knowledge available in pathway databases with miRNA-mRNA interactions from miRNA knowledge bases. It then computes the statistics that are essential for pathway analysis, i.e. the standardized mean difference (SMD) and p-value for differential expression. For each entity, these p-values and the SMDs are computed by combining multiple studies using robust horizontal meta-analysis techniques. Finally, the framework performs a topology-based pathway analysis to identify pathways that are likely to be impacted under the given condition.</p>
    <p>To evaluate the framework, we examine 1,471 samples from 15 mRNA and 14 miRNA expression datasets related to two human cancers, using 6 different meta-analysis approaches (3 MetaPath approaches and 3 meta-analysis approaches that utilize Impact Analysis). We demonstrate that the correct pathways are identified only when the data are integrated both horizontally (combining multiple studies using the same data type) and vertically (combining miRNA with mRNA expression).</p>
    <p>This work serves as a bridge between the two orthogonal types of data integration. The result is to unblock the sample-matched data bottleneck, by successfully integrating mRNA and miRNA datasets measured from independent laboratories for different sets of patients. Furthermore, it increases the power of statistical approaches since it allows many studies to be analyzed together. With vast databases of various data types being made available, this framework is expected to be widely applicable because of its relaxed restrictions on the data being integrated. The framework is flexible enough to integrate data types other than mRNA and miRNA. It can also be modified to suit other purposes besides pathway analysis.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec disp-level="1">
    <title>Additional Information</title>
    <p><bold>How to cite this article</bold>: Nguyen, T. <italic>et al</italic>. Overcoming the matched-sample bottleneck: an orthogonal approach to integrate omic data. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>6</bold>, 29251; doi: 10.1038/srep29251 (2016).</p>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack>
    <p>This research was supported in part by the following grants: NIH R01 DK089167, R42 GM087013 and NSF DBI-0965741, and by the Robert J. Sokol Endowment in Systems Biology. Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this material are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the views of any of the funding agencies.</p>
  </ack>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="b1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>P. K.</given-names></name><etal/>. <article-title>Evaluation of gene expression measurements from commercial microarray platforms</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>31</volume>, <fpage>5676</fpage>–<lpage>5684</lpage> (<year>2003</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14500831</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ein-Dor</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kela</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Getz</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Givol</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Domany</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Outcome signature genes in breast cancer: is there a unique set?</article-title>
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>178</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15308542</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ein-Dor</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zuk</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Domany</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Thousands of samples are needed to generate a robust gene list for predicting outcome in cancer</article-title>. <source>In Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
<volume>103</volume>, <fpage>5923</fpage>–<lpage>5928</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liberzon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/>. <article-title>Molecular signatures database (MSigDB) 3.0</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>27</volume>, <fpage>1739</fpage>–<lpage>1740</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21546393</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ashburner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/>. <article-title>Gene Ontology: tool for the unification of biology</article-title>. <source>Nature Genetics</source><volume>25</volume>, <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage> (<year>2000</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10802651</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Furumichi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>KEGG as a reference resource for gene and protein annotation</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>
<volume>44</volume>, <fpage>D457</fpage>–<lpage>D462</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26476454</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>KEGG: kyoto encyclopedia of genes and genomes</article-title>. <source>Nucleic acids research</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage> (<year>2000</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10592173</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b8">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Croft</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/>. <article-title>The Reactome pathway knowledgebase</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>42</volume>, <fpage>D472</fpage>–<lpage>D477</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24243840</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b9">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Drăghici</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Khatri</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ostermeier</surname><given-names>G. C.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Krawetz</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Global functional profiling of gene expression</article-title>. <source>Genomics</source>
<volume>81</volume>, <fpage>98</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage> (<year>2003</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12620386</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b10">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tavazoie</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Church</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Systematic determination of genetic network architecture</article-title>. <source>Nature Genetics</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>281</fpage>–<lpage>285</lpage> (<year>1999</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10391217</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b11">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/>. <article-title>Gene set enrichment analysis: a knowledge-based approach for interpreting genome-wide expression profiles</article-title>. <source>Proceeding of The National Academy of Sciences of the Unites States of America</source><volume>102</volume>, <fpage>15545</fpage>–<lpage>15550</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b12">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Efron</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Tibshirani</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>On testing the significance of sets of genes</article-title>. <source>The Annals of Applied Statistics</source>
<volume>1</volume>, <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>129</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b13">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rahnenführer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Domingues</surname><given-names>F. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maydt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Lengauer</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Calculating the Statistical Significance of Changes in Pathway Activity From Gene Expression Data</article-title>. <source>Statistical Applications in Genetics and Molecular Biology</source>
<volume>3</volume> (<year>2004</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b14">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Drăghici</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/>. <article-title>A systems biology approach for pathway level analysis</article-title>. <source>Genome Research</source><volume>17</volume>, <fpage>1537</fpage>–<lpage>1545</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17785539</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b15">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>C.-H.</given-names></name><etal/>. <article-title>miRTarBase 2016: updates to the experimentally validated miRNA-target interactions database</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>44</volume>, <fpage>D239</fpage>–<lpage>D247</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26590260</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b16">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dweep</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Gretz</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<article-title>miRWalk2. 0: a comprehensive atlas of microRNA-target interactions</article-title>. <source>Nature Methods</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>697</fpage>–<lpage>697</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26226356</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b17">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.-H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>L.-H.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.-H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>starBase v2. 0: decoding miRNA-ceRNA, miRNA-ncRNA and protein-RNA interaction networks from large-scale CLIP-Seq data</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>
<volume>42</volume>, <fpage>D92</fpage>–<lpage>D97</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24297251</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b18">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>B. P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burge</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Conserved seed pairing, often flanked by adenosines, indicates that thousands of human genes are microRNA targets</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>120</volume>, <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15652477</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b19">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vlachos</surname><given-names>I. S.</given-names></name><etal/>. <article-title>DIANA-miRPath v3. 0: deciphering microRNA function with experimental support</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>43</volume>, <fpage>W460</fpage>–<lpage>W466</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25977294</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b20">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Backes</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meese</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lenhof</surname><given-names>H.-P.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A dictionary on microRNAs and their putative target pathways</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>
<volume>38</volume>, <fpage>4476</fpage>–<lpage>4486</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20299343</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b21">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Calura</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/>. <article-title>Wiring miRNAs to pathways: a topological approach to integrate miRNA and mRNA expression profiles</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>42</volume>, <fpage>e96</fpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24803669</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b22">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vaske</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><etal/>. <article-title>Inference of patient-specific pathway activities from multi-dimensional cancer genomics data using PARADIGM</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>26</volume>, <fpage>i237</fpage>–<lpage>i245</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20529912</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b23">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/>. <article-title>NCBI GEO: archive for functional genomics data sets-update</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>41</volume>, <fpage>D991</fpage>–<lpage>D995</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23193258</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b24">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Domrachev</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Lash</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Gene Expression Omnibus: NCBI gene expression and hybridization array data repository</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11752295</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b25">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rustici</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/>. <article-title>ArrayExpress update-trends in database growth and links to data analysis tools</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>41</volume>, <fpage>D987</fpage>–<lpage>D990</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23193272</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b26">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>G. C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Feingold</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Comprehensive literature review and statistical considerations for microarray meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <fpage>3785</fpage>–<lpage>3799</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22262733</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b27">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barrette</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Chinnaiyan</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Meta-analysis of microarrays interstudy validation of gene expression profiles reveals pathway dysregulation in prostate cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer Research</source>
<volume>62</volume>, <fpage>4427</fpage>–<lpage>4433</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12154050</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b28">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tagett</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Donato</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mitrea</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Drăghici</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A novel bi-level meta-analysis approach-applied to biological pathway analysis</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>32</volume>, <fpage>409</fpage>–<lpage>416</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26471455</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b29">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal/>. <article-title>An R package suite for microarray meta-analysis in quality control, differentially expressed gene analysis and pathway enrichment detection</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>28</volume>, <fpage>2534</fpage>–<lpage>2536</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22863766</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b30">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>G. C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Meta-analysis for pathway enrichment analysis when combining multiple genomic studies</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>1316</fpage>–<lpage>1323</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20410053</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b31">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>G. K.</given-names></name><article-title>Limma: linear models for microarray data. In Gentleman</article-title>, <name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dudoit</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Irizarry</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, R. &amp; <name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name> (eds.) <source>Bioinformatics and Computational Biology Solutions Using R and Bioconductor</source>
<fpage>397</fpage>–<lpage>420</lpage> (Springer, New York, <year>2005</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b32">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Milliken</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>
<source>Analysis of messy data volume 1: designed experiments</source>
<volume>vol. 1</volume> (Chapman &amp; Hall/CRC, London, <year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b33">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Viechtbauer</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><article-title>Bias and efficiency of meta-analytic variance estimators in the random-effects model</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational and Behavioral Statistics</source><volume>30</volume>, <fpage>261</fpage>–<lpage>293</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b34">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>F. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Fixed effects vs. random effects meta-analysis models: Implications for cumulative research knowledge</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Selection and Assessment</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>292</lpage> (<year>2000</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b35">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Erez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Using random rather than fixed effects models in meta-analysis: implications for situational specificity and validity generalization</article-title>. <source>Personnel Psychology</source>
<volume>49</volume>, <fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage> (<year>1996</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b36">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><source>Statistical power analysis for the behavioral sciences</source> (Academic Press, <year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b37">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Borenstein</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hedges</surname><given-names>L. V.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Rothstein</surname><given-names>H. R.</given-names></name>
<source>Introduction to Meta-Analysis</source> (John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York, <year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b38">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hedges</surname><given-names>L. V.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Olkin</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<source>Statistical method for meta-analysis</source> (Academic Press, <year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b39">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><source>Multilevel statistical models</source><volume>vol. 922</volume> (John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York, <year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b40">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Raudenbush</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Bryk</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name>
<source>Hierarchical linear models: Applications and data analysis methods</source>
<volume>vol. 1</volume> (Sage Publications, Thousand Oaks, <year>2002</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b41">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harville</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><article-title>Maximum likelihood approaches to variance component estimation and to related problems</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Statistical Association</source><volume>72</volume>, <fpage>320</fpage>–<lpage>338</lpage> (<year>1977</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b42">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Corbeil</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Searle</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Restricted maximum likelihood (REML) estimation of variance components in the mixed model</article-title>. <source>Technometrics</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage> (<year>1976</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b43">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> Maximum likelihood estimation of components of variance. In <italic>Proceedings of the 8</italic><sup><italic>th</italic></sup>
<italic>international biometric conference,</italic> 197–207 (1975).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b44">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Edgington</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name><article-title>An additive method for combining probability values from independent experiments</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Psychology</source><volume>80</volume>, <fpage>351</fpage>–<lpage>363</lpage> (<year>1972</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b45">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><article-title>The distribution of means for samples of size n drawn from a population in which the variate takes values between 0 and 1, all such values being equally probable</article-title>. <source>Biometrika</source><volume>19</volume>, <fpage>240</fpage>–<lpage>244</lpage> (<year>1927</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b46">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>J. O.</given-names></name><article-title>On the frequency distribution of the means of samples from a population having any law of frequency with finite moments, with special reference to Pearson’s Type II</article-title>. <source>Biometrika</source><volume>19</volume>, <fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage> (<year>1927</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b47">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name><source>Statistical methods for research workers</source> (Oliver &amp; Boyd, Edinburgh, <year>1925</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b48">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stouffer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Suchman</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>DeVinney</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Star</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>RM</article-title>. <source>The American Soldier: Adjustment during army life</source>
<volume>vol. 1</volume> (Princeton University Press, Princeton, <year>1949</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b49">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mitrea</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tagett</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Drăghici</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> DANUBE: Data-driven meta-ANalysis using UnBiased Empirical distributions - applied to biological pathway analysis. <italic>Proceedings of the IEEE</italic> PP, 1–20 (2016).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b50">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kallenberg</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><source>Foundations of modern probability</source> (Springer-Verlag, New York, <year>2002</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b51">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Draghici</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<source>mirIntegrator: Integrating miRNAs into signaling pathways</source> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b52">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tarca</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name><etal/>. <article-title>A novel signaling pathway impact analysis</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>25</volume>, <fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18990722</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b53">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Meltzer</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>GEOquery: a bridge between the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) and BioConductor</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>1846</fpage>–<lpage>1847</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17496320</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b54">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Voichita</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Draghici</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<italic>ROntoTools: R Onto-Tools suite.</italic> URL <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bioconductor.org">http://www.bioconductor.org</ext-link>. R package (2013).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b55">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Controlling the false discovery rate: A practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</article-title>. <source>Journal of The Royal Statistical Society B</source>
<volume>57</volume>, <fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b56">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Viechtbauer</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/>. <article-title>Conducting meta-analyses in R with the metafor package</article-title>. <source>Journal of Statistical Software</source><volume>36</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b57">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><article-title>A statistical consideration in psychological research</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source><volume>48</volume>, <fpage>156</fpage> (<year>1951</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14834286</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b58">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tippett</surname><given-names>L. H. C.</given-names></name><source>The methods of statistics</source> (Williams &amp; Norgate, London, <year>1931</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b59">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J.-I.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Kwak</surname><given-names>J.-Y.</given-names></name> The role of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptors in colorectal cancer. <italic>PPAR research</italic>
<bold>2012</bold> (2012).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b60">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rung</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Brazma</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Reuse of public genome-wide gene expression data</article-title>. <source>Nature Reviews Genetics</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b61">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/>. <article-title>Inferring condition-specific miRNA activity from matched miRNA and mRNA expression data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>30</volume>, <fpage>3070</fpage>–<lpage>3077</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25061069</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b62">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Feinn</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Using effect size-or why the p value is not enough</article-title>. <source>Journal of Graduate Medical Education</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>279</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23997866</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b63">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Advaita Corporation. Pathway Analysis with iPathwayGuide. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.advaitabio.com/ipathwayguide.html">http://www.advaitabio.com/ipathwayguide.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b64">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Maathuis</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kalisch</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Bühlmann</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Predicting causal effects in large-scale systems from observational data</article-title>. <source>Nature Methods</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>247</fpage>–<lpage>248</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20354511</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b65">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Maathuis</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kalisch</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bühlmann</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/>. <article-title>Estimating high-dimensional intervention effects from observational data</article-title>. <source>The Annals of Statistics</source><volume>37</volume>, <fpage>3133</fpage>–<lpage>3164</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b66">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bracken</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Goodall</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Experimental strategies for microRNA target identification</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>
<volume>39</volume>, <fpage>6845</fpage>–<lpage>6853</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21652644</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="b67">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name><etal/>. <article-title>Experimental validation of miRNA targets</article-title>. <source>Methods</source><volume>44</volume>, <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18158132</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
  <fn-group>
    <fn>
      <p><bold>Author Contributions</bold> T.N. and S.D. conceived and designed the approach. T.N. implemented the method in R, performed the data analysis, all computational experiments, and wrote the manuscript. D.D. helped with data preparation and pathway augmentation. R.T. helped with the biological interpretation. R.T. and S.D. revised the manuscript. All authors approved the manuscript.</p>
    </fn>
  </fn-group>
</back>
<floats-group>
  <fig id="f1">
    <label>Figure 1</label>
    <caption>
      <title>Overall pipeline of the proposed framework.</title>
      <p>The input consists of (i) a pathway database and a miRNA database including known targets (panel a), (ii) multiple mRNA expression datasets (panel b), and (iii) multiple miRNA expression datasets (panel c). Each expression dataset consists of two groups of samples, e.g. disease versus control. The framework first augments the signaling pathways with miRNA molecules and their interactions with coding mRNA genes (panel d). It then calculates the standardized mean difference and its standard error in each expression dataset. The summary size effect across multiple datasets for each data type are then estimated using the REstricted Maximum Likelihood (REML) algorithm (panels e,f). Similarly, the p-value for differential expression is calculated for each dataset and then combined using the additive method (add-CLT). The augmented pathways, the combined p-values, and the estimated size effects then serve as input for ImpactAnalysis, which is a topology-aware pathway analysis method (panel g).</p>
    </caption>
    <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep29251-f1"/>
  </fig>
  <fig id="f2">
    <label>Figure 2</label>
    <caption>
      <title>Graphical representation of the augmented pathway <italic>Colorectal cancer</italic>.</title>
      <p>The green rectangle nodes and black arrows show the KEGG genes and their interactions while the blue nodes and red arrows show the miRNAs and their interactions with the genes, respectively. In each miRNA node added, we show the total number of miRNAs (blue circles) that are known to target the gene, and the names of the miRNA (blue rectangles) that were actually measured in the 8 colorectal miRNA datasets. This is a subset of the total set of miRNAs known to target genes on this pathway.</p>
    </caption>
    <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep29251-f2"/>
  </fig>
  <fig id="f3">
    <label>Figure 3</label>
    <caption>
      <title>Graphical representation of the augmented pathway <italic>Pancreatic cancer</italic>.</title>
      <p>The green rectangle nodes and black arrows show the KEGG genes and their interactions while the blue nodes and red arrows show the miRNAs and their interactions with the genes. In each miRNA node added, we show the total number of miRNAs (blue circles) that are known to target the gene, and the names of the miRNA (blue rectangles) that were actually measured in the 6 pancreatic miRNA datasets. This is a subset of the total set of miRNAs known to target genes on this pathway.</p>
    </caption>
    <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep29251-f3"/>
  </fig>
  <table-wrap position="float" id="t1">
    <label>Table 1</label>
    <caption>
      <title>Description of miRNA and mRNA expression datasets used in the experimental studies.</title>
    </caption>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
      <colgroup>
        <col align="left"/>
        <col align="left"/>
        <col align="left"/>
        <col align="center"/>
        <col align="center"/>
        <col align="left"/>
        <col align="left"/>
      </colgroup>
      <thead valign="bottom">
        <tr>
          <th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Cancer</th>
          <th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Data</th>
          <th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Accession ID</th>
          <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Control</th>
          <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Disease</th>
          <th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Tissue</th>
          <th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Platform</th>
        </tr>
      </thead>
      <tbody valign="top">
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="15" align="left" valign="middle" charoff="50">Colorectal</td>
          <td rowspan="7" align="left" valign="middle" charoff="50">mRNA</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE4107</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">10</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">12</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Colonic mucosa</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Affymetrix HG U133 Plus 2.0</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE9348</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">12</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">70</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Colonic mucosa</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Affymetrix HG U133 Plus 2.0</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE15781</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">10</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">13</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Colon</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ABI HG Survey 2</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE21510</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">25</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">123</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Colon</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Affymetrix HG U133 Plus 2.0</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE23878</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">24</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">35</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Colon</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Affymetrix HG U133 Plus 2.0</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE41657</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">12</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">25</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Colonic mucosa, epithelial neoplasm</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Agilent-014850 HG 4×44K G4112F</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE62322</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">18</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">20</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Colon</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Affymetrix HG U133A</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="8" align="left" valign="middle" charoff="50">miRNA</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE33125</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">9</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">9</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Colon</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Illumina Human v2 MicroRNA</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE35834</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">23</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">55</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Colon &amp; rectum</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Affymetrix miRNA 1.0</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE39814</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">9</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">10</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">FHC, HCT116, &amp; SW480 cells</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Agilent-021827 Human miRNA</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE39833</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">11</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">88</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Peripheral blood serum</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Agilent-021827 Human miRNA</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE41655</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">15</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">33</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Colonic mucosa, &amp; epithelial neoplasm</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Agilent-021827 Human miRNA</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE49246</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">40</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">40</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Colon</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Sun Yat-Sen Human microRNA</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE54632</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Colonic and rectal mucosa</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Affymetrix miRNA 1.0</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE73487</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">23</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">90</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Colon</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Affymetrix miRNA 1.0</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="14" align="left" valign="middle" charoff="50">Pancreatic</td>
          <td rowspan="8" align="left" valign="middle" charoff="50">mRNA</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE15471</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">39</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">39</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Pancreas</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Affymetrix HG U133 Plus 2.0</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE19279</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Pancreas, pancreatic duct</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Affymetrix HG U133A</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE27890</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Pancreas, ductal epithelia</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Affymetrix HG U133 Plus 2.0</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE32676</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">7</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">25</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Pancreas</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Affymetrix HG U133 Plus 2.0</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE36076</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">10</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Peripheral blood mononuclear cells</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Affymetrix HG U133 Plus 2.0</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE43288</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Pancreas</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Affymetrix HG U133A</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE45757</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">9</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">132</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Pancreatic epithelial &amp; cancer cells</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Affymetrix HG U133A</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE60601</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">9</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">CD14++ &amp; CD16- cells</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Affymetrix HG U133 Plus 2.0</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="6" align="left" valign="middle" charoff="50">miRNA</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE24279</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">22</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">136</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Pancreas</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Febit human miRBase v11</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE25820</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Pancreatic duct</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Agilent-019118 Human miRNA</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE32678</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">7</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">25</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Pancreas</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">miRCURY LNA microRNA, v.11.0</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE34052</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Pancreas</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Agilent-029297 Human miRNA</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE43796</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">26</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Pancreas</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Agilent-031181 Human miRNA V16</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GSE60978</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">51</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Pancreatic duct</td>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Agilent-031181 Human miRNA V16</td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
    <table-wrap-foot>
      <fn id="t1-fn1">
        <p>All of the data were downloaded from Gene Expression Omnibus.</p>
      </fn>
    </table-wrap-foot>
  </table-wrap>
  <table-wrap position="float" id="t2">
    <label>Table 2</label>
    <caption>
      <title>The 16 top ranked pathways and FDR-corrected p-values obtained by combining colorectal data using 6 approaches: MetaPath_P, MetaPath_G, MetaPath_I, ImpactAnalysis_P, ImpactAnalysis_G, and ImpactAnalysis_I.</title>
    </caption>
    <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep29251-t2"/>
    <table-wrap-foot>
      <fn id="t2-fn1">
        <p>The horizontal lines show the 1% significance threshold. The target pathway <italic>Colorectal cancer</italic> is <italic>highlighted in green</italic>. All other approaches, MetaPath_P, MetaPath_G, MetaPath_I, ImpactAnalysis_P, ImpactAnalysis_G fail to identify the target pathway as significant, and rank it at the positions 16<sup><italic>th</italic></sup>, 9<sup><italic>th</italic></sup>, 15<sup><italic>th</italic></sup>, 61<sup><italic>st</italic></sup>, and 10<sup><italic>th</italic></sup>, respectively. On the contrary, the integrative approach, ImpactAnalysis_I, identifies the target pathway as significant and ranks it on top.</p>
      </fn>
    </table-wrap-foot>
  </table-wrap>
  <table-wrap position="float" id="t3">
    <label>Table 3</label>
    <caption>
      <title>The 10 top ranked pathways and FDR-corrected <italic>p</italic>-values obtained by combining colorectal data using 6 approaches: MetaPath_P, MetaPath_G, MetaPath_I, ImpactAnalysis_P, ImpactAnalysis_G, and ImpactAnalysis_I.</title>
    </caption>
    <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep29251-t3"/>
    <table-wrap-foot>
      <fn id="t3-fn1">
        <p>The horizontal lines show the 1% significance threshold. The target pathway <italic>Pancreatic cancer</italic> is <italic>highlighted in green</italic>. All other approaches, MetaPath_P, MetaPath_G, MetaPath_I, ImpactAnalysis_P, ImpactAnalysis_G fail to identify the target pathway as significant, and rank it at the positions 17<sup><italic>th</italic></sup>, 91<sup><italic>st</italic></sup>, 91<sup><italic>st</italic></sup>, 32<sup><italic>nd</italic></sup>, and 8<sup><italic>th</italic></sup>, respectively. On the contrary, the integrative approach, ImpactAnalysis_I, identifies the target pathway as significant and ranks it on top.</p>
      </fn>
    </table-wrap-foot>
  </table-wrap>
  <table-wrap position="float" id="t4">
    <label>Table 4</label>
    <caption>
      <title>Running time of each pathway analysis in minutes (m).</title>
    </caption>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
      <colgroup>
        <col align="left"/>
        <col align="center"/>
        <col align="center"/>
        <col align="center"/>
      </colgroup>
      <thead valign="bottom">
        <tr>
          <th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Method</th>
          <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Input</th>
          <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Colorectal</th>
          <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Pancreatic</th>
        </tr>
      </thead>
      <tbody valign="top">
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ImpactAnalysis_I</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">mRNA &amp; miRNA</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4 m</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4 m</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">MetaPath</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">mRNA</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">39 m</td>
          <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">47 m</td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
  </table-wrap>
</floats-group>
