<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1367-4803</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1367-4811</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5860143</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29106469</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btx713</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">btx713</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Applications Notes</subject>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading">
          <subject>Genome Analysis</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>DFAST: a flexible prokaryotic genome annotation pipeline for faster genome publication</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Tanizawa</surname>
          <given-names>Yasuhiro</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btx713-aff1"/>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Fujisawa</surname>
          <given-names>Takatomo</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btx713-aff1"/>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Nakamura</surname>
          <given-names>Yasukazu</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btx713-aff1"/>
        <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="btx713-cor1"/>
        <!--<email>yn@nig.ac.jp</email>-->
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name>
          <surname>Hancock</surname>
          <given-names>John</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Associate Editor</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <aff id="btx713-aff1">Center for Information Biology, National Institute of Genetics, Research Organization of Information and Systems, 1111 Yata, Mishima, Japan</aff>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="btx713-cor1">To whom correspondence should be addressed. Email: <email>yn@nig.ac.jp</email></corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
      <day>15</day>
      <month>3</month>
      <year>2018</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2017-11-02">
      <day>02</day>
      <month>11</month>
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>02</day>
      <month>11</month>
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
    <volume>34</volume>
    <issue>6</issue>
    <fpage>1037</fpage>
    <lpage>1039</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2017</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>27</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2017</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>06</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2017</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author 2017. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license license-type="cc-by" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xlink:href="btx713.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <sec id="s1">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <p>We developed a prokaryotic genome annotation pipeline, DFAST, that also supports genome submission to public sequence databases. DFAST was originally started as an on-line annotation server, and to date, over 7000 jobs have been processed since its first launch in 2016. Here, we present a newly implemented background annotation engine for DFAST, which is also available as a standalone command-line program. The new engine can annotate a typical-sized bacterial genome within 10 min, with rich information such as pseudogenes, translation exceptions and orthologous gene assignment between given reference genomes. In addition, the modular framework of DFAST allows users to customize the annotation workflow easily and will also facilitate extensions for new functions and incorporation of new tools in the future.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2">
        <title>Availability and implementation</title>
        <p>The software is implemented in Python 3 and runs in both Python 2.7 and 3.4—on Macintosh and Linux systems. It is freely available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/nigyta/dfast_core/under">https://github.com/nigyta/dfast_core/under</ext-link> the GPLv3 license with external binaries bundled in the software distribution. An on-line version is also available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dfast.nig.ac.jp/">https://dfast.nig.ac.jp/</ext-link>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4">
        <title>Supplementary information</title>
        <p><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary data</xref> are available at <italic>Bioinformatics</italic> online.</p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <named-content content-type="funder-name">JSPS</named-content>
          <named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/501100001691</named-content>
        </funding-source>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="3"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec>
    <title>1 Introduction</title>
    <p>Most scientific journals require newly obtained sequence data to be deposited in the International Nucleotide Sequence Database Collaboration (INSDC) as a condition of publication (<xref rid="btx713-B1" ref-type="bibr">Cochrane <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). However, submission of annotated genomes to public databases remains a burden for researchers. The NCBI provides an annotation service called Prokaryotic Genome Annotation Pipeline (PGAP) (<xref rid="btx713-B10" ref-type="bibr">Tatusova <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>) incorporated in its submission system, but it is only available for GenBank submitters. The on-line server Microbial Genome Annotation Pipeline (MiGAP) (<xref rid="btx713-B7" ref-type="bibr">Sugawara <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>) partly supports DDBJ submission; however, it requires extensive manual revision. To address these issues, we recently developed a web-based pipeline called DDBJ Fast Annotation and Submission Tool (DFAST), aiming to assist users to submit their genomes to DDBJ (<xref rid="btx713-B9" ref-type="bibr">Tanizawa <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). The original version of DFAST employs the lightweight command-line program Prokka (<xref rid="btx713-B6" ref-type="bibr">Seemann, 2014</xref>) as an annotation engine, combined with curated reference databases and a graphical user interface to create submission files to DDBJ.</p>
    <p>Here, we report a new implementation of the background engine of DFAST, which is called DFAST-core to differentiate it from its web version. The new version features unique functions, such as pseudogene annotation and orthologous assignments between reference genomes. DFAST-core is also available as a standalone program, providing a flexible local annotation platform. Hereinafter, we simply refer to it as DFAST in this report.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>2 Materials and methods</title>
    <p>DFAST accepts a FASTA-formatted file as a minimum required input, and users can customize parameters, tools and reference databases by providing command line options or defining an original configuration file (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Note</xref>s for more details). The workflow is mainly composed of two annotation phases, i.e. structural annotation for predicting biological features such as CDSs, RNAs and CRISPRs, and functional annotation for inferring protein functions of predicted CDSs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="btx713-F1">Figure 1</xref> shows a schematic depiction of the pipeline. Each annotation process is implemented as a module with common interfaces, allowing both flexible annotation workflows and extensions for new functions in the future.
</p>
    <fig id="btx713-F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>DFAST annotation workflow. Items marked with asterisks are included in the default workflow</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="btx713f1"/>
    </fig>
    <p>In the default configuration, functional annotation will be processed in the following order:
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Orthologous assignment (optional) All-against-all pairwise protein alignments are conducted between a query and each reference genome. Orthologous genes are identified based on a Reciprocal-Best-Hit approach. It also conducts self-to-self alignments within a query genome, in which genes scoring higher than their corresponding orthologs are considered in-paralogs and assigned with the same protein function. This process is effective in transferring annotations from closely related organisms and in reducing running time.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Homology search against the default reference database DFAST uses GHOSTX as a default aligner, which runs tens to hundred times faster than BLASTP with similar levels of sensitivity where E-values are less than 10<sup>−6</sup> (<xref rid="btx713-B8" ref-type="bibr">Suzuki <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). Users can also choose BLASTP. For accurate annotation, we constructed a reference database from 124 well-curated prokaryotic genomes from public databases. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Data</xref> for the breakdown of the database.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Pseudogene detection CDSs and their flanking regions are re-aligned to their subject protein sequences using LAST, which allows frameshift alignment (<xref rid="btx713-B3" ref-type="bibr">Kiełbasa <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). When stop codons or frameshifts are found in the flanking regions, the query is marked as a possible pseudogene. This also detects translation exceptions such as selenocysteine and pyrrolysine.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Profile HMM database search against TIGRFAM (<xref rid="btx713-B2" ref-type="bibr">Haft <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>) It uses hmmscan of the HMMer software package.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Assignment of COG functional categories RPS-BLAST and the rpsbproc utility are used to search against the Clusters of Orthologous Groups (COG) database provided by the NCBI Conserved Domain Database (<xref rid="btx713-B4" ref-type="bibr">Marchler-Bauer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>).</p></list-item></list>DFAST output files include INSDC submission files as well as standard GFF3, GenBank and FASTA files. For GenBank submission, two input files for the tbl2asn program are generated, a feature table (.tbl) and a sequence file (.fsa). For DDBJ submission, DFAST generates submission files required for DDBJ Mass Submission System (MSS) (<xref rid="btx713-B5" ref-type="bibr">Mashima <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). In particular, if additional metadata such as contact and reference information are supplied, it can generate fully qualified files that are ready for submission to MSS.</p>
    <p>While the workflow described above is fully customizable in the stand-alone version, only limited features are currently available in the web version, e.g. orthologous assignment is not available. As a merit of the web version, users can curate the assigned protein names by using an on-line annotation editor with an easy access to the NCBI BLAST web service. We also offer optional databases for specific organism groups (<italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, lactic acid bacteria, bifidobacteria and cyanobacteria). They are downloadable from our web site and can be used in the stand-alone version. We are updating reference databases to cover more diverse organisms.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>3 Results and discussion</title>
    <p>We annotated the genome of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> O26: H11 str. 11368 using DFAST, Prokka and MiGAP, and compared the results to the INSDC data manually curated by original submitters (deposited in the NCBI Assembly Database under GCA_000091005.1) and the RefSeq data annotated using PGAP (GCF_000091005.1), as summarized in <xref rid="btx713-T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.
<table-wrap id="btx713-T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Comparison of annotation results of <italic>E.coli</italic> O26: H11 str. 11368</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Data source/Annotation tool</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">INSDC<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn2"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RefSeq<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn3"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DFAST</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prokka</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MiGAP</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total CDS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5795</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6243</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5740</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5759</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5721</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> <italic>Pseudogene</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn4"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">276</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">337 (250/87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">344 (158/186)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[30<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn5"><sup>d</sup></xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> <italic>Selenoprotein</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> <italic>With COG number</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3965</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4392</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> <italic>Unknown function</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1203</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1514</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1347</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2068</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">418</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tRNA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rRNA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRISPR array</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Running time</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 m 27 s</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 m 20 s</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 h 43 m</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><p><italic>Note</italic>: Numbers represent annotated features and running time. DFAST and Prokka were run on a 4-core Macintosh laptop with default settings.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn2"><label>a</label><p>Original annotation by submitters (GCA_000091005.1).</p></fn><fn id="tblfn3"><label>b</label><p>Annotated by PGAP (GCF_000091005.1).</p></fn><fn id="tblfn4"><label>c</label><p>Numbers in parentheses denote internal stop codon/frameshift and partial genes, respectively.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn5"><label>d</label><p>Candidates for pseudogenes are mentioned in the log file, not in the result.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
    <p>Our simple strategy to find pseudogenes depends on the accuracy of reference databases. However, when references from close relatives are available, DFAST outperforms other tools. Among 158 CDSs in which internal stop codons or frameshifts were identified, 123 were found to be consistent with the INSDC data (78%). Although the comparison is not straightforward as annotation formats are different, 97 out of 250 identified by PGAP were consistent (39%). Notably, DFAST succeeded in annotating all 3 selenoproteins present in the query genome.</p>
    <p>Another major advantage of our pipeline is its speed. The running time of DFAST is comparable with that of Prokka, yet the default reference database of DFAST (417 922 sequences in total) is 20 times larger than that of Prokka (18 276 sequences). This is mostly attributable to the efficient algorithm of GHOSTX. If BLASTP is used instead, running time will increase up to 40 min under the same condition. In accordance with the database size, the number of genes with assigned function was larger than Prokka, although smaller than MiGAP, which conducts sequence search against a more comprehensive database such as UniProtKB/TrEMBL.</p>
    <p>In general, DFAST performs well with the default settings on well-characterized organisms, such as <italic>Actinobacteria</italic>, <italic>Firmicutes</italic> and <italic>Proteobacteria</italic>. The annotation of the genomes from less-studied species, for which references of close relatives are not present in the default database, may contain relatively large number of uncharacterized genes. In such cases, providing additional references will improve the results as demonstrated in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Notes</xref>.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup1">
      <label>Supplementary Data</label>
      <media xlink:href="btx713_supp.zip">
        <caption>
          <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
        </caption>
      </media>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack>
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <p>We thank Yoshitoshi Ogura and Keiji Nakamura for providing us the sample genome data, Martin Frith for suggestions on pseudogene detection, Yutaka Akiyama and Shuji Suzuki for technical advice for GHOSTX, and Masanori Arita for reviewing the manuscript. MetaGeneAnnotator is redistributed by courtesy of Hideki Noguchi.</p>
    <sec>
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p>This work was supported by JSPS KAKENHI [grant number 16H06279].</p>
      <p><italic>Conflict of Interest</italic>: none declared.</p>
    </sec>
  </ack>
  <ref-list>
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="btx713-B1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cochrane</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) 
<article-title>The International Nucleotide Sequence Database Collaboration</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>D48</fpage>–<lpage>D50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26657633</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btx713-B2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haft</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) 
<article-title>TIGRFAMs and genome properties in 2013</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>D387</fpage>–<lpage>D395</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23197656</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btx713-B3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiełbasa</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) 
<article-title>Adaptive seeds tame genomic sequence comparison</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>., <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>487</fpage>–<lpage>493</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21209072</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btx713-B4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marchler-Bauer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) 
<article-title>CDD/SPARCLE: functional classification of proteins via subfamily domain architectures</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>D200</fpage>–<lpage>D203</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27899674</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btx713-B5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mashima</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) 
<article-title>DNA Data Bank of Japan</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>D25</fpage>–<lpage>D31</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27924010</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btx713-B6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seemann</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) 
<article-title>Prokka: rapid prokaryotic genome annotation</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>2068</fpage>–<lpage>2069</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24642063</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btx713-B7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sugawara</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) Microbial genome annotation pipeline (MiGAP) for diverse users. In: <italic>Proceedings of the 20th International Conference on Genome Informatics</italic>, <italic>Yokohama</italic>, <italic>Japan</italic>, S–001–1–2.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btx713-B8">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) 
<article-title>GHOSTX: an improved sequence homology search algorithm using a query suffix array and a database suffix array</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>e103833</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25099887</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btx713-B9">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanizawa</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) 
<article-title>DFAST and DAGA: Web-based integrated genome annotation tools and resources</article-title>. <source>BMFH</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>184</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27867804</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btx713-B10">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tatusova</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) 
<article-title>NCBI prokaryotic genome annotation pipeline</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>6614</fpage>–<lpage>6624</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27342282</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
