<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genome Biol</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genome Biol</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Genome Biology</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1474-7596</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1474-760X</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5080738</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27782827</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1077</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-016-1077-y</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Method</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>A statistical approach for identifying differential distributions in single-cell RNA-seq experiments</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Korthauer</surname>
          <given-names>Keegan D.</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>keegan@jimmy.harvard.edu</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Chu</surname>
          <given-names>Li-Fang</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>LChu@morgridge.org</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Newton</surname>
          <given-names>Michael A.</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>newton@biostat.wisc.edu</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Li</surname>
          <given-names>Yuan</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>yuanli@stat.wisc.edu</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Thomson</surname>
          <given-names>James</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>jthomson@morgridgeinstitute.org</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Stewart</surname>
          <given-names>Ron</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>RStewart@morgridge.org</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <name>
          <surname>Kendziorski</surname>
          <given-names>Christina</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>kendzior@biostat.wisc.edu</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Biostatistics and Computational Biology, Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, Boston, 02215 MA USA </aff>
      <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Biostatistics, Harvard T. H. Chan School of Public Health, Boston, 02115 MA USA </aff>
      <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Morgridge Institute for Research, University of Wisconsin, Madison, 53706 WI USA </aff>
      <aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Biostatistics, University of Wisconsin, Madison, 53706 WI USA </aff>
      <aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>Department of Statistics, University of Wisconsin, Madison, 53706 WI USA </aff>
      <aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label>Department of Cell and Regenerative Biology, University of Wisconsin, Madison, 53706 WI USA </aff>
      <aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label>Department of Molecular, Cellular, and Developmental Biology, University of California, Santa Barbara, 93106 CA USA </aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>25</day>
      <month>10</month>
      <year>2016</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>25</day>
      <month>10</month>
      <year>2016</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <year>2016</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>17</volume>
    <elocation-id>222</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>4</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>4</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2016</copyright-statement>
      <license license-type="OpenAccess">
        <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract id="Abs1">
      <p>The ability to quantify cellular heterogeneity is a major advantage of single-cell technologies. However, statistical methods often treat cellular heterogeneity as a nuisance. We present a novel method to characterize differences in expression in the presence of distinct expression states within and among biological conditions. We demonstrate that this framework can detect differential expression patterns under a wide range of settings. Compared to existing approaches, this method has higher power to detect subtle differences in gene expression distributions that are more complex than a mean shift, and can characterize those differences. The freely available R package scDD implements the approach.</p>
      <sec>
        <title>Electronic supplementary material</title>
        <p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s13059-016-1077-y) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
      <title>Keywords</title>
      <kwd>Single-cell RNA-seq</kwd>
      <kwd>Differential expression</kwd>
      <kwd>Cellular heterogeneity</kwd>
      <kwd>Mixture modeling</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group>
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000057</institution-id>
            <institution>National Institute of General Medical Sciences</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>GM102756</award-id>
        <principal-award-recipient>
          <name>
            <surname>Kendziorski</surname>
            <given-names>Christina</given-names>
          </name>
        </principal-award-recipient>
      </award-group>
      <award-group>
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000060</institution-id>
            <institution>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>U54AI117924</award-id>
        <principal-award-recipient>
          <name>
            <surname>Kendziorski</surname>
            <given-names>Christina</given-names>
          </name>
        </principal-award-recipient>
      </award-group>
      <award-group>
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000002</institution-id>
            <institution>National Institutes of Health</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>4UH3TR000506-03</award-id>
        <principal-award-recipient>
          <name>
            <surname>Thomson</surname>
            <given-names>James</given-names>
          </name>
        </principal-award-recipient>
      </award-group>
      <award-group>
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000050</institution-id>
            <institution>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>5U01HL099773-06</award-id>
        <principal-award-recipient>
          <name>
            <surname>Thomson</surname>
            <given-names>James</given-names>
          </name>
        </principal-award-recipient>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
        <meta-value>© The Author(s) 2016</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec id="Sec1">
    <title>Background</title>
    <p>Coordinated gene expression is fundamental to an organism’s development and maintenance, and aberrations are common in disease. Consequently, experiments to measure expression on a genome-wide scale are pervasive. The most common experiment involves the quantification of mRNA transcript abundance averaged over a population of thousands or millions of cells. These so-called traditional, or bulk, RNA-seq experiments have proven useful in a multitude of studies. However, because bulk RNA-seq does not provide a measure of cell-specific expression, many important signals go unobserved. A gene that appears to be expressed at a relatively constant level in a bulk RNA-seq experiment, for example, may actually be expressed in sub-groups of cells at levels that vary substantially (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Schematic of the presence of two cell states within a cell population that can lead to bimodal expression distributions. <bold>a</bold> Time series of the underlying expression state of gene X in a population of unsynchronized single cells, which switches back and forth between a low and high state with means <italic>μ</italic>
<sub>1</sub> and <italic>μ</italic>
<sub>2</sub>, respectively. The color of cells at each time point corresponds to the underlying expression state. <bold>b</bold> Population of individual cells shaded by expression state of gene X at a snapshot in time. <bold>c</bold> Histogram of the observed expression level of gene X for the cell population in (<bold>b</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
</p>
    <p>Single-cell RNA-seq (scRNA-seq) facilitates the measurement of genome-wide mRNA abundance in individual cells, and as a result, provides the opportunity to study the extent of gene-specific expression heterogeneity within a biological condition, and the impact of changes across conditions. Doing so is required for discovering novel cell types [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], for elucidating how gene expression changes contribute to development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], for understanding the role of cell heterogeneity on the immune response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] and cancer progression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], and for predicting the response to chemotherapeutic agents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Unfortunately, the statistical methods available for characterizing gene-specific expression within a condition and for identifying differences across conditions in scRNA-seq are greatly limited, largely because they do not fully accommodate the cellular heterogeneity that is prevalent in single-cell data.</p>
    <p>To identify genes with expression that varies across biological conditions in an scRNA-seq experiment, a number of early studies used methods from bulk RNA-seq [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. In general, the methods assume that each gene has a latent level of expression within a biological condition, and that measurements fluctuate around that level due to biological and technical sources of variability. In other words, they assume that gene-specific expression is well characterized by a unimodal distribution within a condition. Further, tests for differences in expression to identify so-called differentially expressed (DE) genes amount to tests for shifts in the unimodal distributions across conditions. A major drawback of these approaches in the single-cell setting is that, due to both biological and technical cell-to-cell variability, there is often an abundance of cells for which a given gene’s expression is unobserved [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] and, consequently, unimodal distributions are insufficient.</p>
    <p>To address this, a number of statistical methods have been developed recently to accommodate bimodality in scRNA-seq data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. In these mixture-model based approaches, one component distribution accommodates unobserved, or dropout, measurements (which include zero and, optionally, thresholded low-magnitude observations) and a second unimodal component describes gene expression in cells where expression is observed. Although these approaches provide an advance over unimodal models used in bulk, they are insufficient for characterizing multi-modal expression data, which is common in scRNA-seq experiments (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of modality in bulk versus single cells. Bar plot of the proportion of genes (or transcripts) in each dataset where the log-transformed nonzero expression measurements are best fit by a 1, 2, or 3 + mode normal mixture model (where 3+ denotes 3 or more). Modality is determined using a Bayesian information selection criterion with filtering (see “<xref rid="Sec27" ref-type="sec">Partition estimation</xref>”). <italic>Red shades</italic> denote bulk RNA-seq datasets, and <italic>blue shades</italic> denote single-cell datasets. The number following each dataset label indicates the number of samples present (e.g., <italic>GE.50</italic> is a bulk dataset with 50 samples). Datasets <italic>GE.50</italic>, <italic>GE.75</italic>, and <italic>GE.100</italic> are constructed by randomly sampling 50, 75, and 100 samples from GEUVADIS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. Dataset <italic>LC</italic> consists of 77 normal samples from the TCGA lung adenocarcinoma study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. For details of the single-cell datasets, see “<xref rid="Sec17" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>”</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig>
</p>
    <p>Specifically, a number of studies have shown that many types of heterogeneity can give rise to multiple expression modes within a given gene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. For example, there are often multiple states among expressed genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] (a schematic is shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The transition between cell states may be primarily stochastic in nature and result from expression bursts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], or result from positive feedback signals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Beyond the existence of multiple stable states, multiple modes in the distribution of expression levels in a population of cells may also arise when the gene is either oscillatory and unsynchronized, or oscillatory with cellular heterogeneity in frequency, phase, and amplitude [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p>
    <p>Figure <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> illustrates common multi-modal distributions within and across biological conditions. When the overall mean expression level for a given gene is shifted across conditions, then bulk methods, or recent methods for scRNA-seq [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], may be able to identify the gene as showing some change. However, as we show here, they would be relatively underpowered to do so, and they would be unable to characterize the change, which is often of interest in an scRNA-seq experiment. For example, the gene in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>
<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">c</xref> shows a differential number of modes (DM), while the gene in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>
<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">b</xref> shows a differential proportion (DP) of cells at each expression level across conditions. Differentiating between DM and DP is important since the former suggests the presence of a distinct cell type in one condition, but not the other, while the latter suggests a change in splicing patterns among individual cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] or cell-specific responses to signaling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Diagram of plausible differential distribution patterns (smoothed density histograms), including <bold>a</bold> traditional differential expression (DE), <bold>b</bold> differential proportion of cells within each component (DP), <bold>c</bold> differential modality (DM), and <bold>d</bold> both differential modality and different component means within each condition (DB). <italic>DB</italic> both differential modality and different component means, <italic>DE</italic> differential expression, <italic>DM</italic> differential modality, <italic>DP</italic> differential proportion</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig>
</p>
    <p>Here we develop a Bayesian modeling framework, scDD, to facilitate the characterization of expression within a biological condition, and to identify genes with differential distributions (DDs) across conditions in an scRNA-seq experiment. A DD gene may be classified as DE, DM, DP, or both DM and differential means of expression states (abbreviated DB). Figure <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> provides an overview of each pattern. Simulation studies suggest that the approach provides improved power and precision for identifying differentially distributed genes. Additional advantages are demonstrated in a case study of human embryonic stem cells (hESCs).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec2">
    <title>Results and discussion</title>
    <sec id="Sec3">
      <title>Human embryonic stem cell data</title>
      <p>scRNA-seq data were generated in the James Thomson Lab at the Morgridge Institute for Research (see “<xref rid="Sec17" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>” and [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] for details). Here we analyze data from two undifferentiated hESC lines: the male H1 line (78 cells) and the female H9 line (87 cells). In addition, we include data from two differentiated cell types that are both derived from H1: definitive endoderm cells (DECs, 64 cells) and neuronal progenitor cells (NPCs, 86 cells). The relationship between these four cell types is summarized by the diagram in Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>. As discussed in the case study results, it is of interest to characterize the differences in distributions of gene expression among these four cell types to gain insight into the genes that regulate the differentiation process.
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Relationship of cell types used in hESC case study. <italic>H1</italic> and <italic>H9</italic> are undifferentiated hESC lines. <italic>NPC</italic> (neuronal progenitor cells) and <italic>DEC</italic> (definitive endoderm cells) are differentiated cell types derived from <italic>H1</italic>. <italic>DEC</italic> definitive endoderm cell, <italic>NPC</italic> neuronal progenitor cell</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig>
</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4">
      <title>Publicly available human myoblast and mouse embryonic stem cell data</title>
      <p>We also apply our method to two publicly available scRNA-seq datasets to determine which genes are differentially distributed following stimulation or inhibition of differentiation via a specialized growth medium. Using data from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], we compare gene expression of human myoblast cells cultured in standard growth medium (T0, 96 cells) with those treated with differentiation-inducing medium for 72 hours (T72, 84 cells). Additionally, we use data from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>] to compare the gene expression of mouse embryonic stem cells (mESCs) cultured in standard medium (Serum + LIF, 93 cells) with those cultured on differentiation-inhibiting medium (2i + LIF, 94 cells).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec5">
      <title>Simulated data</title>
      <p>We evaluate model performance using log-transformed count data simulated from mixtures of negative binomial distributions. The analysis of log-transformed counts from bulk RNA-seq has been shown to perform as well as utilizing count-based modeling assumptions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Recent scRNA-seq analyses have also assumed the normality of log-transformed nonzero measurements [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. For each simulated dataset, 10,000 genes were simulated for two conditions with four different sample size settings (50, 75, 100, and 500 cells in each condition). The majority of the genes (8000) were simulated out of the same model in each condition, and the other 2000 represent genes with the four types of DD outlined in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>. The 2000 DD genes were split equally into the following four categories: 
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>DE: single component with a different mean in each condition</p></list-item><list-item><p>DP: two components in each condition with equal component means across conditions; the proportion in the low mode is 0.33 for condition 1 and 0.66 for condition 2</p></list-item><list-item><p>DM: single component in condition 1; two components in condition 2 with one overlapping component. Half of the condition 2 cells belong to each mode</p></list-item><list-item><p>DB: single component in condition 1; two components in condition 2 with no overlapping components. The mean of condition 1 is half-way between the means in condition 2. Half of the cells in condition 2 belong to each mode</p></list-item></list>
</p>
      <p>Here a component represents the distribution of expression values at a particular expression level (or mode), and different biological groups of interest are referred to as conditions. Of the 8000 null genes, 4000 were generated from a single negative binomial component (EE, or equivalent expression) and the other 4000 from a two-component negative binomial mixture (EP, or equivalent proportions of cells belonging to each component). The parameters of the negative binomial distributions for the unimodal genes were chosen to be representative of the observed means and variances in the H1 dataset. Fold-changes for DE genes were chosen to be representative of those observed in the H1 and DEC comparison. Distances between (log-scale) component means <italic>Δ</italic>
<sub><italic>μ</italic></sub>
<italic>σ</italic> (referred to as component mean distance) in the multi-modal genes were varied, with an equal proportion of genes at each setting of <italic>Δ</italic>
<sub><italic>μ</italic></sub>∈{2,3,4,5,6}, where <italic>σ</italic> is the within-component standard deviation on the log-scale (simulated to be common across components for a given gene and condition). More details are provided in “<xref rid="Sec17" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>”.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec6">
      <title>The scDD modeling framework</title>
      <p>Let <italic>Y</italic>
<sub><italic>g</italic></sub>=(<italic>y</italic>
<sub><italic>g</italic>1</sub>,…,<italic>y</italic>
<sub><italic>g</italic><italic>J</italic></sub>) be the log-transformed nonzero expression measurements of gene <italic>g</italic> in a collection of <italic>J</italic> cells from two biological conditions. We assume that measurements have been normalized to adjust for technical sources of variation including amplification bias and sequencing depth. Under the null hypothesis of equivalent distributions (i.e., no dependence on condition), we let <italic>Y</italic>
<sub><italic>g</italic></sub> be modeled by a conjugate Dirichlet process mixture (DPM) of normals (see “<xref rid="Sec17" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>” for more details). Gene <italic>g</italic> may also have expression measurements of zero in some cells; these are modeled as a separate distributional component (see “<xref rid="Sec8" ref-type="sec">Differential proportion of zeroes</xref>” for more details).</p>
      <p>Ultimately, we would like to calculate a Bayes factor for the evidence that the data arises from two independent condition-specific models (DDs) versus one overall model that ignores condition (equivalent distributions or EDs). Let <inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\mathcal {M}_{\text {DD}}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℳ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>DD</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> denote the DD hypothesis, and <inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\mathcal {M}_{\text {ED}}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℳ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>ED</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_IEq2.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> denote the equivalent distribution hypothesis. A Bayes factor in this context for gene <italic>g</italic> would be: 
<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ \operatorname{BF}_{g} = \frac{f(Y_{g} | \mathcal{M}_{\text{DD}})}{f(Y_{g} | \mathcal{M}_{\text{ED}})} $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>BF</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℳ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>DD</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℳ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>ED</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula> where <inline-formula id="IEq3"><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$f(Y_{g} | \mathcal {M})$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℳ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_IEq3.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> denotes the predictive distribution of the observations from gene <italic>g</italic> under the given hypothesis. In general, there is no analytical solution for this distribution under the DPM model framework. However, under the product partition model (PPM) formulation (see “<xref rid="Sec17" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>” for more details), we can get a closed form solution for <inline-formula id="IEq4"><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$f(Y_{g}, Z_{g} | \mathcal {M})$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℳ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_IEq4.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, where <italic>Z</italic>
<sub><italic>g</italic></sub> represents a partition (or clustering) of samples to mixture components. As the partition <italic>Z</italic>
<sub><italic>g</italic></sub> cannot be integrated out, we introduce an approximate Bayes factor score: 
<disp-formula id="Equb"><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{aligned} \operatorname{Score}_{g} &amp;= \log \left(\frac{f(Y_{g}, Z_{g} | \mathcal{M}_{\text{DD}})}{f(Y_{g}, Z_{g} | \mathcal{M}_{\text{ED}})}\right)\\ &amp;= \log\left(\frac{f_{C1}(Y_{g}^{C1}, Z_{g}^{C1}) f_{C1}(Y_{g}^{C2}, Z_{g}^{C2})}{f_{C1,C2}(Y_{g}, Z_{g})} \right) \end{aligned} $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M12"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Score</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℳ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>DD</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℳ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>ED</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_Equb.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula> where <italic>C</italic>1 and <italic>C</italic>2 denote conditions 1 and 2, respectively, and the score is evaluated at the partition estimate <inline-formula id="IEq5"><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\hat {Z_{g}}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M14"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_IEq5.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. A high value of this score presents evidence that a given gene is differentially distributed. The significance of the score is assessed via a permutation test. Specifically, condition labels are permuted and partition estimates are obtained within the new conditions. For each permuted dataset, the Bayes factor score is calculated; the default in scDD is 1000 permutations. For each gene, an empirical <italic>p</italic> value is calculated, and the false discovery rate (FDR) is controlled for a given target value using the method of [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>].</p>
      <p>If covariates are available, instead of permuting the observed values, the relationship between the clustering and covariates can be preserved by permuting the residuals of a linear model that includes the covariate and using the fitted values [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. As pointed out by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], the cellular detection rate is a potential confounder variable, so the permutation procedure in the case studies is adjusted in this manner. If other known confounders exist and are measured, these can also be incorporated in the same manner. Note that while this procedure adjusts for covariates that affect mean expression levels, it does not adjust for covariate-specific effects on variance. The sensitivity of the approach to various levels of nonlinear confounding effects is evaluated in a simulation study presented in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Section 2.3.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec7">
      <title>Classification of significant DD genes</title>
      <p>For genes that are identified as DD by the Bayes factor score, of interest is classifying them into four categories that represent the distinct DD patterns shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>. To classify the DD genes into these patterns (DE, DM, DP, and DB), scDD utilizes the conditional posterior distribution of the component-specific mean parameters given in Eq. <xref rid="Equ6" ref-type="">6</xref> (see “<xref rid="Sec17" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>”). Posterior sampling is carried out to investigate the overlap of components across conditions. Let <italic>c</italic>
<sub>1</sub> be the number of components in condition 1, <italic>c</italic>
<sub>2</sub> the number of components in condition 2, and <italic>c</italic>
<sub>OA</sub> the number of components overall (when pooling conditions 1 and 2). Only components containing at least three cells are considered to minimize the impact of outlier cells. Note that for interpretability, a DD gene must satisfy: <italic>c</italic>
<sub>1</sub>+<italic>c</italic>
<sub>2</sub>≥<italic>c</italic>
<sub>OA</sub>≥ min(<italic>c</italic>
<sub>1</sub>,<italic>c</italic>
<sub>2</sub>). These bounds on the overall number of components represent the two extreme cases: condition 1 does not overlap with condition 2 at all, versus one condition completely overlaps with the other. Any cases outside of these boundaries are not readily interpretable in this context. The actions to take for all other possible combinations of <italic>c</italic>
<sub>1</sub>, <italic>c</italic>
<sub>2</sub>, and <italic>c</italic>
<sub>OA</sub> are detailed in “<xref rid="Sec17" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>”.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec8">
      <title>Differential proportion of zeroes</title>
      <p>For those genes that do not show DDs in the nonzero values, scDD allows a user to evaluate whether the proportion of zeroes differs significantly between the two conditions. This evaluation is carried out using logistic regression adjusted for the proportion of genes detected in each cell as in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Genes with a <italic>χ</italic>
<sup>2</sup> test <italic>p</italic> value of less than 0.025 (after adjustment for multiple comparisons using the method of [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]) are considered to have a differential proportion of zeroes (DZ).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec9">
      <title>Simulation study</title>
      <p>A simulation study was conducted to assess the performance of scDD in identifying DD genes, and to classify them as DE, DP, DM, or DB. Model performance on the simulated data was assessed based on (1) the ability to estimate the correct number of components, (2) the ability to detect significantly DD genes, and (3) the ability to classify DD genes into their correct categories. These three criteria are explored in the next three sections, respectively. Existing methods for DE analysis are also evaluated for the second criterion.</p>
      <sec id="Sec10">
        <title>Estimation of the number of components</title>
        <p>We first examine the ability of scDD to detect the correct number of components. Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> displays the proportion of bimodal and unimodal simulated genes where the correct number of components was identified. For bimodal genes, results are stratified by component mean distance. It is clear that the ability of the algorithm to identify the correct number of components in bimodal genes improves as the component mean distance or sample size increases. The results for unimodal genes are not as sensitive to sample size; however, the proportion of genes identified as bimodal increases slightly with more samples. We conclude that the partition estimate is able to detect reliably the true number of components for reasonable sample and effect sizes.
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Rate of detection of correct number of components in simulated data</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left" colspan="5">Bimodal</th><th align="left">Unimodal</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Sample</th><th align="left" colspan="5">component mean distance <italic>Δ</italic>
<sub><italic>μ</italic></sub>
</th><th align="left"/></tr><tr><th align="left">size</th><th align="left">2</th><th align="left">3</th><th align="left">4</th><th align="left">5</th><th align="left">6</th><th align="left"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">50</td><td align="left">0.056</td><td align="left">0.196</td><td align="left">0.579</td><td align="left">0.848</td><td align="left">0.922</td><td align="left">0.907</td></tr><tr><td align="left">75</td><td align="left">0.052</td><td align="left">0.252</td><td align="left">0.719</td><td align="left">0.917</td><td align="left">0.957</td><td align="left">0.908</td></tr><tr><td align="left">100</td><td align="left">0.050</td><td align="left">0.302</td><td align="left">0.811</td><td align="left">0.950</td><td align="left">0.974</td><td align="left">0.905</td></tr><tr><td align="left">500</td><td align="left">0.073</td><td align="left">0.417</td><td align="left">0.959</td><td align="left">0.995</td><td align="left">0.991</td><td align="left">0.884</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Average proportion of simulated bimodal and unimodal genes where the correct number of components was identified, averaged over gene category and condition. Averages are calculated over 20 replications. Standard errors were &lt;0.025 (not shown)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec11">
        <title>Detection of DD genes</title>
        <p>Next, we examine the ability of scDD to identify the non-null genes as significantly DD, and compare it to existing methods, SCDE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] and MAST [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. For each method, the target FDR was set at 5 % (see “<xref rid="Sec17" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>” for details). The power to detect each gene pattern as DD for all three methods is shown in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Note that the calculations here are taken before the classification step for scDD, so power is defined as the proportion of genes from each simulated category that are detected as DD. In general, the power to detect DD genes improves with increased sample size for all three methods. Our approach has comparable power to SCDE and MAST for DE and DP genes, but higher overall power to detect DM and DB genes. Interestingly, SCDE has very low power to detect DP genes, whereas MAST shows very low power to detect DB genes. We note that SCDE and MAST do not aim to detect genes with no change in the overall mean level in expressed cells (as in the case of DB genes), so it is expected that scDD will outperform other methods at detecting genes in this category.
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Power to detect DD genes in simulated data</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left"/><th align="left" colspan="4">True gene category</th><th align="left"/></tr><tr><th align="left">Sample size</th><th align="left">Method</th><th align="left">DE</th><th align="left">DP</th><th align="left">DM</th><th align="left">DB</th><th align="left">Overall (FDR)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">50</td><td align="left">scDD</td><td align="left">0.893</td><td align="left">0.418*</td><td align="left">0.898*</td><td align="left">0.572*</td><td align="left">0.695* (0.029)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">SCDE</td><td align="left">0.872</td><td align="left">0.026</td><td align="left">0.817</td><td align="left">0.260</td><td align="left">0.494 (0.004)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">MAST</td><td align="left">0.908*</td><td align="left">0.400</td><td align="left">0.871</td><td align="left">0.019</td><td align="left">0.550 (0.026)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">75</td><td align="left">scDD</td><td align="left">0.951</td><td align="left">0.590</td><td align="left">0.960*</td><td align="left">0.668*</td><td align="left">0.792* (0.031)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">SCDE</td><td align="left">0.948</td><td align="left">0.070</td><td align="left">0.903</td><td align="left">0.387</td><td align="left">0.577 (0.003)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">MAST</td><td align="left">0.956*</td><td align="left">0.633*</td><td align="left">0.943</td><td align="left">0.036</td><td align="left">0.642 (0.022)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">100</td><td align="left">scDD</td><td align="left">0.972</td><td align="left">0.717</td><td align="left">0.982*</td><td align="left">0.727*</td><td align="left">0.850* (0.033)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">SCDE</td><td align="left">0.975</td><td align="left">0.125</td><td align="left">0.946</td><td align="left">0.478</td><td align="left">0.631 (0.003)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">MAST</td><td align="left">0.977*</td><td align="left">0.752*</td><td align="left">0.970</td><td align="left">0.045</td><td align="left">0.686 (0.022)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">500</td><td align="left">scDD</td><td align="left">1.000*</td><td align="left">0.983</td><td align="left">1.000*</td><td align="left">0.905*</td><td align="left">0.972* (0.035)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">SCDE</td><td align="left">1.000*</td><td align="left">0.855</td><td align="left">0.998</td><td align="left">0.787</td><td align="left">0.910 (0.004)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">MAST</td><td align="left">1.000*</td><td align="left">0.993*</td><td align="left">1.000*</td><td align="left">0.170</td><td align="left">0.791 (0.022)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Average power to detect simulated DD genes by true category. Averages are calculated over 20 replications. Standard errors were &lt;0.025 (not shown)</p><p><italic>DB</italic> both differential modality and different component means, <italic>DD</italic> differential distribution, <italic>DE</italic> differential expression, <italic>DM</italic> differential modality, <italic>DP</italic> differential proportion, <italic>FDR</italic> false discovery rate. Values followed by * designate which method(s) achieved the highest power to detect DD genes from each particular gene category (as well as overall) for each sample sample size setting</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec12">
        <title>Classification of DD genes</title>
        <p>Next, we examine the ability of scDD to classify each DD gene into its corresponding category. Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> shows the correct classification rate in each category for DD genes that were correctly identified during the detection step (calculated as the proportion of true positive genes detected as DD for a given category that were classified into the correct category). The classification rates do not depend strongly on sample size, with the exception of DP, which decreases with increasing sample size. This decrease results from an increase in the DD detection rate of DP genes with small component mean distance, which have a lower correct classification rate (as shown below).
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Correct classification rate in simulated data</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left" colspan="4">Gene category</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Sample size</th><th align="left">DE</th><th align="left">DP</th><th align="left">DM</th><th align="left">DB</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">50</td><td align="left">0.719</td><td align="left">0.801</td><td align="left">0.557</td><td align="left">0.665</td></tr><tr><td align="left">75</td><td align="left">0.760</td><td align="left">0.732</td><td align="left">0.576</td><td align="left">0.698</td></tr><tr><td align="left">100</td><td align="left">0.782</td><td align="left">0.678</td><td align="left">0.599</td><td align="left">0.706</td></tr><tr><td align="left">500</td><td align="left">0.816</td><td align="left">0.550</td><td align="left">0.583</td><td align="left">0.646</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Average correct classification rate for detected DD genes. Averages are calculated over 20 replications. Standard errors were &lt;0.025 (not shown)</p><p><italic>DB</italic> both differential modality and different component means, <italic>DD</italic> differential distribution, <italic>DE</italic> differential expression, <italic>DM</italic> differential modality, <italic>DP</italic> differential proportion</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
        <p>Since the ability toclassify a DD gene correctly depends on the ability to detect the correct number of components (see classification algorithm in “<xref rid="Sec17" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>”), we also examine how the correct classification rate varies with component mean distance for the categories that contain bimodal genes (DP, DM, and DB). As shown in Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>, the classification rates improve as <italic>Δ</italic>
<sub><italic>μ</italic></sub> increases. This pattern mirrors the trend in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, and suggests that misclassification events occur largely due to incorrect estimation of the number of components. Performance generally increases with sample size, especially at lower values of <italic>Δ</italic>
<sub><italic>μ</italic></sub>. In general, the ability of the algorithm to classify detected DD genes into their true category is robust when components are well separated and improves with increasing sample size.
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Average correct classification rates by component mean distance</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Sample size</th><th align="left">Gene category</th><th align="left" colspan="5">Component mean distance <italic>Δ</italic>
<sub><italic>μ</italic></sub>
</th></tr><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left"/><th align="left">2</th><th align="left">3</th><th align="left">4</th><th align="left">5</th><th align="left">6</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">50</td><td align="left">DP</td><td align="left">0.02</td><td align="left">0.20</td><td align="left">0.78</td><td align="left">0.94</td><td align="left">0.98</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">DM</td><td align="left">0.10</td><td align="left">0.23</td><td align="left">0.59</td><td align="left">0.81</td><td align="left">0.89</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">DB</td><td align="left">0.08</td><td align="left">0.22</td><td align="left">0.59</td><td align="left">0.80</td><td align="left">0.80</td></tr><tr><td align="left">75</td><td align="left">DP</td><td align="left">0.02</td><td align="left">0.18</td><td align="left">0.77</td><td align="left">0.94</td><td align="left">0.97</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">DM</td><td align="left">0.08</td><td align="left">0.27</td><td align="left">0.69</td><td align="left">0.86</td><td align="left">0.90</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">DB</td><td align="left">0.09</td><td align="left">0.29</td><td align="left">0.71</td><td align="left">0.83</td><td align="left">0.84</td></tr><tr><td align="left">100</td><td align="left">DP</td><td align="left">0.03</td><td align="left">0.16</td><td align="left">0.74</td><td align="left">0.93</td><td align="left">0.95</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">DM</td><td align="left">0.10</td><td align="left">0.32</td><td align="left">0.76</td><td align="left">0.87</td><td align="left">0.91</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">DB</td><td align="left">0.08</td><td align="left">0.32</td><td align="left">0.80</td><td align="left">0.85</td><td align="left">0.84</td></tr><tr><td align="left">500</td><td align="left">DP</td><td align="left">0.01</td><td align="left">0.15</td><td align="left">0.72</td><td align="left">0.91</td><td align="left">0.93</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">DM</td><td align="left">0.12</td><td align="left">0.33</td><td align="left">0.72</td><td align="left">0.85</td><td align="left">0.89</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">DB</td><td align="left">0.03</td><td align="left">0.43</td><td align="left">0.85</td><td align="left">0.85</td><td align="left">0.85</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Average correct classification rates stratified by <italic>Δ</italic>
<sub><italic>μ</italic></sub>. Averages are calculated over 20 replications. Standard errors were &lt;0.025 (not shown)</p><p><italic>DB</italic> both differential modality and different component means, <italic>DM</italic> differential modality, <italic>DP</italic> differential proportion</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec13">
      <title>Case study: identifying DD genes between hESC types</title>
      <p>The comprehensive characterization of transcriptional dynamics across hESC lines and derived cell types aims to provide insight into the gene regulatory processes governing pluripotency and differentiation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Previous work utilizing microarrays and bulk RNA-seq largely focused on identifying genes with changes in average expression level across a population of cells. By examining transcriptional changes at the single-cell level, we can uncover global changes that are undetectable when averaging over the population. In addition, we gain the ability to assess the level of heterogeneity of key differentiation regulators, which may lead to the ability to assess variation in pluripotency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] or the differentiation potential of individual cells.</p>
      <p>The number of significant DD genes for each cell type comparison is shown in Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref> for scDD, SCDE, and MAST. Note that the comparison of H1 and H9 detects the fewest number of DD genes for all three methods, a finding that is consistent with that both of these are undifferentiated hESC lines and it is expected that they are the most similar among the comparisons. In all four comparisons, the number of genes identified by our method is greater than that for SCDE and similar to that for MAST.
<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Number of DD genes identified in the hESC case study data for scDD, SCDE, and MAST</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left" colspan="6">scDD</th><th align="left"/><th align="left"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Comparison</td><td align="left">DE</td><td align="left">DP</td><td align="left">DM</td><td align="left">DB</td><td align="left">DZ</td><td align="left">Total</td><td align="left">SCDE</td><td align="left">MAST</td></tr><tr><td align="left">H1 vs NPC</td><td align="left">1686</td><td align="left">270</td><td align="left">902</td><td align="left">440</td><td align="left">1603</td><td align="left">5555</td><td align="left">2921</td><td align="left">5887</td></tr><tr><td align="left">H1 vs DEC</td><td align="left">913</td><td align="left">254</td><td align="left">890</td><td align="left">516</td><td align="left">911</td><td align="left">5295</td><td align="left">1616</td><td align="left">3724</td></tr><tr><td align="left">NPC vs DEC</td><td align="left">1242</td><td align="left">327</td><td align="left">910</td><td align="left">389</td><td align="left">2021</td><td align="left">5982</td><td align="left">2147</td><td align="left">5624</td></tr><tr><td align="left">H1 vs H9</td><td align="left">260</td><td align="left">55</td><td align="left">85</td><td align="left">37</td><td align="left">145</td><td align="left">739</td><td align="left">111</td><td align="left">1119</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Note that the total for scDD includes genes detected as DD but not categorized</p><p><italic>DB</italic> both differential modality and different component means, <italic>DD</italic> differential distribution, <italic>DE</italic> differential expression, <italic>DEC</italic> definitive endoderm cell, <italic>DM</italic> differential modality, <italic>DP</italic> differential proportion, <italic>DZ</italic> differential zeroes, <italic>hESC</italic> human embryonic stem cell, <italic>NPC</italic> neuronal progenitor cell</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      <p>Figure <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>
<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">a</xref> displays top-ranked genes for each category that are not identified by MAST or SCDE for the H1 versus DEC comparison. Among the genes identified exclusively by scDD for the H1 versus DEC comparison are <italic>CHEK2</italic>, a cell-cycle checkpoint kinase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], and <italic>CDK7</italic>, a cyclin-dependent kinase that plays a key role in cell-cycle regulation through the activation of other cyclin-dependent kinases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. It has been shown that embryonic stem cells express cyclin genes constitutively, whereas in differentiated cells, cyclin levels are oscillatory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. This finding is consistent with the differential modality of the <italic>CDK7</italic> gene shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>
<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">b</xref>. Similarly, scDD identifies several genes involved in the regulation of pluripotency that are not identified by the other two methods (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>
<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">c</xref>). For example, <italic>FOXP1</italic> exhibits alternative splicing activity in hESCs, stimulating expression of several key regulators of pluripotency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. The <italic>PSMD12</italic> gene encodes a subunit of the proteasome complex that is vital to the maintenance of pluripotency and has shown decreased expression in differentiating hESCs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Both of these genes are also differentially distributed between H1 and the other differentiated cell type, NPC.
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Violin plots (smoothed non-parametric kernel density estimates) for Differentially Distributed genes identified between H1 and DEC. Individual observations are displayed with jitter. Within a condition, points with the same shape are predicted to belong to the same component. <bold>a</bold> scDD-exclusive genes: representative genes from each category (DZ, DP, DM, and DB) that are not detected by MAST or SCDE. Selected genes are top-ranked by permutation <italic>p</italic> value in each category (DP, DM, and DB) or had a significant <italic>χ</italic>
<sup>2</sup> test for a difference in the proportion of zeroes (DZ). <bold>b</bold> Cell-cycle genes: DD genes involved in cell-cycle regulation (not detected by MAST or SCDE). <bold>c</bold> Pluripotency genes: DD genes involved in pluripotency regulation (not identified by MAST or SCDE). <italic>DB</italic> both differential modality and different component means, <italic>DD</italic> differential distribution, <italic>DEC</italic> definitive endoderm cell, <italic>DM</italic> differential modality, <italic>DP</italic> differential proportion, <italic>DZ</italic> differential zeroes</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig>
</p>
      <p>In general, the vast majority of the genes found exclusively by scDD are categorized as something other than DE (ranging from 98.3 to 100 <italic>%</italic> in the three case studies, see Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S6), which suggests that they are predominantly characterized by differences that are more complex than the traditional DE pattern. The genes identified by MAST but not scDD are overwhelmingly characterized as those with a weak signal in both the nonzero and zero components (see Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S9), which can be difficult to interpret (see Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Section 3 for more details).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec14">
      <title>Additional case studies</title>
      <p>We also applied scDD and MAST to two additional case studies (the numbers of significant DD genes for each comparison are displayed in Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>). SCDE was not used to analyze these datasets since it is intended for use on raw count data and the processed data made available by the authors of [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>] were already normalized by FPKM and TPM, respectively. Like the results of the hESC case study, MAST and scDD identify similar numbers of significant genes. The genes that scDD finds exclusively are predominantly characterized by something other than a mean shift, a result which is also consistent with the hESC case study (see Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S7).
<table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Number of DD genes identified in the myoblast and mESC case studies for scDD and MAST</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left" colspan="6">scDD</th><th align="left"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Comparison</td><td align="left">DE</td><td align="left">DP</td><td align="left">DM</td><td align="left">DB</td><td align="left">DZ</td><td align="left">Total</td><td align="left">MAST</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Myoblast: T0 vs T72</td><td align="left">312</td><td align="left">44</td><td align="left">200</td><td align="left">36</td><td align="left">1311</td><td align="left">2134</td><td align="left">2904</td></tr><tr><td align="left">mESC: Serum vs 2i</td><td align="left">5233</td><td align="left">76</td><td align="left">1259</td><td align="left">1128</td><td align="left">670</td><td align="left">9130</td><td align="left">9706</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Note that the total for scDD includes genes detected as DD but not categorized</p><p><italic>DB</italic> both differential modality and different component means, <italic>DD</italic> differential distribution, <italic>DE</italic> differential expression, <italic>DM</italic> differential modality, <italic>DP</italic> differential proportion, <italic>DZ</italic> differential zeroes, <italic>mESC</italic> mouse embryonic stem cell</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec15">
      <title>Advantages and limitations of the approach</title>
      <p>We stress that our approach is inherently different from a method that detects traditional DE, such as [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] and [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], which aim to detect a shift in the mean of the expressed values. In addition to identifying genes that have DDs across conditions, our modeling framework allows us to identify subpopulations within each condition that have differing levels of expression of a given gene (i.e., which cells belong to which component). For such genes, the partition estimates automatically provide an estimate of the proportion of cells in each condition that belong to each subpopulation. We also do not require specification of the total number of components, which can vary for each gene.</p>
      <p>When applied to cells at different differentiation stages, this information may provide insight into which genes are responsible for driving phenotypic changes. The gene in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>
<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">b</xref>, for example, shows a DP of cells across conditions, which is important to recognize since DP suggests a change in cell-specific responses to signaling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. This is in contrast to the DM gene in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>
<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">c</xref>, which indicates the presence of a distinct cell type in one condition, but not the other. Recent methods for scRNA-seq [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>] may be able to identify genes such as those shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>
<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">b</xref>–<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">d</xref> as differing between conditions. However, our simulations suggest that they would be relatively underpowered to do so, and they would be unable to characterize the change as DP, DM, or DB.</p>
      <p>We also show through simulation that our approach can accommodate large sample sizes of several hundreds of cells per condition. Note, however, that the real strength in the modeling framework lies in the ability to characterize patterns of DDs. In the presence of extreme sparsity, this will be a challenge, since the number of nonzero observations in a given gene will be small. If the sample size of nonzero measurements is too small, it will be difficult to infer the presence of multiple underlying cell states. In practice, for larger and more sparse datasets, it is recommended to verify that the number of cells expressing a given gene is in the range of the sample sizes considered in this study to utilize fully the available features of scDD.</p>
      <p>The approach is limited in that adjustments for covariates are not directly incorporated into the model. In general, when the relationship between a potential confounding variable and the quantification of expression is well known (e.g., increased sequencing depth is generally associated with increased expression measurements), this should be accounted for in a normalization procedure. For other covariates that are not as well characterized (e.g., the cellular detection rate and batch effects), residuals can be used in the permutation procedure, though a more unified approach would be desirable. We also note that more complex confounding variables may be present in scRNA-seq experiments that are nonlinear in nature (e.g., covariate-specific effects on variance). We show in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Section 2.3 that when these effects are extreme, care must be taken in interpreting DD genes that are uncategorized.</p>
      <p>Additionally, the approach is limited in that only pairwise comparisons across biological conditions are feasible. While an extended Bayes factor score to test for the dependence of a condition on a partition estimation for more than two conditions would be straightforward, the classification into meaningful patterns would be less so, and work is underway in that direction. Finally, we note that while the genes identified by scDD may prove useful in downstream analysis, interpretability is limited as partitions are estimated independently for each gene and consequently do not provide a unified clustering of cells based on global gene expression changes. Extensions in this direction are also underway.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec16" sec-type="conclusion">
    <title>Conclusions</title>
    <p>To our knowledge, we have presented the first statistical method to detect differences in scRNA-seq experiments that explicitly accounts for potential multi-modality of the distribution of expressed cells in each condition. Such multi-modal expression patterns are pervasive in scRNA-seq data and are of great interest, since they represent biological heterogeneity within otherwise homogeneous cell populations; differences across conditions imply differential regulation or response in the two groups. We have introduced a set of five interesting patterns to summarize the key features that can differ between two conditions. Using simulation studies, we have shown that our method has comparable performance to existing methods when differences (mean shifts) exist between unimodal distributions across conditions, and it outperforms existing approaches when there are more complex differences.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec17">
    <title>Methods</title>
    <sec id="Sec18">
      <title>Software implementations and applications</title>
      <p>All analyses were carried out using R version 3.1.1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. The method MAST [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] was implemented using the MAST R package version 0.931, obtained from GitHub at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/RGLab/MAST">https://github.com/RGLab/MAST</ext-link>. The adjustment for cellular detection rate as recommended in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] was included in the case study, but not in the simulation study (only the normal component of the test was considered here since no difference in dropout rate was simulated). The method SCDE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] was implemented using the scde R package version 1.0, obtained from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pklab.med.harvard.edu/scde/index.html">http://pklab.med.harvard.edu/scde/index.html</ext-link>. No adjustment for cellular detection rate was carried out since SCDE cannot accommodate covariates. Since SCDE requires raw integer counts as input, and expected counts are non-integer valued, the ceiling function was applied to the unnormalized counts. For each approach, the target FDR was controlled at 5 %. Specifically, both MAST and SCDE provide gene-specific <italic>p</italic> values and use the method of [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] to control FDR. We followed the same procedure here.</p>
      <p>Our method is implemented using version 1.1.0 of the scDD R package, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/kdkorthauer/scDD">https://github.com/kdkorthauer/scDD</ext-link>. The analysis involves a computationally intensive permutation step, which is executed in parallel on multiple cores if available. On a Linux machine using 12 cores and up to 16 gigabytes of memory, this step took approximately 60 minutes for 1000 permutations of 1000 genes in the simulation of 50 samples per condition. Computation time scales approximately linearly with sample size, and this same task takes approximately 90 minutes for 100 samples per condition, and 300 minutes for a sample size of 500 per condition. The computation time to analyze the simulated datasets for SCDE (MAST) ranged from approximately 3 to 30 (0.5 to 5) minutes across the different sample sizes.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec19">
      <title>hESC culture and differentiation</title>
      <p>All cell culture and scRNA-seq experiments were conducted as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Briefly, undifferentiated H1 and H9 hESCs were routinely maintained at the undifferentiated state in E8 medium on Matrigel (BD Bioscience) coated tissue culture plates with daily medium feeding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. HESCs were passaged every 3 to 4 days with 0.5 mM ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA) in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) at 1:10 to 1:15 ratio for maintenance. H1 were differentiated according to previously established protocols [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. All the cell cultures performed in our laboratory have been routinely tested as negative for mycoplasma contamination.</p>
      <p>For DECs, H1 cells were individualized with Accutase (Life Technologies), seeded in E8 with BMP4 (5 ng/ml), Activin A (25 ng/ml) and CHIR99021 (1 <italic>μ</italic>M) for the first 2 days, then withdraw CHIR99021 for the remaining period of differentiation. DECs were harvested at the end of day 5, and sorted for the CXCR4-positive population for scRNA-seq experiments. For NPCs, the undifferentiated H1-SOX2-mCherry reporter line was treated with 0.5 mM EDTA in PBS for 3 to 5 min and seeded in E6 (E8 minus FGF2, minus TGF <italic>β</italic>1), with 2.5 <italic>μ</italic>g/ml insulin, SB431542 (10 <italic>μ</italic>M) and 100 ng/ml Noggin. NPCs were harvested and enriched at the end of day 7, after sorting for the Cherry-positive population for scRNA-seq experiments. All differentiation media were changed daily.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec20">
      <title>Read mapping, quality control, and normalization</title>
      <p>For each of the cell types studied, expected counts were obtained from RSEM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. In each condition there are a maximum of 96 cells, but all have fewer than 96 cells due to removal by quality control standards. Some cells were removed due to cell death or doublet cell capture, indicated by a post cell capture image analysis as well as a very low percentage of mapped reads. For more details on read mapping and quality control, see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. DESeq normalization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>] was carried out using the MedianNorm function in the EBSeq R package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>] to obtain library sizes. The library sizes were applied to scale the count data. Further, genes with a very low detection rate (detected in fewer than 25 <italic>%</italic> of cells in either condition) are not considered.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec21">
      <title>Publicly available scRNA-seq datasets</title>
      <p>Processed FPKM-normalized data from human myoblast cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>] were obtained from GEO [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>] using accession number GSE52529. In this study, we examined the set of cells cultured on standard growth medium (samples labeled with T0) as well as those treated with differentiation-inducing medium for 72 h (samples labeled with T72). Processed TPM-normalized data from mESCs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>] were also obtained from GEO under accession number GSE60749. In this study, we examined the samples labeled as mESC (cultured in standard medium), along with the samples labeled as TwoiLIF (cultured in 2i + LIF differentiation-inhibitory medium).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec22">
      <title>Publicly available bulk RNA-seq datasets</title>
      <p>The modality of the gene expression distributions in bulk RNA-seq was explored using large, publicly available datasets and the results are displayed in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. In this figure, the red bars depict the bulk RNA-seq results, and datasets are labeled according to their source and sample size. Datasets GE.50, GE.75, and GE.100 are constructed by randomly sampling 50, 75, and 100 samples from GEUVADIS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>] to obtain sample sizes comparable to the single-cell sets under study (obtained from the GEUVADIS consortium data browser at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/arrayexpress/files/E-GEUV-1/analysis_results/GD660.GeneQuantCount.txt.gz">www.ebi.ac.uk/arrayexpress/files/E-GEUV-1/analysis_results/GD660.GeneQuantCount.txt.gz</ext-link>). Dataset LC consists of 77 normal lung tissue samples from the TCGA lung adenocarcinoma study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>] (obtained from GEO [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>] using accession number GSE40419). All datasets were normalized using DESeq normalization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>] except for LC, for which the authors supplied values already normalized by RPKM.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec23">
      <title>Mixture model formulation</title>
      <sec id="Sec24">
        <title>Dirichlet process mixture of normals</title>
        <p>Let <inline-formula id="IEq6"><alternatives><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}${Y^{c}_{g}}=(y^{c}_{g1},\ldots,y^{c}_{g{J_{c}}})$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M16"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>J</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_IEq6.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> be the log-transformed nonzero expression measurements of gene <italic>g</italic> for a collection of <italic>J</italic>
<sub><italic>c</italic></sub> cells in condition <italic>c</italic> out of 2 total conditions. For simplicity of presentation, we drop the dependency on <italic>g</italic> for now, and let the total number of cells with nonzero measurements be <italic>J</italic>. We assume that under the null hypothesis of equivalent distributions (i.e., no dependency on condition), <italic>Y</italic>={<italic>Y</italic>
<sup><italic>c</italic></sup>}<sub><italic>c</italic>=1,2</sub> can be modeled by a conjugate DPM of normals given by 
<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M17">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ \begin{aligned} {y^{c}_{j}} &amp;\sim N(\mu_{j}, \tau_{j}) \\ \mu_{j}, \tau_{j} &amp;\sim G \\ G &amp;\sim \operatorname{DP}(\alpha, G_{0}) \\ G_{0} &amp; = \operatorname{NG} (m_{0}, s_{0}, a_{0}/2, 2/b_{0}) \\ \end{aligned}  $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M18"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>∼</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>∼</mml:mo><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>∼</mml:mo><mml:mo>DP</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>NG</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr/></mml:mtable></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p>
        <p>where DP is the Dirichlet process with base distribution <italic>G</italic>
<sub>0</sub> and precision parameter <italic>α</italic>, <italic>N</italic>(<italic>μ</italic>
<sub><italic>j</italic></sub>,<italic>τ</italic>
<sub><italic>j</italic></sub>) is the normal distribution parameterized with mean <italic>μ</italic>
<sub><italic>j</italic></sub> and precision <italic>τ</italic>
<sub><italic>j</italic></sub> (i.e., with variance <inline-formula id="IEq7"><alternatives><tex-math id="M19">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\tau _{j}^{-2}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M20"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_IEq7.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>), and NG(<italic>m</italic>
<sub>0</sub>,<italic>s</italic>
<sub>0</sub>,<italic>a</italic>
<sub>0</sub>/2,2/<italic>b</italic>
<sub>0</sub>) is the normal-gamma distribution with mean <italic>m</italic>
<sub>0</sub>, precision <italic>s</italic>
<sub>0</sub>
<italic>τ</italic>
<sub><italic>j</italic></sub>, shape <italic>a</italic>
<sub>0</sub>/2, and scale 2/<italic>b</italic>
<sub>0</sub>. Let <italic>K</italic> denote the number of components [unique values among <inline-formula id="IEq8"><alternatives><tex-math id="M21">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$(\mu, \tau) = \{\mu _{j}, \tau _{j}\}_{j=1}^{J}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M22"><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>J</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_IEq8.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>]. Note that two observations indexed by <italic>j</italic> and <italic>j</italic>
<sup>′</sup> belong to the same component if and only if <inline-formula id="IEq9"><alternatives><tex-math id="M23">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$(\mu _{j}, \tau _{j})=(\mu _{j^{\prime }}, \phantom {\dot {i}\!}\tau _{j^{\prime }})$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M24"><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_IEq9.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec25">
        <title>Product partition models</title>
        <p>The posterior distribution of (<italic>μ</italic>,<italic>τ</italic>) is intractable even for moderate sample sizes. This is because the number of possible partitions (clusterings) of the data grows extremely rapidly as the sample size increases (according to the Bell number). However, if we let <italic>Z</italic>=(<italic>z</italic>
<sub>1</sub>,…,<italic>z</italic>
<sub><italic>J</italic></sub>) be the vector of component memberships of gene <italic>g</italic> for all samples, where the number of unique <italic>Z</italic> values is <italic>K</italic>, the probability density of <italic>Y</italic> conditional on <italic>Z</italic> can be viewed as a PPM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. Thus, it can be written as a product over all component-specific densities: 
<disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M25">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ f(Y|Z) = \prod_{k=1}^{K} f(y^{(k)}) \\  $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M26"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∏</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p>
        <p>where <italic>y</italic>
<sup>(<italic>k</italic>)</sup> is the vector of observations belonging to component <italic>k</italic> and <italic>f</italic>(<italic>y</italic>
<sup>(<italic>k</italic>)</sup>) is the component-specific distribution after integrating over all other parameters. In the conjugate normal-gamma setting, this has a closed form given by 
<disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M27">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ f(y^{(k)}) \propto \frac{\Gamma(a_{k}/2) }{(b_{k}/2)^{a_{k}/2}} s_{k}^{-1/2}.  $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M28"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∝</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_Equ3.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p>
        <p>The posterior for the parameters (<italic>μ</italic>
<sub><italic>k</italic></sub>,<italic>τ</italic>
<sub><italic>k</italic></sub>) conditional on the partition is 
<disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M29">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ (\mu_{k}, \tau_{k}) | Y, Z \sim \operatorname{NG} (m_{k}, s_{k}, a_{k}/2, 2/b_{k}).  $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M30"><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mo>∼</mml:mo><mml:mo>NG</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_Equ4.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p>
        <p>The posterior parameters (<italic>m</italic>
<sub><italic>k</italic></sub>, <italic>s</italic>
<sub><italic>k</italic></sub>, <italic>a</italic>
<sub><italic>k</italic></sub>, <italic>b</italic>
<sub><italic>k</italic></sub>) also have a closed form due to the conjugacy of the model given by Eq. <xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="">1</xref>. These parameters are given by 
<disp-formula id="Equ5"><label>5</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M31">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ \begin{aligned} s_{k} &amp;= s_{0} + n^{(k)} \\ m_{k} &amp;= \frac{s_{0} m_{0} + \sum y^{(k)}}{s_{k}} \\ a_{k} &amp;= a_{0} + n^{(k)} \\ b_{k} &amp;= b_{0} + \sum (y^{(k)})^{2} + s_{0}{m_{0}^{2}} - s_{k}{m_{k}^{2}} \\ \end{aligned}  $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M32"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr/></mml:mtable></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_Equ5.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p>
        <p>where <italic>n</italic>
<sup>(<italic>k</italic>)</sup> is the number of observations in component <italic>k</italic>. It follows that the marginal posterior distribution of <italic>μ</italic>
<sub><italic>k</italic></sub> conditional on the partition is 
<disp-formula id="Equ6"><label>6</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M33">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ \mu_{k} | Y, Z \sim t_{a_{k}} \left(m_{k}, \frac{b_{k}}{a_{k} s_{k}}\right)  $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M34"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mo>∼</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_Equ6.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p>
        <p>where <italic>t</italic>
<sub><italic>a</italic></sub>(<italic>b</italic>,<italic>c</italic>) denotes the generalized Student’s <italic>t</italic> distribution with <italic>a</italic> degrees of freedom, noncentrality parameter <italic>b</italic>, and scale parameter <italic>c</italic>. The product partition DPM model can be simplified as follows: 
<disp-formula id="Equ7"><label>7</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M35">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ \begin{aligned} y_{j} \, | z_{j}=k, \mu_{k}, \tau_{k} &amp;\sim N(\mu_{k}, \tau_{k}) \\ \mu_{k}, \tau_{k} &amp;\sim \operatorname{NG} (m_{0}, s_{0}, a_{0}/2, 2/b_{0}) \\ z &amp;\sim \frac{\alpha^{K} \Gamma(\alpha)}{\Gamma(\alpha+J)} \prod_{k=1}^{K} \Gamma(n^{(k)}). \end{aligned}  $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M36"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>∼</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>∼</mml:mo><mml:mo>NG</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>∼</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∏</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_Equ7.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p>
        <p>Then we can obtain the joint predictive distribution of the data <italic>Y</italic> and partition <italic>Z</italic> by incorporating Eq. <xref rid="Equ7" ref-type="">7</xref>: 
<disp-formula id="Equ8"><label>8</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M37">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ \begin{aligned} f(Y, Z) &amp;= f(Z) \prod_{k=1}^{K} f(y^{(k)}) \\ &amp; \propto \alpha^{K} \prod_{k=1}^{K} \frac{\Gamma(n^{(k)}) \Gamma(a_{k}/2) }{ (b_{k}/2)^{a_{k}/2}} s_{k}^{-1/2}. \end{aligned}  $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M38"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∏</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>∝</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∏</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_Equ8.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec26">
        <title>Model-fitting</title>
        <p>The fitting of the model given in Eq. <xref rid="Equ7" ref-type="">7</xref> involves obtaining an estimate <inline-formula id="IEq10"><alternatives><tex-math id="M39">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\hat {Z}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M40"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_IEq10.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> of the partition. The goal is to find the partition that yields the highest posterior mass in Eq. <xref rid="Equ8" ref-type="">8</xref>, referred to as the maximum a posteriori (MAP) partition estimate. Under this modeling framework, the solution for the MAP estimate is not deterministic and several computational procedures have been developed utilizing Polya urn Gibbs sampling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>], agglomerative greedy search algorithms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>], or an iterative stochastic search [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>].</p>
        <p>These procedures generally involve evaluation of the posterior at many different candidate partitions, and as such tend to be computationally intensive. To avoid this challenge, we recognize the relation to the corresponding estimation problem in the finite mixture model framework, where the partition estimate can be obtained by optimizing the Bayesian information criterion (BIC) of the marginal density <italic>f</italic>(<italic>Y</italic>|<italic>Z</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. In fact, for certain settings of the prior distribution over partitions, the MAP estimate is identical to the estimate obtained by optimizing the BIC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. In practice, even when these settings are not invoked, the performance of partition estimates obtained via BIC optimization show comparable performance (see Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Section 1). We obtain the partition estimate <inline-formula id="IEq11"><alternatives><tex-math id="M41">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\hat {Z}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M42"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_IEq11.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> that optimizes the BIC using the Mclust R package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>] and satisfies the criteria for multi-modality described in the next section.</p>
        <p>The hyperparameters for the component-specific mean and precision parameters were chosen so as to encode a heavy-tailed distribution over the parameters. Specifically, the parameters were set to <italic>μ</italic>
<sub>0</sub>=0, <inline-formula id="IEq12"><alternatives><tex-math id="M43">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}${\tau _{0}^{2}}=0.01$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M44"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.01</mml:mn></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_IEq12.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <italic>a</italic>
<sub>0</sub>=0.01, and <italic>b</italic>
<sub>0</sub>=0.01. The Dirichlet concentration parameter was set to <italic>α</italic>=0.01, and choosing this is shown in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Section 1 to be robust to many different settings in a sensitivity analysis.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec27">
        <title>Partition estimation</title>
        <p>The partition estimate <inline-formula id="IEq13"><alternatives><tex-math id="M45">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\hat {Z}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M46"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_IEq13.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is obtained that optimizes BIC using Mclust [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>], in addition to the following filtering criteria. Note that the only constraint imposed on the number of components <italic>K</italic> in the modeling framework is that <italic>K</italic>≤<italic>J</italic>. However, under the sample sizes in this study, we consider only <italic>K</italic>≤5. The first filtering criterion is based on the notion that a two-component mixture model is not necessarily bimodal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>], and relaxes the requirement that the MAP estimate corresponds to the model with the lowest BIC. Specifically, for each candidate model fitted by BIC with <italic>K</italic> components, a split step (if <italic>K</italic>=1, obtain a new partition estimate <inline-formula id="IEq14"><alternatives><tex-math id="M47">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\hat {Z}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M48"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_IEq14.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> with <italic>K</italic>=2 unique elements) or a merge step (if <italic>K</italic>≥2, obtain a new partition estimate <inline-formula id="IEq15"><alternatives><tex-math id="M49">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\hat {Z}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M50"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_IEq15.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> restricted to <italic>K</italic>−1 unique elements) is carried out to generate a new candidate partition. The candidate partition with the larger value of <italic>K</italic> becomes the partition estimate only if the component separation suggests multi-modality. Component separation between any pair of components is assessed with the bimodality index (BI) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]: 
<disp-formula id="Equc"><alternatives><tex-math id="M51">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ \text{BI} = 2 \times \sqrt{\frac{n_{1} n_{2}}{(n_{1}+n_{2})^{2}}} \left(\frac{| \mu_{1} - \mu_{2} | }{\sigma} \right) $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M52"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>BI</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_Equc.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula> where the component means <italic>μ</italic>
<sub>1</sub> and <italic>μ</italic>
<sub>2</sub> are estimated via maximum likelihood, the common within-component standard deviation <italic>σ</italic> is conservatively estimated with the maximum within-component standard deviation among all components, and <italic>n</italic>
<sub>1</sub> and <italic>n</italic>
<sub>2</sub> are the number of cells belonging to each component. BI thresholds for the split and merge step were determined empirically and vary by sample size, as multiple modes are more easily detected as sample size increases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>] (for more details see Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Section 4).</p>
        <p>The second filtering criterion is designed to reduce the impact of outlier cells. Specifically, components with fewer than three cells are not considered, and the merge step is also carried out if one of the components present has an extremely large variance compared to the others (more than 20 times larger than any other component). Likewise, the split step is not carried out if one of the proposed components has a variance more than 10 times larger than any other component.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec28">
      <title>Simulation details</title>
      <sec id="Sec29">
        <title>Component means and variances</title>
        <p>Each gene was simulated based on the characteristics of a randomly sampled unimodal gene with at least 25 <italic>%</italic> nonzero measurements in the H1 dataset. For unimodal genes, the mean and variance were chosen to match the observed mean and variance; for bimodal genes, the component means and variances were selected to be near the observed mean and variance. The proportion of zeroes is chosen to match that observed in the randomly sampled gene, and is not varied by condition. Details are provided in the following sections.</p>
        <p>Distances between (log-scale) component means <italic>Δ</italic>
<sub><italic>μ</italic></sub>
<italic>σ</italic> in the multi-modal genes were chosen such that components were separated by a minimum of two and a maximum of six standard deviations, where the standard deviation <italic>σ</italic> is assumed constant (on the log-scale) across components. The specific values of <italic>σ</italic> used for the simulated genes are empirical estimates of the standard deviations of the unimodal case study genes (assuming a lognormal distribution on the raw scale). In this setting, the component distance can also be thought of as a fold-change within condition (across components), where the ratio of the component means (untransformed-scale) is equal to <inline-formula id="IEq16"><alternatives><tex-math id="M53">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\mathrm {e}^{\Delta _{\mu }\hat {\sigma }}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M54"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Article_IEq16.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. The ratio of the component standard deviations (raw scale) is also equal to this same fold-change (see Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Section 2.1 for more details). The component mean distance values were chosen to represent a range of settings for which the difficulty of detecting multi-modality is widely varied, as well as to reflect the range of observed component mean distances detected empirically in the case studies.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec30">
        <title>Unimodal genes</title>
        <p>The parameters of the negative binomial distribution for unimodal genes were estimated from the randomly sampled observed genes using the method of moments. These empirical parameters were used as is to simulate both conditions of EE genes, and condition 1 of DE and DB. Condition 1 of DM was simulated by decreasing the mean by half the value of <italic>Δ</italic>
<sub><italic>μ</italic></sub>. The second condition for DE genes was simulated based on condition 1 parameters using randomly sampled fold-changes that were between two and three standard deviations of the observed fold-changes between H1 and DEC.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec31">
        <title>Bimodal genes</title>
        <p>The parameters for the mixture of negative binomial distributions in bimodal genes were also generated using empirically estimated means and variances. The first (lower) component mean was decreased by half the value of <italic>Δ</italic>
<sub><italic>μ</italic></sub> and the second (higher) component mean was increased by half the value of <italic>Δ</italic>
<sub><italic>μ</italic></sub>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec32">
      <title>DD classification algorithm</title>
      <p>Genes detected as significantly DD from the permutation test of the Bayes factor score are categorized into patterns of interest. The genes that are not classified as DE, DP, DM, or DB are considered to be no calls, abbreviated NC. These represent patterns that are not of primary interest, such as those that differ only in variance (but not in the number of components or their means). This type of difference may result from cell-specific differences in technical variation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], which can only be decomposed from biological variation in experimental protocols that allow for independent estimation of technical effects using spike-in controls, for example [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>].</p>
      <p>An additional step to improve the power to detect genes in the DP category was also implemented. This step was motivated by the observation that the Bayes factor score tends to be small when the clustering process within each condition is consistent with that overall, as in the case of DP. Thus, for genes that were not significantly DD by permutation but had the same number of components within condition as overall, Fisher’s exact test was used to test for independence with biological condition. If the <italic>p</italic> value for that test is less than 0.05, then the gene was added to the DP category (this did not result in the addition of any false positives in the simulation study). In addition, since the Bayes factor score depends on the estimated partition, we increase the robustness of the approach to detect DD genes under possible misspecification of the partition by also assessing evidence of DD in the form of an overall mean shift for genes not significant by the permutation test (using a <italic>t</italic>-statistic with FDR controlled by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]). This resulted in the detection of between 121 and 689 additional genes in the hESC comparisons and did not add any false positives in 94 <italic>%</italic> of simulation replications (with only a single false positive gene in the other 6 <italic>%</italic> of replications).</p>
      <p>Here we present pseudocode for the classification of DD genes into the categories DE, DP, DM, or DB. For every pair of components, we obtain a sample of 10,000 observations from the posterior distribution of the difference in means. The components are considered to overlap if the 100 <italic>%</italic> credible interval contains 0.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec33">
      <title>DD classification algorithm</title>
      <p>
        <graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_Figa_HTML.gif" id="MO6"/>
      </p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <app-group>
    <app id="App1">
      <sec id="Sec34">
        <title>Additional file</title>
        <p>
          <media position="anchor" xlink:href="13059_2016_1077_MOESM1_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM1">
            <label>Additional file 1</label>
            <caption>
              <p>Supplement. Sensitivity analyses of MAP estimation method, further methodological details, and additional results. (PDF 553 kb)</p>
            </caption>
          </media>
        </p>
      </sec>
    </app>
  </app-group>
  <glossary>
    <title>Abbreviations</title>
    <def-list>
      <def-item>
        <term>BIC</term>
        <def>
          <p>Bayesian information criterion</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>DD</term>
        <def>
          <p>differential distribution</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>DE</term>
        <def>
          <p>Differential expression</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>DEC</term>
        <def>
          <p>Definitive endoderm cell</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>DP</term>
        <def>
          <p>Differential proportion</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>DM</term>
        <def>
          <p>Differential modality</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>DB</term>
        <def>
          <p>Both differential modality and different component means</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>DPM</term>
        <def>
          <p>Dirichlet process mixture</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>DZ</term>
        <def>
          <p>Differential zeroes</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>ED</term>
        <def>
          <p>Equivalent distribution</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>EDTA</term>
        <def>
          <p>Ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>EE</term>
        <def>
          <p>Equivalent expression</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>EP</term>
        <def>
          <p>Equivalent proportion</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>FDR</term>
        <def>
          <p>False discovery rate</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>hESC</term>
        <def>
          <p>Human embryonic stem cell</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>mESC</term>
        <def>
          <p>Mouse embryonic stem cell</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>MAP</term>
        <def>
          <p>Maximum a posteriori</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>NC</term>
        <def>
          <p>no call</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>NPC</term>
        <def>
          <p>Neuronal progenitor cell</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>PBS</term>
        <def>
          <p>Phosphate-buffered saline</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>PPM</term>
        <def>
          <p>Product partition model</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>scDD</term>
        <def>
          <p>Single-cell differential distributions</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>scRNA-seq</term>
        <def>
          <p>Single-cell RNA sequencing</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
    </def-list>
  </glossary>
  <ack>
    <p>The authors thank the editorial staff and two anonymous reviewers for insightful comments and suggestions that helped improve the quality of the manuscript.</p>
    <sec id="d30e5287">
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p>This work was supported by National Institutes of Health (NIH) grant GM102756 (CK), NIH grant U54AI117924 (CK), NIH grant 4UH3TR000506-03 (JAT), and grant 5U01HL099773-06 (JAT).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="d30e5292">
      <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
      <p>The hESC data has been deposited in GEO [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>] with accession number GSE75748 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>].</p>
      <p>Sensitivity analyses, further methodological details, and additional results are provided in a supplement.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="d30e5305">
      <title>Authors’ contributions</title>
      <p>CK, L-FC, JAT, RMS, and KDK formulated the problem. CK, KDK, and MAN developed the scDD model. KDK implemented the scDD model in R, developed and implemented the simulations, and applied scDD to the hESC case study data. YL assisted with the simulation study. L-FC conducted the hESC experiments. CK, L-FC, RMS, and KDK interpreted the results. KDK and CK wrote the paper. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="d30e5310">
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="d30e5315">
      <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
      <p>Not applicable.</p>
    </sec>
  </ack>
  <ref-list id="Bib1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="CR1">
      <label>1</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Buettner</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Natarajan</surname>
            <given-names>KN</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Casale</surname>
            <given-names>FP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Proserpio</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Scialdone</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Theis</surname>
            <given-names>FJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Computational analysis of cell-to-cell heterogeneity in single-cell RNA-sequencing data reveals hidden subpopulations of cells</article-title>
        <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>32</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <fpage>155</fpage>
        <lpage>60</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.3102</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR2">
      <label>2</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Trombetta</surname>
            <given-names>JJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gennert</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Satija</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shalek</surname>
            <given-names>AK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Regev</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Preparation of single-cell RNA-seq libraries for next generation sequencing</article-title>
        <source>Curr Protoc Mol Biol</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>107</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <fpage>4</fpage>
        <lpage>22</lpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 24984854?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24984854</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR3">
      <label>3</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tang</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Barbacioru</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bao</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nordman</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Tracing the derivation of embryonic stem cells from the inner cell mass by single-cell RNA-seq analysis</article-title>
        <source>Cell Stem Cell</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <issue>5</issue>
        <fpage>468</fpage>
        <lpage>78</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2010.03.015</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 20452321?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20452321</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR4">
      <label>4</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yan</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Guo</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Single-cell RNA-seq profiling of human preimplantation embryos and embryonic stem cells</article-title>
        <source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>20</volume>
        <issue>9</issue>
        <fpage>1131</fpage>
        <lpage>9</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nsmb.2660</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 23934149?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23934149</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR5">
      <label>5</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xue</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cai</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cai</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jiang</surname>
            <given-names>C-y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Feng</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Genetic programs in human and mouse early embryos revealed by single-cell RNA sequencing</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>500</volume>
        <issue>7464</issue>
        <fpage>593</fpage>
        <lpage>7</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature12364</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 23892778?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23892778</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR6">
      <label>6</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Patel</surname>
            <given-names>AP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tirosh</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Trombetta</surname>
            <given-names>JJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shalek</surname>
            <given-names>AK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gillespie</surname>
            <given-names>SM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wakimoto</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Single-cell RNA-seq highlights intratumoral heterogeneity in primary glioblastoma</article-title>
        <source>Science</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>344</volume>
        <issue>6190</issue>
        <fpage>1396</fpage>
        <lpage>401</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1254257</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24925914?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24925914</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR7">
      <label>7</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shalek</surname>
            <given-names>AK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Satija</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Adiconis</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gertner</surname>
            <given-names>RS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gaublomme</surname>
            <given-names>JT</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Raychowdhury</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Single-cell transcriptomics reveals bimodality in expression and splicing in immune cells</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>498</volume>
        <issue>7453</issue>
        <fpage>236</fpage>
        <lpage>40</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature12172</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 23685454?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23685454</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR8">
      <label>8</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Treutlein</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Brownfield</surname>
            <given-names>DG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>AR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Neff</surname>
            <given-names>NF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mantalas</surname>
            <given-names>GL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Espinoza</surname>
            <given-names>FH</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Reconstructing lineage hierarchies of the distal lung epithelium using single-cell RNA-seq</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>509</volume>
        <issue>7500</issue>
        <fpage>371</fpage>
        <lpage>5</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature13173</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24739965?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24739965</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR9">
      <label>9</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hong</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jin</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xiong</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Canonical correlation analysis for RNA-seq co-expression networks</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>41</volume>
        <issue>8</issue>
        <fpage>95</fpage>
        <lpage>5</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt145</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR10">
      <label>10</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ramsköld</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Luo</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>YC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Deng</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Faridani</surname>
            <given-names>OR</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Full-length mRNA-seq from single-cell levels of RNA and individual circulating tumor cells</article-title>
        <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>30</volume>
        <issue>8</issue>
        <fpage>777</fpage>
        <lpage>82</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.2282</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 22820318?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22820318</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR11">
      <label>11</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>KT</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>HW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>HO</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>SC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Seo</surname>
            <given-names>YJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chung</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Single-cell mRNA sequencing identifies subclonal heterogeneity in anti-cancer drug responses of lung adenocarcinoma cells</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>16</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>127</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-015-0692-3</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 26084335?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26084335</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR12">
      <label>12</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>M-CW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lopez-Diaz</surname>
            <given-names>FJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Khan</surname>
            <given-names>SY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tariq</surname>
            <given-names>MA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dayn</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vaske</surname>
            <given-names>CJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Single-cell analyses of transcriptional heterogeneity during drug tolerance transition in cancer cells by RNA sequencing</article-title>
        <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>111</volume>
        <issue>44</issue>
        <fpage>4726</fpage>
        <lpage>35</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1404656111</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR13">
      <label>13</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Powell</surname>
            <given-names>AA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Talasaz</surname>
            <given-names>AH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Coram</surname>
            <given-names>MA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Reddy</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Deng</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Single cell profiling of circulating tumor cells: transcriptional heterogeneity and diversity from breast cancer cell lines</article-title>
        <source>PloS ONE</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <issue>5</issue>
        <fpage>33788</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0033788</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR14">
      <label>14</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hashimshony</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wagner</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sher</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yanai</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>CEL-seq: single-cell RNA-seq by multiplexed linear amplification</article-title>
        <source>Cell Rep</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>2</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <fpage>666</fpage>
        <lpage>73</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2012.08.003</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 22939981?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22939981</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR15">
      <label>15</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Brunskill</surname>
            <given-names>EW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>JS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chung</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Magella</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Potter</surname>
            <given-names>SS</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Single cell dissection of early kidney development: multilineage priming</article-title>
        <source>Development</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>141</volume>
        <issue>15</issue>
        <fpage>3093</fpage>
        <lpage>101</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.110601</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25053437?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25053437</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR16">
      <label>16</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Marinov</surname>
            <given-names>GK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Williams</surname>
            <given-names>BA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McCue</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schroth</surname>
            <given-names>GP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gertz</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Myers</surname>
            <given-names>RM</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>From single-cell to cell-pool transcriptomes: stochasticity in gene expression and RNA splicing</article-title>
        <source>Genome Res</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>24</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <fpage>496</fpage>
        <lpage>510</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.161034.113</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24299736?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24299736</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR17">
      <label>17</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kharchenko</surname>
            <given-names>PV</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Silberstein</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Scadden</surname>
            <given-names>DT</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Bayesian approach to single-cell differential expression analysis</article-title>
        <source>Nat Methods</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <issue>7</issue>
        <fpage>740</fpage>
        <lpage>2</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2967</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24836921?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24836921</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR18">
      <label>18</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Finak</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McDavid</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yajima</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Deng</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gersuk</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shalek</surname>
            <given-names>AK</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Mast: a flexible statistical framework for assessing transcriptional changes and characterizing heterogeneity in single-cell RNA sequencing data</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>16</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <lpage>13</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-015-0844-5</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25583448</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR19">
      <label>19</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kærn</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Elston</surname>
            <given-names>TC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Blake</surname>
            <given-names>WJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Collins</surname>
            <given-names>JJ</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Stochasticity in gene expression: from theories to phenotypes</article-title>
        <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>
        <year>2005</year>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <issue>6</issue>
        <fpage>451</fpage>
        <lpage>64</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg1615</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 15883588?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15883588</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR20">
      <label>20</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Birtwistle</surname>
            <given-names>MR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rauch</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kiyatkin</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Aksamitiene</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dobrzyński</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hoek</surname>
            <given-names>JB</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Emergence of bimodal cell population responses from the interplay between analog single-cell signaling and protein expression noise</article-title>
        <source>BMC Syst Biol</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>109</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1752-0509-6-109</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 22920937?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22920937</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR21">
      <label>21</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dobrzyński</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fey</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nguyen</surname>
            <given-names>LK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kholodenko</surname>
            <given-names>BN</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Bimodal protein distributions in heterogeneous oscillating systems</article-title>
        <source>Computational methods in systems biology</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <publisher-loc>Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
        <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR22">
      <label>22</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Singer</surname>
            <given-names>ZS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yong</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tischler</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hackett</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Altinok</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Surani</surname>
            <given-names>MA</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Dynamic heterogeneity and DNA methylation in embryonic stem cells</article-title>
        <source>Mol Cell</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>55</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <fpage>319</fpage>
        <lpage>31</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2014.06.029</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25038413?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25038413</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR23">
      <label>23</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dobrzyński</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nguyen</surname>
            <given-names>LK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Birtwistle</surname>
            <given-names>MR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>von Kriegsheim</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fernández</surname>
            <given-names>AB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cheong</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Nonlinear signalling networks and cell-to-cell variability transform external signals into broadly distributed or bimodal responses</article-title>
        <source>J R Soc Interface</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <issue>98</issue>
        <fpage>20140383</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsif.2014.0383</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24966234?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24966234</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR24">
      <label>24</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ozbudak</surname>
            <given-names>EM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Thattai</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kurtser</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Grossman</surname>
            <given-names>AD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>van Oudenaarden</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Regulation of noise in the expression of a single gene</article-title>
        <source>Nat Genet</source>
        <year>2002</year>
        <volume>31</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>69</fpage>
        <lpage>73</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng869</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 11967532?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11967532</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR25">
      <label>25</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Raj</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Peskin</surname>
            <given-names>CS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tranchina</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vargas</surname>
            <given-names>DY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tyagi</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Stochastic mRNA synthesis in mammalian cells</article-title>
        <source>PLoS Biol</source>
        <year>2006</year>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <fpage>309</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0040309</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR26">
      <label>26</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Thattai</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Van Oudenaarden</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Intrinsic noise in gene regulatory networks</article-title>
        <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source>
        <year>2001</year>
        <volume>98</volume>
        <issue>15</issue>
        <fpage>8614</fpage>
        <lpage>19</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.151588598</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 11438714?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11438714</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR27">
      <label>27</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Delmans M, Hemberg M. Discrete distributional differential expression (D3E) – a tool for gene expression analysis of single-cell RNA-seq data. bioRxiv. 2015. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/020735">10.1101/020735</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR28">
      <label>28</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Katayama</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Töhönen</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Linnarsson</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kere</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>SAMstrt: statistical test for differential expression in single-cell transcriptome with spike-in normalization</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>29</volume>
        <issue>22</issue>
        <fpage>2943</fpage>
        <lpage>5</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt511</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 23995393?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23995393</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR29">
      <label>29</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tay</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hughey</surname>
            <given-names>JJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>TK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lipniacki</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Quake</surname>
            <given-names>SR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Covert</surname>
            <given-names>MW</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Single-cell NF- <italic>κ</italic> B dynamics reveal digital activation and analogue information processing</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>466</volume>
        <issue>7303</issue>
        <fpage>267</fpage>
        <lpage>71</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature09145</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 20581820?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20581820</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR30">
      <label>30</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chu</surname>
            <given-names>Li-Fang</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Single-cell RNA-seq reveals novel regulators of human embryonic stem cell differentiation to definitive endoderm</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol.</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>17</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>173</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-016-1033-x</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 27534536?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27534536</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR31">
      <label>31</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Trapnell</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cacchiarelli</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Grimsby</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pokharel</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Morse</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The dynamics and regulators of cell fate decisions are revealed by pseudotemporal ordering of single cells</article-title>
        <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>32</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <fpage>381</fpage>
        <lpage>6</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.2859</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24658644?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24658644</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR32">
      <label>32</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kumar</surname>
            <given-names>RM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cahan</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shalek</surname>
            <given-names>AK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Satija</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>DaleyKeyser</surname>
            <given-names>AJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Deconstructing transcriptional heterogeneity in pluripotent stem cells</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>516</volume>
        <issue>7529</issue>
        <fpage>56</fpage>
        <lpage>61</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature13920</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25471879?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25471879</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR33">
      <label>33</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rapaport</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Khanin</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liang</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pirun</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Krek</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zumbo</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Comprehensive evaluation of differential gene expression analysis methods for RNA-seq data</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>14</volume>
        <issue>9</issue>
        <fpage>95</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2013-14-9-r95</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR34">
      <label>34</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Law</surname>
            <given-names>CW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shi</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Smyth</surname>
            <given-names>GK</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Voom: precision weights unlock linear model analysis tools for RNA-seq read counts</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>15</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <fpage>29</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2014-15-2-r29</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR35">
      <label>35</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Benjamini</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hochberg</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</article-title>
        <source>J R Stat Soc Ser B Methodol</source>
        <year>1995</year>
        <volume>57</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>289</fpage>
        <lpage>300</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR36">
      <label>36</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wagner</surname>
            <given-names>BD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zerbe</surname>
            <given-names>GO</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mexal</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Leonard</surname>
            <given-names>SS</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Permutation-based adjustments for the significance of partial regression coefficients in microarray data analysis</article-title>
        <source>Genet Epidemiol</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>32</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <lpage>8</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/gepi.20255</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 17630650?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17630650</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR37">
      <label>37</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Miura</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Luo</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Khrebtukova</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Brandenberger</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhou</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Scott Thies</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Monitoring early differentiation events in human embryonic stem cells by massively parallel signature sequencing and expressed sequence tag scan</article-title>
        <source>Stem Cells Dev</source>
        <year>2004</year>
        <volume>13</volume>
        <issue>6</issue>
        <fpage>694</fpage>
        <lpage>715</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/scd.2004.13.694</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 15684837?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15684837</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR38">
      <label>38</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Armstrong</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hughes</surname>
            <given-names>O</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yung</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hyslop</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stewart</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wappler</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The role of pi3k/akt, mapk/erk and nf <italic>κ</italic><italic>β</italic> signalling in the maintenance of human embryonic stem cell pluripotency and viability highlighted by transcriptional profiling and functional analysis</article-title>
        <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>
        <year>2006</year>
        <volume>15</volume>
        <issue>11</issue>
        <fpage>1894</fpage>
        <lpage>913</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/ddl112</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 16644866?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16644866</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR39">
      <label>39</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shi</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>YH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sierant</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cui</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Guan</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Developmental transcriptome analysis of humwan erythropoiesis</article-title>
        <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>23</volume>
        <issue>17</issue>
        <fpage>4528</fpage>
        <lpage>42</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/ddu167</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24781209?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24781209</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR40">
      <label>40</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kolodziejczyk</surname>
            <given-names>AA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>JK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tsang</surname>
            <given-names>JC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ilicic</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Henriksson</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Natarajan</surname>
            <given-names>KN</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Single cell RNA-sequencing of pluripotent states unlocks modular transcriptional variation</article-title>
        <source>Cell Stem Cell</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>17</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <fpage>471</fpage>
        <lpage>85</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2015.09.011</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 26431182?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26431182</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR41">
      <label>41</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Walworth</surname>
            <given-names>NC</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Cell-cycle checkpoint kinases: checking in on the cell cycle</article-title>
        <source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source>
        <year>2000</year>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <issue>6</issue>
        <fpage>697</fpage>
        <lpage>704</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0955-0674(00)00154-X</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 11063934?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11063934</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR42">
      <label>42</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Malumbres</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Barbacid</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Mammalian cyclin-dependent kinases</article-title>
        <source>Trends Biochem Sci</source>
        <year>2005</year>
        <volume>30</volume>
        <issue>11</issue>
        <fpage>630</fpage>
        <lpage>41</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tibs.2005.09.005</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 16236519?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16236519</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR43">
      <label>43</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>White</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dalton</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Cell cycle control of embryonic stem cells</article-title>
        <source>Stem Cell Rev</source>
        <year>2005</year>
        <volume>1</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <fpage>131</fpage>
        <lpage>8</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1385/SCR:1:2:131</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 17142847?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17142847</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR44">
      <label>44</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gabut</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Samavarchi-Tehrani</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Slobodeniuc</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>O’Hanlon</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sung</surname>
            <given-names>HK</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>An alternative splicing switch regulates embryonic stem cell pluripotency and reprogramming</article-title>
        <source>Cell</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>147</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>132</fpage>
        <lpage>46</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2011.08.023</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 21924763?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21924763</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR45">
      <label>45</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Atkinson</surname>
            <given-names>SP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Collin</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Irina</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Anyfantis</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kyung</surname>
            <given-names>BK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lako</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A putative role for the immunoproteasome in the maintenance of pluripotency in human embryonic stem cells</article-title>
        <source>Stem Cells</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>30</volume>
        <issue>7</issue>
        <fpage>1373</fpage>
        <lpage>84</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/stem.1113</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 22532526?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22532526</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR46">
      <label>46</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>JK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Marioni</surname>
            <given-names>JC</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Inferring the kinetics of stochastic gene expression from single-cell RNA-sequencing data</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>14</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>7</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2013-14-1-r7</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR47">
      <label>47</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <collab>R Core Team</collab>
        </person-group>
        <source>R: a language and environment for statistical computing</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <publisher-loc>Vienna</publisher-loc>
        <publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR48">
      <label>48</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Leng</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chu</surname>
            <given-names>LF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Barry</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Choi</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Oscope identifies oscillatory genes in unsynchronized single-cell RNA-seq experiments</article-title>
        <source>Nat Methods</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <fpage>947</fpage>
        <lpage>50</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.3549</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 26301841?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26301841</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR49">
      <label>49</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gulbranson</surname>
            <given-names>DR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hou</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bolin</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ruotti</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Probasco</surname>
            <given-names>MD</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Chemically defined conditions for human iPSC derivation and culture</article-title>
        <source>Nat Methods</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <issue>5</issue>
        <fpage>424</fpage>
        <lpage>9</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1593</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 21478862?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21478862</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR50">
      <label>50</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xie</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schultz</surname>
            <given-names>MD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lister</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hou</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rajagopal</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ray</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Epigenomic analysis of multilineage differentiation of human embryonic stem cells</article-title>
        <source>Cell</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>153</volume>
        <issue>5</issue>
        <fpage>1134</fpage>
        <lpage>48</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2013.04.022</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 23664764?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23664764</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR51">
      <label>51</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Schwartz</surname>
            <given-names>MP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hou</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Propson</surname>
            <given-names>NE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Engstrom</surname>
            <given-names>CJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Costa</surname>
            <given-names>VS</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Human pluripotent stem cell-derived neural constructs for predicting neural toxicity</article-title>
        <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>112</volume>
        <issue>40</issue>
        <fpage>12516</fpage>
        <lpage>21</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1516645112</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 26392547?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26392547</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR52">
      <label>52</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dewey</surname>
            <given-names>CN</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Rsem: accurate transcript quantification from RNA-seq data with or without a reference genome</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinform</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>323</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-12-323</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR53">
      <label>53</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Anders</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huber</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Differential expression analysis for sequence count data</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <fpage>106</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2010-11-10-r106</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20236492</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR54">
      <label>54</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Leng</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dawson</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Thomson</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ruotti</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rissman</surname>
            <given-names>AI</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Smits</surname>
            <given-names>BM</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Ebseq: an empirical Bayes hierarchical model for inference in RNA-seq experiments</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>29</volume>
        <issue>8</issue>
        <fpage>1035</fpage>
        <lpage>43</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt087</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 23428641?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23428641</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR55">
      <label>55</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Edgar</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Domrachev</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lash</surname>
            <given-names>AE</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Gene expression omnibus: NCBI gene expression and hybridization array data repository</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
        <year>2002</year>
        <volume>30</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>207</fpage>
        <lpage>10</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/30.1.207</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 11752295?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11752295</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR56">
      <label>56</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lappalainen</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sammeth</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Friedländer</surname>
            <given-names>MR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>AC ’t Hoen</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Monlong</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rivas</surname>
            <given-names>MA</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Transcriptome and genome sequencing uncovers functional variation in humans</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>501</volume>
        <issue>7468</issue>
        <fpage>506</fpage>
        <lpage>11</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature12531</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24037378?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24037378</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR57">
      <label>57</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Seo</surname>
            <given-names>JS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ju</surname>
            <given-names>YS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>WC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shin</surname>
            <given-names>JY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>JK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bleazard</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The transcriptional landscape and mutational profile of lung adenocarcinoma</article-title>
        <source>Genome Res</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>22</volume>
        <fpage>2109</fpage>
        <lpage>19</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.145144.112</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 22975805?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22975805</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR58">
      <label>58</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hartigan</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Partition models</article-title>
        <source>Commun Stat Theory Meth</source>
        <year>1990</year>
        <volume>19</volume>
        <issue>8</issue>
        <fpage>2745</fpage>
        <lpage>56</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03610929008830345</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR59">
      <label>59</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shotwell</surname>
            <given-names>MS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Slate</surname>
            <given-names>EH</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Bayesian outlier detection with dirichlet process mixtures</article-title>
        <source>Bayesian Anal</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <fpage>665</fpage>
        <lpage>90</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1214/11-BA625</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR60">
      <label>60</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>MacEachern</surname>
            <given-names>SN</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Estimating normal means with a conjugate style Dirichlet process prior</article-title>
        <source>Commun Stat Simul Comput</source>
        <year>1994</year>
        <volume>23</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <fpage>727</fpage>
        <lpage>41</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03610919408813196</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR61">
      <label>61</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bush</surname>
            <given-names>CA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>MacEachern</surname>
            <given-names>SN</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A semiparametric Bayesian model for randomised block designs</article-title>
        <source>Biometrika</source>
        <year>1996</year>
        <volume>83</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <fpage>275</fpage>
        <lpage>85</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/biomet/83.2.275</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR62">
      <label>62</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>MacEachern</surname>
            <given-names>SN</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Müller</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Estimating mixture of Dirichlet process models</article-title>
        <source>J Comput Graph Stat</source>
        <year>1998</year>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <fpage>223</fpage>
        <lpage>38</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR63">
      <label>63</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ward Jr</surname>
            <given-names>JH</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Hierarchical grouping to optimize an objective function</article-title>
        <source>J Am Stat Assoc</source>
        <year>1963</year>
        <volume>58</volume>
        <issue>301</issue>
        <fpage>236</fpage>
        <lpage>44</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01621459.1963.10500845</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR64">
      <label>64</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dunson</surname>
            <given-names>DB</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Fast Bayesian inference in Dirichlet process mixture models</article-title>
        <source>J Comput Graph Stat</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>20</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>196</fpage>
        <lpage>216</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1198/jcgs.2010.07081</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR65">
      <label>65</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shotwell</surname>
            <given-names>MS</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>profdpm: An R package for MAP estimation in a class of conjugate product partition models</article-title>
        <source>J Stat Softw</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>53</volume>
        <issue>8</issue>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <lpage>18</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18637/jss.v053.i08</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR66">
      <label>66</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fraley C, Raftery AE, Murphy TB, Scrucca L. MCLUST version 4 for r: Normal mixture modeling for model-based clustering, classification, and density estimation. University of Washington, Department of Statistics. 2012. Technical report 597.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR67">
      <label>67</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tarpey</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yun</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Petkova</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Model misspecification finite mixture or homogeneous?</article-title>
        <source>Stat Model</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <fpage>199</fpage>
        <lpage>218</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1471082X0800800204</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR68">
      <label>68</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wen</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Symmans</surname>
            <given-names>WF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pusztai</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Coombes</surname>
            <given-names>KR</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The bimodality index: a criterion for discovering and ranking bimodal signatures from cancer gene expression profiling data</article-title>
        <source>Cancer Informat</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <fpage>199</fpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR69">
      <label>69</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Vallejos</surname>
            <given-names>CA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Richardson</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Marioni</surname>
            <given-names>JC</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Beyond comparisons of means: understanding changes in gene expression at the single-cell level</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>17</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-016-0930-3</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26753840</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
