<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">bioinfo</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1367-4803</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1367-4811</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5039916</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw325</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">btw325</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Applications Notes</subject>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Genome Analysis</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>GenVisR: Genomic Visualizations in R</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Skidmore</surname>
          <given-names>Zachary L.</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btw325-aff1">
          <sup>1</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Wagner</surname>
          <given-names>Alex H.</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btw325-aff1">
          <sup>1</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Lesurf</surname>
          <given-names>Robert</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btw325-aff1">
          <sup>1</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Campbell</surname>
          <given-names>Katie M.</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btw325-aff1">
          <sup>1</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Kunisaki</surname>
          <given-names>Jason</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btw325-aff1">
          <sup>1</sup>
        </xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Griffith</surname>
          <given-names>Obi L.</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btw325-aff1">
          <sup>1</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btw325-aff2">
          <sup>2</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btw325-aff3">
          <sup>3</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btw325-aff4">
          <sup>4</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="btw325-cor1">*</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Griffith</surname>
          <given-names>Malachi</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btw325-aff1">
          <sup>1</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btw325-aff3">
          <sup>3</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btw325-aff4">
          <sup>4</sup>
        </xref>
        <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="btw325-cor1">*</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="btw325-aff1"><sup>1</sup>McDonnell Genome Institute, Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO 63108, USA</aff>
      <aff id="btw325-aff2"><sup>2</sup>Department of Medicine</aff>
      <aff id="btw325-aff3"><sup>3</sup>Siteman Cancer Center</aff>
      <aff id="btw325-aff4"><sup>4</sup>Department of Genetics, Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO 63110, USA</aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="btw325-cor1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed.</corresp>
      <fn id="btw325-FM1">
        <p>Associate Editor: Inanc Birol</p>
      </fn>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
      <day>01</day>
      <month>10</month>
      <year>2016</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>10</day>
      <month>6</month>
      <year>2016</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>10</day>
      <month>6</month>
      <year>2016</year>
    </pub-date>
    <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
    <volume>32</volume>
    <issue>19</issue>
    <fpage>3012</fpage>
    <lpage>3014</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>02</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>18</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
      <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" license-type="creative-commons">
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract>
      <p><bold>Summary:</bold> Visualizing and summarizing data from genomic studies continues to be a challenge. Here, we introduce the GenVisR package to addresses this challenge by providing highly customizable, publication-quality graphics focused on cohort level genome analyses. GenVisR provides a rapid and easy-to-use suite of genomic visualization tools, while maintaining a high degree of flexibility by leveraging the abilities of ggplot2 and Bioconductor.</p>
      <p><bold>Availability and Implementation:</bold> GenVisR is an R package available via Bioconductor (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bioconductor.org/packages/GenVisR">https://bioconductor.org/packages/GenVisR</ext-link>) under GPLv3. Support is available via GitHub (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/griffithlab/GenVisR/issues">https://github.com/griffithlab/GenVisR/issues</ext-link>) and the Bioconductor support website.</p>
      <p><bold>Contacts:</bold><email>obigriffith@wustl.edu</email> or <email>mgriffit@wustl.edu</email></p>
      <p><bold>Supplementary information:</bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btw325/-/DC1">Supplementary data</ext-link> are available at <italic>Bioinformatics</italic> online.</p>
    </abstract>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="3"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec>
    <title>1 Introduction</title>
    <p>The continued development of massively parallel sequencing technologies has led to an exponential growth in the amount of genomic data produced (<xref rid="btw325-B9" ref-type="bibr">Kodama <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). This growth has in turn enabled scientists to investigate increasingly large, cohort-level genomic datasets. Generating intuitive visualizations is a critical component in recognizing patterns and investigating underlying biological properties in cohorts under study. A significant bottleneck exists, however, between data generation and subsequent visualization and interpretation (<xref rid="btw325-B5" ref-type="bibr">Good <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). Additionally, generating publication-quality figures for effective communication of these data typically requires <italic>ad hoc</italic> methods such as manual creation or extensive graphic manipulation with third party software. This process is both time intensive and difficult to automate/reproduce. Further, the absence of software supporting multiple species can make this process even more demanding. Here, we present GenVisR, a Bioconductor package to address these issues. GenVisR provides a user-friendly, flexible and comprehensive suite of tools for visualizing complex genomic data in three categories (small variants, copy number alterations and data quality) for multiple species of interest.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>2 Visualization of small variants</title>
    <p>The identification of small variants (SNVs and indels) within a genomic context is of paramount importance for the elucidation of the genetic basis of disease. Numerous tools and resources have been created to identify variants in sequencing data (<xref rid="btw325-B16" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Conversely, few tools exist to visually display and summarize these variants across sample cohorts. Given a gene of interest, it is often useful to view variant occurrences in the context of the translated protein product (<xref rid="btw325-B19" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). A variety of options exist to achieve this; however tools that offer both automation and flexibility to perform this task are lacking (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btw325/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link>) (<xref rid="btw325-B7" ref-type="bibr">Griffith <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="btw325-B11" ref-type="bibr">Leiserson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="btw325-B13" ref-type="bibr">Nilsen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="btw325-B18" ref-type="bibr">Yin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="btw325-B20" ref-type="bibr">Zhou <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). The function lolliplot was developed to allow for precise control over visualization options (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="btw325-F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). This includes the ability to choose Ensembl annotation databases for protein domain displays and to plot multiple tracks of mutations above and below the protein representation. Another common objective of genomic studies is to identify variant recurrence across multiple genes within a cohort. The GenVisR function waterfall was developed to calculate and rapidly illustrate the mutational burden of variants on both a gene and sample level, and further differentiates between variant types (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="btw325-F1">Fig. 1B</xref>) (<xref rid="btw325-B10" ref-type="bibr">Krysiak <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="btw325-B12" ref-type="bibr">Ma <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="btw325-B15" ref-type="bibr">Wagner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). Mutually exclusive genomic events at the variant level are emphasized in this visualization by arranging samples in a hierarchical fashion such that samples with mutations in the most recurrently mutated genes are ranked first. Finally, it is often informative to investigate the rate of transition and transversion mutations observed across a set of cases. For example, lung tumors originating from patients with a history of tobacco smoke exposure display a pattern of enrichment for C to A or G to T transversions (<xref rid="btw325-B6" ref-type="bibr">Govindan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). The function TvTi (transversion/transition) was developed to improve recognition of these types of patterns within a cohort.
<fig id="btw325-F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Selected representation of GenVisR visualizations. (<bold>A</bold>) Output from lolliplot for select TCGA breast cancer samples (<xref rid="btw325-B2" ref-type="bibr">Cancer Genome Atlas Network, 2012</xref>) shows two mutational hotspots in PIK3CA within the accessory and catalytic kinase domains. (<bold>B</bold>) Output from waterfall shows mutations for five genes across 50 select TCGA breast cancer samples with mutation type indicated by colour in the grid and per sample/gene mutation rates indicated in the top and left sidebars. (<bold>C</bold>) Output from genCov displays coverage (bottom plots) showing focal deletions in sample A (last exon) and B (second intron) within a gene of interest. GC content (top plot) is encoded via a range of colours for each exon. (<bold>D</bold>) Output from lohSpec for HCC1395 (<xref rid="btw325-B7" ref-type="bibr">Griffith <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>), HCC38 and HCC1143 (<xref rid="btw325-B4" ref-type="bibr">Daemen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>) breast cancer cell lines shows LOH events, across all chromosomes, shaded as dark blue. (<bold>E</bold>) Output from covBars shows cumulative coverage for 10 samples indicating that for each sample, at least ∼75% of targeted regions were covered at ≥ 35× depth. (<bold>F</bold>) Output from compIdent for the HCC1395 breast cancer cell line (tumor and normal) shows variant coverage (bottom plot) and SNP allele fraction (main plot) indicating highly related samples. Note that 4/24 positions are discrepant and likely result from extensive LOH in this cell line</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="btw325f1p"/></fig>
</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>3 Visualization of copy number alterations</title>
    <p>Copy number alterations occurring within the genome are implicated in a variety of diseases (<xref rid="btw325-B1" ref-type="bibr">Beroukhim <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). The function GenCov illustrates amplifications and deletions across one or more samples in a genomic region of interest (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="btw325-F1">Fig. 1C</xref>). A key feature of GenCov is the effective use of plot space, especially for large regions of interest, via the differential compression of various features (introns, exons, UTR) within the region of interest. For a broader view the function cnView plots copy number calls, and the corresponding ideogram, for an individual sample at the chromosome level. The function cnSpec displays amplifications and deletions on a still larger scale via copy number segments calls. This information is displayed as a heat map arranged in a grid indexed by chromosomes and samples. Alternatively, cnFreq displays the frequency of samples within a cohort that are observed to have copy number gains or losses at specific genomic loci. In addition to copy number changes, loss of heterozygosity (LOH) often plays an important role in genomic diseases. For example, in acute myeloid leukemia copy neutral LOH has been associated with shorter complete remission and worse overall survival (<xref rid="btw325-B8" ref-type="bibr">Gronseth <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). The function lohSpec displays LOH regions observed within a cohort (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="btw325-F1">Fig. 1D</xref>) by plotting a sliding window mean difference in variant allele fractions for tumor and normal germline variants.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>4 Visualization of data quality</title>
    <p>In genomic studies, the quality of sequencing data is of critical importance to the proper interpretation of observed variations. Therefore, we provide a suite of functions focused on data quality assessment and visualization. The first of these, covBars, provides a framework for displaying the sequencing coverage achieved for targeted bases in a study (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="btw325-F1">Fig. 1E</xref>). A second function, compIdent, aids in the identification of mix-ups among samples that are thought to originate from the same individual (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="btw325-F1">Fig. 1F</xref>). This is achieved by displaying the variant allele fraction of SNPs in relation to each sample. By default, 24 biallelic ‘identity SNPs’ (<xref rid="btw325-B14" ref-type="bibr">Pengelly <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>) are used to determine sample identity.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>5 Example usage</title>
    <p>GenVisR was developed with the naïve R user in mind. Functions are well documented and have reasonable defaults set for optional parameters. To illustrate, creating <xref ref-type="fig" rid="btw325-F1">Figure 1B</xref> was as simple as executing the waterfall function call on a standard MAF (version 2.4) file containing variant mutation data and choosing which genes to plot:<disp-quote content-type="extract"><p>genes = c(“PIK3CA”, “TP53”, “USH2”, “MLL3”, “BRCA1”)</p><p>G<sc>en</sc>V<sc>is</sc>R::<sc>waterfall</sc>(<sc>x</sc><sc>=</sc><sc>maf</sc>_<sc>file</sc>, <sc>plot</sc>G<sc>enes=genes</sc>)</p></disp-quote></p>
    <p>The MAF file format originally developed for The Cancer Genome Atlas project (Cancer Genome Atlas Research Network, 2008) is the default file format accepted by waterfall. This format was chosen based on its simplicity and accessibility. A number of resources exist to convert VCF files common to most variant callers to MAF format. In the interest of maintaining flexibility, the waterfall and other GenVisR functions are able to accept alternative file types as input.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>6 Conclusion</title>
    <p>GenVisR provides features and functions for many popular genomic visualizations not otherwise available in a single convenient package (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btw325/-/DC1">Table S1</ext-link>). By leveraging the abilities of ggplot2 (<xref rid="btw325-B17" ref-type="bibr">Wickham, 2009</xref>) it confers a level of customizability not previously possible. Virtually any aspect of a plot can be changed simply by adding an additional layer onto the graphical object. Thus, GenVisR allows for publication quality figures with a minimal amount of required input and data manipulation while maintaining a high degree of flexibility and customizability.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
      <caption>
        <title>Supplementary Data</title>
      </caption>
      <media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_32_19_3012__index.html"/>
      <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_btw325_TableS1_software_comparison.pdf"/>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack>
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <p>The authors would like to thank Richard K. Wilson and Elaine R. Mardis for their encouragement and support in the creation of this work. We also thank Chris A. Miller and Dave Larson for their creative guidance.</p>
  </ack>
  <sec>
    <title>Funding</title>
    <p>MG was supported by the National Human Genome Research Institute (K99HG007940). OLG was supported by the National Cancer Institute (K22CA188163).</p>
    <p><italic>Conflict of Interest</italic>: none declared.</p>
  </sec>
  <ref-list>
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="btw325-B1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beroukhim</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The landscape of somatic copy-number alteration across human cancers</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>463</volume>, <fpage>899</fpage>–<lpage>905</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20164920</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btw325-B2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Cancer Genome Atlas Network</collab>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Comprehensive molecular portraits of human breast tumours</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>490</volume>, <fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23000897</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btw325-B3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Cancer Genome Atlas Research Network</collab>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Comprehensive genomic characterization defines human glioblastoma genes and core pathways</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>455</volume>, <fpage>1061</fpage>–<lpage>1068</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18772890</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btw325-B4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daemen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Modeling precision treatment of breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>., <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>R110</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24176112</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btw325-B5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Good</surname><given-names>B.M.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Organizing knowledge to enable personalization of medicine in cancer</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>., <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>438</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25222080</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btw325-B6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Govindan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Genomic landscape of non-small cell lung cancer in smokers and never-smokers</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>150</volume>, <fpage>1121</fpage>–<lpage>1134</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22980976</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btw325-B7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Genome Modeling System: A Knowledge Management Platform for Genomics</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput. Biol</source>., <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>e1004274</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26158448</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btw325-B8">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gronseth</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Prognostic significance of acquired copy-neutral loss of heterozygosity in acute myeloid leukemia</article-title>. <source>Cancer</source>, <volume>121</volume>, <fpage>2900</fpage>–<lpage>2908</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26033747</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btw325-B9">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kodama</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The Sequence Read Archive: explosive growth of sequencing data</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>D54</fpage>–<lpage>D56</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22009675</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btw325-B10">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krysiak</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>A genomic analysis of Philadelphia chromosome-negative AML arising in patients with CML</article-title>. <source>Blood Cancer J</source>., <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>e413</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27058228</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btw325-B11">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leiserson</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>MAGI: visualization and collaborative annotation of genomic aberrations</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>483</fpage>–<lpage>484</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26020500</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btw325-B12">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>C.X.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>A phase I trial of BKM120 (Buparlisib) in combination with fulvestrant in postmenopausal women with estrogen receptor-positive metastatic breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Clin. Cancer Res</source>., <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>1583</fpage>–<lpage>1591</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26563128</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btw325-B13">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nilsen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Copynumber: efficient algorithms for single- and multi-track copy number segmentation</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>591</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23442169</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btw325-B14">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pengelly</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>A SNP profiling panel for sample tracking in whole-exome sequencing studies</article-title>. <source>Genome Med</source>., <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>89</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24070238</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btw325-B15">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>DGIdb 2.0: mining clinically relevant drug-gene interactions</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>D1036</fpage>–<lpage>D1044</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26531824</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btw325-B16">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Detecting somatic point mutations in cancer genome sequencing data: a comparison of mutation callers</article-title>. <source>Genome Med</source>., <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>91</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24112718</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btw325-B17">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wickham</surname><given-names>H. (</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year>) <source>ggplot2: Elegant Graphics for Data Analysis</source>. <publisher-name>Springer Publishing Company, Incorporated, New York</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btw325-B18">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>ggbio: an R package for extending the grammar of graphics for genomic data</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>., <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>R77.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22937822</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btw325-B19">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The genetic basis of early T-cell precursor acute lymphoblastic leukaemia</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>481</volume>, <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>163</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22237106</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btw325-B20">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Exploring genomic alteration in pediatric cancer using ProteinPaint</article-title>. <source>Nat. Genet</source>., <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>4</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26711108</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
