<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20050630//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformation</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformation</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Bioinformation</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Bioinformation</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">0973-2063</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Biomedical Informatics</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5450252</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">97320630013101</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6026/97320630013101</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Software</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>optCluster: An R Package for Determining the Optimal Clustering Algorithm</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Sekula</surname>
          <given-names>Michael</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Datta</surname>
          <given-names>Somnath</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Datta</surname>
          <given-names>Susmita</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Bioinformatics and Biostatistics, University of Louisville, Louisville, Kentucky, 40202, USA;</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Biostatistics, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida, 32611, USA;</aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="COR1"><label>*</label>Susmita Datta<email>susmita.datta@ufl.edu</email></corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>31</day>
      <month>3</month>
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>13</volume>
    <issue>3</issue>
    <fpage>101</fpage>
    <lpage>103</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>27</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2017</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>10</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2017</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>11</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2017</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© 2017 Biomedical Informatics</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article which permits unrestricted use, distribution, 
and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. This is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract>
      <p>There exist numerous programs and packages that perform validation for a given clustering solution; however, clustering algorithms
fare differently as judged by different validation measures. If more than one performance measure is used to evaluate multiple
clustering partitions, an optimal result is often difficult to determine by visual inspection alone. This paper introduces optCluster, an R
package that uses a single function to simultaneously compare numerous clustering partitions (created by different algorithms and/or
numbers of clusters) and obtain a “best” option for a given dataset. The method of weighted rank aggregation is utilized by this
package to objectively aggregate various performance measure scores, thereby taking away the guesswork that often follows a visual
inspection of cluster results. The optCluster package contains biological validation measures as well as clustering algorithms
developed specifically for RNA sequencing data, making it a useful tool for clustering genomic data.</p>
      <sec id="s0">
        <title>Availability:</title>
        <p>This package is available for free through the Comprehensive R Archive Network (CRAN) at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cran.rproject.org/web/packages/optCluster/">
http://cran.rproject.org/web/packages/optCluster/</ext-link></p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <kwd-group>
      <kwd>Clustering</kwd>
      <kwd>Validation</kwd>
      <kwd>Gene Expression</kwd>
      <kwd>RNA-Seq</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec id="s1">
    <title>Background</title>
    <p>Cluster analysis is playing an increasingly important role with
many of the new advancements in the field of bioinformatics.
Researchers often attempt to expose underlying structures inside
large datasets in hopes that molecular profiles are organized into
biologically meaningful clusters. For example, genes with similar
biological functions would ideally be grouped into the same
cluster. When “little” or “no” information is known about the
data, clustering algorithms are necessary for assigning similar
observations together into the same group. Different algorithms
naturally create different clustering partitions, so choosing the
“best” partition can be a potentially daunting endeavor. Since
clustering is an unsupervised learning task, there is no correct
answer to what the “best” partition for a dataset really is.
Therefore, researchers turn to validation measures as a method of
comparing multiple clustering results. These validation measures
evaluate clusters based on specific performance criteria such as
compactness, separation, or biological homogeneity. An inherent
problem with cluster validation is that a clustering algorithm may
perform well for one index but perform poorly for another. In
fact, it is quite common for a different choice of validation
measure to result in a different optimal clustering solution. The
detailed article by [<xref rid="R01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] examines the potential issues associated
with cluster validation in the field of bioinformatics and suggests
using multiple validation indices to compare different partitions.
Unfortunately, choosing the “best” clustering option based on a
visual inspection of multiple validation results can be problematic
since the results typically consist of multiple “best” options.
Hence, an algorithmic method that can provide a unique solution
to this problem would be useful.</p>
    <p>In this paper, we present an R [<xref rid="R02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] package called optCluster to
help researchers establish an optimal or “best” solution to cluster
analysis. Using a single function call, the user is able to evaluate
various combinations of clustering algorithms and numbers of
clusters with multiple validation measures, and determine the
most ideal clustering partition for a particular dataset through an
aggregation of ranked validation measure lists.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="methods" id="s2">
    <title>Methodology</title>
    <p>The core of the optCluster package is weighted rank aggregation,
which was proposed by [<xref rid="R03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] as a technique to evaluate a set of
validation measure results. Clustering partitions, created by
different algorithms and/or numbers of clusters, can be sorted 
into a ranked list, Vi, based on their performances for a specific
validation index. When using more than one validation measure
in a cluster analysis, a set of ranked lists is created. The idea
behind rank aggregation is to combine these lists together and
generate an optimally ranked list that is as close as possible to the
entire collection of original lists. In this context, rank aggregation
is essentially an optimization problem. Suppose there are m
number of ranked lists (V1, … , Vm) such that each Vi is associated
with a corresponding importance weight wi. An objective function
for a proposed list L can be defined as</p>
    <p>
      <mml:math id="M1">
        <mml:mstyle displaystyle="true">
          <mml:mrow>
            <mml:mi>Φ</mml:mi>
          </mml:mrow>
          <mml:mrow>
            <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
          </mml:mrow>
          <mml:mrow>
            <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
          </mml:mrow>
          <mml:mrow>
            <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
          </mml:mrow>
          <mml:mrow>
            <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
          </mml:mrow>
          <mml:munderover>
            <mml:mrow>
              <mml:mi>∑</mml:mi>
            </mml:mrow>
            <mml:mrow>
              <mml:mi>i=1</mml:mi>
            </mml:mrow>
            <mml:mrow>
              <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
            </mml:mrow>
          </mml:munderover>
          <mml:msub>
            <mml:mrow>
              <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
            </mml:mrow>
            <mml:mrow>
              <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
            </mml:mrow>
          </mml:msub>
          <mml:mrow>
            <mml:mi>×</mml:mi>
          </mml:mrow>
          <mml:mrow>
            <mml:mi>dist</mml:mi>
          </mml:mrow>
          <mml:mrow>
            <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
          </mml:mrow>
          <mml:mrow>
            <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
          </mml:mrow>
          <mml:mrow>
            <mml:mi>¸</mml:mi>
          </mml:mrow>
          <mml:msub>
            <mml:mrow>
              <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
            </mml:mrow>
            <mml:mrow>
              <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
            </mml:mrow>
          </mml:msub>
          <mml:msup>
            <mml:mrow>
              <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
            </mml:mrow>
            <mml:mrow>
              <mml:mi>´</mml:mi>
            </mml:mrow>
          </mml:msup>
        </mml:mstyle>
      </mml:math>
    </p>
    <p>where dist(L,Vi) represents a distance function. The ultimate
goal is to use an aggregation algorithm to minimize this
objective function and find some list L* that has the smallest
total distance between itself and all of the Vi’s. In the
simplest sense, all of the ranked lists can be given the same
value of importance weight; however, a researcher may
choose to weigh lists differently for more control over the
aggregation process. For example, one might choose to give
validation indices with more relevance heavier weights
while down-weighting indices measuring similar
characteristics.</p>
    <sec id="s2a">
      <title>Software input</title>
      <p>The optCluster package extends the popular validation
package clValid [<xref rid="R04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] by producing an optimal clustering
solution based on rank aggregation of multiple validation
scores and including clustering algorithm options
appropriate for genomic count data. The main function,
optCluster, has a simple interface that only requires the user
to input a minimum of four initial arguments. These
arguments are: ‘obj’ = dataset, ‘nClust’ = number of clusters,
‘clMethods’ = clustering algorithm names, and ‘validation’ =
validation measure types. The user must provide a matrix
or data frame for the ‘obj’ argument (where the samples to
be clustered are the rows of the data) and input a range of
numbers of clusters (or a specific number of clusters) for
‘nClust’. For the other two arguments, the optCluster
package provides a variety of options for the user to select
from. These options are displayed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">table 1</xref>.</p>
      <p>The ten clustering algorithms offered by clValid for
continuous data are available for the user to input into the
‘clMethods’ argument, as well as six model-based clustering
approaches for RNA sequencing (RNA-Seq) read count
data (or any other count data). The expectation
maximization (EM) algorithm and two of its variations, the
deterministic annealing (DA) algorithm and the simulated
annealing (SA) algorithm, were proposed by [<xref rid="R05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] for
clustering RNA-Seq count data based on a mixture of either
Poisson or negative binomial distributions. Combining each
related algorithm with each discrete distribution results in
the six available options for clustering count data in this
package.</p>
      <p>There are nine possible validation measures offered by
optCluster that are categorized into three distinct types for
the ‘validation’ argument input: “internal”, “stability”, and
“biological”. Internal validation measures examine the
statistical properties of clusters while using only
information from the dataset and the created clustering
partition. Stability validation measures are specialized
internal measures that evaluate whether the cluster
assignments remain stable with respect to small
perturbations to the dataset. Biological validation measures
are external measures that assess the performance of an
algorithm to produce clusters of biologically similar genes
in an analysis of gene expression data such as microarray or
RNA-Seq data.</p>
      <p>For weighted rank aggregation, this package provides the
weighted Spearman’s footrule and the weighted Kendall’s
tau as possible distance measures, and the cross-entropy
Monte Carlo algorithm and the genetic algorithm as options
for aggregation algorithms. Details on the use of these
measures and algorithms in rank aggregation can be found
in [<xref rid="R03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. As default, optCluster assumes equal weights on
each validation measure list while using the weighted
Spearman’s footrule distance and the cross-entropy Monte
Carlo algorithm. The user may change these options with
the arguments of ‘importance’, ‘distance’, and ‘rankMethod’,
respectively. In addition to the arguments listed above, the
optCluster function has a variety of other arguments to
allow the analysis to be fine-tuned according to the user’s preferences. A complete list of these arguments is included
in the reference manual of the package.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2b">
      <title>Software output</title>
      <p>An S4 object of class “optCluster” is generated as the output
from the optCluster function. This object contains detailed
information on the created clustering partitions, calculated
validation measure scores, and optimized rank aggregation
results. In addition to obtaining the “best” clustering
partition, this package includes several methods developed
specifically for accessing the information contained within
an “optCluster” object. For viewing the results from cluster
validation, the valScores method outputs the calculated
scores for each validation measure of interest and the
optimalScores method displays the top performing
clustering algorithm and number of clusters for each
measure. The ordered lists used in rank aggregation
consisting of either clustering partitions or validation scores
are extracted with the methodRanks and scoreRanks
methods, respectively. Additionally, clustering results for a
specific algorithm are obtained with the clusterResults
method.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2c">
      <title>Comparison to similar packages</title>
      <p>There are only a handful of packages currently available in
R that offer some form of simultaneous optimization of
cluster analysis with respect to multiple validation
measures. Two packages, MOCCA [<xref rid="R07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] and NbClust [<xref rid="R08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>],
both find an appropriate number of clusters for a dataset,
but only for a limited number of clustering algorithms.
MOCCA provides a multi-objective optimization of
validation indices to determine an optimal number of
clusters based on three different clustering algorithms and
four validation measures. NbClust finds the ideal number
of clusters for either the K-means algorithm or a
hierarchical clustering algorithm by analyzing up to thirty
validity indices. A third package, COMMUNAL [<xref rid="R09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], offers
one function that evaluates up to fourteen clustering
algorithms across up to eighteen performance measures
and a second function that combines the results of selected
clustering algorithms to create a clustering partition for a
given number of clusters. This package, however, does not
generate the optimal number of clusters for the user.
Instead, it relies on the user to determine the “best” number
based on a visualization of performance measure results.</p>
      <p>The optCluster package is unique compared to these three
packages because it provides a solution (both clustering
algorithm and number of clusters) using a single function.
In addition, algorithms for clustering count data and
validation measures for evaluating clusters based on
biological gene functionality are included in this package
but not in the others.</p>
      <p>A cluster analysis was performed on a subset of RNA-Seq
count data from [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] to compare the results obtained by
optCluster to the results provided by the three similar
packages. After normalizing the data (which is available in
the optCluster package) with respect to library size, the
appropriate function in each package was run using a range
of two to four clusters and all possible validation measures
and clustering algorithms suitable for continuous data.
Hierarchical clustering using the Unweighted Pair Group
Method with Arithmetic Mean (UPGMA) and three clusters
was chosen by optCluster as the optimal clustering
algorithm and number of clusters for this normalized
dataset. The visualization produced by COMMUNAL
agreed with this result as it suggested that three clusters
was ideal, and the NbClust analysis, using either UPGMA
or K-means, also selected three clusters as the most
appropriate number. MOCCA was the only package that
provided a different result, as it determined four clusters to
be the “best”. With the continuous data, the optimal
number of clusters determined by optCluster was
consistent with two out of the three similar packages.
Interestingly, when optCluster was run on the count data,
two clusters was determined to be the ideal number with
the “best” clustering algorithm being the DA algorithm
based on the negative binomial distribution.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2d">
      <title>Caveats and future development</title>
      <p>The optCluster package is suitable for a variety of different
cluster analyses. As new clustering and validation methodology
is developed for genomic data, future developments may include
adding more options for validation measures and clustering
algorithms.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack>
    <p>This work was supported by the research
funding from NIH grant CA 170091-01A1 to Susmita Datta.</p>
  </ack>
  <fn-group>
    <fn id="FN" fn-type="other">
      <p>
        <bold>Edited by P Kangueane</bold>
      </p>
    </fn>
  </fn-group>
  <fn-group>
    <fn id="FN1" fn-type="other">
      <p><bold>Citation: </bold>Sekula <italic>et al.</italic> Bioinformation 13(3): 100-103 (2017)</p>
    </fn>
  </fn-group>
  <ref-list>
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="R01">
      <label>1</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Handl</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <source>Bioinformatics.</source>
        <year>2005</year>
        <volume>21(15):</volume>
        <fpage>3201</fpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 15914541?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15914541</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R02">
      <label>2</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
        <comment>
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.R-project.org/">http://www.R-project.org/</ext-link>
        </comment>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R03">
      <label>3</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pihur</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <source>Bioinformatics.</source>
        <year>2007</year>
        <volume>23(13):</volume>
        <fpage>1607</fpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 17483500?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17483500</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R04">
      <label>4</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Brock</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <source>J Stat Softw.</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R05">
      <label>5</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Si</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <source>Bioinformatics.</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>30(2):</volume>
        <fpage>197</fpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 24191069?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24191069</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R06">
      <label>6</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pihur</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <source>BMC Bioinformatics.</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <fpage>62</fpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 19228411?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19228411</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R07">
      <label>7</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kraus</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <source>Comput Stat.</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>26(2):</volume>
        <fpage>341</fpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R08">
      <label>8</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Charrad</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <source>J Stat Softw.</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>61</volume>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R09">
      <label>9</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sweeney</surname>
            <given-names>TE</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <source>Sci Rep.</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>5</volume>
        <fpage>16971</fpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 26581809?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26581809</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R10">
      <label>10</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Di</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <source>Stat Appl Genet Mol Biol.</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>10(1):</volume>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
<floats-group>
  <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
    <label>Table 1</label>
    <caption>
      <title>Clustering algorithm and validation measure options
offered by the optCluster package. Clustering algorithms are selected
individually and divided into two categories: continuous data and count
data. Validation measures are selected in groups and divided into three
classifications: internal, stability, and biological.</title>
    </caption>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
      <thead>
        <tr>
          <td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Clustering algorithms</td>
        </tr>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="10" colspan="1">Continuous data</td>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hierarchical</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agnes</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diana</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">K-means</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pam</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clara</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fanny</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model-based</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOM</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOTA</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="6" colspan="1">Count data</td>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EM negative binomial</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DA negative binomial</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SA negative binomial</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EM Poisson</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DA Poisson</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SA Poisson</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Validation measures</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Internal</td>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Connectivity</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dunn index</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Silhouette width</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Stability</td>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average proportion of non-overlap</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average distance</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average distance between means</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Figure of merit</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Biological</td>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biological homogeneity index</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biological stability index</td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
  </table-wrap>
</floats-group>
