<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ACS//DTD ACS Journal DTD v1.02 20061031//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName ACSJournal-v102.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.02?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName acs2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">ACS Omega</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">ACS Omega</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ao</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="coden">acsodf</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>ACS Omega</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">2470-1343</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>American Chemical Society</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6645227</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31458051</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsomega.8b01834</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group>
        <subject>Article</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>QSPR Modeling of the Refractive Index for Diverse
Polymers Using 2D Descriptors</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath1">
        <name>
          <surname>Khan</surname>
          <given-names>Pathan
Mohsin</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">†</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath2">
        <name>
          <surname>Rasulev</surname>
          <given-names>Bakhtiyor</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">‡</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="ath3">
        <name>
          <surname>Roy</surname>
          <given-names>Kunal</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="other">*</xref>
        <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">§</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>†</label>Department
of Pharmacoinformatics, <institution>National Institute
of Pharmaceutical Educational and Research (NIPER)</institution>, Chunilal Bhawan, 168, Manikata Main Road, 700054 Kolkata, <country>India</country></aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>‡</label>Department
of Coatings and Polymeric Materials, <institution>North
Dakota State University</institution>, Fargo, North Dakota 58108-6050, <country>United States</country></aff>
      <aff id="aff3"><label>§</label>Drug
Theoretics and Cheminformatics Laboratory, Division of Medicinal and
Pharmaceutical Chemistry, Department of Pharmaceutical Technology, <institution>Jadavpur University</institution>, 700032 Kolkata, <country>India</country></aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>E-mail: <email>kunalroy_in@yahoo.com</email>, <email>kunal.roy@jadavpuruniversity.in</email>.</corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>17</day>
      <month>10</month>
      <year>2018</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <day>31</day>
      <month>10</month>
      <year>2018</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>3</volume>
    <issue>10</issue>
    <fpage>13374</fpage>
    <lpage>13386</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>31</day>
        <month>07</month>
        <year>2018</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>09</month>
        <year>2018</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2018 American Chemical
Society</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2018</copyright-year>
      <copyright-holder>American Chemical
Society</copyright-holder>
      <license>
        <license-p>This is an open access article published under a Creative Commons Attribution (CC-BY) <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/page/policy/authorchoice_ccby_termsofuse.html">License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the author and source are cited.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract>
      <p content-type="toc-graphic">
        <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao-2018-018345_0007" id="ab-tgr1"/>
      </p>
      <p>In the present work, predictive quantitative
structure–property
relationship models have been developed to predict refractive indices
(RIs) of a set of 221 diverse organic polymers using theoretical two-dimensional
descriptors generated on the basis of the structures of polymers’
monomer units. Four models have been developed by applying partial
least squares (PLS) regression with a different combination of six
descriptors obtained via double cross-validation approaches. The predictive
ability and robustness of the proposed models were checked using multiple
validation strategies. Subsequently, the validated models were used
for the generation of “intelligent” consensus models
(<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://teqip.jdvu.ac.in/QSAR_Tools/DTCLab/">http://teqip.jdvu.ac.in/QSAR_Tools/DTCLab/</uri>) to improve the quality of predictions for the external data set.
The selected consensus models were used for the prediction of refractive
index values of various classes of polymers. The final selected model
was used to predict the refractive index of four small virtual libraries
of monomers recently reported. We also used a true external data set
of 98 diverse monomer units with the experimental RI values of the
corresponding polymers. The obtained models showed a good predictive
ability as evidenced from a very good external predicted variance.</p>
    </abstract>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>document-id-old-9</meta-name>
        <meta-value>ao8b01834</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>document-id-new-14</meta-name>
        <meta-value>ao-2018-018345</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>ccc-price</meta-name>
        <meta-value/>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec id="sec1">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <p>Polymers are macromolecules
made up of multiple repeating units
or monomers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref></sup> Due to the presence of multiple
repeating units, polymer molecules possess high relative molecular
mass and various associated properties. Over the past few decades,
polymers have been intensively studied due to their broad applications
in multiple fields such as petrochemical industries, oil and gas storage,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>−<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref></sup> and plastic industries that involve bags, boxes, etc. They are used
in packaging of food items, agricultural products, etc. and are also
used in the synthesis of catalysts and sensor substrates,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>−<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref></sup> in drug delivery,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref></sup> and in chromatographic
separation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref></sup></p>
    <p>Among several physical
properties, the refractive index (RI) is
an important one. The refractive index of a polymer is defined as
the velocity of light in a vacuum relative to the velocity of light
in  the polymeric material.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref></sup> It is an important optical property as it is directly associated
with additional fundamental properties such as other optical, electrical,
and magnetic properties.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref></sup> For example,
specific refractive index increment in light scattering is an essential
factor that can be used for the determination of molecular weight,
size, and shape of a polymeric molecule.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref></sup> The knowledge of refractive indices of polymers is needed for understanding
the behavior of polymers in the optical wavelength range and is extensively
used to design optical devices in the industry. Over the last decades,
high-refractive-index polymers have grabbed a considerable attention
of scientific research community due to their wide range of applications,
including advanced optoelectronic fabrications such as high-performance
substrates for advanced display devices,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref></sup> optical adhesives or encapsulants for organic light-emitting diode
devices,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> antireflective coatings for
advanced optical applications,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>−<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref></sup> immersion lithography,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref></sup> microlens components for charge-coupled devices,
complementary metal oxide semiconductor image sensors,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref></sup> optical data storage,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref></sup> lenses,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref></sup> ophthalmic applications,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref></sup> image sensors,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref></sup> optical
fibers,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref></sup> integrated optics, and optoelectronics.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref></sup></p>
    <p>Moreover, nanocomposites are related to a multiphase solid
material
made up of high-refractive-index organic polymer matrices and inorganic
nanoparticles. They can easily attain a higher refractive index value
above 1.80. These polymer nanocomposites have some demerits such as
storage instability, high optical loss, and poor processability.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref></sup> The nanoparticle content and size inversely affect the shelf life
and processability of nanocomposites, rendering them unstable and
hence unsuitable for various applications.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref></sup> Therefore, researchers are synthesizing new organic polymers with
higher refractive index values as these polymers would have various
advantages such as easy storage, transport, tunability, and processability.
In the present work, we have used an in silico method called quantitative
structure–property relationship (QSPR) to predict the refractive
indices of a diverse set of polymers.</p>
    <p>QSPR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref32">32</xref></sup> is a quantitative method providing a mathematical
relationship between different properties such as physical, chemical,
and physicochemical properties with the information encoded in the
chemical structure of molecules. A QSPR model is composed of dependent
and independent variables. In the QSPR model, the dependent variable
is estimated from the independent variables. Independent variables
are molecular descriptors computed from the chemical structure of
compounds, and the dependent variable is the endpoint of the study.
A statistically significant and robust QSPR model can be obtained
by the selection of relevant molecular descriptors and using a suitable
statistical modeling technique.</p>
    <p>In the past, several studies
were reported to predict the refractive
indices of polymers from their respective chemical structure using
different statistical methods. Several efforts have been made using
QSPR modeling to predict the refractive indices of polymers. For example,
Bicerano<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">33</xref></sup> reported a ten-descriptor model
with a good determination coefficient of <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.954 using a set of 183 polymers. Katritzky et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref></sup> predicted the refractive index of a set of 95
polymers using software called Comprehensive Descriptors for Structural
and Statistical Analysis; they developed a five-descriptor model with
a correlation of <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.940. Xu et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref34">34</xref></sup> obtained a four-descriptor QSPR model using
a set of 121 linear polymers with a correlation coefficient of <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.929 and mean relative error (MRE) of 0.87%.
Astray et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref35">35</xref></sup> generated a model for prediction
of refractive indices of diverse polymers using density functional
theory (DFT) and obtained a model with a correlation coefficient of <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.92. Yu et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref36">36</xref></sup> also used DFT to compute quantum-chemical descriptors from repeating
units of polymers and obtained a QSPR model with <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> of 0.926 and mean relative error (MRE) of 1.048%. Linear
and nonlinear QSPR models with <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.94
and 0.97, respectively, were built by Xu et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref37">37</xref></sup> using a diverse set of 120 polymers, by employing the multilinear
regression analysis and artificial neural network statistical techniques,
respectively. Duchowicz et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38">38</xref></sup> developed
a single-descriptor model using the conformation-independent approach
with a correlation coefficient of <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> =
0.96 from a set 234 polymers to predict refractive indices of polymers.
Tong et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39">39</xref></sup> developed a model using the
multiple linear regression (MLR) approach from a 121 unconjugated
polymer data set to predict the refractive indices and obtained a
good correlation coefficient of <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.91.
García-Domenech et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref40">40</xref></sup> developed
a ten-descriptor model using the topological indices with correlation
coefficient of <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.962.</p>
    <p>Most
of the previously reported models were developed using quantum-chemical
descriptors, which are computationally demanding, requiring time-consuming
and extensive computations. To overcome this problem, a two-dimensional
(2D) QSPR approach based on constitutional and topological molecular
descriptors of molecules can be applied.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref42">42</xref></sup> The developed model’s predictive ability can be improved
by excluding three-dimensional-structural feature aspects, by avoiding
the problems associated with ambiguities, resulting from an incorrect
computational geometry optimization due to the existence of molecules
in more than one conformational state. Small data sets of polymers
or homologous series of polymers were involved in model development
in many of the previous studies, leading to a small applicability
domain (AD) of the developed models. Most importantly, none of the
reported studies considers mixtures/copolymers for modeling of refractivity
of polymers.</p>
    <p>The purpose of the present work was to develop
novel QSPR models
to predict the refractive index from a set of diverse polymers including
mixtures. In this work, we have developed models using only 2D descriptors
that are effective, avoiding the computational complexity of energy
minimization, conformational analysis, and alignment problems. We
have used experimental refractive index values for a set of 221 diverse
organic polymers including mixtures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref43">43</xref></sup> for
model development. Subsequently, the validated individual models (IMs)
were used for the generation of consensus models to improve the quality
of external predictions. Finally, the selected consensus model was
used to predict the refractive indices of various classes of virtual
polymers. In this study, we have screened four small virtual libraries
of monomers previously designed by Jabeen et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref></sup> and one small library of monomers designed by current authors.
The refractive indices of novel monomers were predicted using the
newly developed consensus QSPR models.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2">
    <title>Result and Discussion</title>
    <sec id="sec2.1">
      <title>QSPR Modeling
of the Refractive Index</title>
      <p>The data set
used for the present QSPR modeling of the refractive index of a diverse
set of polymers comprises 221 data points obtained from the Scientific
Polymer Products, Inc.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref43">43</xref></sup> These polymers
consist of repeating units (monomers); due to the presence of a number
of repeating units, polymers have a large size and complex nature
as well as a higher molecular weight. Because of the large overall
structure of polymers, it is quite difficult to calculate the molecular
descriptors directly from the polymer molecules. Hence, only single
monomeric units end-capped with hydrogen were used to drive the descriptors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref45">45</xref></sup></p>
      <p>The data set of 221 diverse polymers was
split into a training set and a test set by the Kennard–Stone
method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref46">46</xref></sup> using the software tool Dataset
Division version 1.2 (<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://teqip.jdvu.ac.in/QSAR_Tools/DTCLab/">http://teqip.jdvu.ac.in/QSAR_Tools/DTCLab/</uri>). The training set consisting of 154 polymeric compounds (<italic>n</italic><sub>training</sub> = 154) was used to develop the model,
and the test set comprising 67 compounds (<italic>n</italic><sub>test</sub> = 67) was used for external validation of the model. In the current
studies, the final statistically most convincing and robust models
for a set of diverse polymers were obtained by double cross-validation
(DCV)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref47">47</xref></sup> followed by partial least squares
(PLS).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref48">48</xref></sup> We have four best models developed
using the same training set with a different combination of descriptors
to predict the refractive indices of polymers. These four PLS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref48">48</xref></sup> models were developed using three, four, three,
and three latent variables (LVs), respectively, which contained the
extracted information from the descriptors appearing in the individual
models. Each of the final four models with a different combination
of descriptors to predict refractive indices of diverse polymers contains
six descriptors, obtained from Dragon<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref49">49</xref></sup> and PaDEL-Descriptor<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref50">50</xref></sup> software, as depicted
in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">1</xref></xref>. However, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.8b01834/suppl_file/ao8b01834_si_001.pdf">Figure S1</ext-link> in the Supporting Information provides
scatter plots of four individual models obtained from observed and
predicted values of the training and test sets. The finally selected
models were satisfactory in terms of all of the internal as well as
external validation metrics including mean absolute error (MAE)-based
criteria<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref51">51</xref></sup> and Golbraikh and Tropsha’s
criteria,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref52">52</xref></sup> proving the significance of
the models. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.8b01834/suppl_file/ao8b01834_si_001.pdf">Table S1</ext-link> in the Supporting
Information lists the diverse organic polymers and their experimental
refractive values, transformed logarithmic values, and predicted refractivity
obtained from four individual models.</p>
      <table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float">
        <label>Table 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Detailed
Results of Various QSPR Modeling
Studies of the Refractive Indices for Diverse Polymers (221 Data
Points, <italic>N</italic><sub>training</sub> = 154, <italic>N</italic><sub>test</sub> = 67)</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao-2018-018345_0010" id="gr7" position="float"/>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>The obtained models possess acceptable values for
internal as well
as external validation metrics.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref32">32</xref></sup> The complete
list of values of validation parameters of all of the four DCV-PLS
models is depicted in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">1</xref></xref>, which proves reliability and statistical significance of
all of the four QSPR models.</p>
      <p>Mi stands for a mean first ionization
potential (scaled on a carbon
atom), and it belongs to the category of constitutional descriptors.
The first ionization potential is defined as the amount of energy
required to remove one valence electron from a neutral atom, and it
is an atomic property that reflects the outermost electronic configuration
and provides information on the binding energy of valence electrons
and therefore also on the degree of relativistic stabilization.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref53">53</xref></sup> This descriptor negatively contributes to the
refractive index of polymers in all of the obtained QSPR models, which
means that the higher the value of the descriptor, the lower the refractive
index and, in contrast, the lower the value of the Mi descriptor,
the higher the refractive index. We can see from the data set that
the compounds with higher values of descriptor (<bold>#6</bold>, <bold>3</bold>, <bold>17</bold>, 7, and <bold>4</bold>) showed low refractive
index (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></xref>). Molecule <bold>6</bold> (poly(tetrafluoroethylene)) has a high value of descriptor
due to the presence of fluorine atoms; fluorine has a dense electron
cloud in its valence shell since the outer shell electrons in fluorine
are closer to the nucleus, and it takes more energy to remove the
electrons from the fluorine atom, which ultimately results in the
high first ionization potential. This consequently contributed to
a low refractive index value of the corresponding polymer. On the
other hand, molecules with low values of the descriptor (<bold>#187</bold>, <bold>225</bold>, <bold>222</bold>, <bold>180</bold>, and <bold>227</bold>) showed a high refractive index.</p>
      <fig id="fig1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Contributions of Mi and
SpPosA_D/Dt descriptors to the refractive
index of diverse polymers.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao-2018-018345_0001" id="gr1" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>SpPosA_D/Dt represents the normalized spectral positive sum
from
the distance/detour matrix; it is estimated by the ratio of the sum
of the positive eigenvalues obtained from the distance/detour matrix
to the number of non-H atoms in the molecule.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref54">54</xref></sup> This descriptor showed a negative contribution to the refractive
index of polymers, and it occurs in three obtained QSPR models (<bold>1</bold>, <bold>3</bold>, and <bold>4</bold>). The negative coefficients
of the SpPosA_D/Dt descriptor suggest that an increase in the value
of descriptor would lead to a decrease in the refractive indices of
compounds and vice versa. The polymers with a comparatively high value
of descriptor (<bold>#3</bold>, <bold>4</bold>, <bold>7</bold>, <bold>29</bold>, and <bold>67</bold>) showed low refractive indices (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></xref>). In comparison,
the polymers with low values of descriptors (<bold>#186</bold>, <bold>73</bold>, <bold>207</bold>, <bold>176</bold>, and <bold>181</bold>) show high refractive index values.</p>
      <p>MLFER_E is a molecular
linear free energy relation (MLFER) descriptor,
which refers to the excessive molar refraction that characterizes
the solute’s polarizability as well as providing information
about the ability of a solute to interact with a solvent through n-
and π-electron pairs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref55">55</xref>−<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref57">57</xref></sup> In simple words, the excess molar
refraction can be defined as the difference between the solute molar
refraction and the molar refraction of an alkane with the same characteristic
volume. Equations 1–4 indicate that the MLFER_E descriptor
shows a positive contribution to the refractive index of polymers,
which means that a polymer molecule having higher values for the MLFER_E
descriptor tend to have a higher refractive index value. This is actually
observed in the data set that the molecules with high values of MLFER_E
descriptors (#<bold>224</bold>, <bold>225</bold>, <bold>222</bold>, <bold>187</bold>, and <bold>186</bold>) show high refractive index
values and the polymers with low values of the descriptor (#<bold>3</bold>, <bold>4</bold>, <bold>7</bold>, <bold>5</bold>, and <bold>8</bold>) exhibit low refractive values (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>). The low values of the descriptor occur
in the case of, for example, the presence of fluorine atoms in the
monomeric unit. Compound <bold>3</bold> (poly(pentadecafluorooctyl
acrylate)) having a low value of the descriptor due to the presence
of fluorine atoms into its structure shows a low refractive index
value because of low electronic polarizability of the carbon–fluorine
bond and the presence of greater fractional free volume in polymer
chain packing.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref58">58</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref59">59</xref></sup></p>
      <fig id="fig2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Contributions of MLFER_E and B01[O–Si]
descriptors to the
refractive index of diverse organic polymers.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao-2018-018345_0002" id="gr2" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>B01[O–Si] (presence/absence of O–Si at topological
distance 1) belongs to the class of 2D atom pair (ap) descriptors,
and it is calculated based on the distance between the pair of atoms.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref60">60</xref></sup> In the original atom pair (ap), “atom
type” includes element, number of neighbors, and number of
π electrons and the distance is measured in bonds along the
shortest path. The descriptor B01[O–Si] indicates a topological
distance between the pair of oxygen–silicon atoms of one edge,
which provides information on the distribution of atomic properties
along the topological structure. This descriptor is found in all obtained
QSPR models with negative contributions to the refractive index of
polymers, suggesting that the presence of the O–Si atom pair
at topological distance 1 (as in <bold>#19</bold>, <bold>20</bold>, <bold>29</bold>, <bold>30</bold>, and <bold>31</bold>) leads to
lower refractive index values (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>). On the other hand, high refractive index is observed
in the absence of the O–Si atom pair at a distance of one edge
(<bold>#187</bold>, <bold>186</bold>, <bold>184</bold>, <bold>227</bold>, and <bold>182</bold>).</p>
      <p>Mp is a constitutional descriptor,
which stands for mean atomic
polarizability, calculated as the mean of all atomic polarizabilities
scaled over the carbon atoms. It describes the response of electron
cloud to an external field of atom or molecules.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref61">61</xref></sup> The atoms with least electronegativity and a wider covalent
radius have the maximum average atomic polarizabilities and vice versa.
The average atomic polarizabilities of atoms decrease in the following
manner: I, Br, S, P, Cl, C, N, O, F, and H.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref62">62</xref></sup> In the obtained QSPR models <bold>1</bold> and <bold>3</bold>, the
occurrence of Mp suggests that an increase in the polarizability of
the molecules resulted in enhanced refractive index values of polymers
and a decrease in the polarizability of polymers leads to low-refractive-index
polymers. The compounds with high Mp values (<bold>#187</bold>, <bold>171</bold>, <bold>180</bold>, <bold>19</bold>, and <bold>121</bold>) showed a high refractive index, whereas the compounds with low
Mp values (<bold>#73</bold>, <bold>6</bold>, <bold>42</bold>, <bold>27</bold>, and <bold>56</bold>) showed low refractive index of polymers
(<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref></xref>). Molecule <bold>187</bold> (poly(pentabromophenyl methacrylate)) showed a high polarizability
value due to the presence of a less electronegative atom, i.e., bromine,
in the chemical structure. In contrast, molecule <bold>6</bold> (poly(tetrafluoroethylene))
showed low polarization because of the presence of a highly electronegative
atom, i.e., fluorine in its chemical structure.</p>
      <fig id="fig3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Contributions of Mp and
SpMaxA_D/Dt descriptors to the refractive
index of diverse organic polymers.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao-2018-018345_0003" id="gr3" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>B01[C–F] also belongs to the class of 2D atom pair
descriptors;
it represents presence/absence of C–F at topological distance
1.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref60">60</xref></sup> According to the QSPR eq 1, the absence
of pair of carbon and fluorine at topological distance one would lead
to an increase in the refractive index of polymers, and the presence
of C–F atom pair at topological distance one result into the
low value of refractive indices because of low electronic polarizability
of carbon–fluorine bond and presence of greater fractional
free volume in polymer chain packing. The compounds with the absence
of a pair of these atoms at the stated distance 1 (<bold>#180</bold>, <bold>225</bold>, <bold>224</bold>, <bold>186</bold>, and <bold>222</bold>) are found to be with high refractive index values than
the compounds with the presence of C–F atom pair at a distance
1 (<bold>#45</bold>, <bold>26</bold>, <bold>23</bold>, <bold>24</bold>, and <bold>28</bold>). From this observation, we can conclude that
a decrease in the polarizability leads to a decrease in the refractive
index of a polymer.</p>
      <p>SpMaxA_D/Dt belonging to the class of 2D
matrix-based descriptors
accounts for normalized leading eigenvalue from the distance/detour
matrix.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref63">63</xref></sup> The distance/detour matrix is
derived from detour and distance matrices. It is a square symmetric
matrix, whose off-diagonal entries are the ratios of the lengths of
the shortest over the longest path between any pair of vertices. These
descriptors convey the information about the molecular branching and
cyclicity of the molecules. In the current QSPR eq 2, this descriptor
was found to be negatively correlated with the refractive index of
polymers, suggesting that for lower values of the descriptor the refractive
index will be high and vice versa. For example, polymers with low
values of this descriptor (<bold>#186</bold>, <bold>176</bold>, <bold>73</bold>, <bold>100</bold>, and <bold>225</bold>) showed a high
refractive index (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref></xref>). The repeat unit of polymer molecule <bold>186</bold> (poly(<italic>N</italic>-vinyl carbazole)) contained an aromatic heterocyclic ring
(carbazole), which shows a low value of the descriptor due to the
greater longest path between the pair of vertices. On the other hand,
the polymers with high values of SpMaxA_D/Dt descriptor (<bold>#3</bold>, <bold>4</bold>, <bold>67</bold>, <bold>7</bold>, and <bold>29</bold>) showed low refractive index values. For example, the monomeric
unit of polymer molecule <bold>3</bold> (poly(pentadecafluorooctyl
acrylate)) shows a high value of the descriptor, which corresponds
to a low refractive index due to the presence of too many numbers
of branching vertex in the molecule, leading to the shorter longest
path between a pair of vertices.</p>
      <p>nCIC stands for the number
of rings (cyclomatic number), and it
belongs to a category of ring descriptors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref60">60</xref></sup> It provides a numerical value about the presence of the ring in
a molecule and is derived using the Euler formula<disp-formula id="ueq1"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao-2018-018345_m001" position="anchor"/></disp-formula>In the above equation,
μ is a cyclomatic
number and <italic>B</italic> and <italic>A</italic> are the total
numbers of bonds and atoms, respectively. Equation 2 shows that nCIC
has a negative contribution to the refractive index, suggesting that
a higher value of the descriptor leads to a higher refractive index
and vice versa. The molecules with higher descriptor values include <bold>163</bold>, <bold>217</bold>, <bold>127</bold>, and <bold>216</bold> due to the presence of a number of rings in the molecular structure,
and they showed low refractive index values. On the other hand, molecules
with low values of the descriptor (<bold>#170</bold>, <bold>220</bold>, <bold>130</bold>, <bold>129</bold>, and <bold>128</bold>) due to
the absence of ring in the molecular structure showed high refractive
index values.</p>
      <p>The SpMax_EA(bo) descriptor, an edge adjacency
indices descriptor,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref64">64</xref></sup> accounts for the
leading eigenvalue from the
edge adjacency matrix weighted by bond order, and it encodes the connectivity
between graph edges. SpMax_EA(bo) reflects the molecular shape, and
it implies the substituent position in the phenyl ring of the polymer
material; the substitution at the p- or α-position of the phenyl
or naphthalene ring has a larger value of SpMax_EA(bo), and substituents
at the o- or β-position lead to a lower value of the descriptor.
This means that substitution at the o- or β-position of the
phenyl or naphthalene ring, respectively, leads to a decrease in refractive
index values. In QSPR eq 2, this descriptor contributes positively
to the refractive index, as can be found from the data set that polymers
with high values of the SpMax_EA(bo) descriptor (#<bold>147</bold>, <bold>182</bold>, <bold>171</bold>, <bold>187</bold>, and <bold>179</bold>) have high refractive index values, in contrast to the
molecules with low descriptor values (#<bold>73</bold>, <bold>100</bold>, <bold>19</bold>, <bold>35</bold>, and <bold>125</bold>) having
low refractive index values (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref></xref>).</p>
      <fig id="fig4" position="float">
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Contributions of SpMax_EA(bo) and TI1_L descriptors to
the refractive
index of diverse organic polymers.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao-2018-018345_0004" id="gr4" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>TI1_L, described as the first Mohar index from the Laplace
matrix,
belongs to the class of 2D matrix-based descriptors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref65">65</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref66">66</xref></sup> The Laplace matrix (<italic>L</italic>) is a symmetrical matrix
estimated from the difference between the adjacency matrix and the
vertex degree matrix; therefore, the diagonal entries of the matrix
are vertex degrees of atoms in a molecule and off-diagonal entries
representing the pairs of bonded atoms are set at −1, otherwise
at 0. The first Mohar index (TI1_L) is calculated from the eigenvalues
of the Laplacian matrix as follows<disp-formula id="ueq2"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao-2018-018345_m002" position="anchor"/></disp-formula>In the above equation, QW_L is the quasi-Wiener
index and nBO and nSK are the numbers of non-H bonds and non-H atoms
in the molecules. In the currently studied QSPR model (3), the TI1_L
descriptor is inversely correlated with refractive indices of polymers,
showing that a greater value of the descriptor <bold>(#208</bold>, <bold>216</bold>, <bold>157</bold>, and <bold>14</bold>) leads to a lower-refractive-index
polymer (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref></xref>).
Compounds with lower values of the TI1_L descriptor <bold>(#187</bold>, <bold>171</bold>, <bold>180</bold>, <bold>181</bold>, and <bold>178</bold>) showed high refractive index values.</p>
      <p>Eta_betaP_A
is defined as the sum of β values of all nonhydrogen
bonds including a lone pair of electrons involved in the resonance
of a structure relative to a number of vertices in the molecule.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref67">67</xref></sup> It describes the electron-richness of molecules
relative to the molecular size and the presence of multiple bonded
electronegative atoms like O, S, etc.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref68">68</xref></sup> In the present QSPR eq 4, Eta_betaP_A has a positive coefficient.
This reflects that the Eta_betaP_A descriptor is directly proportional
to refractive indices of diverse polymers. The compounds with high
values of this descriptor (<bold>#186</bold>, <bold>222</bold>, <bold>224</bold>, <bold>225</bold>, and <bold>227</bold>) showed a high
refractive index (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref></xref>) due to the presence of lone pairs of electrons involved
in the resonance of the aromatic ring system in their chemical structure
in comparison with the compounds with low values of descriptors <bold>(#7</bold>, <bold>14</bold>, <bold>17</bold>, <bold>19</bold>, and <bold>20</bold>).</p>
      <fig id="fig5" position="float">
        <label>Figure 5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Contributions of Eta_beta_A and piPC10 descriptors to
the refractive
index of diverse organic polymers.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao-2018-018345_0005" id="gr5" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>piPC10, a topological descriptor, stands for molecular multiple
path count of order 10. It describes size, shape, symmetry, and atom
distribution in a molecule.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref69">69</xref></sup> In our QSPR
eq 4, the appearance of the piPC10 descriptor might indicate the size
of polymers, and it correlates negatively with the refractive indices
of polymers. This suggests that the polymers with high values of the
descriptor (<bold>#7</bold>, <bold>47</bold>, <bold>37</bold>, <bold>63</bold>, and <bold>29</bold>) due to the larger size of monomers
lead to low refractive indices in comparison of the compounds with
lower values of the descriptor (<bold>#184</bold>, <bold>181</bold>, <bold>180</bold>, <bold>178</bold>, and <bold>172</bold>) (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref></xref>)</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.2">
      <title>Importance
and Ranking of Variables in Different QSPR Models</title>
      <p>In the
present study, we have reported four individual QSPR models
for prediction of refractive index with a different combination of
descriptors. A repetition of some molecular descriptors in different
models simply describes their importance in terms of their contribution
to the response. Each final model has at least one or two different
descriptors not present in other models; in this way, all four models
covered all of the necessary features for QSPR model generation for
refractive index prediction. Some variables are consistently repeating
in all of the models, showing that these descriptors have impact on
the response modeled and are vital for the model development.</p>
      <p>To rank the variables based upon their importance in the obtained
QSPR models, we derived the variable importance plot (VIP) by considering
various parameters such as the classical PLS regression coefficient,
weight vector, and <italic>t</italic>-statistic cutoff threshold.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref70">70</xref></sup> The VIPs of four individual models are depicted
in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.8b01834/suppl_file/ao8b01834_si_001.pdf">Figure S2</ext-link> in the Supporting Information.
The VIP summarizes the importance of each descriptor presented in
the obtained QSPR equations based on the score and loading plot observations.
The VIP reflects the importance of descriptors in the model with respect
to the <italic>Y</italic> variable (correlation with property) and <italic>X</italic> variable (projection). A variable with a score more than
1 shows more significance than the variables with low VIP scores.
In the present work, we developed four individual QSPR models; we
can see that the variable MLFER_E has the highest impact on the response
in model 1 and Mi has the highest relative importance to the response
in models 2, 3, and 4. The least important descriptor in all of the
generated models is B01[O–Si].</p>
      <p>Next, we have derived
loading plots to find out the most influential
variables in the obtained QSPR equations. The loading plots of four
individual models are shown in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.8b01834/suppl_file/ao8b01834_si_001.pdf">Figure S3</ext-link> in the Supporting Information. The variable MLFER_E is highly influential
with a positive correlation toward the <italic>Y</italic> variable
in model 1; at the same time, the variable Mi has been found to be
the most influential variable in models 2, 3, and 4 with a negative
contribution to the refractivity of polymers. In contrast, the variable
B01[O–Si] with the least influence and with a negative correlation
with the property is found in all of the obtained models.</p>
      <p>In
addition, it was shown that the final models were not obtained
by chance (random) as evidenced from randomization plots (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.8b01834/suppl_file/ao8b01834_si_001.pdf">Figure S4</ext-link> in the Supporting Information). A number
of models are generated by shuffling the values of <italic>Y</italic> variables keeping the <italic>X</italic> variables intact. The new
(random) models were generated using the permuted data, and the quality
of such models was compared to that of the nonrandom models. Here,
we have used 100 permutations. The value of the <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup><italic><sub>Y</sub></italic> intercept should not exceed
0.3, and the value of the <italic>q</italic><sup>2</sup><italic><sub>Y</sub></italic> intercept should not exceed 0.05. The obtained models
in the current study show the intercept at <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup><italic><sub>Y</sub></italic> = −0.0157, <italic>q</italic><sup>2</sup><italic><sub>Y</sub></italic> = −0.173, <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup><italic><sub>Y</sub></italic> = −0.0205, <italic>q</italic><sup>2</sup><italic><sub>Y</sub></italic> = −0.211, <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup><italic><sub>Y</sub></italic> = −0.0171, <italic>q</italic><sup>2</sup><italic><sub>Y</sub></italic> = −0.174,
and <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup><italic><sub>Y</sub></italic> =
−0.0245, <italic>q</italic><sup>2</sup><italic><sub>Y</sub></italic> = −0.187 (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref></xref>), signifying the validity of the models. This proves
that the finally selected models were nonrandom and robust.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.3">
      <title>AD Studies
of All Individual QSPR Models for Refractive Index
Prediction</title>
      <p>The final assessments of the developed models
were done by defining the applicability domain (AD) of obtained models
using the distance to model in the <italic>X</italic>-space (DModX)
approach using SIMCA-P<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref57">57</xref></sup> software. The
compounds in the training set outside this domain were considered
as outliers, and the compounds in the test set having DModX values
greater than the threshold value are called outside AD. The list of
compounds that are outliers and outside of AD in different models
is depicted in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">Table <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">2</xref></xref>.</p>
      <table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float">
        <label>Table 2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>List of Compounds That Are Outliers
and Outside AD in Different QSPR Models</title>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0">
          <colgroup>
            <col align="left"/>
            <col align="left"/>
            <col align="left"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th style="border:none;" align="center">model no.</th>
              <th style="border:none;" align="center">training
set (outlier)</th>
              <th style="border:none;" align="center">test set (outside AD)</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">model 1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">poly(oxymethylene),
polyethylene, poly(<italic>N</italic>-vinyl carbazole), poly(pentabromophenyl methacrylate), polysulfone resin.</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left"> </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">model 2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">polysulfone resin</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left"> </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">model 3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">poly(tetrafluoroethylene), poly(methyl 3,3,3-trifluoropropyl siloxane), poly(chlorotrifluoroethylene), poly(vinylidene fluoride), poly(2-bromo-4-trifluoromethyl styrene), poly(<italic>N</italic>-vinyl carbazole), cellulose nitrate, cellulose, polysulfone
resin.</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">poly(hexafluoropropylene oxide), poly(2-vinylnaphthalene)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">model 4</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">poly(methyl hydrosiloxane), poly(dimethylsiloxane), poly(methyl octadecylsiloxane), poly(methyl hexylsiloxane), poly(methyl octylsiloxane), poly(methyl hexadecylsiloxane), poly(methyl tetradecylsiloxane), poly(acryloxypropyl methylsiloxane), poly(dicyanopropylsiloxane), poly(mercaptopropyl methylsiloxane), poly(methyl phenylsiloxane), poly(methyl <italic>m</italic>-chlorophenylethylsiloxane), poly(dimethylsiloxane-<italic>co</italic>-diphenylsiloxane)</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">poly(methyl <italic>m</italic>-chlorophenylsiloxane)</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>After analysis
of AD of the QSPR models, the coverage of models
1 and 2 was 100% in the case of the test set (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.8b01834/suppl_file/ao8b01834_si_001.pdf">Figure S5</ext-link> in the Supporting Information), but the training
set (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.8b01834/suppl_file/ao8b01834_si_001.pdf">Figure S6</ext-link> in the Supporting Information)
has five and one structural outliers, respectively, although their
prediction quality is good. In the case of model 3, the training set
has nine outliers and two compounds outside the AD in the test set
while it is found that the prediction quality of the compounds outside
AD is good. Model 4 shows that 13 compounds are outliers in the training
set (all of them belong to the class of polysilylenes, and the descriptors
obtained in the model do not cover the chemical features of this class
of compounds) and one compound is outside the AD in the test set;
however, all of these compounds have excellent prediction quality.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.4">
      <title>Intelligent Consensus Prediction (ICP) for Refractive Indices
of Polymers</title>
      <p>In this study, the data set of 221 diverse polymers
was divided into a training set (154 compounds) and a test set (67
compounds). Then, we have used the derived four models for application
of the Intelligent Consensus Predictor (<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://teqip.jdvu.ac.in/QSAR_Tools/DTCLab/">http://teqip.jdvu.ac.in/QSAR_Tools/DTCLab/</uri>) with an objective to improve the quality of predictions. We have
compared the results of predictions from individual models (IMs) with
those four consensus models (CM0–CM3). The analysis shows that
values of external validation metrics are better in consensus models,
particularly CM0, than in IM models. In addition, based upon the MAE95%
metric, three consensus models (CM0, CM1, and CM2) possess significantly
lower error values than the IM.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.5">
      <title>True External Set Predictions</title>
      <p>For QSPR modeling, in
general, the whole data set is divided into training and test sets
prior to model building; during this step, it is ensured that each
compound of the test set has a few similar structural analogues in
the training set and the test set is used to determine the predictive
capability of the developed model. However, the compounds in the true
external set are not designed to be similar to the training set compounds
and they are used as an unseen data set (not employed while modeling)
to determine the external predictive quality of the model. To validate
the predictive ability of generated individual models, we also used
a true external data set of 98 diverse monomer units with the experimental
RI values of the corresponding polymers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38">38</xref></sup><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.8b01834/suppl_file/ao8b01834_si_001.pdf">Table S2</ext-link> in the Supporting Information
lists the true external set polymers and their experimental refractive
values, transformed logarithmic values, and predicted refractivity
obtained from four CM3 models. The derived models showed good predictive
ability, as evidenced from the very good external predicted variance.
Also, the corresponding values of <italic>r</italic><sub>m</sub><sup>2</sup> metrics imply the accuracy of predictions of all of the individual
models. Furthermore, we have applied consensus models obtained from
the individual models using the Intelligent Consensus Predictor tool
(<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://teqip.jdvu.ac.in/QSAR_Tools/DTCLab/">http://teqip.jdvu.ac.in/QSAR_Tools/DTCLab/</uri>) with an objective to improve the quality of predictions. Finally,
we have compared the results of predictions from individual models
(IMs) with those from four consensus models (CM0–CM3). The
values of external validation metrics of the individual as well as
consensus models are depicted in <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="other">Table <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="other">3</xref></xref>.</p>
      <table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float">
        <label>Table 3</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Summary of External Prediction Quality
(Based on MAE<sub>100%</sub>) of Individual and Consensus Models for
the True External Data Set<xref rid="t3fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></title>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0">
          <colgroup>
            <col align="left"/>
            <col align="char" char="."/>
            <col align="char" char="."/>
            <col align="char" char="."/>
            <col align="char" char="."/>
            <col align="char" char="."/>
            <col align="char" char="."/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th style="border:none;" align="center">model no.</th>
              <th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">
                <italic>R</italic>
                <sub>pred</sub>
                <sup arrange="stack">2</sup>
              </th>
              <th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">
                <italic>R</italic>
                <sub>pred(95%)</sub>
                <sup arrange="stack">2</sup>
              </th>
              <th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">
                <italic>r</italic>
                <sub>m</sub>
                <sup arrange="stack">2</sup>
              </th>
              <th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">Δ<italic>r</italic><sub>m</sub><sup arrange="stack">2</sup></th>
              <th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">MAE<sub>100%</sub></th>
              <th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">MAE<sub>95%</sub></th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">IM1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.867</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.918</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.819</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.044</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.006</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.005</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">IM2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.884</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.936</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.831</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.022</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.006</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.005</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">IM3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.878</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.929</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.826</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.003</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.006</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.005</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">IM4</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.878</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.931</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.827</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.011</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.006</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.005</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">CM0</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.887</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.931</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.839</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.001</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.006</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.005</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">CM1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.887</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.931</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.839</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.001</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.006</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.005</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">CM2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.889</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.933</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.841</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.006</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.006</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.005</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">CM3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">
                <bold>0.895</bold>
              </td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.940</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.847</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.017</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">
                <bold>0.005</bold>
              </td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.005</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="t3fn1">
            <label>a</label>
            <p>The best model based on the MAE100%
is shown in bold.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>After
analysis of the results from four IMs (IM1–IM4) and
the corresponding four generated consensus models (CM0–CM3),
it was evident that the results of external validation metrics of
consensus models were better than those of the individual models.
Considering the external predicted variance (<italic>R</italic><sub>pred</sub><sup>2</sup>) and MAE100% metrics, consensus model 3 was
found to have considerably higher predictive ability and lower error
values than those of the other ones.</p>
      <p>After the complete analysis
of the results obtained from the true
external data set, we can conclude that prediction errors for the
external set compounds can be dropped significantly using the “intelligent”
consensus prediction models, and, particularly, CM3 appears to be
most useful and reliable among all of the developed consensus models.</p>
      <p>Additionally, the quality of predictions for external compounds
from the finally selected individual QSPR models has been checked
using the “Prediction Reliability Indicator” software
tool.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref76">76</xref></sup> This tool generates the prediction
quality composite score, and on the basis of the obtained score, it
categorizes the quality of predictions into three different classes,
that is, good (score 3), moderate (score 2), and bad predictions (score
1) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.8b01834/suppl_file/ao8b01834_si_001.pdf">Table S3</ext-link> in the Supporting Information).
The results show that most of the predictions are of good quality.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.6">
      <title>Virtual Screening of the Obtained Library of New Monomeric Units
of Polymers</title>
      <p>Four sets of small virtual libraries of monomers
designed by Jabeen et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref></sup> were screened
using the generated consensus model CM0 to predict the refractive
index of designed monomers. We have then compared the predicted refractive
indices obtained from consensus model CM0 with the predictions reported
in the previous work. The monomers of four different libraries were
sorted out on the basis of predicted refractive index values (high
to low), and top 25% compounds (24 compounds) from individual libraries
with the higher predicted refractive indices were selected for comparison
with the top 25% predicted values from the model reported by Jabeen
et al. It was found that 21 compounds (out of 24 compounds from each
set) were common in the sorted lists from both models.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.7">
      <title>Virtual Screening
of the Designed Library of New Monomeric Units
of Polymers</title>
      <p>We have also designed a virtual monomer library
of 91 compounds using the basic chemistry knowledge. The two basic
scaffolds selected for the design of library are (poly(2-vinylthiophene)
(<italic>n</italic> = 1.6376) and poly(phenyl α-bromoacrylate)
(<italic>n</italic> = 1.612). The selected core was substituted by
various functional groups (halogen, nitro, carboxy, etc.) to form
a library of novel monomers. The structure of monomers was drawn and
optimized using Marvin Sketch (version 14.10.27) (<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.chemaxon.com">https://www.chemaxon.com</uri>) software,
and, finally, the refractive index values of the designed monomer
library were predicted using the generated models.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.8">
      <title>Comparison
with a Previously Developed RI Model</title>
      <p>Next,
we compared our results with those of the previous study carried out
by Jabeen et al.,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref></sup> where authors have
reported a QSPR model for the prediction of refractive indices (<italic>n</italic>) in a diverse set of organic polymers. They developed
models by the genetic algorithm (GA)–MLR statistical technique,
which gave reliable predictions of the refractive index. To obtain
the model, they have used the data set of 133 diverse polymers and
the data set was divided randomly into a training set and a test set.
During the initial step of model development, they have marked six
molecules as outliers, which were removed. The final statistically
reliable model was developed using the set of 98 training compounds
and validated by 29 test compounds. The final model for prediction
of refractive indices had four variables obtained from Dragon software,
and the model quality was as follows: <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.932, <italic>Q</italic><sub>LOO</sub><sup>2</sup> = 0.914, and
the <italic>R</italic><sub>ext</sub><sup>2</sup> for the test set
was found to be 0.882. Also, the final selected model is used to predict
the refractive index of four small virtual libraries. Several structures
from each set of virtual libraries were reported to have high values
of predicted refractive indices.</p>
      <p>In the present study, we have
collected a larger data set and developed several models for refractive
index using the double cross-validation approach followed by PLS,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref48">48</xref></sup> from an extended list of diverse polymers offering
a broader applicability domain. The extended data set comprised 221
diverse polymers. The data set was split into a training set and a
test set using the Kennard–Stone method. The training set (<italic>N</italic><sub>train</sub> = 154) was used to develop the models,
and the test set (<italic>N</italic><sub>test</sub> = 67) was used
for external validation. The final statistically most convincing and
robust model for prediction of refractive indices was obtained by
double cross-validation (DCV) followed by PLS.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref48">48</xref></sup> The final model for diverse polymers including some mixtures
had six 2D descriptors, obtained from Dragon and PaDEL-Descriptor
software, and the model quality was as follows: <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.911, <italic>Q</italic><sub>LOO</sub><sup>2</sup> = 0.902, and <italic>R</italic><sub>pred</sub><sup>2</sup> for the
test set was found to be 0.893. We have used the final selected model
for the prediction of the refractive index of four small virtual libraries
of monomers designed by Jabeen et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref></sup> and finally compared the predictions of refractive indices from
our model with previously reported model predictions. The monomers
were sorted out on the basis of higher refractive index predictions,
and 25% of compounds (24 compounds) with the higher predicted refractive
indices (in either set) were selected for comparison. It was found
that 21 compounds (out of 24 compounds from each set) were common
in the sorted lists from both models. Furthermore, when multiple models
were used for application of the Intelligent Consensus Predictor (<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://teqip.jdvu.ac.in/QSAR_Tools/DTCLab/">http://teqip.jdvu.ac.in/QSAR_Tools/DTCLab/</uri>), the quality of external predictions was further improved.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec3">
    <title>Conclusions</title>
    <p>We developed four individual QSPR models with six different combinations
of variables using a diverse set of polymers with significant predictive
power. All of the internal as well as external validation parameters
were examined to confirm the quality, significance, robustness, and
high predictive ability. To determine the predictive ability, we have
used a true external set that shows the good predictive ability of
models. Furthermore, to improve the quality of prediction of the external
set, we have generated consensus models from the obtained multiple
models. Finally, the selected consensus model was used for screening
of a small set of virtual design libraries.</p>
    <p>From the presented
work, we have found out that a number of different
variables play an essential role to predict the refractive index of
diverse polymers. These variables encode information to predict the
refractivity of polymers. The descriptors SpMaxA_D/Dt and Eta_betaP_A
suggest that the presence of the aromatic ring in monomers increases
refractivity. The descriptor SpMax_EA(bo) implies the substituent
position in the phenyl ring of the polymer material; the substitution
at the p- or α-position of the phenyl or naphthalene ring has
a larger value of SpMax_EA(bo), and substituents at the o- or β-position
lead to a lower value of the descriptor. The Mi descriptor shows that
a higher mean ionization potential caused an increase in the refractivity
of polymers. The MLFER_E and Mp descriptors, which are polarizability-weighted,
show that the increase in the polarizability value increases the refractivity
index. Furthermore, the F01[C–F] and B01[O–Si] descriptors
confirm that the number of C–F groups and the number of O–Si
groups, respectively, would lead to a decrease in the refractivity
index of the investigated polymers. Finally, the presence of piPC10
descriptor confirms the importance of the size of monomeric units.</p>
    <p>Also, we have screened five small virtual libraries of monomers
encompassing one small library of monomers designed by us and four
designed by Jabeen et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref></sup> and then predicted
their respective refractive indices by utilizing the developed models.
Various monomers from each set of small libraries predicted higher
refractive index values as compared to those from polymers used in
the original data set. By using the approaches used in this study,
a suitable number of polymers with higher refractive index values
can be developed and transformed into the new, stable, easy-to-handle,
and processable novel polymers for different applications in materials
or optical science such as new optical devices, lenses, etc.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec4">
    <title>Materials
and Methods</title>
    <p>The data set of 221 diverse polymers was employed
for the development
of QSPR models for prediction of refractive index values. The data
set includes nine mixtures/copolymers in a particular ratio of monomers
(%). The experimental refractive index (<italic>n</italic>) values
of polymers were obtained from the Scientific Polymer Products, Inc.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref43">43</xref></sup><xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref></xref> depicts the summary of the applied methodology in the present
work.</p>
    <fig id="fig6" position="float">
      <label>Figure 6</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Work flow diagram of the used methodology.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao-2018-018345_0006" id="gr6" position="float"/>
    </fig>
    <p>After gathering experimental data and selection of the data
set,
the data were further carefully checked to remove duplicate compounds.
For ease of estimation and interpretation, the experimental refractive
index values were converted into the logarithmic scale, i.e., log(<italic>n</italic>). A lower value of log(<italic>n</italic>) represents
a lower refractive index and vice versa. The data set used is diverse,
which comprises various classes of organic polymers such as polyolefins,
polysilylenes, polyimides, polyamides, polyacrylates, and polyesters.</p>
    <sec id="sec4.1">
      <title>Chemical
Structures and Molecular Descriptors</title>
      <p>The chemical
structures of monomers or repeating units, end-capped with hydrogen,
were drawn using Marvin Sketch (version 14.10.27) (<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.chemaxon.com">https://www.chemaxon.com</uri>) software.
The structures were saved as .sdf format, which is the recommended
input format for PaDEL-Descriptor<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref50">50</xref></sup> and
Dragon<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref49">49</xref></sup> Descriptor software. We may mention
here that QSPR modeling was done in this work using 2D descriptors
that are estimated from the monomeric unit of polymers. The calculated
descriptors contained the information related to the topology of the
monomer unit. Although the monomeric unit is not capable of accounting
the overall molecular topology of polymers, it provides important
information for model building. On the other hand, use of the whole
polymer structure is difficult and a challenging job because of the
large size of polymer molecules, complex structure, and high molecular
weight; it is difficult to estimate molecular descriptors from the
entire polymer structure.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec4.2">
      <title>Calculation of Descriptors for Mixtures/Copolymers</title>
      <p>To calculate the descriptors from copolymers/mixtures, we have
used
both monomer units of copolymers individually for the estimation of
descriptors, and then the obtained descriptor values from individual
monomers were multiplied by their percentage ratio present in the
copolymers and finally added together to get the final descriptor
values for copolymers/mixtures. For example, in the case of the ethylene/vinyl
acetate copolymer (28% vinyl acetate), we have calculated the descriptors
from ethylene and vinyl acetate monomers individually; then, descriptor
values of ethylene were multiplied by 0.72 and those of vinyl acetate
with 0.28 and finally both values were added to obtain the descriptors
for the ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymer.</p>
      <p>In the present study,
to obtain the QSPR models, a wide range of molecular descriptors (2D)
were used that included 2D matrix-based descriptors, 2D atom pairs,
constitutional indices, ring descriptors, connectivity indices, functional
group count, atom-centered fragments, atom type, CATS2D descriptor,
E-state indices calculated from Dragon<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref49">49</xref></sup> software version 7, and also the extended topochemical atom and
the MLFER descriptor calculated by the PaDEL-Descriptor<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref50">50</xref></sup> (version 2.21).</p>
      <p>Tuning of the generated
initial pool of descriptors was carefully
done by removing the descriptors with constant and near-constant values
or zero values, descriptors with at least one missing value, descriptors
with all missing values, and descriptors with (absolute) pair correlation
larger than or equal to 0.90.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec4.3">
      <title>QSPR Modeling</title>
      <sec id="sec4.3.1">
        <title>Division
of the Data set</title>
        <p>The data set of 221 diverse
polymers was divided into a training set (∼70% of compounds)
and a test set (∼30% of compounds) using the Kennard–Stone
method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref46">46</xref></sup> using the software tool Dataset
Division version 1.2 available at <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://teqip.jdvu.ac.in/QSAR_Tools/DTCLab/">http://teqip.jdvu.ac.in/QSAR_Tools/DTCLab/</uri>. The training set was used for model development and the test set
for external validation. The test set compounds were not included
at all in the model development stage to select the descriptors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref68">68</xref></sup></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec4.3.2">
        <title>Variable Selection and Model Development</title>
        <p>Further descriptor
selection has been done by employing a genetic algorithm (GA)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref71">71</xref></sup> method. GA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref71">71</xref></sup> is based
on a genetic evolution principle where at the first step a random
population of models is generated, and parents are selected for mating
based upon the fitness score of the individual models. In later generations,
the parents are replaced by daughter models and the fitness of the
new model is checked; the process continues until it gets the best
set of descriptors in that run. In our work, the process was repeated
several times to find the best correlating descriptors. Finally, the
selected descriptors (35 descriptors out of an initial pool of 1730
descriptors) were subjected to the double cross-validation (DCV) tool<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref51">51</xref></sup> followed by partial least squares (PLS) regression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref48">48</xref></sup> to obtain the optimum models for the prediction of the
refractive index of polymers. The DCV tool algorithm is based on two
nested loops that are internal and external cross-validation loops.
In the outer loop, the data set is divided into training and test
sets. In the inner loop, the training set compounds used for model
development and model selection were repeatedly split into calibration
(used for model development) and validation (to estimate the error)
data sets. Finally, the model with the least prediction error was
selected from the inner loop. Then, the test set that was present
in the outer loop was used for assessing the predictive performance
of the selected models.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref51">51</xref></sup> Finally, four statistically
most convincing and robust models with different sets of descriptor
combinations were derived.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec4.3.3">
        <title>Model Validation</title>
        <p>Validation of the
obtained QSPR models
was performed by analyzing the various statistical parameters of internal
stability and the external prediction, according to the OECD principles
for QSAR validation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref72">72</xref></sup> The values of determination coefficients
indicate the goodness of fit; other internal validation parameters
of models were determined on the basis of leave-one-out (LOO) cross-validation.
The external predictive power of models was estimated using the test
set. The reported validation metrics included <italic>R</italic><sub>train</sub><sup>2</sup>, LOO-<italic>Q</italic><sup>2</sup> for the
training set, and <italic>R</italic><sub>pred</sub><sup>2</sup> for
the test set predictions. However, these parameters were primarily
based on the sum of squared differences between observed values of
the training/test set compounds and the mean observed value of the
training set compounds. Thus, to avoid bias in the predictive potential
of models, we have additionally reported <italic>r</italic><sub>m</sub><sup arrange="stack">2</sup> metrics<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref73">73</xref></sup> such as <italic>rm</italic><sub>LOO</sub><sup arrange="stack">2</sup>, Δ<italic>rm</italic><sub>LOO</sub><sup arrange="stack">2</sup>, <italic>rm</italic><sub>test</sub><sup arrange="stack">2</sup>, and Δ<italic>rm</italic><sub>test</sub><sup arrange="stack">2</sup> proposed by Roy et al. Finally, the mean absolute
error (MAE)-based criteria proposed by Roy et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref51">51</xref></sup> and Golbraikh and Tropsha<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref52">52</xref></sup> criteria
were examined to justify the robustness of reported models.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec4.3.4">
        <title>Applicability
Domain (AD) Studies</title>
        <p>To define the AD
of the generated models, we used the distance to model in the <italic>X</italic>-space (DModX) approach using SIMCA-P<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref74">74</xref></sup> software. In this case, the quality of the model has been
judged on the basis of the <italic>X</italic> residual values.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref48">48</xref></sup> In general, <italic>X</italic> residual values
are high in numbers, so the <italic>X</italic> residual was abstracted
by SD of the <italic>X</italic>-residuals of the corresponding row
of the residual matrix. The SD of <italic>X</italic>-residuals is
directly linked to the distance between each data point and the model
plane in <italic>X</italic>-space, often called DModX (distance to
the model in <italic>X</italic>-space). Molecules having the DModX
values higher than the critical value are outliers (training set)/outside
of AD (test set) of the model.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref48">48</xref></sup></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec4.3.5">
        <title>Intelligent
Consensus Refractive Indices’ QSPR Modeling
of Polymers</title>
        <p>Consensus models were generated by integrating
all validated individual models by application of the Intelligent
Consensus Predictor tool (<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://teqip.jdvu.ac.in/QSAR_Tools/DTCLab/">http://teqip.jdvu.ac.in/QSAR_Tools/DTCLab/</uri>) to improve the quality of external predictions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref75">75</xref></sup> A consensus model covers different issues such as all features
of the chemical structure of training set compounds in large descriptor
space from all of the individual models as well as a vast applicability
domain (the consensus method can also afford greater chemical space
coverage) in comparison of individual models (IMs). Consensus models
can improve the prediction quality for test set compounds in contrast
to IM. The approach of Intelligent Consensus Predictor (ICP) is based
on a similarity principle to identify the best model for the prediction
of test compounds. In this method, at the first step, 10 most similar
training compounds are selected for each test set compound. In this
way, every generated model contained 10 similar compounds for each
test set compound. Note that the selected 10 compounds should not
to be outliers in terms of chemical structure similarity. The selection
of 10 training set compounds is made on the basis of the criteria
that the Euclidean distance of the test set compound to a particular
training set compound out of those 10 selected ones is not higher
than the set threshold value. The threshold value is obtained from
the mean Euclidean distance plus 3 times standard deviation (SD) (threshold
= mean + 3 × SD), which is estimated from the Euclidean distance
scores of the entire training set compounds using descriptor values
present in the particular model. The threshold value for each test
compound might be different for different models. Finally, “<italic>n</italic>” number of qualified models were obtained with
acceptable specified criteria and can be further compared with the
predictive performance of IM. In ICP, three different ways of consensus
predictions were integrated including (1) consensus model 0 (original
consensus): average of predictions from all individual input models,
(2) consensus model 1 (CM1): average of predictions from all qualified
individual models, (3) consensus model 2 (CM2): weighted average prediction
from all qualified individual models, and (4) consensus model 3 (CM3):
best selection of predictions (compoundwise) from individual models.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref75">75</xref></sup> The finally selected consensus models were used
for the screening of the external set (and designed libraries of monomers).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec4.3.6">
        <title>Virtual Screening of a Designed Library of New Monomeric Units
of Polymers</title>
        <p>Four sets of small virtual libraries of monomers
were introduced by Jabeen et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref></sup> by selecting
a scaffold of two polymers poly(<italic>N</italic>-vinyl carbazole)
(<italic>n</italic> = 1.683) and poly(pentabromophenyl methacrylate)
(<italic>n</italic> = 1.71). The library was obtained by substitution
of different functional groups to the two primary selected cores.
The designed libraries were screened in the present work using the
generated models to predict the refractive index of designed monomers,
and predictions obtained from our models were compared to those of
Jabeen et al. In this work, we have also designed a virtual monomer
library of 91 compounds by substituting the various functional groups
on the selected fundamental core of two polymers from the data set,
i.e., (poly(2-vinylthiophene) (<italic>n</italic> = 1.6376) and poly(phenyl
α-bromoacrylate) (<italic>n</italic> = 1.612). The refractive
indices of the designed monomer library were predicted using the generated
models.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <notes id="NOTES-d7e1892-autogenerated" notes-type="si">
    <title>Supporting Information Available</title>
    <p>The Supporting Information is available
free of charge on the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org">ACS Publications
website</ext-link> at DOI: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/acsomega.8b01834">10.1021/acsomega.8b01834</ext-link>.<list id="silist" list-type="simple"><list-item><p>(<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.8b01834/suppl_file/ao8b01834_si_001.pdf">PDF</ext-link>)</p></list-item></list></p>
  </notes>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sifile1">
      <media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao8b01834_si_001.pdf">
        <caption>
          <p>ao8b01834_si_001.pdf</p>
        </caption>
      </media>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
  <notes notes-type="COI-statement" id="notes-1">
    <p>The authors
declare no competing financial interest.</p>
  </notes>
  <ack>
    <title>Acknowledgments</title>
    <p>P.M.K. would like
to thank the Ministry of Chemicals &amp;
Fertilizers, Department of Pharmaceuticals, Government of India, and
the National Institute of Pharmaceutical Education and Research-Kolkata
(NIPER-Kolkata) for providing financial assistance in the form of
a fellowship during this work. B.R. thanks National Science Foundation
for the support under NSF ND EPSCoR Award No. IIA-1355466 and the
State of North Dakota.</p>
  </ack>
  <ref-list>
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="ref1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit1"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Painter</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Fundamentals of Polymer
Science: An Introductory Text</source>; <publisher-name>Technomic
Publishing Company Inc.</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>Pennsylvania</publisher-loc>, <year>1997</year>; pp <fpage>412</fpage>–<lpage>413</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit2"><name><surname>Budd</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Selbie</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mahmood</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>McKeown</surname><given-names>N. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ghanem</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Msayib</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Book</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Walton</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><article-title>The potential
of organic polymer-based hydrogen storage materials</article-title>. <source>Phys. Chem. Chem. Phys.</source><year>2007</year>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>1802</fpage>–<lpage>1808</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/b618053a</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17415491</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit3"><name><surname>McKeown</surname><given-names>N.
B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Budd</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Book</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><article-title>Microporous polymers as potential
hydrogen storage materials</article-title>. <source>Macromol. Rapid
Commun.</source><year>2007</year>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>995</fpage>–<lpage>1002</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/marc.200700054</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit4"><name><surname>Germain</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fréchet</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Svec</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><article-title>Nanoporous polymers for hydrogen
storage</article-title>. <source>Small</source><year>2009</year>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>1098</fpage>–<lpage>1111</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/smll.200801762</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19360719</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit5"><name><surname>McKeown</surname><given-names>N. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Budd</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name><article-title>Polymers of intrinsic microporosity (PIMs): organic
materials for membrane separations, heterogeneous catalysis and hydrogen
storage</article-title>. <source>Chem. Soc. Rev.</source><year>2006</year>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>675</fpage>–<lpage>683</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/b600349d</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16862268</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit6"><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><article-title>Nanoporous
polymers: Bridging the gap between molecular and solid catalysts?</article-title>. <source>ChemCatChem</source><year>2014</year>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>1166</fpage>–<lpage>1182</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cctc.201301071</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit7"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><article-title>Tröger’s
base-functionalised organic nanoporous polymer
for heterogeneous catalysis</article-title>. <source>Chem. Commun.</source><year>2010</year>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>970</fpage>–<lpage>972</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/b920113k</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref8">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit8"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fei</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><article-title>Humidity sensing properties of LiCl-loaded porous polymers
with good stability and rapid response and recovery</article-title>. <source>Sens. Actuators, B</source><year>2014</year>, <volume>199</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.snb.2014.03.047</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref9">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit9"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kuang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fei</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><article-title>Preparation of lithium-modified
porous polymer for enhanced humidity sensitive properties</article-title>. <source>Sens. Actuators, B</source><year>2014</year>, <volume>203</volume>, <fpage>752</fpage>–<lpage>758</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.snb.2014.07.020</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref10">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit10"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Majeed</surname><given-names>M. I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><article-title>Hollow microporous
organic capsules</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2013</year>, <volume>3</volume>, <elocation-id>2128</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep02128</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23820511</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref11">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit11"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Davankov</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tsyurupa</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Hypercrosslinked Polymeric
Networks and Adsorbing Materials: Synthesis, Properties, Structure,
and Applications</source>; <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>, <year>2010</year>; Vol. <volume>56</volume>, pp <fpage>445</fpage>–<lpage>497</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref12">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit12"><name><surname>Katritzky</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sild</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Karelson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><article-title>General quantitative structure–property
relationship treatment of the refractive index of organic compounds</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Inf. Model.</source><year>1998</year>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>840</fpage>–<lpage>844</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ci980028i</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref13">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit13"><name><surname>Knoll</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><article-title>Interfaces
and thin films as seen by bound electromagnetic waves</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Phys. Chem.</source><year>1998</year>, <volume>49</volume>, <fpage>569</fpage>–<lpage>638</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.physchem.49.1.569</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15012436</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref14">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit14"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Van Krevelen</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Te Nijenhuis</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Properties
of Polymers: Their Correlation with Chemical Structure; Their Numerical
Estimation and Prediction from Additive Group Contributions</source>; <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>, <year>2009</year>; pp <fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref15">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit15"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Juni</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tsutsumi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><article-title>Enhanced coupling of
light from organic electroluminescent device using diffusive particle
dispersed high refractive index resin substrate</article-title>. <source>Opt. Rev.</source><year>2006</year>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>104</fpage>–<lpage>110</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10043-006-0104-8</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref16">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit16"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><article-title>Elastomeric polymer
light-emitting devices and displays</article-title>. <source>Nat. Photonics</source><year>2013</year>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>817</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nphoton.2013.242</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref17">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit17"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.-W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.-C.</given-names></name><article-title>Synthesis, properties, and anti-reflective
applications
of new colorless polyimide-inorganic hybrid optical materials</article-title>. <source>Compos. Sci. Technol.</source><year>2010</year>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>769</fpage>–<lpage>775</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.compscitech.2010.01.008</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref18">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit18"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><article-title>Polymer thin
films for antireflection coatings</article-title>. <source>J. Mater.
Chem. C</source><year>2013</year>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>2266</fpage>–<lpage>2285</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c2tc00529h</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref19">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit19"><name><surname>Krogman</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Druffel</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sunkara</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name><article-title>Anti-reflective
optical coatings
incorporating nanoparticles</article-title>. <source>Nanotechnology</source><year>2005</year>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>S338</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/0957-4484/16/7/005</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21727450</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref20">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit20"><name><surname>Dammel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Houlihan</surname><given-names>F. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sakamuri</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rentkiewicz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><article-title>193 nm immersion lithography-Taking the plunge</article-title>. <source>J. Photopolym. Sci. Technol.</source><year>2004</year>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>587</fpage>–<lpage>601</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2494/photopolymer.17.587</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref21">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit21"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chitnis</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Walls</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Drysdale</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cumming</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><article-title>A CMOS image sensor
integrated with plasmonic colour
filters</article-title>. <source>Plasmonics</source><year>2012</year>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>695</fpage>–<lpage>699</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11468-012-9360-6</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref22">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit22"><name><surname>Yetisen</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Montelongo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Butt</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><article-title>Rewritable three-dimensional
holographic
data storage via optical forces</article-title>. <source>Appl. Phys.
Lett.</source><year>2016</year>, <volume>109</volume>, <elocation-id>061106</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.4960710</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref23">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit23"><name><surname>Simmrock</surname><given-names>H. U.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mathy</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dominguez</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wegner</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><article-title>Polymers with
a high refractive index and low optical dispersion</article-title>. <source>Angew. Chem., Int. Ed.</source><year>1989</year>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>1122</fpage>–<lpage>1123</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.198911221</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref24">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="patent" id="cit24"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Mentak</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High Refractive
Index Polymers for Ophthalmic Applications</article-title>. <patent>US7,354,980</patent><year>2008</year>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref25">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit25"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Srdanov</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Heeger</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><article-title>Large area, full-color,
digital image sensors made
with semiconducting polymers</article-title>. <source>Synth. Met.</source><year>2000</year>, <volume>111–112</volume>, <fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>137</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0379-6779(99)00327-6</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref26">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit26"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><article-title>Low-loss polymeric
materials for passive waveguide components in fiber optical telecommunication</article-title>. <source>Opt. Eng.</source><year>2002</year>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>1631</fpage>–<lpage>1644</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1117/1.1481895</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref27">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit27"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.-g.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><article-title>High refractive index
polymers: fundamental research and practical
applications</article-title>. <source>J. Mater. Chem.</source><year>2009</year>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>8907</fpage>–<lpage>8919</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/b909690f</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref28">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit28"><name><surname>Macdonald</surname><given-names>E. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shaver</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name><article-title>Intrinsic high refractive index polymers</article-title>. <source>Polym. Int.</source><year>2015</year>, <volume>64</volume>, <fpage>6</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pi.4821</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref29">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit29"><name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>I.-Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Baek</surname><given-names>J.-B.</given-names></name><article-title>Nanocomposites derived
from polymers and inorganic
nanoparticles</article-title>. <source>Materials</source><year>2010</year>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>3654</fpage>–<lpage>3674</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ma3063654</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref30">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit30"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Toprak</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Muhammed</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><article-title>Nanocomposites
of polymer and inorganic nanoparticles for optical and magnetic applications</article-title>. <source>Nano Rev.</source><year>2010</year>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>5214</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3402/nano.v1i0.5214</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref31">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit31"><name><surname>Dearden</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><article-title>The history
and development of quantitative structure-activity relationships (QSARs)</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Quant. Struct.–Prop. Relat.</source><year>2016</year>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4018/IJQSPR.2016010101</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref32">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit32"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>R. N.</given-names></name></person-group><source>A Primer on QSAR/QSPR
Modeling: Fundamental
Concepts</source>; <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>, <year>2015</year>; pp <fpage>24</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref33">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit33"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Bicerano</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Prediction of Polymer
Properties</source>; <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>, <year>2002</year>; pp <fpage>321</fpage>–<lpage>340</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref34">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit34"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><article-title>Prediction of refractive
indices of linear polymers by a four-descriptor QSPR model</article-title>. <source>Polymer</source><year>2004</year>, <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>8651</fpage>–<lpage>8659</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.polymer.2004.10.057</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref35">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit35"><name><surname>Astray</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cid</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Moldes</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ferreiro-Lage</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gálvez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mejuto</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><article-title>Prediction of refractive
index of polymers using artificial
neural networks</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Eng. Data</source><year>2010</year>, <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>5388</fpage>–<lpage>5393</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/je100885f</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref36">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit36"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><article-title>Prediction of refractive index of vinyl polymers by
using density functional theory</article-title>. <source>J. Comput.
Chem.</source><year>2007</year>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>2336</fpage>–<lpage>2341</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcc.20752</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17476666</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref37">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit37"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><article-title>Linear and nonlinear QSPR models
to predict refractive indices of
polymers from cyclic dimer structures</article-title>. <source>Chemom.
Intell. Lab. Syst.</source><year>2008</year>, <volume>92</volume>, <fpage>152</fpage>–<lpage>156</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemolab.2008.02.006</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref38">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit38"><name><surname>Duchowicz</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fioressi</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bacelo</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Saavedra</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Toropova</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Toropov</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><article-title>QSPR studies on
refractive indices of structurally
heterogeneous polymers</article-title>. <source>Chemom. Intell. Lab.
Syst.</source><year>2015</year>, <volume>140</volume>, <fpage>86</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemolab.2014.11.008</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref39">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit39"><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>J.-b.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X.-m.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>F.-l.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>J.-w.</given-names></name><article-title>QSPR Study
on Part of the Refractive Index of the Polymer</article-title>. <source>J. Shaanxi Univ. Sci. Technol. (Nat. Sci. Ed.)</source><year>2012</year>, <volume>5</volume>, <elocation-id>014</elocation-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref40">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit40"><name><surname>García-Domenech</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>de Julián-Ortiz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><article-title>Prediction of indices of refraction
and glass transition temperatures of linear polymers by using graph
theoretical indices</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Chem. B</source><year>2002</year>, <volume>106</volume>, <fpage>1501</fpage>–<lpage>1507</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jp012360u</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref41">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit41"><name><surname>Duchowicz</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Comelli</surname><given-names>N. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>E. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name><article-title>QSAR study for carcinogenicity
in a large set of organic compounds</article-title>. <source>Curr. Drug
Saf.</source><year>2012</year>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>282</fpage>–<lpage>288</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/157488612804096623</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23062240</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref42">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit42"><name><surname>Talevi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bellera</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Di Ianni</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Duchowicz</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bruno-Blanch</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name><article-title>An integrated drug
development approach
applying topological descriptors</article-title>. <source>Curr. Comput.
Aided Drug Des.</source><year>2012</year>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>172</fpage>–<lpage>181</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/157340912801619076</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22734704</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref43">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="weblink" id="cit43"><collab>Scientific Polymer Products, Inc.</collab><year>2018</year>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://scientificpolymer.com/technical-library/refractive-index-of-polymers-by-index/">http://scientificpolymer.com/technical-library/refractive-index-of-polymers-by-index/</uri> (accessed on April 2018).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref44">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit44"><name><surname>Jabeen</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rasulev</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ossowski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Boudjouk</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><article-title>Refractive
indices of diverse data set of polymers: A computational QSPR based
study</article-title>. <source>Comput. Mater. Sci.</source><year>2017</year>, <volume>137</volume>, <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.commatsci.2017.05.022</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref45">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit45"><name><surname>Katritzky</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kuanar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Slavov</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Karelson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dobchev</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><article-title>Quantitative
correlation of physical
and chemical properties with chemical structure: utility for prediction</article-title>. <source>Chem. Rev.</source><year>2010</year>, <volume>110</volume>, <fpage>5714</fpage>–<lpage>5789</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/cr900238d</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20731377</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref46">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit46"><name><surname>Kennard</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name><article-title>Computer aided design
of experiments</article-title>. <source>Technometrics</source><year>1969</year>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>148</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00401706.1969.10490666</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref47">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit47"><name><surname>Baumann</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Baumann</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><article-title>Reliable estimation
of prediction errors for QSAR models
under model uncertainty using double cross-validation</article-title>. <source>J. Cheminf.</source><year>2014</year>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>47</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13321-014-0047-1</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref48">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit48"><name><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sjöström</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><article-title>PLS-regression: a basic
tool of chemometrics</article-title>. <source>Chemom. Intell. Lab. Syst.</source><year>2001</year>, <volume>58</volume>, <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>130</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0169-7439(01)00155-1</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref49">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit49"><name><surname>Mauri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Consonni</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pavan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Todeschini</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><article-title>Dragon software:
An easy approach to molecular descriptor calculations</article-title>. <source>MATCH Commun. Math. Comput. Chem.</source><year>2006</year>, <volume>56</volume>, <fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>248</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref50">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit50"><name><surname>Yap</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name><article-title>PaDEL-descriptor:
An open source software to calculate molecular descriptors and fingerprints</article-title>. <source>J. Comput. Chem.</source><year>2011</year>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>1466</fpage>–<lpage>1474</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcc.21707</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21425294</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref51">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit51"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>R. N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ambure</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Aher</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name><article-title>Be aware of error
measures. Further studies on validation of predictive QSAR models</article-title>. <source>Chemom. Intell. Lab. Syst.</source><year>2016</year>, <volume>152</volume>, <fpage>18</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemolab.2016.01.008</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref52">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit52"><name><surname>Golbraikh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tropsha</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><article-title>Beware of q2!</article-title>. <source>J. Mol. Graphics
Modell.</source><year>2002</year>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>269</fpage>–<lpage>276</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1093-3263(01)00123-1</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref53">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit53"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Asai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Borschevsky</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Stora</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kaneya</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tsukada</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Düllmann</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Eberhardt</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Eliav</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; et al. <article-title>Measurement
of the first
ionization potential of lawrencium, element 103</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><year>2015</year>, <volume>520</volume>, <fpage>209</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature14342</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25855457</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref54">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit54"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><article-title>Development
of predictive models for predicting binding affinity of endocrine
disrupting chemicals to fish sex hormone-binding globulin</article-title>. <source>Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf.</source><year>2017</year>, <volume>136</volume>, <fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2016.10.032</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27816713</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref55">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit55"><name><surname>Platts</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Butina</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hersey</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><article-title>Estimation
of molecular
linear free energy relation descriptors using a group contribution
approach</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Inf. Model.</source><year>1999</year>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>835</fpage>–<lpage>845</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ci980339t</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref56">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit56"><name><surname>Antanasijević</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Antanasijević</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pocajt</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Trišović</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fodor-Csorba</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><article-title>A QSPR study on the liquid crystallinity of five-ring
bent-core molecules using decision trees, MARS and artificial neural
networks</article-title>. <source>RSC Adv.</source><year>2016</year>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>18452</fpage>–<lpage>18464</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C5RA20775D</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref57">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit57"><name><surname>Basant</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><article-title>Modeling uptake of nanoparticles in multiple human cells using structure–activity
relationships and intercellular uptake correlations</article-title>. <source>Nanotoxicology</source><year>2017</year>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>20</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17435390.2016.1257075</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27809641</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref58">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit58"><name><surname>Hougham</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tesoro</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Viehbeck</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><article-title>Influence
of free volume change on
the relative permittivity and refractive index in fluoropolyimides</article-title>. <source>Macromolecules</source><year>1996</year>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>3453</fpage>–<lpage>3456</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ma9503423</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref59">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit59"><name><surname>Hougham</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tesoro</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Viehbeck</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chapple-Sokol</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><article-title>Polarization
effects of fluorine on the relative permittivity in polyimides</article-title>. <source>Macromolecules</source><year>1994</year>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>5964</fpage>–<lpage>5971</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ma00099a006</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref60">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit60"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Todeschini</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Consonni</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Handbook
of Molecular Descriptors</source>; <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp;
Sons</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year>; Vol. <volume>11</volume>, p <fpage>91</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref61">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit61"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>X.-Q.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><article-title>Fast approaches for
molecular polarizability calculations</article-title>. <source>J. Phys.
Chem. A</source><year>2007</year>, <volume>111</volume>, <fpage>4443</fpage>–<lpage>4448</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jp068423w</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17461556</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref62">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit62"><name><surname>Bosque</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sales</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><article-title>Polarizabilities of
solvents from the chemical composition</article-title>. <source>J. Chem.
Inf. Model.</source><year>2002</year>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>1154</fpage>–<lpage>1163</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ci025528x</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref63">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit63"><name><surname>Randić</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><article-title>On characterization
of cyclic structures</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Inf. Model.</source><year>1997</year>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>1063</fpage>–<lpage>1071</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ci9702407</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref64">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit64"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><article-title>A quantitative relationship between Tgs and chain segment structures
of polystyrenes</article-title>. <source>Polímeros</source><year>2017</year>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0104-1428.00916</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref65">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit65"><name><surname>Mohar</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Babic</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Trinajstic</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><article-title>A novel definition of the Wiener
index for trees</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Inf. Model.</source><year>1993</year>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>154</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ci00011a023</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref66">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit66"><name><surname>Trinajstic</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Babic</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nikolic</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Plavsic</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Amic</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mihalic</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><article-title>The Laplacian matrix in chemistry</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Inf. Model.</source><year>1994</year>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>368</fpage>–<lpage>376</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ci00018a023</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref67">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit67"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Quantitative Structure-Activity
Relationships in Drug Design, Predictive Toxicology, and Risk Assessment</source>; <publisher-name>IGI Global</publisher-name>, <year>2015</year>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref68">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit68"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>R. N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><article-title>Predictive modeling studies for the
ecotoxicity of ionic liquids
towards the green algae Scenedesmus vacuolatus</article-title>. <source>Chemosphere</source><year>2014</year>, <volume>104</volume>, <fpage>170</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2013.11.002</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24296027</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref69">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit69"><name><surname>Farkas</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zenkevich</surname><given-names>I. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Stout</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kalivas</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Héberger</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><article-title>Prediction
of retention indices for identification of fatty acid methyl esters</article-title>. <source>J. Chromatogr. A</source><year>2008</year>, <volume>1198–1199</volume>, <fpage>188</fpage>–<lpage>195</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chroma.2008.05.019</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref70">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit70"><name><surname>Akarachantachote</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chadcham</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Saithanu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><article-title>Cutoff threshold
of variable importance
in projection for variable selection</article-title>. <source>Int. J.
Pure Appl. Math.</source><year>2014</year>, <volume>94</volume>, <fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>322</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12732/ijpam.v94i3.2</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref71">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit71"><name><surname>Ambure</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Aher</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gajewicz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Puzyn</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><article-title>“NanoBRIDGES”
software: Open access tools to perform QSAR and nano-QSAR modeling</article-title>. <source>Chemom. Intell. Lab. Syst.</source><year>2015</year>, <volume>147</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemolab.2015.07.007</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref72">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit72"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><collab>OECD</collab></person-group>. <source>OECD Principles for the Validation, for
Regulatory Purposes,
of (Quantitative) Structure–Activity Relationship Models</source>; <publisher-name>Organisation for Economic-Operation and Development</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>, <year>2004</year>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref73">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit73"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ojha</surname><given-names>P. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>R. N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kabir</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><article-title>Introduction of rm2 (rank) metric incorporating rank-order predictions
as an additional tool for validation of QSAR/QSPR models</article-title>. <source>Chemom. Intell. Lab. Syst.</source><year>2012</year>, <volume>118</volume>, <fpage>200</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemolab.2012.06.004</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref74">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="weblink" id="cit74"><source>SIMCA-P</source>, version 10.0; <publisher-name>Umetrics</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>Umea, Sweden</publisher-loc>, <year>2002</year>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://info@umetrics.com">info@umetrics.com</uri>, <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.umetrics.com">www.umetrics.com</uri>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref75">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit75"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ambure</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ojha</surname><given-names>P. K.</given-names></name><article-title>Is it possible to
improve the quality of predictions from an “intelligent”
use of multiple QSAR/QSPR/QSTR models?</article-title>. <source>J. Chemom.</source><year>2018</year>, <elocation-id>e2992</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cem.2992</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref76">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit76"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ambure</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><article-title>How Precise Are Our Quantitative
Structure–Activity Relationship Derived Predictions for New
Query Chemicals?</article-title>. <source>ACS Omega</source><year>2018</year>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>11392</fpage>–<lpage>11406</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsomega.8b01647</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31459245</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
