<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>BMC Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1471-2105</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6006580</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2220</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-018-2220-4</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Research Article</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>Predicting drug-disease associations by using similarity constrained matrix factorization</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <name>
          <surname>Zhang</surname>
          <given-names>Wen</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>zhangwen@whu.edu.cn</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Yue</surname>
          <given-names>Xiang</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>tommy96@whu.edu.cn</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Lin</surname>
          <given-names>Weiran</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>waynelin@whu.edu.cn</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Wu</surname>
          <given-names>Wenjian</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>westonwu@whu.edu.cn</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Liu</surname>
          <given-names>Ruoqi</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>ruoqiliu1996@whu.edu.cn</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Huang</surname>
          <given-names>Feng</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>fhuang@whu.edu.cn</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <name>
          <surname>Liu</surname>
          <given-names>Feng</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>fliuwhu@whu.edu.cn</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2331 6153</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.49470.3e</institution-id><institution>School of Computer Science, </institution><institution>Wuhan University, </institution></institution-wrap>Wuhan, 430072 China </aff>
      <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2331 6153</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.49470.3e</institution-id><institution>School of Electronic Information, </institution><institution>Wuhan University, </institution></institution-wrap>Wuhan, 430072 China </aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>19</day>
      <month>6</month>
      <year>2018</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>19</day>
      <month>6</month>
      <year>2018</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <year>2018</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>19</volume>
    <elocation-id>233</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>11</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2017</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2018</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s). 2018</copyright-statement>
      <license license-type="OpenAccess">
        <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract id="Abs1">
      <sec>
        <title>Background</title>
        <p id="Par1">Drug-disease associations provide important information for the drug discovery. Wet experiments that identify drug-disease associations are time-consuming and expensive. However, many drug-disease associations are still unobserved or unknown. The development of computational methods for predicting unobserved drug-disease associations is an important and urgent task.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Results</title>
        <p id="Par2">In this paper, we proposed a <bold>s</bold>imilarity <bold>c</bold>onstrained <bold>m</bold>atrix <bold>f</bold>actorization method for the <bold>d</bold>rug-<bold>d</bold>isease association prediction (SCMFDD), which makes use of known drug-disease associations, drug features and disease semantic information. SCMFDD projects the drug-disease association relationship into two low-rank spaces, which uncover latent features for drugs and diseases, and then introduces drug feature-based similarities and disease semantic similarity as constraints for drugs and diseases in low-rank spaces. Different from the classic matrix factorization technique, SCMFDD takes the biological context of the problem into account. In computational experiments, the proposed method can produce high-accuracy performances on benchmark datasets, and outperform existing state-of-the-art prediction methods when evaluated by five-fold cross validation and independent testing.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <p id="Par3">We developed a user-friendly web server by using known associations collected from the CTD database, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bioinfotech.cn/SCMFDD">http://www.bioinfotech.cn/SCMFDD/</ext-link>. The case studies show that the server can find out novel associations, which are not included in the CTD database.</p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
      <title>Keywords</title>
      <kwd>Drug-disease associations</kwd>
      <kwd>Similarity constrained matrix factorization</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group>
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id>
            <institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>61772381</award-id>
        <award-id>61572368</award-id>
        <principal-award-recipient>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Wen</given-names>
          </name>
        </principal-award-recipient>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group>
        <funding-source>
          <institution>Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities</institution>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>2042017kf0219</award-id>
        <principal-award-recipient>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Wen</given-names>
          </name>
        </principal-award-recipient>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
        <meta-value>© The Author(s) 2018</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec id="Sec1">
    <title>Background</title>
    <p id="Par7">A drug is a chemical that treats, cures, prevents, or diagnoses diseases. The drug design has three stages: discovery stage, preclinical stage and clinical development stage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], and the development of a new drug take 15 years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] and cost 800 million dollars [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p>
    <p id="Par8">The drug-disease associations refer to the events that drugs exert effects on diseases, which can be classified into two types: drug indications and drug side-effects. Some drugs could have a therapeutic role in a disease, e.g. a drug treats leukemia &amp; lymphoma; other drugs could play a role in the etiology of a disease, e.g. exposure to a drug causes lung cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Drug-disease associations reveal the close relations between drugs and diseases, and have gained great attention. Computational methods can screen possible drug-disease associations, and complement or guide laborious and costly wet experiments.</p>
    <p id="Par9">In recent years, a great number of computational methods have been proposed to predict drug-disease associations. As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, existing methods are roughly classified as two types. One type of methods makes use of biological elements shared by drugs and diseases to predict drug-disease associations. Eichborn J et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] studied drug-disease relations based on drug side effects. Wang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] and Wiegers et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] considered drug-gene-disease relations. Yu et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] used common protein complexes related to drugs and diseases. These methods have to use elements shared by drugs and diseases, but many drugs and diseases do not share any elements, and these methods fail to work in this case. The other type of methods predicts novel drug-disease associations by using known drug-disease associations, drug features and disease features. Gottlieb et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] constructed a universal predictor named PREDICT for drug repositioning to express drug-disease associations in a large-scale manner that integrated molecular structure, molecular activity and disease semantic data. Yang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] built Naive Bayes models to predict indications for diseases based on their side effects. Wang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] proposed the method “PreDR” that trained a support vector machine (SVM) model based on drug structures, drug target proteins, and drug side effects. Huang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] combined three different networks of drugs, genomic and disease phenotypes to build a heterogeneous network to predict drug-disease associations. Oh et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] proposed scoring methods to obtain quantified scores as features between drugs and diseases, and built classifiers based on the extracted features to predict novel drug-disease associations. Wang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] proposed a three-layer heterogeneous network model (TL-HGBI), and applied the approach on drug repositioning by using existing omics data of diseases, drugs and drug targets. Martínez et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>] built a network of interconnected drugs, proteins and diseases to identify their relations. Wang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>] adopted recommendation systems to predict drug-disease relations. Moghadam et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] combined drug features and disease features by using kernel fusion, and then built SVM-based prediction model. Liang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] proposed a Laplacian regularized sparse subspace learning method (LRSSL), which integrated drug chemical information, drug target domain information and target annotation information.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Two types of drug-disease association prediction methods. <bold>a</bold> Infer drug-disease associations without known associations; <bold>b</bold> Infer unobserved drug-disease associations based on known associations</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
    <p id="Par10">A great number of drug-disease associations have been identified and stored in databases. However, many associations remain unobserved and need to be discovered. In this paper, we proposed a <bold>s</bold>imilarity <bold>c</bold>onstrained <bold>m</bold>atrix <bold>f</bold>actorization method for the <bold>d</bold>rug-<bold>d</bold>isease association prediction (SCMFDD), which makes use of known drug-disease associations, drug features and disease semantic information. SCMFDD projects the drug-disease association relationship into two low-rank spaces, which uncover latent features for drugs and diseases, and then introduces drug feature-based similarity and disease semantic similarity as constraints for drugs and diseases in low-rank spaces. Different from the classic matrix factorization technique, SCMFDD can take the biological context of the problem into account. Computational experiments show that SCMFDD can produce high-accuracy performances on benchmark datasets and outperform existing state-of-the-art prediction methods, i.e. PREDICT, TL-HGBI and LRSSL when evaluated by five-fold cross validation and independent testing on the same datasets. Moreover, a web server is constructed on known associations collected from the CTD database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], and case studies show that the web server can help to find out novel associations.</p>
    <p id="Par11">The main contributions of this paper include: 1) we proposed a novel matrix factorization approach (SCMFDD), which is different from the traditional matrix factorization methods. SCMFDD incorporates drug features and disease semantic information into the matrix factorization frame; 2) an efficient optimization algorithm is developed to obtain the solution of SCMFDD; 3) we developed a user-friendly web server to facilitate the drug-disease association prediction, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bioinfotech.cn/SCMFDD">http://www.bioinfotech.cn/SCMFDD/</ext-link>.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec2">
    <title>Methods</title>
    <sec id="Sec3">
      <title>Datasets</title>
      <p id="Par12">CTD database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] is a publicly available database that intends to advance understanding about how environmental exposures affect human health. CTD database provides curated and inferred chemical-disease associations. The curated associations are real associations extracted from literature. Several databases describe features for drugs and diseases. PubChem Compound database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] provides drug substructures. DrugBank database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] is a comprehensive resource for drug targets, drug enzymes and drug-drug interactions. KEGG DRUG database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] provides pathway information for approved drugs in Japan, USA and Europe. U.S. National Library of Medicine stores disease MeSH descriptors, which reflect the hierarchy of diseases.</p>
      <p id="Par13">We downloaded real drug-disease associations from CTD database, and collected features for drugs and diseases to compile our datasets. In order to avoid sparsity of drug-disease associations, we selected drugs that are associated with more than 10 diseases, and also selected diseases that are associated with more than 10 drugs. Moreover, we collected drug features: substructures, targets, enzymes, pathways and drug-drug interactions as well as disease MeSH descriptors. Thus, we compiled a dataset named “SCMFDD-S”, which contains 18,416 associations between 269 drugs and 598 diseases. Further, we selected drugs associated with at least one disease as well as diseases associated with at least one drug, and collected drug substructures and disease MeSH descriptors. Thus, we compiled a larger dataset named “SCMFDD-L”, which contains 49,217 associations between 1323 drugs and 2834 diseases. Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> summarizes the datasets “SCMFDD-S” and “SCMFDD-L”.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The summary of SCMFDD-S dataset and SCMFDD-L dataset</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Dataset</th><th rowspan="2">Drugs</th><th rowspan="2">Diseases</th><th rowspan="2">Associations</th><th rowspan="2">Richness</th><th colspan="5">Drug features</th></tr><tr><th>Substructure</th><th>Target</th><th>Enzyme</th><th>Pathway</th><th>Drug Interactions</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>SCMFDD-S</td><td>269</td><td>598</td><td>18,416</td><td>11.4%</td><td>881</td><td>623</td><td>247</td><td>465</td><td>2086</td></tr><tr><td>SCMFDD-L</td><td>1323</td><td>2834</td><td>49,217</td><td>1.31%</td><td>881</td><td>N.A.</td><td>N.A.</td><td>N.A.</td><td>N.A.</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Numbers for drug features represent the numbers of descriptors. For example, the PubChem Compound defines 881 types of substructure descriptors for compound substructures, and a drug has some substructures and is thus described by a subset of substructure descriptors. Richness is the ratio of association number vs drug-disease pair number. N.A. indicates that the information is not available</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p id="Par14">Several benchmark datasets were used in the drug-disease association prediction. Gottlieb et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] compiled a dataset with 1933 associations between 593 drugs in DrugBank and 313 diseases in OMIM, and used it for the method “PREDICT”. This dataset contains five types of drug-drug similarities and two types of disease-disease similarities. Three drug-drug similarities are calculated based on drug-related genes, by using Smith-Waterman sequence alignment score [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], all-pairs shortest paths algorithm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] and semantic similarity scores [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] respectively; other two drug-drug similarities are drug structure-based Tanimoto similarity and drug side effect-based Jaccard similarity. Two disease-disease similarity measures are semantic similarity and genetic similarity. Wang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] compiled a dataset with 1461 interactions between 1409 drugs in DrugBank database and 5080 diseases in OMIM database, and used it for the method “TL-HGBI”. The dataset also contains the drug-drug structure similarity and disease semantic similarity. Liang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] obtained 3051 associations between 763 drugs and 681 diseases from the study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], and collected drug substructures, protein domains of target proteins, gene ontology terms of target proteins to calculate three types of drug-drug similarities as well as the disease-disease semantic similarity. The dataset was used for the method “LRSSL”. We name these datasets as “PREDICT dataset”, “TL-HGBI dataset” and “LRSSL datasets”.</p>
      <p id="Par15">Therefore, we adopt SCMFDD-S dataset, SCMFDD-L dataset, PREDICT dataset, TL-HGBI dataset and LRSSL datasets as benchmark datasets.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4">
      <title>Similarity constrained matrix factorization method</title>
      <p id="Par16">The aim of this study is to predict unobserved drug-disease associations by using drug features, disease semantic information and known associations. Figure <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> illustrates the basic idea of the similarity constrained matrix factorization method for the drug-disease association prediction (SCMFDD).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>The basic idea of similarity constrained matrix factorization</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>Drug-drug similarities</title>
        <p id="Par17">Actually, a feature is a set of descriptors. A drug has a subset of descriptors, and thus is represented as a bit vector, whose dimensions indicate the presence or absence of corresponding descriptors with the value 1 or 0. Let <italic>P</italic> and <italic>Q</italic> denote feature vectors of two drugs, we can calculate the Jaccard similarity between two drugs by using,<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \mathrm{J}\left(\mathrm{P},\mathrm{Q}\right)=\frac{\mid \mathrm{P}\cap \mathrm{Q}\mid }{\mid \mathrm{P}\cup \mathrm{Q}\mid } $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">J</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=","><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Q</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mo>∩</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Q</mml:mi><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mo>∪</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Q</mml:mi><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where P ∩ Q∣ is the number of bits where <italic>P</italic> and <italic>Q</italic> both have the value 1, and P ∪ Q∣ is the number of bits where either <italic>P</italic> and <italic>Q</italic> has the value 1.</p>
        <p id="Par18">When we have different features of a drug, i.e. substructures, targets, enzymes, pathways and drug-drug interactions, we can represent them as feature vectors in different feature spaces, and calculate different types of drug-drug similarities.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec6">
        <title>Disease-disease semantic similarity</title>
        <p id="Par19">MeSH is the National Library of Medicine’s controlled vocabulary thesaurus, and MeSH provides hierarchical descriptors for diseases. As described in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], we can calculate disease-disease semantic similarity by using MeSH information.</p>
        <p id="Par20">For each disease, a directed acyclic graph (<italic>DAG</italic>) is constructed based on hierarchical descriptors, in which nodes represent disease MeSH descriptors (or disease terms) and the edges represent the relationship between the current node and its ancestors. For the disease <italic>A</italic>, the <italic>DAG</italic> is denoted as <italic>DAG</italic>(<italic>A</italic>) = (<italic>N</italic>(<italic>A</italic>), <italic>E</italic>(<italic>E</italic>)), where <italic>N</italic>(<italic>A</italic>) is the set of all ancestors of <italic>A</italic> (including itself) and <italic>E</italic>(<italic>A</italic>) is the set of their corresponding links.</p>
        <p id="Par21">We define the contribution of a node <italic>d d</italic> in <italic>DAG</italic>(<italic>A</italic>) to the semantic value of disease <italic>A</italic>:<disp-formula id="Equb"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {C}_A(d)=\left\{\begin{array}{c}1\kern16.75em if\ d=A\\ {}\mathit{\max}\left\{\Delta  \ast {C}_A\left({d}^{\prime}\right)|{d}^{\prime}\in children\ of\ \left.d\right\}\kern0.5em if\ d\ne A\right.\end{array}\right. $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="" open="{"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mspace width="16.25em"/><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">if</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:mo mathvariant="italic">max</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="" open="{" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∆</mml:mi><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:msup><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">children of</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mfenced close="}" open=""><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">if</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>≠</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mfenced></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Article_Equb.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>∆</italic> is the semantic contribution factor, and we set <italic>∆</italic> = 0.5 in the study.</p>
        <p id="Par22">The semantic value of disease <italic>A</italic> is defined as,<disp-formula id="Equc"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ DV(A)=\sum \limits_{d\in N(A)}{C}_A(d) $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6" display="block"><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">DV</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Article_Equc.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
        <p id="Par23">The semantic similarity between two diseases <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic> is calculated by,<disp-formula id="Equd"><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {S}_{A,B}=\frac{\sum_{d\in N\left(\mathrm{A}\right)\cap N(B)}\left({C}_A(d)+{C}_B(d)\right)}{DV(A)+ DV(B)} $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>∩</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">DV</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">DV</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Article_Equd.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec7">
        <title>Objective Function</title>
        <p id="Par24">The observed drug-disease associations can be formulated as a bipartite network, and represented by a binary matrix <italic>A</italic> ∈ <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>n</italic> × <italic>m</italic></sup>, where <italic>n</italic> is the number of drugs and <italic>m</italic> is the number of diseases. <italic>a</italic><sub><italic>ij</italic></sub> is the (<italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic>)th entry of <italic>A</italic>. If the vertex (drug) <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and the vertex (disease) <italic>dis</italic><sub><italic>j</italic></sub> are connected, <italic>a</italic><sub><italic>ij</italic></sub> = 1; otherwise <italic>a</italic><sub><italic>ij</italic></sub> = 0. The bipartite network and the association matrix are demonstrated in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>The bipartite network and the association network</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
        <p id="Par25">SCMFDD factorizes the drug-disease association matrix <italic>A</italic> into two low-rank feature matrices <italic>X</italic> ∈ <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>n</italic> × <italic>k</italic></sup> and <italic>Y</italic> ∈ <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>m</italic> × <italic>k</italic></sup>, where <italic>k</italic> is the dimension of drug feature and disease feature in the low-rank spaces. The drug-disease association can be approximated by inner product between the drug feature vector and the disease feature vector: <inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {a}_{ij}\approx {\boldsymbol{x}}_i{\boldsymbol{y}}_j^T $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, where <bold><italic>x</italic></bold><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> is the <italic>i</italic>th row of <italic>X</italic>, and <bold><italic>y</italic></bold><sub><italic>j</italic></sub> is the <italic>j</italic>th row of <italic>Y</italic>.The objective function is defined as:<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \mathit{\min}\frac{1}{2}\sum \limits_{ij}{\left({a}_{ij}-{\boldsymbol{x}}_i{\boldsymbol{y}}_j^T\right)}^2 $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M12" display="block"><mml:mo mathvariant="italic">min</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msup><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
        <p id="Par26">Then, to avoid overfitting problem, <italic>L</italic><sub>2</sub> regularization terms of <bold><italic>x</italic></bold><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and <bold><italic>y</italic></bold><sub><italic>j</italic></sub> are added to the objective function (<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="">1</xref>),<disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \mathit{\min}\frac{1}{2}\sum \limits_{ij}{\left({a}_{ij}-{\boldsymbol{x}}_i{\boldsymbol{y}}_j^T\right)}^2+\frac{\mu }{2}\sum \limits_i{\left\Vert {\boldsymbol{x}}_i\right\Vert}^2+\frac{\mu }{2}\sum \limits_j{\left\Vert {\boldsymbol{y}}_j\right\Vert}^2 $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M14" display="block"><mml:mo mathvariant="italic">min</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msup><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msup><mml:mfenced close="‖" open="‖"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msup><mml:mfenced close="‖" open="‖"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>μ</italic> is the regularization parameter for <bold><italic>x</italic></bold><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and <bold><italic>y</italic></bold><sub><italic>j</italic></sub>.</p>
        <p id="Par27">Recent studies on manifold learning theory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>], spectral graph theory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>] and their applications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] show that the geometric and topological structure of data points may be maintained when they are mapped from high dimensional space into low dimensional space. Considering that the similarity matrix <italic>w</italic><sup><italic>d</italic></sup> and <italic>w</italic><sup><italic>s</italic></sup> not only can be defined to represent statistical correlation but also can be regarded as geometric properties of the data points, we introduce the similarity constraint terms <italic>R</italic><sub><italic>X</italic></sub> and <italic>R</italic><sub><italic>Y</italic></sub>:<disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {R}_X=\frac{1}{2}\sum \limits_{ij}{\left\Vert {\boldsymbol{x}}_i-{\boldsymbol{x}}_j\right\Vert}^2{w}_{ij}^d $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M16" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msup><mml:mfenced close="‖" open="‖"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Article_Equ3.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M17">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {R}_Y=\frac{1}{2}\sum \limits_{ij}{\left\Vert {\boldsymbol{y}}_i-{\boldsymbol{y}}_j\right\Vert}^2{w}_{ij}^s $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M18" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msup><mml:mfenced close="‖" open="‖"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Article_Equ4.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="M19">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {w}_{ij}^d $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M20" display="inline"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Article_IEq2.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> denotes the similarity between the drug <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and the drug <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>j</italic></sub>, which is calculated in the drug feature space; <inline-formula id="IEq3"><alternatives><tex-math id="M21">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {w}_{ij}^s $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M22" display="inline"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Article_IEq3.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> denotes the similarity between the disease <italic>dis</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and the disease <italic>dis</italic><sub><italic>j</italic></sub>, which is calculated in the disease feature space. It is generally believed that the similarity between two data points is higher if the distance of them is smaller. Therefore, <italic>R</italic><sub><italic>X</italic></sub>(or <italic>R</italic><sub><italic>Y</italic></sub>) incurs a heavy penalty if drug <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and the drug <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>j</italic></sub>(disease <italic>dis</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and the disease <italic>dis</italic><sub><italic>j</italic></sub>) are close in the drug feature space (or disease feature space) and thus minimizing it further incurs that drug <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and the drug <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>j</italic></sub>(or disease <italic>dis</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and the disease <italic>dis</italic><sub><italic>j</italic></sub>) are mapped closely in low-rank spaces. Hence, we could maintain effectively the topological structure of drug data points and disease data points by minimizing <italic>R</italic><sub><italic>X</italic></sub> and <italic>R</italic><sub><italic>Y</italic></sub>.</p>
        <p id="Par28">By combining <italic>R</italic><sub><italic>X</italic></sub> and <italic>R</italic><sub><italic>Y</italic></sub> with the original objective function (<xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="">2</xref>), we propose the objective function of SCMFDD,<disp-formula id="Equ5"><label>5</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M23">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \underset{X,Y}{\min }L=\frac{1}{2}\sum \limits_{ij}{\left({a}_{ij}-{\boldsymbol{x}}_i{\boldsymbol{y}}_j^T\right)}^2+\frac{\mu }{2}\sum \limits_i{\left\Vert {\boldsymbol{x}}_i\right\Vert}^2+\frac{\mu }{2}\sum \limits_j{\left\Vert {\boldsymbol{y}}_j\right\Vert}^2+\frac{\uplambda}{2}\sum \limits_{ij}{\left\Vert {\boldsymbol{x}}_i-{\boldsymbol{x}}_j\right\Vert}^2{w}_{ij}^d+\frac{\uplambda}{2}\sum \limits_{ij}{\left\Vert {\boldsymbol{y}}_i-{\boldsymbol{y}}_j\right\Vert}^2{w}_{ij}^s $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M24" display="block"><mml:munder><mml:mo>min</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msup><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msup><mml:mfenced close="‖" open="‖"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msup><mml:mfenced close="‖" open="‖"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">λ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msup><mml:mfenced close="‖" open="‖"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">λ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msup><mml:mfenced close="‖" open="‖"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Article_Equ5.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where λ is the hyper parameter controlling the smoothness of the similarity consistency.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec8">
        <title>Optimization algorithm</title>
        <p id="Par29">Here, we develop an efficient optimization algorithm to solve the objective function in (<xref rid="Equ5" ref-type="">5</xref>). First, we calculate the partial derivatives of <italic>L</italic> with respect to <bold><italic>x</italic></bold><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and <bold><italic>y</italic></bold><sub><italic>j</italic></sub>,<disp-formula id="Equ6"><label>6</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M25">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {\nabla}_{{\boldsymbol{x}}_i}L=\sum \limits_j\left({\boldsymbol{x}}_i{\boldsymbol{y}}_j^T-{a}_{ij}\right){y}_j+{\mu \boldsymbol{x}}_i+\uplambda \left(\sum \limits_j\left({\boldsymbol{x}}_i-{\boldsymbol{x}}_j\right){w}_{ij}^d-\sum \limits_j\left({\boldsymbol{x}}_j-{\boldsymbol{x}}_i\right){w}_{ji}^d\right)={\boldsymbol{x}}_i\left({Y}^TY+\mu I+\uplambda \left(\sum \limits_j{w}_{ij}^d+\sum \limits_j{w}_{ji}^d\right)I\right)-A\left(i,:\right)Y-\uplambda \sum \limits_j\left({w}_{ij}^d+{w}_{ji}^d\right){\boldsymbol{x}}_j $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M26" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mi>∇</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">λ</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ji</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">μI</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">λ</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ji</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=","><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">λ</mml:mi><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ji</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Article_Equ6.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ7"><label>7</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M27">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {\nabla}_{{\boldsymbol{y}}_j}L=\sum \limits_i\left({\boldsymbol{y}}_j{\boldsymbol{x}}_i^T-{a}_{ij}\right){x}_i+\mu {\boldsymbol{y}}_j+\uplambda \left(\sum \limits_i\left({\boldsymbol{y}}_j-{\boldsymbol{y}}_i\right){w}_{ji}^s-\sum \limits_i\left({\boldsymbol{y}}_i-{\boldsymbol{y}}_j\right){w}_{ij}^s\right)={\boldsymbol{y}}_j\left({X}^TX+\mu I+\uplambda \left(\sum \limits_i{w}_{ij}^s+\sum \limits_i{w}_{ji}^s\right)I\right)-A{\left(:,j\right)}^TX-\uplambda \sum \limits_i\left({w}_{ij}^s+{w}_{ji}^s\right){\boldsymbol{y}}_i $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M28" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mi>∇</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">λ</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ji</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">μI</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">λ</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ji</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=","><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">λ</mml:mi><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ji</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Article_Equ7.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
        <p id="Par30"><italic>A</italic>(<italic>i</italic>, :) represents the <italic>i</italic>th row of <italic>A</italic> and <italic>A</italic>(:, <italic>j</italic>) represents the <italic>j</italic>th column of <italic>A</italic>.</p>
        <p id="Par31">Then, we can calculate the second derivatives of <italic>L</italic> with respect to <bold><italic>x</italic></bold><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and <bold><italic>y</italic></bold><sub><italic>j</italic></sub>:<disp-formula id="Equ8"><label>8</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M29">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {\nabla}_{{\boldsymbol{x}}_i}^2L={Y}^TY+\mu I+\uplambda \left(\sum \limits_j{w}_{ij}^d+\sum \limits_j{w}_{ji}^d\right)I $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M30" display="block"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>∇</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">μI</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">λ</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ji</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Article_Equ8.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ9"><label>9</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M31">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {\nabla}_{{\boldsymbol{y}}_j}^2L={X}^TX+\mu I+\uplambda \left(\sum \limits_i{w}_{ij}^s+\sum \limits_i{w}_{ji}^s\right)I $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M32" display="block"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>∇</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">μI</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">λ</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ji</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Article_Equ9.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
        <p id="Par32">Utilizing Newton’s method, we have:<disp-formula id="Equ10"><label>10</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M33">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {\boldsymbol{x}}_i\leftarrow {\boldsymbol{x}}_i-{\nabla}_{{\boldsymbol{x}}_i}L{\left({\nabla}_{{\boldsymbol{x}}_i}^2L\right)}^{-1} $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M34" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>←</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>∇</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>∇</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Article_Equ10.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ11"><label>11</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M35">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {\boldsymbol{y}}_j\leftarrow {\boldsymbol{y}}_j-{\nabla}_{{\boldsymbol{y}}_j}L{\left({\nabla}_{{\boldsymbol{y}}_j}^2L\right)}^{-1} $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M36" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>←</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>∇</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>∇</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Article_Equ11.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
        <p id="Par33">Thus, we can obtain the updating rules:<disp-formula id="Equ12"><label>12</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M37">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {\boldsymbol{x}}_i=\left(A\left(i,:\right)Y+\uplambda \sum \limits_j\left({w}_{ij}^d+{w}_{ji}^d\right){\boldsymbol{x}}_j\right){\left({Y}^TY+\mu I+\uplambda \left(\sum \limits_j{w}_{ij}^d+\sum \limits_j{w}_{ji}^d\right)I\right)}^{-1} $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M38" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=","><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">λ</mml:mi><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ji</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msup><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">μI</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">λ</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ji</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Article_Equ12.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ13"><label>13</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M39">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {\boldsymbol{y}}_j=\left(A{\left(:,j\right)}^TX+\uplambda \sum \limits_i\left({w}_{ij}^s+{w}_{ji}^s\right){\boldsymbol{y}}_i\right){\left({X}^TX+\mu I+\uplambda \left(\sum \limits_i{w}_{ij}^s+\sum \limits_i{w}_{ji}^s\right)I\right)}^{-1} $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M40" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=","><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">λ</mml:mi><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ji</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msup><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">μI</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">λ</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ji</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Article_Equ13.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
        <p id="Par34">We alternatively update <bold><italic>x</italic></bold><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and <bold><italic>y</italic></bold><sub><italic>j</italic></sub> with Eq. (<xref rid="Equ12" ref-type="">12</xref>) and Eq. (<xref rid="Equ13" ref-type="">13</xref>) until convergence. The prediction matrix is given by<disp-formula id="Equ14"><label>14</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M41">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {A}_{predict}=X{Y}^T $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M42" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">predict</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Article_Equ14.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
        <p id="Par35">The score of (<italic>A</italic><sub><italic>predict</italic></sub>)<sub><italic>ij</italic></sub> represents the probability that the drug <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and the disease <italic>dis</italic><sub><italic>j</italic></sub> has the association. The optimization algorithm is summarized in Algorithm 1.<table-wrap id="Taba"><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td colspan="2"><bold>Algorithm 1</bold> Algorithm to solve objective function (<xref rid="Equ5" ref-type="">5</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><bold>Input:</bold> known drug-disease association matrix, <italic>A</italic> ∈ <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>n</italic> × <italic>m</italic></sup>;<break/>drug similarity matrix, <italic>W</italic><sup><italic>d</italic></sup> ∈ <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>n</italic> × <italic>n</italic></sup>;<break/>disease similarity matrix, <italic>W</italic><sup><italic>s</italic></sup> ∈ <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>m</italic> × <italic>m</italic></sup>;<break/>dimension of the low-rank feature space, <italic>k</italic> &lt; min(<italic>m</italic>, <italic>n</italic>);<break/>regularization parameter, <italic>μ</italic> &gt; 0, <italic>λ</italic> &gt; 0;<break/><bold>Output:</bold> the prediction matrix <italic>A</italic><sub><italic>predict</italic></sub><break/>1 Initialize <italic>X</italic> ∈ <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>n</italic> × <italic>k</italic></sup>, <italic>Y</italic> ∈ <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>m</italic> × <italic>k</italic></sup> as two random matrices;<break/>2 <bold>Repeat</bold><break/>3 <bold>Update</bold>
<italic>X</italic>:<break/>4 <bold>for</bold> each <italic>i</italic>(1 ≤ <italic>i</italic> ≤ <italic>n</italic>) <bold>do</bold><break/>5 update <italic>x</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> by Eq. (<xref rid="Equ12" ref-type="">12</xref>);<break/>6 <bold>end</bold><break/>7 <bold>Update</bold>
<italic>Y</italic>:<break/>8 <bold>for</bold> each <italic>j</italic>(1 ≤ <italic>j</italic> ≤ <italic>m</italic>) <bold>do</bold><break/>9 update <italic>y</italic><sub><italic>j</italic></sub> by Eq. (<xref rid="Equ13" ref-type="">13</xref>);<break/>10 <bold>end</bold><break/>11 <bold>Until</bold> Converges;<break/>12 Calculate the prediction matrix <italic>A</italic><sub><italic>predict</italic></sub> by Eq. (<xref rid="Equ14" ref-type="">14</xref>);<break/>13 Output <italic>A</italic><sub><italic>predict</italic></sub>;</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec9">
    <title>Results and discussion</title>
    <sec id="Sec10">
      <title>Evaluation metrics</title>
      <p id="Par36">In our experiments, we adopted five-fold cross validation (5-CV) to test performances of prediction models. To implement five-fold cross validation, we randomly split all known drug-disease associations into five equal-sized subsets. In each fold, we combined four subsets as the training set, and used the other subset as the testing set. We constructed the prediction model based on known associations in the training set, and predicted associations in the testing set. Training and testing were repeated five times, and the average of performances was adopted.</p>
      <p id="Par37">AUC and AUPR are popular metrics for evaluating prediction models. Since drug-disease pairs without associations are much more than known drug-disease associations, we adopted AUPR as the primary metric, which takes into recall and precision. We also considered several binary classification metrics, i.e. sensitivity (SN, also known as recall), specificity (SP), accuracy (ACC) and F-measure (F).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec11">
      <title>Performances of SCMFDD</title>
      <p id="Par38">First of all, we discussed the influence of parameters on SCMFDD models by using SCMFDD-S dataset. SCMFDD has three parameters, i.e. the number of latent variables <italic>k</italic>, the regularization parameter <italic>μ</italic> and the regularization parameter λ. <italic>k</italic> is the dimension of drugs and diseases in low-rank spaces, and <italic>k</italic> is less than row number and column number of the association matrix, and <italic>k</italic> &lt; <italic>k</italic><sub>0</sub> = min(<italic>m</italic>, <italic>n</italic>). For simplicity, we set <italic>k</italic> as the percentage of <italic>k</italic><sub>0</sub>.</p>
      <p id="Par39">SCMFDD builds prediction model constrained by drug-drug similarity and disease-disease semantic similarity. We have several drug features in SCMFDD-S dataset, and can calculate several types of drug-drug similarities. Here, we used the drug interaction-based similarity and the disease semantic similarity to build SCMFDD models for analysis. We considered all combinations of following values λ ∈ {2<sup>−3</sup>, 2<sup>−2</sup>, 2<sup>−1</sup>, 2<sup>0</sup>, 2<sup>1</sup>, 2<sup>2</sup>, 2<sup>3</sup>}, <italic>μ</italic> ∈ {2<sup>−3</sup>, 2<sup>−2</sup>, 2<sup>−1</sup>, 2<sup>0</sup>, 2<sup>1</sup>, 2<sup>2</sup>, 2<sup>3</sup>} and <italic>k</italic> ∈ {5%, 10%, 15 % …, 50%} to build SCMFDD models, and implemented five-fold cross validation to evaluate models. The experiments for all parameter combinations cost about 12 h on a PC with Intel i7 7700 K CPU and 16GB RAM.</p>
      <p id="Par40">In computational experiments, SCMFDD produced the best AUPR score when <italic>k</italic> = 45 % ,  <italic>μ</italic> = 2<sup>0</sup> and λ = 2<sup>2</sup>. Then, we fixed the latent variable number <italic>k</italic> = 45%, and evaluated the influence of parameters <italic>μ</italic> and λ, and results are shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>. Clearly, <italic>μ</italic> and λ have great impact on the model. When <italic>μ</italic> is a small value, greater λ could lead to better performances; when <italic>μ</italic> is a great value, greater λ contributes to poorer performances. Further, we fixed the parameters <italic>μ</italic> = 2<sup>0</sup> and λ = 2<sup>2</sup>, and tested the influence of the latent variable number <italic>k</italic>. The latent variable numbers and AUPR scores of corresponding models are shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>. Clearly, performances of SCMFDD will increase as <italic>k</italic> increases, and remain unchanged after reaching a threshold.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>The influence of parameters on SCMFDD models. <bold>a</bold> the influnce of μ and λ <bold>b</bold> the influence of k</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p>
      <p id="Par41">Further, we tested the impact of different similarity constraints on SCMFDD models. We have various features of drugs, and can calculate different types of drug-drug similarities, i.e. substructure similarity, target similarity, pathway similarity, enzyme similarity and drug interaction similarity. These similarities can be used as the constraint terms for SCMFDD models. We set <italic>k</italic> = 45%, <italic>μ</italic> = 2<sup>0</sup> and λ = 2<sup>2</sup> in the experiments. As shown in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, SCMFDD models using different drug-drug similarities produce high-accuracy and robust performances. Since drug structures directly influence functions and drug interactions may induce drug effects, drug substructures and drug interactions lead to better results than other features.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The performances of SCMFDD models based on different drug features</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>AUPR</th><th>AUC</th><th>SN</th><th>SP</th><th>ACC</th><th>F</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Substructure</td><td>0.2644</td><td>0.8737</td><td>0.3329</td><td>0.9795</td><td>0.9632</td><td>0.3130</td></tr><tr><td>Target</td><td>0.1947</td><td>0.8410</td><td>0.2751</td><td>0.9751</td><td>0.9575</td><td>0.2456</td></tr><tr><td>Pathway</td><td>0.2582</td><td>0.8706</td><td>0.3435</td><td>0.9771</td><td>0.9611</td><td>0.3079</td></tr><tr><td>Enzyme</td><td>0.2496</td><td>0.8671</td><td>0.3331</td><td>0.9768</td><td>0.9606</td><td>0.2990</td></tr><tr><td>Drug interaction</td><td>0.2638</td><td>0.8734</td><td>0.3505</td><td>0.9769</td><td>0.9611</td><td>0.3120</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
      <p id="Par42">The known drug-disease association is an important resource for predicting unobserved drug-disease associations. The data richness, which is the ratio of association number vs drug-disease pair number, may influence performances of SCMFDD. Here, we used the dataset SCMFDD-L for analysis. We removed drugs that are associated with less than <italic>m</italic> diseases, and removed diseases that associated with less than <italic>m</italic> drugs from SCMFDD-L dataset, <italic>m</italic> ∈ {2,  3, 4, 5, 6…10}. As displayed in Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, the data richness will increase as the threshold <italic>m</italic> increases, and then improve performances of SCMFDD models. Although the data richness influences the performances, SCMFDD could still produce robust performances.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>The influence of association exclusion criteria on data richness (<bold>a</bold>) and model performance (<bold>b</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec12">
      <title>Comparison with state-of-the-art prediction methods</title>
      <p id="Par43">In this section, we compared our method with three state-of-the-art drug-disease association prediction methods: PREDICT [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], TL-HGBI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] and LRSSL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. PREDICT constructed a universal predictor for drug repositioning to express drug-disease associations in a large-scale manner that integrates molecular structure, molecular activity and semantic data. TL-HGBI was a computational framework based on a three-layer heterogeneous network model, which made use of Omics data about diseases, drugs and drug targets to make predictions. LRSSL was a Laplacian regularized sparse subspace learning method, which integrated drug chemical information, drug target domains and target annotation information to make predictions. We obtained datasets of PREDICT [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], datasets and source codes of TL-HGBI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] from authors. The datasets and source codes of LRSSL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] are publicly available. Therefore, we can adopt these methods as benchmark methods for fair comparison.</p>
      <p id="Par44">First, we compared our method with PREDICT based on the PREDICT dataset by using five-fold cross validation. SCMFDD uses one drug similarity constraint and one disease similarity constraint. The PREDICT dataset contains five kinds of drug-drug similarities and two kinds of diseases-disease similarity. Thus, we built 10 different SCMFDD models by combining drug-drug similarities and diseases-disease similarities. As shown in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, SCMFDD models and PREDICT produce similar AUC scores, but SCMFDD models yield much greater AUPR scores than PREDICT. Moreover, SCMFDD models were robust to different similarities, and the models based on the drug Genes-Waterman similarity and disease Gene Signature similarity produced the best results.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Performance of PREDICT and SCMFDD on PREDICT Dataset</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Methods</th><th>AUPR</th><th>AUC</th><th>SN</th><th>SP</th><th>ACC</th><th>F</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>PREDICT</td><td>0.1507</td><td>0.9020</td><td>0.3414</td><td>0.9929</td><td>0.9915</td><td>0.1437</td></tr><tr><td>SCMFDD-Che-GS</td><td>0.3141</td><td>0.9005</td><td>0.3663</td><td>0.9988</td><td>0.9974</td><td>0.3753</td></tr><tr><td>SCMFDD-Che-Phen</td><td>0.3153</td><td>0.9038</td><td>0.3678</td><td>0.9988</td><td>0.9974</td><td>0.3769</td></tr><tr><td>SCMFDD-SE-GS</td><td>0.3157</td><td>0.9082</td><td>0.3663</td><td>0.9988</td><td>0.9974</td><td>0.3753</td></tr><tr><td>SCMFDD-SE-Phen</td><td>0.3176</td><td>0.9109</td><td>0.3678</td><td>0.9988</td><td>0.9974</td><td>0.3769</td></tr><tr><td>SCMFDD-GP-GS</td><td>0.3210</td><td>0.9129</td><td>0.3720</td><td>0.9988</td><td>0.9975</td><td>0.3811</td></tr><tr><td>SCMFDD-GP-Phen</td><td>0.3224</td><td>0.9157</td><td>0.3714</td><td>0.9988</td><td>0.9975</td><td>0.3806</td></tr><tr><td>SCMFDD-GO-GS</td><td>0.3147</td><td>0.9035</td><td>0.3678</td><td>0.9988</td><td>0.9974</td><td>0.3769</td></tr><tr><td>SCMFDD-GO-Phen</td><td>0.3159</td><td>0.9065</td><td>0.3678</td><td>0.9988</td><td>0.9974</td><td>0.3769</td></tr><tr><td>SCMFDD-GW-GS</td><td>0.3249</td><td>0.9173</td><td>0.3389</td><td>0.9991</td><td>0.9977</td><td>0.3843</td></tr><tr><td>SCMFDD-GW-Phen</td><td>0.3284</td><td>0.9203</td><td>0.3776</td><td>0.9988</td><td>0.9975</td><td>0.3870</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>For drugs, <italic>Che</italic> Chemical fingerprints Similarity, <italic>SE</italic> Side Effect Similarity, <italic>GP</italic> Genes-Perlman Similarity, <italic>GO</italic> Genes- Ovaska Similarity, <italic>GW</italic> Genes-Waterman Similarity. For diseases, <italic>GS</italic> Gene Signature Similarity, <italic>Phen</italic> Phenotypic Similarity</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p id="Par45">Then, we compared our method with TL-HGBI by using TL-HGBI dataset. TL-HGBI dataset contains one drug chemical structure similarity and one disease phenotypic similarity. We constructed the SCMFDD model by using drug structure similarity and disease phenotypic similarity. As shown in Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>, SCMFDD produced similar AUC score but much greater AUPR score compared with TL-HGBI.</p>
      <p id="Par46">Further, we compared SCMFDD and LRSSL by using LRSSL dataset. Since LRSSL dataset contains three features of drugs: chemical substructures, protein domains of target proteins, gene ontology information of target proteins. Three drug similarities were calculated, and disease semantic similarity was provided as well. Therefore, we can construct three SCMFDD models by combing three drug similarities and the disease semantic similarity. Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref> shows the performances of prediction models evaluated by five-fold cross validation. Clearly, three SCMFDD models can produce better performance than LRSSL.<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Performance of TL-HGBI and SCMFDD on TL-HGBI Dataset</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Methods</th><th>AUPR</th><th>AUC</th><th>SN</th><th>SP</th><th>ACC</th><th>F</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>TL-HGBI</td><td>0.0492</td><td>0.9584</td><td>0.1697</td><td>0.9999</td><td>0.9998</td><td>0.0840</td></tr><tr><td>SCMFDD</td><td>0.1500</td><td>0.9752</td><td>0.2136</td><td>0.9990</td><td>0.9990</td><td>0.0168</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Performance of LRSSL and SCMFDD on Liang Dataset</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Methods</th><th>AUPR</th><th>AUC</th><th>SN</th><th>SP</th><th>ACC</th><th>F</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>LRSSL</td><td>0.1789</td><td>0.8250</td><td>0.2167</td><td>0.9989</td><td>0.9979</td><td>0.2018</td></tr><tr><td>SCMFDD-Che-Sem</td><td>0.2518</td><td>0.9020</td><td>0.2799</td><td>0.9993</td><td>0.9985</td><td>0.3030</td></tr><tr><td>SCMFDD-Dom-Sem</td><td>0.2673</td><td>0.9228</td><td>0.2851</td><td>0.9993</td><td>0.9985</td><td>0.3088</td></tr><tr><td>SCMFDD-Go-Sem</td><td>0.2585</td><td>0.9210</td><td>0.2897</td><td>0.9993</td><td>0.9985</td><td>0.3137</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>For drugs, <italic>Che</italic> Chemical Similarity, <italic>Dom</italic> Protein Domains Similarity, <italic>Go</italic> Gene ontology Similarity. For diseases, Sem: Semantic Similarity</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec13">
      <title>Independent experiments</title>
      <p id="Par47">In this section, we conducted independent experiments to test performances of our method in predicting novel drug-disease associations.</p>
      <p id="Par48">CTD database is an up-to-date resource about the experimentally determined drug-disease associations. Since PREDICT dataset and LRSSL dataset were compiled several years ago, we can build prediction models by using PREDICT dataset and LRSSL dataset, and check up the predictions in the CTD database. Different drugs and diseases could be matched according to their names and synonyms (provided by CTD database “Chemical vocabulary” and “Disease vocabulary”). PREDICT dataset and LRSSL dataset include different types of drug-drug similarities, and we build different similarity-based SCMFDD models for the comprehensive comparison. The PREDICT model and the LRSSL model respectively predict novel interaction by using PREDICT dataset and LRSSL dataset.</p>
      <p id="Par49">We considered the top predictions from top 2 to top 1000 in a step size of 2, and respectively counted how many predicted associations can be confirmed in CTD database. Figure <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> shows the number of checked predictions and the number of confirmed associations. Clearly, our method finds out more novel associations than benchmark methods, and has the good performances in the independent experiments.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>The number of confirmed associations in top predictions of PREDICT, LRSSL, SCMFDD. (a) For drugs, Che: Chemical Similarity, SE: Chemical Similarity, GP: Genes-Perlman Similarity, GO: Genes- Ovaska Similarity, GW: Genes-Waterman Similarity. For diseases, GS: Gene Signature Similarity, Phen: Phenotypic Similarity (b) For drugs, Che: Chemical Similarity, Dom: Protein Domains Similarity, Go: Gene ontology Similarity. For diseases, Sem: Semantic Similarity</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec14">
      <title>Web server and applications</title>
      <p id="Par50">To facilitate the drug-disease association prediction, we developed a web server named “SCMFDD” by using the dataset SCMFDD-L, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bioinfotech.cn/SCMFDD">http://www.bioinfotech.cn/SCMFDD/</ext-link>. Users can predict novel drug-disease associations for a given drug or a given disease, and then visualize predictions. Here, we used two case studies to illustrate the usefulness for the drug-disease association prediction of our web server.</p>
      <p id="Par51">Clozapine is an effective drug to treat patients with refractory schizophrenia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Clozapine works by changing the actions of chemicals in the brain. Here, the web server predicts diseases that are associated with Clozapine. Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref> lists top 10 predictions among all unknown relationships between Clozapine and diseases in the SCMFDD-L dataset. Then, we analyze these predicted diseases case by case. From <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clozapine">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clozapine</ext-link> (access on 2018–2-1), three diseases: sleep initiation and maintenance disorders (also insomnia), status epilepticus and headache have been reported as side effects of Clozapine, indicating that they have associations with the drug “Clozapine”. Further, the study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>] found that Clozapine improved the syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion(SIADH) in a patient; the studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] revealed that Clozapine can be used for the treatment of post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD); the study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>] demonstrated that Clozapine can be used for the treatment of Parkinson’s disease; the study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>] indicated that Clozapine can affect the visual memory.<table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Top 10 predicted diseases associated with Clozapine</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Index</th><th>Disease Name</th><th>Disease ID</th><th>Score</th><th>Evidence</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>Sleep Initiation and Maintenance Disorders</td><td>D007319</td><td>1</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clozapine">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clozapine</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>Anxiety Disorders</td><td>D001008</td><td>0.9117</td><td>N.A.</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>Inappropriate ADH Syndrome</td><td>D007177</td><td>0.7434</td><td>A Case report [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</td><td>D013313</td><td>0.7267</td><td>Report [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>Parkinson Disease, Secondary</td><td>D010302</td><td>0.7179</td><td>Review [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>Memory Disorders</td><td>D008569</td><td>0.7123</td><td>An animal study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>Status Epilepticus</td><td>D013226</td><td>0.6312</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clozapine">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clozapine</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>Headache</td><td>D006261</td><td>0.6166</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clozapine">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clozapine</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>Torsades de Pointes</td><td>D016171</td><td>0.5953</td><td>N.A.</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>Attention Deficit Disorder with Hyperactivity</td><td>D001289</td><td>0.5913</td><td>N.A.</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Scores are normalized by using ((score-min)/(max-min))</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p id="Par52">Alzheimer’s disease (AD) is a chronic neurodegenerative disorder that leads to disturbances of cognitive functions. The radical cause and effective treatment of AD remain unclear, and AD has attracted many scientists to study its pathogenic mechanism and therapeutic function. Table <xref rid="Tab7" ref-type="table">7</xref> lists top 10 predicted drugs associated with Alzheimer’s disease, and evidence is available for six drugs. For example, the study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>] revealed that Olanzapine appears to be effective in treating psychotic and behavioral disturbances associated with AD; the study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>] found that stimulation of the dopaminergic system could improve cognitive function in a murine model and suggested that Levodopa that works in the dopaminergic system could ameliorate typical symptoms of AD: learning and memory deficits. The study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>] revealed that the presence of Malondialdehyde level is a risk factor for AD. The study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>] confirmed that progesterone significantly could reduce and inhibit tau hyperphosphorylation, a chemical process implicated in AD. The study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>] demonstrated that Valproic Acid (VPA) could decrease β-amyloid(Aβ) production which is the key risk factor in AD and improve memory deficits of AD model mice. The study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>] showed that Ethanol protect neurons against Aβ-induced synapse damage and explained epidemiological reports that moderate alcohol consumption protects against the development of AD.<table-wrap id="Tab7"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Top 10 predicted drugs associated with Alzheimer’s disease</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Index</th><th>Drug Name</th><th>Drug MeSH ID</th><th>DrugBank ID</th><th>PubChem CID</th><th>Score(normalized)</th><th>Evidence</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>Nitroprusside</td><td>D009599</td><td>DB00325</td><td>11,963,622</td><td>1</td><td>N.A.</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>Tamoxifen</td><td>D013629</td><td>DB00675</td><td>2,733,526</td><td>0.7644</td><td>N.A.</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>Olanzapine</td><td>C076029</td><td>DB00334</td><td>4585</td><td>0.7269</td><td>A clinical study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>Sucralfate</td><td>D013392</td><td>DB00364</td><td>70,789,197</td><td>0.7223</td><td>N.A.</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>Levodopa</td><td>D007980</td><td>DB01235</td><td>6047</td><td>0.6893</td><td>An animal study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>Malondialdehyde</td><td>D008315</td><td>DB03057</td><td>10,964</td><td>0.6767</td><td>A clinical study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>Progesterone</td><td>D011374</td><td>DB00396</td><td>5994</td><td>0.6695</td><td>An animal study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>Valproic Acid</td><td>D014635</td><td>DB00313</td><td>3121</td><td>0.6625</td><td>An animal study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>Scopolamine Hydrobromide</td><td>D012601</td><td>DB00747</td><td>3,000,322</td><td>0.6522</td><td>N.A.</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>D000431</td><td>DB00898</td><td>702</td><td>0.6402</td><td>A clinical study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Scores are normalized by using ((score-min)/(max-min))</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p id="Par53">The server can visualize the predictions. Figure <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref> shows the top 100 predictions for Clozapine and top 200 predictions for Alzheimer’s disease. As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a</xref>, “dark blue circle” stands for a disease, which has a known association with Clozapine, and “red square” stands for predicted diseases, which have an association with Clozapine. As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7b</xref>, “dark blue circle” stands for a drug, which has a known association with Alzheimer’s disease, and “red square” stands for predicted drugs, which have an association with Alzheimer’s disease. Users can adjust the number of predictions for visualization.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Web Visualization of predictions for Clozapine <bold>a</bold> and predictions for Headache <bold>b</bold></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2018_2220_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec15">
    <title>Conclusion</title>
    <p id="Par54">In this paper, we proposed a computational method “SCMFDD” to predict unobserved drug-disease associations. SCMFDD incorporate drug feature-based similarities and disease semantic similarity into the matrix factorization frame. Experimental results show that SCMFDD can produce high-accuracy performances on five benchmark datasets when evaluated by five-fold cross validation, and SCMFDD outperforms state-of-the-art methods under fair comparison. Moreover, SCMFDD produces satisfying performances for different similarity constraints, and is also robust to the data richness. We constructed a web server based on drug-disease associations, which are collected from the CTD database. The server can predict novel drug-disease associations, and also can help researchers to quickly find associations for interested drugs or diseases.</p>
    <p id="Par55">In recent years, the deep learning methods have been applied to similar tasks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. However, designing an effective neural network is a hard task, and the training process also costs a great amount of time. Compared to deep learning-based methods, SCMFDD is easy to implement, and SCMFDD can be applied into similar tasks in bioinformatics.</p>
    <p id="Par56">However, SCMFDD still has several limitations. First, SCMFDD has three parameters, and there is no good way of determining suitable parameters except going through all combinations. For our datasets, it costs dozens of hours to determine optimal parameters. Second, SCMFDD only uses individual drug feature-based similarity to build prediction models. When we have multiple drug features, we can calculate different drug feature-based similarities. Combining diverse information can usually lead to improved performances [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>], and how to integrate multiple similarities in a model is our future work. Third, the server can make predictions for the drugs and diseases in our dataset, but can’t support other drugs or diseases.</p>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <glossary>
    <title>Abbreviations</title>
    <def-list>
      <def-item>
        <term>AUC</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par4">Area under ROC curve</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>AUPR</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par5">Area under the precision-recall curve</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>SCMFDD</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par6">Similarity constrained matrix factorization method</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
    </def-list>
  </glossary>
  <ack>
    <sec id="FPar1">
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p id="Par57">This work is supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (61772381, 61572368), the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities (2042017kf0219). The fundings have no role in the design of the study and collection, analysis, and interpretation of data and writing the manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="FPar2">
      <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
      <p id="Par58">a user-friendly web server available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bioinfotech.cn/SCMFDD/">http://www.bioinfotech.cn/SCMFDD/</ext-link>.</p>
    </sec>
  </ack>
  <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
    <title>Authors’ contributions</title>
    <p>WZ and FL conceived the project; XY, WL and WZ designed the experiments; XY, WL and FH performed the experiments; WW and RL designed the server; WZ and XY wrote the paper. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
  </notes>
  <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
    <sec id="FPar3">
      <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
      <p id="Par59">Not applicable.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="FPar4">
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p id="Par60">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="FPar5">
      <title>Publisher’s Note</title>
      <p id="Par61">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
    </sec>
  </notes>
  <ref-list id="Bib1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="CR1">
      <label>1.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wilson</surname>
            <given-names>JF</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Alterations in processes and priorities needed for new drug development</article-title>
        <source>Ann Intern Med</source>
        <year>2006</year>
        <volume>145</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <fpage>793</fpage>
        <lpage>796</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-145-10-200611210-00024</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 17116936?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17116936</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR2">
      <label>2.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dimasi</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>New drug development in the United States from 1963 to 1999</article-title>
        <source>Clin Pharmacol Ther</source>
        <year>2001</year>
        <volume>69</volume>
        <issue>5</issue>
        <fpage>286</fpage>
        <lpage>296</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/mcp.2001.115132</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 11371996?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11371996</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR3">
      <label>3.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Adams</surname>
            <given-names>CP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Brantner</surname>
            <given-names>VV</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Estimating the cost of new drug development: is it really 802 million dollars?</article-title>
        <source>Health Aff</source>
        <year>2006</year>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <fpage>420</fpage>
        <lpage>428</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1377/hlthaff.25.2.420</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR4">
      <label>4.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Davis</surname>
            <given-names>AP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Grondin</surname>
            <given-names>CJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Johnson</surname>
            <given-names>RJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sciaky</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>King</surname>
            <given-names>BL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McMorran</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wiegers</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wiegers</surname>
            <given-names>TC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mattingly</surname>
            <given-names>CJ</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The comparative Toxicogenomics database: update 2017</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>45</volume>
        <issue>D1</issue>
        <fpage>D972</fpage>
        <lpage>D978</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkw838</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 27651457?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27651457</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR5">
      <label>5.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>von Eichborn</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Murgueitio</surname>
            <given-names>MS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dunkel</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Koerner</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bourne</surname>
            <given-names>PE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Preissner</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>PROMISCUOUS: a database for network-based drug-repositioning</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>39</volume>
        <issue>Database</issue>
        <fpage>D1060</fpage>
        <lpage>D1066</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkq1037</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 21071407?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21071407</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR6">
      <label>6.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Systematic analysis of new drug indications by drug-gene-disease coherent subnetworks</article-title>
        <source>CPT: pharmacometrics &amp; systems pharmacology</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>3</volume>
        <fpage>e146</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25390685</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR7">
      <label>7.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wiegers</surname>
            <given-names>TC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Davis</surname>
            <given-names>AP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cohen</surname>
            <given-names>KB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hirschman</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mattingly</surname>
            <given-names>CJ</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Text mining and manual curation of chemical-gene-disease networks for the comparative toxicogenomics database (CTD)</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <fpage>326</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-10-326</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 19814812?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19814812</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR8">
      <label>8.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yu L, Huang J, Ma Z, Zhang J, Zou Y, Gao L. Inferring drug-disease associations based on known protein complexes. BMC Med Genet. 2015;8(Suppl 2, S2)</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR9">
      <label>9.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gottlieb</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stein</surname>
            <given-names>GY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ruppin</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sharan</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>PREDICT: a method for inferring novel drug indications with application to personalized medicine</article-title>
        <source>Mol Syst Biol</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <fpage>496</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/msb.2011.26</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 21654673?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21654673</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR10">
      <label>10.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Agarwal</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Systematic drug repositioning based on clinical side-effects</article-title>
        <source>PLoS One</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <issue>12</issue>
        <fpage>e28025</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028025</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 22205936?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22205936</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR11">
      <label>11.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Deng</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Drug repositioning by kernel-based integration of molecular structure, molecular activity, and phenotype data</article-title>
        <source>PLoS One</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <issue>11</issue>
        <fpage>e78518</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0078518</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24244318?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24244318</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR12">
      <label>12.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <given-names>YF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yeh</surname>
            <given-names>HY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Soo</surname>
            <given-names>VW</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Inferring drug-disease associations from integration of chemical, genomic and phenotype data using network propagation</article-title>
        <source>BMC Med Genet</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <issue>Suppl 3</issue>
        <fpage>S4</fpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR13">
      <label>13.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Oh</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ahn</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yoon</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A network-based classification model for deriving novel drug-disease associations and assessing their molecular actions</article-title>
        <source>PLoS One</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <fpage>e111668</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0111668</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25356910?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25356910</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR14">
      <label>14.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Drug repositioning by integrating target information through a heterogeneous network model</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>30</volume>
        <issue>20</issue>
        <fpage>2923</fpage>
        <lpage>2930</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu403</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24974205?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24974205</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR15">
      <label>15.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Martinez</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Navarro</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cano</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fajardo</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Blanco</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>DrugNet: network-based drug-disease prioritization by integrating heterogeneous data</article-title>
        <source>Artif Intell Med</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>63</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>41</fpage>
        <lpage>49</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.artmed.2014.11.003</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25704113?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25704113</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR16">
      <label>16.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gu</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wei</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cao</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Mining drug-disease relationships as a complement to medical genetics-based drug repositioning: where a recommendation system meets genome-wide association studies</article-title>
        <source>Clin Pharmacol Ther</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>97</volume>
        <issue>5</issue>
        <fpage>451</fpage>
        <lpage>454</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cpt.82</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25670647?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25670647</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR17">
      <label>17.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Moghadam</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rahgozar</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gharaghani</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Scoring multiple features to predict drug disease associations using information fusion and aggregation</article-title>
        <source>SAR QSAR Environ Res</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>27</volume>
        <issue>8</issue>
        <fpage>609</fpage>
        <lpage>628</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1062936X.2016.1209241</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 27455069?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27455069</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR18">
      <label>18.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liang</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yan</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fu</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Peng</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Qu</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shao</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>LRSSL: predict and interpret drug–disease associations based on data integration using sparse subspace learning</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>33</volume>
        <issue>8</issue>
        <fpage>1187</fpage>
        <lpage>1196</lpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 28096083?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28096083</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR19">
      <label>19.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cheng</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bryant</surname>
            <given-names>SH</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>PubChem as a public resource for drug discovery</article-title>
        <source>Drug Discov Today</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>15</volume>
        <issue>23–24</issue>
        <fpage>1052</fpage>
        <lpage>1057</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drudis.2010.10.003</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 20970519?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20970519</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR20">
      <label>20.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Law</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Knox</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Djoumbou</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jewison</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Guo</surname>
            <given-names>AC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Maciejewski</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Arndt</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wilson</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Neveu</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>DrugBank 4.0: shedding new light on drug metabolism</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>42</volume>
        <issue>Database issue</issue>
        <fpage>D1091</fpage>
        <lpage>D1097</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt1068</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24203711?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24203711</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR21">
      <label>21.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kanehisa</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Goto</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Furumichi</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tanabe</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hirakawa</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>KEGG for representation and analysis of molecular networks involving diseases and drugs</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>38</volume>
        <issue>Database issue</issue>
        <fpage>D355</fpage>
        <lpage>D360</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkp896</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 19880382?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19880382</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR22">
      <label>22.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Smith</surname>
            <given-names>TF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Waterman</surname>
            <given-names>MS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Burks</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The statistical distribution of nucleic acid similarities</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
        <year>1985</year>
        <volume>13</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <fpage>645</fpage>
        <lpage>656</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/13.2.645</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 3871073?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3871073</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR23">
      <label>23.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Perlman</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gottlieb</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Atias</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ruppin</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sharan</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Combining drug and gene similarity measures for drug-target elucidation</article-title>
        <source>J Comput Biol</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>18</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <fpage>133</fpage>
        <lpage>145</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/cmb.2010.0213</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 21314453?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21314453</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR24">
      <label>24.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ovaska</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Laakso</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hautaniemi</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Fast gene ontology based clustering for microarray experiments</article-title>
        <source>BioData Min</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>1</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>11</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-0381-1-11</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 19025591?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19025591</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR25">
      <label>25.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cao</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sorrentino</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Exploring the associations between drug side-effects and therapeutic indications</article-title>
        <source>J Biomed Inform</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>51</volume>
        <fpage>15</fpage>
        <lpage>23</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbi.2014.03.014</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24727480?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24727480</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR26">
      <label>26.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xuan</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Han</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Guo</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Guo</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ding</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dai</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Teng</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Prediction of microRNAs associated with human diseases based on weighted k most similar neighbors</article-title>
        <source>PLoS One</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <issue>8</issue>
        <fpage>e70204</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0070204</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 23950912?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23950912</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR27">
      <label>27.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yan</surname>
            <given-names>CC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Luo</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ji</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dai</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Constructing lncRNA functional similarity network based on lncRNA-disease associations and disease semantic similarity</article-title>
        <source>Sci Rep</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>5</volume>
        <fpage>11338</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep11338</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 26061969?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26061969</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR28">
      <label>28.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Song</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cui</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Inferring the human microRNA functional similarity and functional network based on microRNA-associated diseases</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>26</volume>
        <issue>13</issue>
        <fpage>1644</fpage>
        <lpage>1650</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq241</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 20439255?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20439255</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR29">
      <label>29.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ma</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fu</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Manifold learning theory and applications</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <publisher-loc>Boca Raton</publisher-loc>
        <publisher-name>CRC; Taylor &amp; Francis distributor</publisher-name>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR30">
      <label>30.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Feature-derived graph regularized matrix factorization for predicting drug side effects</article-title>
        <source>Neurocomputing</source>
        <year>2018</year>
        <volume>287</volume>
        <fpage>154</fpage>
        <lpage>162</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neucom.2018.01.085</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR31">
      <label>31.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rana</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Juneja</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Saxena</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gudwani</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kumaran</surname>
            <given-names>SS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Behari</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Agrawal</surname>
            <given-names>RK</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Graph-theory-based spectral feature selection for computer aided diagnosis of Parkinson's disease using T1-weighted MRI International Journal of Imaging Systems and Technology Volume 25, Issue 3</article-title>
        <source>Int J Imaging Syst Technol</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <fpage>245</fpage>
        <lpage>255</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ima.22141</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR32">
      <label>32.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chung FRK: Spectral graph theory. Providence, R.I.: published for the conference board of the mathematical sciences by the American Mathematical Society; 1997.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR33">
      <label>33.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Drug-target interaction prediction through label propagation with linear neighborhood information</article-title>
        <source>Molecules</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>22</volume>
        <issue>12</issue>
        <fpage>2056</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules22122056</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR34">
      <label>34.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Qu</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The linear neighborhood propagation method for predicting long non-coding RNA–protein interactions</article-title>
        <source>Neurocomputing</source>
        <year>2018</year>
        <volume>273</volume>
        <fpage>526</fpage>
        <lpage>534</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neucom.2017.07.065</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR35">
      <label>35.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhang W, Yue X, Chen Y, Lin W, Li B, Liu F, Li X. Predicting drug-disease associations based on the known association bipartite network. IEEE Int Conf Bioinformatics Biomed. 2017:503–9.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR36">
      <label>36.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhang W, Chen Y, Tu S, Liu F, Qu Q. Drug side effect prediction through linear neighborhoods and multiple data source integration. IEEE Int C Bioinform. 2016:427–34.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR37">
      <label>37.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ruan</surname>
            <given-names>CY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>YC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ma</surname>
            <given-names>JG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>HJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Aickelin</surname>
            <given-names>U</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>SF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>THCluster:herb supplements categorization for precision traditional Chinese medicine</article-title>
        <source>IEEE Int Conf Bioinformatics And Biomedicine</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>2017</volume>
        <fpage>417</fpage>
        <lpage>424</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR38">
      <label>38.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhang W, Yue X, Liu F, Chen YL, Tu SK, Zhang XN. A unified frame of predicting side effects of drugs by using linear neighborhood similarity. BMC Syst Biol. 2017;11</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR39">
      <label>39.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Alvir</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lieberman</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Safferman</surname>
            <given-names>AZ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schwimmer</surname>
            <given-names>JL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schaaf</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Clozapine-induced agranulocytosis. Incidence and risk factors in the United States</article-title>
        <source>N Engl J Med</source>
        <year>1993</year>
        <volume>329</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <fpage>162</fpage>
        <lpage>167</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM199307153290303</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 8515788?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8515788</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR40">
      <label>40.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lieberman</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Alvir</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A report of clozapine-induced agranulocytosis in the United States. Incidence and risk factors</article-title>
        <source>Drug Saf</source>
        <year>1992</year>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <issue>Suppl 1</issue>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <lpage>2</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/00002018-199200071-00003</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 1503671?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1503671</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR41">
      <label>41.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Fujimoto</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hashimoto</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yamamori</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yasuda</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ohi</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Iwatani</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Isaka</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Takeda</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Clozapine improved the syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion in a patient with treatment-resistant schizophrenia</article-title>
        <source>Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>70</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <fpage>469</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pcn.12435</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 27539233?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27539233</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR42">
      <label>42.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Abejuela HR, Festin FE, Lynn E. Clozapine for Treatment- Resistant Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD). J Traum Stress Disord Treatment. 2014;3(2):1–9.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR43">
      <label>43.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kant</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chalansani</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chengappa</surname>
            <given-names>KN</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dieringer</surname>
            <given-names>MF</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The off-label use of clozapine in adolescents with bipolar disorder, intermittent explosive disorder, or posttraumatic stress disorder</article-title>
        <source>J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol</source>
        <year>2004</year>
        <volume>14</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>57</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/104454604773840490</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 15142392?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15142392</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR44">
      <label>44.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Klein</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gordon</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pollak</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rabey</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Clozapine in Parkinson's disease psychosis: 5-year follow-up review</article-title>
        <source>Clin Neuropharmacol</source>
        <year>2003</year>
        <volume>26</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>8</fpage>
        <lpage>11</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00002826-200301000-00003</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 12567158?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12567158</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR45">
      <label>45.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mutlu</surname>
            <given-names>O</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ulak</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Celikyurt</surname>
            <given-names>IK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Akar</surname>
            <given-names>FY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Erden</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tanyeri</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Effects of olanzapine, sertindole and clozapine on MK-801 induced visual memory deficits in mice</article-title>
        <source>Pharmacol Biochem Behav</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>99</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <fpage>557</fpage>
        <lpage>565</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbb.2011.06.011</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 21693127?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21693127</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR46">
      <label>46.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Schatz</surname>
            <given-names>RA</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Olanzapine for psychotic and behavioral disturbances in Alzheimer disease</article-title>
        <source>Ann Pharmacother</source>
        <year>2003</year>
        <volume>37</volume>
        <issue>9</issue>
        <fpage>1321</fpage>
        <lpage>1324</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1345/aph.1D050</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 12921516?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12921516</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR47">
      <label>47.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ambrée</surname>
            <given-names>O</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Richter</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sachser</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lewejohann</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dere</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ma</surname>
            <given-names>DSS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Herring</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Keyvani</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Paulus</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schäbitz</surname>
            <given-names>WR</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Levodopa ameliorates learning and memory deficits in a murine model of Alzheimer's disease</article-title>
        <source>Neurobiol Aging</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>30</volume>
        <issue>8</issue>
        <fpage>1192</fpage>
        <lpage>1204</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neurobiolaging.2007.11.010</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 18079024?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18079024</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR48">
      <label>48.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lópezriquelme</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Alompoveda</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vicianomorote</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Llinaresibor</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tormodíaz</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Apolipoprotein E ε4 allele and malondialdehyde level are independent risk factors for Alzheimer’s disease</article-title>
        <source>SAGE Open Med</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <issue>2016–1-22</issue>
        <fpage>4</fpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR49">
      <label>49.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Carroll</surname>
            <given-names>JC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rosario</surname>
            <given-names>ER</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chang</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stanczyk</surname>
            <given-names>FZ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Oddo</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Laferla</surname>
            <given-names>FM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pike</surname>
            <given-names>CJ</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Progesterone and estrogen regulate Alzheimer-like neuropathology in female 3xTg-AD mice</article-title>
        <source>J. Neurosci. Off. J. Soc. Neurosci</source>
        <year>2007</year>
        <volume>27</volume>
        <issue>48</issue>
        <fpage>13357</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2718-07.2007</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR50">
      <label>50.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hong</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>He</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ly</surname>
            <given-names>PTT</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fox</surname>
            <given-names>CJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Staufenbiel</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cai</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wei</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>CH</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Valproic acid inhibits Aβ production, neuritic plaque formation, and behavioral deficits in Alzheimer's disease mouse models</article-title>
        <source>J Exp Med</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>205</volume>
        <issue>12</issue>
        <fpage>2781</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20081588</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18955571</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR51">
      <label>51.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bate</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Williams</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Ethanol protects cultured neurons against amyloid-β and α-synuclein-induced synapse damage</article-title>
        <source>Neuropharmacology</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>61</volume>
        <issue>8</issue>
        <fpage>1406</fpage>
        <lpage>1412</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropharm.2011.08.030</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 21903110?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21903110</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR52">
      <label>52.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cohen</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Widdows</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Embedding of semantic predications</article-title>
        <source>J Biomed Inform</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>68</volume>
        <fpage>150</fpage>
        <lpage>166</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbi.2017.03.003</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 28284761?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28284761</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR53">
      <label>53.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mower</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Subramanian</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shang</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cohen</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Classification-by-analogy: using vector representations of implicit relationships to identify plausibly causal drug/side-effect relationships</article-title>
        <source>AMIA Annu Symp Proc</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>2016</volume>
        <fpage>1940</fpage>
        <lpage>1949</lpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 28269953?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28269953</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR54">
      <label>54.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fu</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tsuji</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Weng</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Predicting human splicing branchpoints by combining sequence-derived features and multi-label learning methods</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>18</volume>
        <issue>Suppl 13</issue>
        <fpage>464</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-017-1875-6</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 29219070?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29219070</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR55">
      <label>55.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Niu</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zou</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Luo</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Accurate prediction of immunogenic T-cell epitopes from epitope sequences using the genetic algorithm-based ensemble learning</article-title>
        <source>PLoS One</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <issue>5</issue>
        <fpage>e0128194</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128194</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 26020952?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26020952</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR56">
      <label>56.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Luo</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Predicting drug side effects by multi-label learning and ensemble learning</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>16</volume>
        <fpage>365</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-015-0774-y</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 26537615?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26537615</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR57">
      <label>57.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Luo</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Luo</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A genetic algorithm-based weighted ensemble method for predicting transposon-derived piRNAs</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>17</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>329</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-016-1206-3</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 27578422?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27578422</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR58">
      <label>58.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Luo L, Li D, Zhang W, Tu S, Zhu X, Tian G. Accurate prediction of transposon-derived piRNAs by integrating various sequential and physicochemical features. PLoS One. 2016;11(4).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR59">
      <label>59.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhang W, Chen YL, Liu F, Luo F, Tian G, Li XH. Predicting potential drug-drug interactions by integrating chemical, biological, phenotypic and network data. Bmc Bioinformatics. 2017;18:18.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR60">
      <label>60.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shi</surname>
            <given-names>JW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tang</surname>
            <given-names>GF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>WJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yue</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>DF</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Predicting small RNAs in bacteria via sequence learning ensemble method</article-title>
        <source>IEEE Int Conf Bioinformatics Biomed</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>2017</volume>
        <fpage>643</fpage>
        <lpage>647</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
