<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1367-4803</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1367-4811</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6612869</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btz362</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">btz362</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Ismb/Eccb 2019 Conference Proceedings</subject>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading">
          <subject>Comparative and Functional Genomics</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>Selfish: discovery of differential chromatin interactions via a self-similarity measure</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Ardakany</surname>
          <given-names>Abbas Roayaei</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btz362-aff1">1</xref>
        <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="btz362-cor1"/>
        <!--<email>aroay001@ucr.edu</email>-->
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Ay</surname>
          <given-names>Ferhat</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btz362-aff2">2</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btz362-aff3">3</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2696-7274</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Lonardi</surname>
          <given-names>Stefano</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btz362-aff1">1</xref>
        <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="btz362-cor1"/>
        <!--<email>stelo@cs.ucr.edu</email>-->
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <aff id="btz362-aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Computer Science and Engineering, University of California, Riverside, Riverside, CA, USA</aff>
    <aff id="btz362-aff2"><label>2</label>Division of Vaccine Discovery, La Jolla Institute for Allergy and Immunology, UC San Diego, La Jolla, CA, USA</aff>
    <aff id="btz362-aff3"><label>3</label>School of Medicine, Department of Pediatrics, UC San Diego, La Jolla, CA, USA</aff>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="btz362-cor1">To whom correspondence should be addressed. <email>aroay001@ucr.edu</email> or <email>stelo@cs.ucr.edu</email></corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2019</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2019-07-05">
      <day>05</day>
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2019</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>05</day>
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2019</year>
    </pub-date>
    <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
    <volume>35</volume>
    <issue>14</issue>
    <fpage>i145</fpage>
    <lpage>i153</lpage>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2019. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
      <license license-type="cc-by-nc" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xlink:href="btz362.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <sec id="s1">
        <title>Motivation</title>
        <p>High-throughput conformation capture experiments, such as Hi-C provide genome-wide maps of chromatin interactions, enabling life scientists to investigate the role of the three-dimensional structure of genomes in gene regulation and other essential cellular functions. A fundamental problem in the analysis of Hi-C data is how to compare two contact maps derived from Hi-C experiments. Detecting similarities and differences between contact maps are critical in evaluating the reproducibility of replicate experiments and for identifying differential genomic regions with biological significance. Due to the complexity of chromatin conformations and the presence of technology-driven and sequence-specific biases, the comparative analysis of Hi-C data is analytically and computationally challenging.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2">
        <title>Results</title>
        <p>We present a novel method called Selfish for the comparative analysis of Hi-C data that takes advantage of the structural self-similarity in contact maps. We define a novel self-similarity measure to design algorithms for (i) measuring reproducibility for Hi-C replicate experiments and (ii) finding differential chromatin interactions between two contact maps. Extensive experimental results on simulated and real data show that Selfish is more accurate and robust than state-of-the-art methods.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3">
        <title>Availability and implementation</title>
        <p>
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/ucrbioinfo/Selfish">https://github.com/ucrbioinfo/Selfish</ext-link>
        </p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <named-content content-type="funder-name">US National Science Foundation</named-content>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>IOS-1543963</award-id>
        <award-id>IIS-1526742</award-id>
        <award-id>IIS-1814359</award-id>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="9"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec>
    <title>1 Introduction</title>
    <p>Recent studies have revealed that genomic DNA in eukaryotes is not arbitrarily packed into the nucleus. The chromatin has a well-organized and regulated structure in accordance to the stage of the cell cycle and environmental conditions (<xref rid="btz362-B23" ref-type="bibr">Ma <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="btz362-B27" ref-type="bibr">Pederson, 1972</xref>). The chromatin structure in the nucleus plays a critical role in many essential cellular processes, including regulation of gene expression and DNA replication (<xref rid="btz362-B9" ref-type="bibr">Dixon <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>, <xref rid="btz362-B10" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; <xref rid="btz362-B29" ref-type="bibr">Rao <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="btz362-B32" ref-type="bibr">Sexton <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>).</p>
    <p>Technological and scientific advancements in genome-wide DNA proximity ligation (Hi-C) have enabled life scientists to study how chromatin folding regulates cellular functions (<xref rid="btz362-B6" ref-type="bibr">Cavalli and Misteli, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="btz362-B7" ref-type="bibr">Chen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="btz362-B15" ref-type="bibr">Gorkin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="btz362-B20" ref-type="bibr">Lieberman-Aiden <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). The analysis of Hi-C led to the discovery of new structural features of chromosomes such as topologically associating domains (TADs) (<xref rid="btz362-B9" ref-type="bibr">Dixon <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="btz362-B42" ref-type="bibr">Zufferey <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>) and chromatin loops (<xref rid="btz362-B5" ref-type="bibr">Cao <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="btz362-B29" ref-type="bibr">Rao <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>).</p>
    <p>With the decreasing cost of Hi-C experiments and the higher availability of Hi-C data for different cell types in diverse conditions, there is a growing need for reliable and robust measures to systematically compare contact maps to discover similarities and differences. However, the comparative analysis of Hi-C data presents computational and analytical challenges due to presence of technology-driven and sequence-specific biases. Technology-driven biases include sequencing depth, cross-linking conditions, circularization length, and restriction enzyme sites length (<xref rid="btz362-B8" ref-type="bibr">Cournac <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="btz362-B25" ref-type="bibr">O’Sullivan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="btz362-B34" ref-type="bibr">Stansfield and Dozmorov, 2017</xref>). Sequence-specific biases include GC content of trimmed ligation junctions, sequence uniqueness and nucleotide composition (<xref rid="btz362-B38" ref-type="bibr">Yaffe and Tanay, 2011</xref>). For instance, it is well-known that contact maps from replicate experiments can contain significant differences solely due to these biases, which could be falsely interpreted as biological differences if these biases were not accounted for (<xref rid="btz362-B40" ref-type="bibr">Yardimci <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>) . Several normalization methods have been developed to compensate for these biases and improve the reproducibility of Hi-C experiments (e.g. <xref rid="btz362-B18" ref-type="bibr">Imakaev <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="btz362-B19" ref-type="bibr">Knight and Ruiz, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="btz362-B20" ref-type="bibr">Lieberman-Aiden <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="btz362-B38" ref-type="bibr">Yaffe and Tanay, 2011</xref>). While several computational methods have been proposed to extract statistically significant differences in normalized contact maps (<xref rid="btz362-B1" ref-type="bibr">Ay <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="btz362-B4" ref-type="bibr">Cairns <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="btz362-B29" ref-type="bibr">Rao <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="btz362-B30" ref-type="bibr">Ron <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>), their performance is still not entirely satisfactory due to the inherent complexity, inter-dependency and unaccounted biases in chromatin interaction data.</p>
    <p>There are two major domains of application for the comparative analysis of Hi-C contact maps. The first application domain is focused on quantifying the reproducibility of Hi-C biological/technical replicate experiments (<xref rid="btz362-B40" ref-type="bibr">Yardimci <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>). For instance, <xref rid="btz362-B39" ref-type="bibr">Yang <italic>et al.</italic> (2017)</xref> defined a reproducibility measure based on the <italic>stratum-adjusted correlation coefficient statistic</italic> defined on the unique spatial features of Hi-C data. Their method HiCRep (i) reduces the effect of noise and biases by applying a 2D averaging filter on the data, (ii) addresses the distance dependence of Hi-C data by stratifying the data with respect to the genomic distance, (iii) calculates a Pearson correlation coefficient for each stratum and (iv) aggregates the computed stratum-specific correlation coefficients using a weighted average.</p>
    <p>In the same application domain aimed at quantifying reproducibility or concordance of contact maps, <xref rid="btz362-B36" ref-type="bibr">Ursu <italic>et al.</italic> (2018)</xref> presented a method called GenomeDISCO to measure the differences between smoothed contact maps. GenomeDISCO represents contact map as a graph, where each node represents a genomic locus and each edge represents an interaction between two loci. Edges are weighted by the normalized frequency of the corresponding pairs of loci. GenomeDisco executes iteratively the two following steps: (i) traverses the graph using random walks, which has the effect of denoising (smoothing) the data, (ii) computes the normalized difference between smoothed contact maps using the <italic>L</italic><sub>1</sub> distance between two contact maps.</p>
    <p>The second application domain is aimed at finding statistically significant differences between contact maps for cells in different states (tissues, developmental states, healthy/diseased, time-points, etc.). It is well-known that chromatin interactions that are mediated by specific protein can have distinct frequencies in different cell types or in different cell conditions (<xref rid="btz362-B14" ref-type="bibr">Gong <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="btz362-B26" ref-type="bibr">Patel <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Differences in chromatin interactions can be associated with cell-type-specific gene expression or mis-regulation of oncogenes or anti-oncogenes (<xref rid="btz362-B17" ref-type="bibr">Hnisz <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="btz362-B21" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="btz362-B31" ref-type="bibr">Schmitt <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>).</p>
    <p><xref rid="btz362-B37" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref> proposed the first method to discover differences in Hi-C contact maps. The authors used a simple fold change of the normalized local interactions to discover that estrogen stimulation significantly impacts chromatin interactions in MCF7 cells. Building on this idea, <xref rid="btz362-B10" ref-type="bibr">Dixon <italic>et al.</italic> (2015)</xref> proposed a method that (i) quantile normalizes contact maps to compensate for the bias induced by different sequencing depth, and (ii) determines the significance of normalized differences between two contact maps (augmented by feature vectors representing epigenetic signals) using a Random Forest model. Their method can (i) determine whether the epigenetic signal is predictive of changes in interaction frequency and (ii) discover which epigenetic signals are most predictive of changes in higher-order chromatin structure.</p>
    <p><xref rid="btz362-B34" ref-type="bibr">Stansfield and Dozmorov (2017)</xref> developed a non-parametric method to account for between-datasets biases. They used locally weighted polynomial regression to fit a simple model trained on the difference between the two datasets. Based on the assumption that the majority of the interactions should be relatively unchanged among similar Hi-C datasets and by centering the average difference to zero, loci which are far from the average are considered potentially significant differential interaction.</p>
    <p>Unlike other methods which assume independence among pairwise interactions (which holds true only for low resolution Hi-C) <xref rid="btz362-B11" ref-type="bibr">Djekidel <italic>et al.</italic> (2018)</xref> presented a method that takes into account the dependency of adjacent loci in higher resolutions. Based on the fact that interacting neighboring loci are known to be inter-dependent, structural differences can be detected by observing the differences in a neighborhood of the corresponding loci pair. In contrast, random noises tend to affect singular pairwise interactions only. By considering a three-dimensional space in which the <italic>x</italic> and <italic>y</italic> are the coordinates of the genomic loci and <italic>z</italic> is their pairwise interaction frequency, the authors define a chromatin interaction between two conditions to be <italic>differential</italic> when the intensity of the majority of <italic>k</italic>-nearest neighbors of (<italic>x</italic>, <italic>y</italic>) exhibit a significant change.</p>
    <p>In this work, we address three major weaknesses of these existing methods for the comparative analysis of contact maps, namely, (i) ignoring the inter-dependency of chromatin interactions, (ii) requiring a pre-processing (normalization) step based on a flawed assumption that biases between two contact maps can be accurately modeled and (iii) being extremely computationally demanding for the analysis of high-resolution Hi-C data. We present new comparative methods for the analysis of Hi-C data based on the notion of self-similarity (<xref rid="btz362-B33" ref-type="bibr">Shechtman and Irani, 2007</xref>). We show that our self-similarity measure is robust to biases and does not need complex and computationally intensive normalization steps, such as Minus versus Average (MA) (<xref rid="btz362-B12" ref-type="bibr">Dudoit <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>) or Minus versus Distance (MD) (<xref rid="btz362-B34" ref-type="bibr">Stansfield and Dozmorov, 2017</xref>). In the first part of the paper, we show that our self-similarity measure can be used as a tool to quantify the reproducibility of Hi-C biological/technical replicate experiments. In the second part, we show that our measure can also be employed for finding statistically significant differences between Hi-C contact maps.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>2 Materials and methods</title>
    <p>Although existing methods for comparing contact maps vary widely, they all share the following assumption. Given two contact maps that are expected to be similar (e.g. technical replicates of the same biological experiment), it is possible to devise (or train) a common underlying model can faithfully represent both. We believe that this approach is fundamentally flawed, because the inherent biases present in the Hi-C data are very hard to model and completely eliminate. Here we propose to use the intrinsic self-similarity structure in contact maps to avoid dealing with the modeling problem.</p>
    <p>In the application domain of object detection in complex visual data, the notion of self-similarity was first introduced by <xref rid="btz362-B33" ref-type="bibr">Shechtman and Irani (2007)</xref>. The idea of self-similarity on images can be explained as follows. <xref rid="btz362-B33" ref-type="bibr">Shechtman and Irani (2007)</xref> showed that given two images of a certain object, the most relevant correlations between them are not necessarily the raw values of pixels (or an underlying model describing those pixel values) but the internal organization of self-similarities of local regions at similar relative geometric positions. Given two images of the same object, the relation between these local self-similarities tend to be more preserved than the similarities between the images.</p>
    <sec>
      <title>2.1 Self-similarity and reproducibility</title>
      <p>As said, existing methods for measuring the reproducibility of Hi-C experiments compute correlations or distances between normalized interaction frequencies of loci pairs, which is error-prone due to technology-driven and sequence-specific biases. Here we show that this comparison can be done indirectly by using self-similarity.</p>
      <p>When we compare two contact maps that are expected to be similar, e.g. for two technical replicates of the same biological experiment, we expect to have similar internal layout of interactions. More precisely, given two contact maps <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic> for two replicates, if we observe more chromatin interactions in block <italic>α</italic> than in block <italic>β</italic> in contact map <italic>A</italic>, we expect to have more chromatin interactions in block <italic>α</italic> than block <italic>β</italic> in contact map <italic>B</italic> as well, for several local choices of <italic>α</italic>, <italic>β</italic>. In other words, to measure similarity we do not need to depend on the absolute number of interactions in each contact map, rather we can rely on pairwise comparison between many local interactions. Here we claim that the Boolean vectors representing binary comparison between local interactions encode enough information to define a similarity measure that can be used to quantify reproducibility for contact maps.</p>
      <p>Henceforth, a Hi-C contact map is a <italic>N </italic>×<italic> N</italic> matrix where entry (<italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic>) in the matrix denotes the frequency of interaction between locus (or <italic>bin</italic>) <italic>i</italic> and locus (or <italic>bin</italic>) <italic>j</italic> in the genome. First, we slide a square block of size <inline-formula id="IE1"><mml:math id="IM1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> along the main diagonal of the contact map using a stride of <inline-formula id="IE2"><mml:math id="IM2"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> so each pair of adjacent blocks overlap by half of their size. For each position of the sliding block, we compute the sum of interaction frequencies inside the block. We store these sums in vector <italic>B</italic>, which has 2<italic>k</italic> components. Then, we compare all <inline-formula id="IE3"><mml:math id="IM3"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> pairs of block sums, and set the matrix <inline-formula id="IE4"><mml:math id="IM4"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for all choices of <inline-formula id="IE5"><mml:math id="IM5"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <bold>I</bold> is the indicator function.</p>
      <p>We claim that the matrix <italic>C</italic> is a compact representation of the interaction distribution along the main diagonal of the contact maps, which is robust to noise and biases (thus does not require normalization) because it relies on comparing entities that belong to the same contact map, and not across maps. We compute the similarity <inline-formula id="IE6"><mml:math id="IM6"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> between contact map <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic> as follows
<disp-formula id="E1"><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:malignmark/><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>‖</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>‖</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msub><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <italic>c</italic> is a constant, <italic>C<sub>A</sub></italic> is the Boolean matrix for contact map <italic>A</italic>, <italic>C<sub>B</sub></italic> is the Boolean matrix for contact map <italic>B</italic>. The value of <italic>k</italic> should be chosen so that the size of the resulting blocks <italic>N</italic>/<italic>k</italic> is sufficient large to enclose important chromatin structures (e.g. TADs). Parameters <italic>c</italic> and <italic>k</italic> are determined experimentally.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>2.2 Self-similarity and differential chromatin interactions</title>
      <p>For the accurate detection of differential chromatin interactions (DCI), we need to be able to distinguish true differences (which might have biological relevance) from differences caused by biases or other artifacts in the data. Since there is no ground truth for DCIs between cell types, conditions or developmental stages, there is no possibility of learning from real examples. The only differences that can be trusted are those that significantly exceed the differences observed between biological replicates. For this reason, we can also employ our self-similarity metric in a method for finding DCIs between two Hi-C contact maps. In our self-similarity representation described below, each interaction frequency is represented by a series of comparison between its surrounding local regions.</p>
      <p>We first observe that DCIs have <italic>locality</italic> properties. If contact map <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic> have a DCI at coordinate (<italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic>), this is not only reflected in the interaction difference of <inline-formula id="IE7"><mml:math id="IM7"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> but also in the neighborhood of (<italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic>). We call <italic>impact region</italic> the neighborhood affected by the DCI. We call <italic>impact radius</italic> the size of the neighborhood being affected, which is proportional to the magnitude of the DCI. We argue that what determines the statistical significance of a DCI in a particular location (<italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic>) does not only depend on the statistical significance of the difference <inline-formula id="IE8"><mml:math id="IM8"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> but also on the statistical significance of the difference between their region centered at (<italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic>). Isolated locations that have the large interaction frequency differences are often not significant and are likely to be due to noise or other artifacts.</p>
      <p>To incorporate locality information in our self-similarity representation, each interaction <italic>A</italic>(<italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic>) is represented by a linear combination of its neighboring interactions. To penalize interactions which are progressively farther from (<italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic>), we weight these local interactions via a Gaussian filter centered at (<italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic>) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="btz362-F1">Fig. 1</xref> for an example). By gradually increasing the size of the Gaussian filter, we capture impact regions with larger and larger radii. We denote with <inline-formula id="IE9"><mml:math id="IM9"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the matrix resulting from the convolution between a Gaussian filter with radius <italic>r<sub>k</sub></italic> and the contact map <italic>A</italic>. We first compute <inline-formula id="IE10"><mml:math id="IM10"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for a set of <italic>n</italic> radii <inline-formula id="IE11"><mml:math id="IM11"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and collect them in vector Γ<sub><italic>A</italic></sub> as follows
<disp-formula id="E2"><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Γ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
      <fig id="btz362-F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Our self-similarity metric for representing chromatin interactions is obtained by first convolving a contact map with a set of Gaussian filters with radii <inline-formula id="IE12"><mml:math id="IM12"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The shade represents the intensity of the convolution for different radii. In this example, a sharp frequency change can be observed between radius <italic>r</italic><sub>2</sub> and <italic>r</italic><sub>3</sub> in contact map <italic>A</italic> but not in contact map <italic>B</italic>. This difference can indicate a potential DCI</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="btz362f1"/>
      </fig>
      <p>It is well-known that interactions in Hi-C contact maps are more frequent when the pairs of interacting loci are closer in genomic distance due to random polymer interactions driven by one-dimensional genome proximity. To compensate for the amplification of contact frequency due to proximity, we <italic>Z</italic>-normalize the interaction frequencies in <italic>A</italic> with respect to their genomic distances along each diagonal <italic>d</italic> as follows.
<disp-formula id="E3"><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>μ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>σ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula id="IE13"><mml:math id="IM13"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula id="IE14"><mml:math id="IM14"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>μ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>σ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are the average and the standard deviation along the diagonal <italic>d</italic>, respectively.</p>
      <p>If (<italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic>) is not a DCI between <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>, we expect vectors <inline-formula id="IE15"><mml:math id="IM15"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Γ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IE16"><mml:math id="IM16"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Γ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to exhibit similar trends along their components, because they represents aggregate interaction frequency in gradually increasing neighborhood centered at (<italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic>). If (<italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic>) is a DCI with impact radius <italic>r</italic>, we expect to observe a significant difference between the <italic>k</italic>th Gaussian representations of that interaction, where <italic>k</italic> is the index of the radius <italic>r<sub>k</sub></italic> closest to <italic>r</italic>. Due to biases in the interaction frequencies across different contact maps, the difference between the two feature vectors <inline-formula id="IE17"><mml:math id="IM17"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Γ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IE18"><mml:math id="IM18"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Γ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> cannot be directly used to indicate the significance of a change. We address this issue by take advantage of self-similarity, i.e. by using local comparison of local regions in contact maps.</p>
      <p>According to <xref rid="btz362-B24" ref-type="bibr">Mikolajczyk (2002)</xref>, the Gaussian filter scale <italic>r</italic> must be distributed exponentially between the inner (<italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub>) and outer (<italic>r<sub>n</sub></italic>) scale limits (impact radii) <inline-formula id="IE19"><mml:math id="IM19"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, in order to maintain a uniform change of information between successive levels of Gaussian filtering. For 5-kb resolution data, we set <inline-formula id="IE20"><mml:math id="IM20"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <italic>s </italic> =<italic> </italic> 2 and <italic>n  </italic>= <italic> </italic>10.</p>
      <p>Inspired by the work of <xref rid="btz362-B22" ref-type="bibr">Lowe (2004</xref>), instead of using Γ to define the behavior of interaction frequency across a set of impact regions, we use the first-order derivative of Γ with respect to impact radius <italic>r</italic>, which can be estimated by the difference <inline-formula id="IE21"><mml:math id="IM21"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.
<disp-formula id="E4"><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>Γ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dr</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:mo>Δ</mml:mo><mml:mo>Γ</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
      <p>By computing the first-order derivative for various choices of the impact radii, we carry out a comparison of local contact map regions (<inline-formula id="IE22"><mml:math id="IM22"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="btz362-F2">Figure 2</xref> shows the first-order derivatives of <inline-formula id="IE23"><mml:math id="IM23"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Γ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IE24"><mml:math id="IM24"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Γ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and the difference between them for the DCI reported later in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="btz362-F8">Figure 8</xref>. Observe the sharp change between the derivatives at radius <italic>r</italic><sub>2</sub> which corresponds to a DCI with that radius.
</p>
      <fig id="btz362-F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The first-order derivatives <inline-formula id="IE25"><mml:math id="IM25"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Δ</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Γ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IE26"><mml:math id="IM26"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Δ</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Γ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and the difference between them for the DCI reported later in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="btz362-F8">Figure 8</xref>. A large difference between <inline-formula id="IE27"><mml:math id="IM27"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Δ</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Γ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IE28"><mml:math id="IM28"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Δ</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Γ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> at radius <italic>r</italic><sub>2</sub> indicates the presence of a potential DCI</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="btz362f2"/>
      </fig>
      <p>In the last step of our algorithm, we compute the mean <italic>μ</italic> and standard deviation <italic>σ</italic> for the normal distribution fitted on the difference of the first-order derivatives <inline-formula id="IE29"><mml:math id="IM29"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Δ</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Γ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo>Δ</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Γ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for each radius <italic>r<sub>k</sub></italic>. Then, we compute the <italic>P</italic>-value <inline-formula id="IE30"><mml:math id="IM30"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for location (<italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic>) and radius <italic>r<sub>k</sub></italic> as follows
<disp-formula id="E5"><mml:math id="M5"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">P</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Γ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dr</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Γ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dr</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula id="IE31"><mml:math id="IM31"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>μ</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>σ</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
      <p>From the set of <italic>k P</italic>-values for each index (<italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic>), we choose the smallest <italic>P</italic>-value of the difference between two contact maps <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic> at that index, as follows.
<disp-formula id="E6"><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mi>min</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
      <p>These <italic>P</italic>-values <inline-formula id="IE32"><mml:math id="IM32"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are finally fed into the Benjamini–Hochberg algorithm to calculate the final probabilities (<xref rid="btz362-B2" ref-type="bibr">Benjamini and Hochberg, 1995</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>3 Results</title>
    <sec>
      <title>3.1 Reproducibility</title>
      <p>We evaluated our reproducibility measure on a Hi-C dataset obtained from <xref rid="btz362-B31" ref-type="bibr">Schmitt <italic>et al.</italic> (2016)</xref> that has a variable total number of interactions and resolution. The dataset consists of five different cell types: hESC (H1), Mesendoderm (MES), Mesenchymal Stem Cell (MSC), Neural Progenitor Cell (NPC) and Trophoblast-like Cell (TRO). Each cell type has two biological replicates. All experiments were carried out on a single chromosome (chromosome 1 for this work) with 40 kb resolution. According to our experience, parameter <italic>c</italic> is dependent on the particular Hi-C protocol used. Parameter <italic>k</italic> must be chosen such that the resulting blocks enclose the primary structures of contact maps which are likely to be preserved between cell types, e.g. TADs. Parameter <italic>c</italic> has to be set to the largest integer value such that the computed reproducibility for biological replicates is at least 0.9. For this dataset, we set <italic>k </italic>=<italic> </italic>100 and <italic>c </italic>=<italic> </italic>5. We compared our method Selfish against two state-of-the-art reproducibility methods, namely HiCRep (<xref rid="btz362-B39" ref-type="bibr">Yang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>) and GenomeDISCO (<xref rid="btz362-B36" ref-type="bibr">Ursu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>).</p>
      <p>First, we assessed the effect of the total number of intra-chromosomal interactions captured by Hi-C experiment on different reproducibility measure. Given two biological replicates, we generated pseudo-replicates by first summing the two Hi-C matrices and then down-sampling the resulting matrix. Any pair of contact maps, which are either replicates or pseudo-replicates are called <italic>non-replicates</italic>. Next, each individual replicate was down-sampled to a wide range of total interactions (<inline-formula id="IE33"><mml:math id="IM33"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). For each of these choices, we computed the pair-wise reproducibility score.</p>
      <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="btz362-F3">Figure 3a–c</xref> illustrates the effect of the total number of interactions (which depends on the Hi-C sequencing depth) on the performance of reproducibility measures. A desirable feature for a reproducibility measure is to produce similarity scores that are invariant from the total number of interactions. Observe in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="btz362-F3">Figure 3a–c</xref> that Selfish is much more invariant to the total number of interactions than HiCRep and GenomeDISCO. Both these latter methods failed to report stable reproducibility scores which are independent from the sequencing depth.
</p>
      <fig id="btz362-F3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Illustrating the effect of the total number of interactions on reproducibility score of (<bold>a</bold>) non-replicates, (<bold>b</bold>) pseudo-replicates and (<bold>c</bold>) biological replicates. Panel (<bold>d</bold>) illustrates the effect of data resolution (bin size) on reproducibility score of two replicates of cell type GM12878 from <xref rid="btz362-B29" ref-type="bibr">Rao <italic>et al.</italic> (2014)</xref></p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="btz362f3"/>
      </fig>
      <p>In the next experiment, we evaluated the effect of binning resolution of Hi-C data on the reproducibility methods. For this experiment, we used deeply sequenced Hi-C data of cell type GM12878 from <xref rid="btz362-B29" ref-type="bibr">Rao <italic>et al.</italic> (2014)</xref>. Again, a desirable property of a reproducibility score is to be robust to changes in resolution. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="btz362-F3">Figure 3d</xref> shows that reproducibility scores for 5 kb, 10 kb, 25 kb, 50 kb and 500 kb resolutions are very stable for Selfish, whereas HiCRep and GenomeDISCO scores are resolution dependent, in particular for GenomeDISCO.</p>
      <p>We also tested our reproducibility measure to cluster different cell and tissue types. Contact maps of 14 different tissues and 2 cell types were obtained from <xref rid="btz362-B31" ref-type="bibr">Schmitt <italic>et al.</italic> (2016)</xref>. A visual inspection of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="btz362-F4">Figure 4</xref> shows that our reproducibility measure can cluster similar cell and tissue types. For instance, observe that Selfish correctly clusters the right and left ventricles, IMR90 and lung as well as hippocampus and cortex together.
</p>
      <fig id="btz362-F4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 4.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Clustering of 14 human primary tissues and two cell lines obtained from <xref rid="btz362-B31" ref-type="bibr">Schmitt <italic>et al.</italic> (2016)</xref>. The dendrograms are computed based on the pairwise similarity calculated using (<bold>a</bold>) GenomeDisco, (<bold>b</bold>) Selfish and (<bold>c</bold>) HiCRep</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="btz362f4"/>
      </fig>
      <p>These experimental results clearly indicate that Selfish outperforms existing methods in terms of robustness to changes in sequencing depth and binning size. Both of these are very desirable features which can significantly simplify Hi-C data analysis in terms of quality control for reproducibility in replicate experiments.</p>
      <p>We also compared the average running time of the three methods on two replicates of cell type GM12878 from <xref rid="btz362-B29" ref-type="bibr">Rao <italic>et al.</italic> (2014)</xref>. <xref rid="btz362-T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> shows that Selfish is by far more efficient than HiCRep and GenomeDISCO.</p>
      <table-wrap id="btz362-T1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Table 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Average running time of HiCRep, GenomeDisco and Selfish for different choices of the data resolution</p>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
          <colgroup span="1">
            <col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/>
            <col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/>
            <col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/>
            <col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/>
            <col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/>
            <col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Method</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">500 kb</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 kb</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 kb</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 kb</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 kb</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HiCRep</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 s</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">636 s</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1045 s</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 479 s</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <inline-formula id="IE34">
                  <mml:math id="IM34">
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:msup>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msup>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:math>
                </inline-formula>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenomeDisco</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 s</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2989 s</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4933 s</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 238 s</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 004 s</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Selfish</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75 s</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 s</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">184 s</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">345 s</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">474 s</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="tblfn1">
            <label>a</label>
            <p>HiCRep fails to run on 5-kb data on a server machine with 256 GB of RAM.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>3.2 Differential chromatin interaction</title>
      <p>We compared Selfish to the current state-of-the-art method for detecting differential chromatin interaction called FIND (<xref rid="btz362-B11" ref-type="bibr">Djekidel <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>). To the best of our knowledge, FIND is the only DCI detection method which works on high-resolution Hi-C data by taking into account the chromatin interactions inter-dependency. Extensive experimental results in <xref rid="btz362-B11" ref-type="bibr">Djekidel <italic>et al.</italic> (2018)</xref> show that FIND performs better than previously published methods for DCI detection.</p>
      <p>We ran Selfish and FIND on Hi-C contact maps for cell types GM12878 and K562 obtained from <xref rid="btz362-B29" ref-type="bibr">Rao <italic>et al.</italic> (2014)</xref>. We replicated some of the experiments proposed in <xref rid="btz362-B11" ref-type="bibr">Djekidel <italic>et al.</italic> (2018)</xref> in order to make a fair comparison with FIND. First, we analyzed the enrichment of epigenetic signals in the neighborhood of detected DCIs as well as the percentage of nearby genes having significant expression fold changes. We evaluated the enrichment of four important epigenetic markers, namely the binding of CTCF, POLII and P300, as well as the presence of histone modification H3K4me3. CTCF is widely recognized as a main driver of chromatin structure (<xref rid="btz362-B29" ref-type="bibr">Rao <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="btz362-B35" ref-type="bibr">Tang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). We computed the enrichment of CTCF differential peaks (i.e. peaks that are different between two cell types) around detected DCIs. For this part of the analysis, we obtained the FIND’s detected DCIs from <xref rid="btz362-B11" ref-type="bibr">Djekidel <italic>et al.</italic> (2018)</xref>.</p>
      <p>To compute the enrichment of each marker in the neighborhood of the detected DCIs, we calculated the distance of marker peaks to their closest anchor of DCIs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="btz362-F5">Figure 5</xref> shows the enrichment of epigenetic markers near DCIs. Observe that CTCF and H3K4me3 are more enriched around the <sc>Selfish’</sc>s reported DCIs than those detected by FIND, even though the number of reported DCIs for Selfish is twice as large (30 456 versus 14 131).
</p>
      <fig id="btz362-F5" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 5.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Enrichment of differential transcription factor binding and epigenetic marks (CTCF, POLII, P300 and H3K4me3) around reported DCIs for (<bold>a</bold>) cell type GM12878 and (<bold>b</bold>) cell type K562</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="btz362f5"/>
      </fig>
      <p>We also calculated the expression fold change of nearby genes for the two cell types. We first determined the set of genes which have overlap with any of the detected DCIs’ anchors. Then we computed the percentage of those genes having an expression fold change of two or greater. For the set of genes overlapping FIND’s DCIs, 71.46% of them were over-expressed. For Selfish, 78.78% were over-expressed. This analysis confirmed that the differences in chromatin structure are strongly associated with the changes in gene regulation. However, the DCIs detected by Selfish have stronger associations to differences in gene regulation than FIND. For the gene expression analysis, we used the dataset from <xref rid="btz362-B11" ref-type="bibr">Djekidel <italic>et al.</italic> (2018)</xref>. The expression data were obtained from ENCODE, accession numbers GSE78553 and GSE78625, for cell types GM12878 and K562, respectively.</p>
      <p>To quantify how well the Hi-C data supported the detected DCIs between two cell types GM12878 and K562, we generated a modified aggregate peak analysis (APA) plots (<xref rid="btz362-B28" ref-type="bibr">Phanstiel <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="btz362-B29" ref-type="bibr">Rao <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). The interaction frequencies in contact maps were first Z-normalized along the diagonals as explained in Section 2. Then, for each detected DCI, we calculated the interaction differences between the contact maps in a  ±-50Kb neighborhood. By averaging over all DCIs, we computed the APA plot for differences. The differential APA score, i.e. the value of the central index in the plot compared to neighboring regions shows how different the interactions are at reported DCIs with respect to their expected interaction frequency with that genomic distance.</p>
      <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="btz362-F6">Figure 6</xref> shows that Selfish produces the expected Gaussian-shaped plot around its reported DCIs while the DCIs from FIND failed to generate a similar pattern. Correspondingly, the computed APA score is higher for Selfish (4.46) compared to FIND (3.06) suggesting a stronger detection of DCIs. Finally the peak pixel of the APA plot for FIND (score of 4.17) is not centered on the called DCI pairs suggesting that Selfish performs better at pinpointing anchor points of chromatin interactions at high resolution.
</p>
      <fig id="btz362-F6" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 6.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>A modified APA plots for reported DCIs between two cell types GM12878 and K562 by (<bold>a</bold>) Selfish and (<bold>b</bold>) FIND</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="btz362f6"/>
      </fig>
      <p>We also compared the runtime of FIND and Selfish on the 5-kb-resolution dataset described above. FIND failed to run on the whole genome or even on large segments of contact maps. To compare the efficiency of Selfish and FIND, we computed the average runtime required to process random contact map segments of 6 Mb. Selfish took an average of 101.6 s. FIND required an average of 12 839.6 s, about 120× slower than Selfish.</p>
      <p>To further investigate the accuracy of detected DCIs, we used simulated Hi-C data generated by the method proposed in <xref rid="btz362-B41" ref-type="bibr">Zhou <italic>et al.</italic> (2014)</xref>. We generated 100 pairs of simulated contact maps, each of which had known location for DCIs. After running Selfish and FIND on these simulated datasets, we obtained a <italic>P</italic>-value for each DCI location for all 100 simulated pairs of contact maps. Given the <italic>P</italic>-values and the true locations of DCIs (true positives), we computed a precision–recall curve for each simulated pair of contact maps. We used the threshold averaging method proposed by <xref rid="btz362-B13" ref-type="bibr">Fawcett (2006)</xref> to combine the 100 precision–recall curves to get the overall performance curve. We thresholded over the ratio of all indices in the contact map used for computing the precision and recall for each simulated pair. To combine the curves, we averaged all 100 calculated precision and recall values for each threshold. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="btz362-F7">Figure 7a–c</xref> shows the performance of both methods for 2-fold, 5-fold and 10-fold DCIs. The vertical and horizontal bars represent the 95% confidence interval for precision and recall at that threshold respectively. Selfish performed better than FIND on all fold change settings, confirming the stronger performance that we observed on real Hi-C data. The performance difference is most striking for small fold change values, which are more relevant for comparisons of real Hi-C datasets and yet have a very large effect on gene regulation (<xref rid="btz362-B16" ref-type="bibr">Greenwald <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>). It is also important to note that <sc>Selfish’</sc>s performance is quite consistent across different samples as indicated by small confidence intervals.
</p>
      <fig id="btz362-F7" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 7.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Precision–recall curves for Selfish (magenta) and FIND (green) for (<bold>a</bold>) 2-fold, (<bold>b</bold>) 5-fold and (<bold>c</bold>) 10-fold DCIs. The vertical and horizontal bars represent the 95% confidence interval for precision and recall at that threshold respectively. (<bold>d</bold>) The distribution of distances of FPs to closest TPs</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="btz362f7"/>
      </fig>
      <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="btz362-F7">Figure 7d</xref> shows the distribution of distances between false positive DCIs produced by Selfish and FIND to true DCIs (true positives). To generate this figure, we set the number of returned DCIs equal to the number of true DCIs. Then, for each falsely detected DCI, we calculated its distance to the closest true DCI. These results clearly show that most of <sc>Selfish’</sc>s false positives are located in close proximity of true DCIs confirming their relevance to true differences and their non-random distribution. FIND’s false positive are instead much farther from true DCIs and are more scattered in the contact map.</p>
      <p>In our final experiment to assess the performance of two methods, we tested Selfish and FIND on a real test case from <xref rid="btz362-B3" ref-type="bibr">Bonev <italic>et al.</italic> (2017)</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="btz362-F8">Figure 8</xref> shows a 2-Mb region around the <italic>Brn2</italic> promoter (also known as <italic>Pou3f2</italic>) for mouse embryonic stem cells (ES) and neuronal progenitor cells (NPC). Dashed circles show the contact between the <italic>Brn2</italic> promoter and an NPC specific enhancer. Insets show the magnified view of this contact. Observe that the contact between the promoter and enhancer is strongly present in the NPC cell (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="btz362-F8">Fig. 8a</xref>) in contrast with the ES cell in which this interaction is weak (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="btz362-F8">Fig. 8b</xref>). The mentioned contrast shows itself as a subtle but important difference of interactions between two cell types. The highlighted regions of the epigenetic signals show the difference in the specified regions between two cell types. Detected DCIs by Selfish and FIND for <italic>q</italic>-value <inline-formula id="IE35"><mml:math id="IM35"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are shown in magenta and green squares, respectively. Observe that Selfish can identify this contact region as a DCI between two cell types, but FIND fails to detect it.
</p>
      <fig id="btz362-F8" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 8.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>A 2-Mb region shown around Brn2 promoter of chromosome 4 of mouse neural cells: (<bold>a</bold>) ES and (<bold>b</bold>) NPC. Dashed circles show the contact between the Brn2 promoter and an NPC-specific enhancer. Insets show the magnified view of this contact</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="btz362f8"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>4 Conclusion</title>
    <p>We presented a new approach for comparative analysis of Hi-C data using a novel self-similarity measure. We showed the utility of our measure by providing solutions to two important problems in the analysis of Hi-C data, namely the problem of measuring reproducibility of replicated Hi-C experiments and the problem of finding differential chromatin interactions between two contact maps.</p>
    <p>We showed that a simple binary comparison operation between blocks in the contact maps can be used to encode the local and global features in a manner that is robust to the data resolution and sequencing depth. This encoded information is used to build a feature vector for each contact map, which in turn allows to define a simple but effective similarity metric using the distance between their feature vectors. Experimental results showed that our self-similarity-based measure outperformed two state-of-the-art methods (HiCRep and GenomeDISCO) for measuring reproducibility of replicated Hi-C experiments.</p>
    <p>We also introduced a new method for finding differential chromatin interactions between two contact maps. Selfish is designed based on the idea that each pairwise chromatin interaction can be represented by its neighboring interactions. Therefore, each interaction difference reveal itself as a weighted impact on the neighboring interactions. We capture this impact using a set of gradually increasing Gaussian filters. By extensively testing Selfish on simulated and real test data, we showed that it outperforms the state-of-the-art DCI detection method FIND both in accuracy and efficiency.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>Funding</title>
    <p>This work was supported, in part, by the US National Science Foundation [IOS-1543963, IIS-1526742, IIS-1814359].</p>
    <p><italic>Conflict of Interest</italic>: none declared.</p>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ref-list id="ref1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="btz362-B1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ay</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) 
<article-title>Statistical confidence estimation for Hi-C data reveals regulatory chromatin contacts</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>., <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>999</fpage>–<lpage>1011</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24501021</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) 
<article-title>Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</article-title>. <source>J. R. Stat. Soc. B</source>, <volume>57</volume>, <fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonev</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) 
<article-title>Multiscale 3D genome rewiring during mouse neural development</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>171</volume>, <fpage>557</fpage>–<lpage>572.e24</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29053968</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cairns</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) 
<article-title>CHiCAGO: robust detection of DNA looping interactions in capture Hi-C data</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>., <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>127.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27306882</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) Accurate loop calling for 3d genomic data with cLoops. bioRxiv, doi:10.1101/465849.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cavalli</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Misteli</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) 
<article-title>Functional implications of genome topology</article-title>. <source>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol</source>., <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>290</fpage>–<lpage>299</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23463314</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) 
<article-title>Functional organization of the human 4D nucleome</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>112</volume>, <fpage>8002</fpage>–<lpage>8007</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26080430</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B8">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cournac</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>Normalization of a chromosomal contact map</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>436.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22935139</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B9">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>Topological domains in mammalian genomes identified by analysis of chromatin interactions</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>485</volume>, <fpage>376</fpage>–<lpage>380</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22495300</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B10">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) 
<article-title>Chromatin architecture reorganization during stem cell differentiation</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>518</volume>, <fpage>331</fpage>–<lpage>336</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25693564</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B11">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Djekidel</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) 
<article-title>FIND: difFerential chromatin INteractions Detection using a spatial Poisson process</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>., [Epub ahead of print, doi:10.1101/gr.212241.116, February 12, 2018].</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B12">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dudoit</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) 
<article-title>Statistical methods for identifying differentially expressed genes in replicated CDNA microarray experiments</article-title>. <source>Stat. Sin</source>., <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>139</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B13">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fawcett</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) 
<article-title>An introduction to ROC analysis</article-title>. <source>Pattern Recognit. Lett</source>., <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>861</fpage>–<lpage>874</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B14">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) 
<article-title>The BCL2 gene is regulated by a special AT-rich sequence binding protein 1-mediated long range chromosomal interaction between the promoter and the distal element located within the 3’-UTR</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>4640</fpage>–<lpage>4652</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21310710</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B15">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorkin</surname><given-names>D.U.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) 
<article-title>The 3D genome in transcriptional regulation and pluripotency</article-title>. <source>Cell Stem Cell</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>762</fpage>–<lpage>775</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24905166</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B16">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenwald</surname><given-names>W.W.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) Integration of phased Hi-C and molecular phenotype data to study genetic and epigenetic effects on chromatin looping. bioRxiv, doi:10.1101/352682.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B17">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hnisz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) 
<article-title>Activation of proto-oncogenes by disruption of chromosome neighborhoods</article-title>. <source>Science</source>, <volume>351</volume>, <fpage>1454</fpage>–<lpage>1458</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26940867</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B18">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Imakaev</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>Iterative correction of Hi-C data reveals hallmarks of chromosome organization</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>999</fpage>–<lpage>1003</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22941365</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B19">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) 
<article-title>A fast algorithm for matrix balancing</article-title>. <source>IMA J. Numer. Anal</source>., <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>1029</fpage>–<lpage>1047</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B20">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lieberman-Aiden</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) 
<article-title>Comprehensive mapping of long-range interactions reveals folding principles of the human genome</article-title>. <source>Science</source>, <volume>326</volume>, <fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>293</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19815776</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B21">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) 
<article-title>TiGER: a database for tissue-specific gene expression and regulation</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>271.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18541026</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B22">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>D.G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) 
<article-title>Distinctive image features from scale-invariant keypoints</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Comput. Vis</source>., <volume>60</volume>, <fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>110</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B23">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) 
<article-title>How the cell cycle impacts chromatin architecture and influences cell fate</article-title>. <source>Front. Genet</source>., <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>19.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25691891</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B24">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikolajczyk</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) Detection of local features invariant to affine transformations: application to matching and recognition. PhD Thesis, Grenoble INPG, Grenoble, France.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B25">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Sullivan</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) 
<article-title>The statistical-mechanics of chromosome conformation capture</article-title>. <source>Nucleus</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>390</fpage>–<lpage>398</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24051548</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B26">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>CTCF mediated enhancer and promoter interaction regulates differential expression of TAL1 oncogene in normal and malignant hematopoiesis</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>, <volume>120</volume>, <fpage>281</fpage>–<lpage>281</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B27">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pederson</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1972</year>) 
<article-title>Chromatin structure and the cell cycle</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>69</volume>, <fpage>2224</fpage>–<lpage>2228</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4626402</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B28">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Phanstiel</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) 
<article-title>Mango: a bias-correcting ChIA-PET analysis pipeline</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>3092</fpage>–<lpage>3098</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26034063</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B29">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>S.S.P.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) 
<article-title>A 3D map of the human genome at kilobase resolution reveals principles of chromatin looping</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>159</volume>, <fpage>1665</fpage>–<lpage>1680</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25497547</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B30">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ron</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) 
<article-title>Promoter-enhancer interactions identified from Hi-C data using probabilistic models and hierarchical topological domains</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun</source>., <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>2237.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29269730</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B31">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) 
<article-title>A compendium of chromatin contact maps reveals spatially active regions in the human genome</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep</source>., <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>2042</fpage>–<lpage>2059</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27851967</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B32">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sexton</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>Three-dimensional folding and functional organization principles of the drosophila genome</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>148</volume>, <fpage>458</fpage>–<lpage>472</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22265598</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B33">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shechtman</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Irani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) Matching local self-similarities across images and videos. In: <italic>2007 IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition</italic> pp. <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>, 17-22 June 2007, Minneapolis, MN, USA.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B34">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stansfield</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dozmorov</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) HiCcompare: an R-package for joint normalization and comparison of HI-C datasets. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-018-2288-x</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B35">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) 
<article-title>CTCF-mediated human 3D genome architecture reveals chromatin topology for transcription</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>163</volume>, <fpage>1611</fpage>–<lpage>1627</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26686651</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B36">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ursu</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) 
<article-title>GenomeDISCO: a concordance score for chromosome conformation capture experiments using random walks on contact map graphs</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>2701</fpage>–<lpage>2707</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29554289</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B37">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) 
<article-title>Genome-wide analysis uncovers high frequency, strong differential chromosomal interactions and their associated epigenetic patterns in e2-mediated gene regulation</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>70.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23368971</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B38">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yaffe</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tanay</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) 
<article-title>Probabilistic modeling of Hi-C contact maps eliminates systematic biases to characterize global chromosomal architecture</article-title>. <source>Nat. Genet</source>., <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>1059</fpage>–<lpage>1065</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22001755</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B39">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) 
<article-title>HiCRep: assessing the reproducibility of Hi-C data using a stratum-adjusted correlation coefficient</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>., <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>1939</fpage>–<lpage>1949</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28855260</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B40">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yardimci</surname><given-names>GG.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) Measuring the reproducibility and quality of Hi-C data. bioRxiv, doi:10.1101/188755.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B41">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) 
<article-title>Robustly detecting differential expression in RNA sequencing data using observation weights</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>e91.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24753412</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz362-B42">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zufferey</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) 
<article-title>Comparison of computational methods for the identification of topologically associating domains</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>., <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>217.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30526631</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
