<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1367-4803</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1367-4811</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6022667</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bty075</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bty075</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Applications Notes</subject>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading">
          <subject>Genome Analysis</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>chromswitch: a flexible method to detect chromatin state switches</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Jessa</surname>
          <given-names>Selin</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="bty075-aff1"/>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Kleinman</surname>
          <given-names>Claudia L</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="bty075-aff1"/>
        <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="bty075-cor1"/>
        <!--<email>claudia.kleinman@mcgill.ca</email>-->
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name>
          <surname>Hancock</surname>
          <given-names>John</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Associate Editor</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <aff id="bty075-aff1">Department of Human Genetics, McGill University, Montreal, QC, Canada and Lady Davis Research Institute, Jewish General Hospital, Montreal, QC, Canada</aff>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="bty075-cor1">To whom correspondence should be addressed. <email>claudia.kleinman@mcgill.ca</email></corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
      <day>01</day>
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2018</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2018-02-09">
      <day>09</day>
      <month>2</month>
      <year>2018</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>09</day>
      <month>2</month>
      <year>2018</year>
    </pub-date>
    <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
    <volume>34</volume>
    <issue>13</issue>
    <issue-title>ISMB 2018 Proceedings July 6 to July 10, 2018, Chicago, IL, United States</issue-title>
    <fpage>2286</fpage>
    <lpage>2288</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>11</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2017</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>26</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2018</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>08</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2018</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2018. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2018</copyright-year>
      <license license-type="cc-by-nc" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xlink:href="bty075.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <sec id="s1">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <p>Chromatin state plays a major role in controlling gene expression, and comparative analysis of ChIP-seq data is key to understanding epigenetic regulation. We present chromswitch, an R/Bioconductor package to integrate epigenomic data in a defined window of interest to detect an overall switch in chromatin state. Chromswitch accurately classifies a benchmarking dataset, and when applied genome-wide, the tool successfully detects chromatin changes that result in brain-specific expression.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2">
        <title>Availability and implementation</title>
        <p>Chromswitch is implemented as an R package available from Bioconductor at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bioconductor.org/packages/chromswitch">https://bioconductor.org/packages/chromswitch</ext-link>. All data and code for reproducing the analysis presented in this paper are available at https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1101260.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3">
        <title>Supplementary information</title>
        <p><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary data</xref> are available at <italic>Bioinformatics</italic> online.</p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <named-content content-type="funder-name">Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada</named-content>
          <named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/501100000038</named-content>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>RGPIN-2016-04911</award-id>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <named-content content-type="funder-name">Fonds de Recherche du Québec-Santé</named-content>
        </funding-source>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <named-content content-type="funder-name">Canadian Institutes of Health Research</named-content>
          <named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/501100000024</named-content>
        </funding-source>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <named-content content-type="funder-name">Calcul Quebec and Compute Canada</named-content>
        </funding-source>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="3"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec>
    <title>1 Introduction</title>
    <p>A routine question in epigenomic studies is how histone modifications and chromatin state differ among groups of samples. These can represent, for instance, distinct developmental, differentiation, or disease states. Several methods exist to process and interpret the raw signal from chromatin immunoprecipitation sequencing (ChIP-Seq), typically by identifying regions of significant enrichment (peaks) (<xref rid="bty075-B3" ref-type="bibr">Furey, 2012</xref>) or learning a genome-wide chromatin state segmentation (<xref rid="bty075-B2" ref-type="bibr">Ernst and Kellis, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bty075-B4" ref-type="bibr">Hoffman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bty075-B6" ref-type="bibr">Mammana and Chung, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bty075-B11" ref-type="bibr">Song and Chen, 2015</xref>). Combining the output of these methods across samples is not straightforward, and various tools have been developed for differential analysis at the peak level (<xref rid="bty075-B1" ref-type="bibr">Chen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bty075-B5" ref-type="bibr">Liang and Keleş, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bty075-B8" ref-type="bibr">Ross-Innes <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>), or for the joint analysis of samples to discover regions of change throughout the genome (<xref rid="bty075-B10" ref-type="bibr">Sohn <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bty075-B12" ref-type="bibr">Yen and Kellis, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bty075-B13" ref-type="bibr">Zeng <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). However, answering the common question of whether a large chromatin state change occurs in a specific, predefined region of interest usually requires <italic>ad hoc</italic> downstream analyses to interrogate inferred peaks or chromatin state assignments across the region.</p>
    <p>Here, we present a flexible strategy to identify chromatin state changes in genomic windows. Given a query region and epigenomic features in two biological conditions as input, chromswitch uses hierarchical clustering and external validity measures to predict a chromatin state switch.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>2 Materials and methods</title>
    <sec>
      <title>2.1 Input and pre-processing</title>
      <p>Chromswitch takes as input: (i) a query region specified by its genomic coordinates and (ii) BED files storing epigenetic features previously inferred for each sample, such as ChIP-seq peak calls or chromatin state segmentations. For simplicity, we refer to these features as <italic>peaks</italic> in what follows, but the algorithm is applicable to any feature represented by genomic coordinates and some associated metrics. For example, peak calling tools typically output fold change and significance values for each peak. Chromswitch can filter peaks using user-defined thresholds on these metrics. Next, these metrics are normalized genome-wide on a per-sample basis: for a vector of genome-wide values for one metric, we rescale the central 99% of values to the range [0, 1] and bound lower and upper outliers to 0 and 1 respectively. This step accounts for some of the technical variation between samples (e.g. in ChIP-seq efficiency) and allows for comparison of metrics with different ranges.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>2.2 Feature matrix construction</title>
      <p>Chromswitch then constructs a sample-by-feature matrix from the data to use as input for clustering, following one of two strategies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="bty075-F1">Fig. 1a</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S1</xref>). In the <italic>summary strategy</italic>, the feature vector for each sample contains summary statistics compiled from all peaks present in the query region. These can include the mean, median and max of each metric, as well as the fraction of the region overlapped by peaks or their average number. In the <italic>binary strategy</italic>, in turn, a set of unique peaks is defined as the union of all peaks present in at least one sample, where peaks are collapsed if they have a reciprocal overlap above a user-specified minimum fraction. Peaks can also be merged if they are separated by less than a user-specified gap. The feature vector for each sample is, in this case, a binary vector encoding the presence or absence of each unique peak in that sample (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S1</xref>, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Methods</xref> for details).
</p>
      <fig id="bty075-F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>(<bold>a</bold>) Overview of the method. (<bold>b</bold>) ROC curve and AUROC for chromswitch applied to a benchmark dataset, comparing the two feature matrix construction strategies. Two types of input were tested: ChIP-seq peaks for H3K4me3, or ChromHMM assignments of the state ‘active transcription’. (<bold>c</bold>) Mean expression (in reads per kilobase per million reads, RPKM) in tissues from the GTEx database, in genes containing candidate chromatin state switches detected using H3K4me3 peaks as input. N indicates number of candidate genes using a threshold on the consensus score of 0.75. (<bold>d</bold>) Mean log2 fold change of expression between GTEx brain and other tissues across candidate chromatin switches as a function of the threshold on the consensus score used for prediction</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="bty075f1"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>2.3 Chromatin state switch calls</title>
      <p>Chromswitch then clusters samples using hierarchical clustering and selects the partition with the highest average Silhouette width, which measures cluster cohesion and separation (<xref rid="bty075-B9" ref-type="bibr">Rousseeuw, 1987</xref>). Inferred cluster assignments are then scored using a consensus (mean) of three external cluster validity indices designed to validate clustering solutions against ground-truth class labels: the Adjusted Rand Index, the Normalized Mutual Information and the V measure (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table S1</xref>). The consensus score can then be used to threshold or rank putative chromatin state switches (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Methods</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>3 Results</title>
    <p>To evaluate chromswitch, we first assembled a benchmark dataset comprising data for 7 brain and 16 other tissues from the NIH Roadmap Epigenomics Project (<xref rid="bty075-B7" ref-type="bibr">Roadmap Epigenomics Consortium, 2015</xref>). We included ChIP-seq peaks for the H3K4me3 mark (a histone modification associated with active transcription), DNase I hypersensitive sites (associated with open chromatin), RNA-seq (measuring expression, the functional consequence of chromatin changes) and chromatin state assignments by a ChromHMM model trained on 60 Roadmap epigenomes. We identified a set of 60 5kbp regions surrounding transcription start sites (TSS) of genes where a clear chromatin state switch between brain and other tissues was evident in a genome browser for all data types, and 60 control regions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table S2</xref>). Area under the Receiver-Operating Characteristic curve (AUROC) calculation shows that chromswitch accurately classified these benchmark regions over a range of combinations of input data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="bty075-F1">Fig. 1b</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S2</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Methods</xref>). Chromswitch preserved accuracy with small sample sizes (e.g. AUC = 0.95 for a dataset of 4 samples per condition, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S3</xref>) and high class imbalance (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S3</xref>). Furthermore, the method is robust to changes in tuning parameters when constructing the feature matrix using the binary strategy (<italic>gap</italic> and minimum reciprocal overlap, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S4</xref>). An exploration of the effect of variations in window size, which determines the signal to noise ratio, is presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figure S5</xref>. Finally, chromswitch is applicable to the analysis of sparse marks covering broad domains, such as H3K27me3 (Supplementary Figs S6–S8).</p>
    <p>We next evaluated chromswitch genome-wide, assessing whether it could identify chromatin switches that result in tissue-specific expression. Using as input either H3K4me3 peaks, DNase I hypersensitivity sites or ChromHMM assignments to the state ‘active transcription’, we applied chromswitch to 5 kbp windows surrounding all annotated TSS in the RefSeq annotation (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Methods</xref>). Genes for which chromswitch detected an active state in brain samples and a silent state otherwise were validated using gene expression data in corresponding tissues from the Genotype-Tissue Expression Project (GTEx). We found that brain-specific chromatin state changes detected by chromswitch were recapitulated at the expression level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="bty075-F1">Fig. 1c</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figs S9, S10</xref>). As expected, the median fold change of expression across candidate switches increased as a function of the threshold score used for predictions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="bty075-F1">Fig. 1d</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S11</xref>).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>4 Conclusion</title>
    <p>Chromswitch equips users to detect spatial, temporal, or tissue-specific chromatin state changes in specific query regions. The tool is free from data-intensive training steps, suitable for histone marks with diverse profiles and applicable downstream of existing tools for chromatin analysis. The method is robust to small sample sizes and high class imbalance, common scenarios in functional genomics projects. Chromswitch is implemented as an R package, designed for modularity and ease of use to facilitate investigation into epigenetic regulation and its consequences.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup1">
      <label>Supplementary Data</label>
      <media xlink:href="bty075_chromswitch_supplementary.pdf">
        <caption>
          <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
        </caption>
      </media>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack>
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <p>We thank Nicolas De Jay, Alexis Blanchet-Cohen, Steven Hébert and Karine Choquet for code review and testing. We thank Maud Marques and Vincenzo Forgetta for critical reading of the manuscript.</p>
    <sec>
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p>This work was supported by by the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (RGPIN-2016-04911). C.L.K. receives salary awards from the Fonds de Recherche du Québec-Santé. S.J. is a recipient of a Canadian Institutes of Health Research award. The computing and networking infrastructure were provided by Calcul Quebec and Compute Canada.</p>
      <p><italic>Conflict of Interest</italic>: none declared.</p>
    </sec>
  </ack>
  <ref-list>
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="bty075-B1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) 
<article-title>A novel statistical method for quantitative comparison of multiple ChIP-seq datasets</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>1889</fpage>–<lpage>1896</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25682068</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bty075-B2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kellis</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>ChromHMM: automating chromatin-state discovery and characterization</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>216</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22373907</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bty075-B3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Furey</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>ChIP-seq and Beyond: new and improved methodologies to detect and characterize protein-DNA interactions</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Genet</source>., <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>840</fpage>–<lpage>852</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23090257</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bty075-B4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>Unsupervised pattern discovery in human chromatin structure through genomic segmentation</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>473</fpage>–<lpage>476</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22426492</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bty075-B5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keleş</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>Detecting differential binding of transcription factors with ChIP-seq</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>122</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22057161</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bty075-B6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mammana</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>H.R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) 
<article-title>Chromatin segmentation based on a probabilistic model for read counts explains a large portion of the epigenome</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>., <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>151.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26206277</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bty075-B7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Roadmap Epigenomics Consortium</collab> (<year>2015</year>) 
<article-title>Integrative analysis of 111 reference human epigenomes</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>518</volume>, <fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>330</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25693563</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bty075-B8">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross-Innes</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>Differential oestrogen receptor binding is associated with clinical outcome in breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>481</volume>, <fpage>389</fpage>–<lpage>393</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22217937</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bty075-B9">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rousseeuw</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>) Silhouettes: a graphical aid to the interpretation and validation of cluster analysis. <source>J. Computat. Appl. Math</source>., <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bty075-B10">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sohn</surname><given-names>K.-A.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) 
<article-title>hiHMM: bayesian non-parametric joint inference of chromatin state maps</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>2066</fpage>–<lpage>2074</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25725496</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bty075-B11">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K.C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) 
<article-title>Spectacle: fast chromatin state annotation using spectral learning</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>., <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>33.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25786205</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bty075-B12">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kellis</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) 
<article-title>Systematic chromatin state comparison of epigenomes associated with diverse properties including sex and tissue type</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun</source>., <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>7973.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26282110</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bty075-B13">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) 
<article-title>jMOSAiCS: joint analysis of multiple ChIP-seq datasets</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>., <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>R38</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23844871</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
