<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>BMC Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1471-2105</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6427896</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2709</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-019-2709-5</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Methodology Article</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>A likelihood ratio test for changes in homeolog expression bias</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Smith</surname>
          <given-names>Ronald D.</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>rdsmith@email.wm.edu</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Kinser</surname>
          <given-names>Taliesin J.</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>tjkinser@email.wm.edu</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Smith</surname>
          <given-names>Gregory D. Conradi</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>greg@wm.edu</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8019-9993</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Puzey</surname>
          <given-names>Joshua R.</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>jrpuzey@wm.edu</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1940 3051</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.264889.9</institution-id><institution>Department of Applied Science, The College of William &amp; Mary, </institution></institution-wrap>Williamsburg, 23187 VA USA </aff>
      <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1940 3051</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.264889.9</institution-id><institution>Department of Biology, The College of William &amp; Mary, </institution></institution-wrap>Williamsburg, 23187 VA USA </aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>20</day>
      <month>3</month>
      <year>2019</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>20</day>
      <month>3</month>
      <year>2019</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <year>2019</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>20</volume>
    <elocation-id>149</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>7</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2017</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>1</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2019</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement>
      <license license-type="OpenAccess">
        <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract id="Abs1">
      <sec>
        <title>Background</title>
        <p>Gene duplications are a major source of raw material for evolution and a likely contributor to the diversity of life on earth. Duplicate genes (i.e., homeologs, in the case of a whole genome duplication) may retain their ancestral function, sub- or neofunctionalize, or be lost entirely. A primary way that duplicate genes evolve new functions is by altering their expression patterns. Comparing the expression patterns of duplicate genes gives clues as to whether any of these evolutionary processes have occurred.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Results</title>
        <p>We develop a likelihood ratio test for the analysis of the expression ratios of duplicate genes across two conditions (e.g., tissues). We demonstrate an application of this test by comparing homeolog expression patterns of 1448 homeologous gene pairs using RNA-seq data generated from leaves and petals of an allotetraploid monkeyflower (<italic>Mimulus luteus</italic>). We assess the sensitivity of this test to different levels of homeolog expression bias and compare the method to several alternatives.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Conclusions</title>
        <p>The likelihood ratio test derived here is a direct, transparent, and easily implemented method for detecting changes in homeolog expression bias that outperforms alternative approaches. While our method was derived with homeolog analysis in mind, this method can be used to analyze changes in the ratio of expression levels between any two genes in any two conditions.</p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
      <title>Keywords</title>
      <kwd>Homeolog expression bias</kwd>
      <kwd>Likelihood ratio test</kwd>
      <kwd>Polyploid</kwd>
      <kwd>RNA-seq</kwd>
      <kwd>Whole genome duplication</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group>
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000001</institution-id>
            <institution>National Science Foundation</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>1121606</award-id>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group>
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100006470</institution-id>
            <institution>College of Arts and Sciences, College of William and Mary</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>Summer Research Award</award-id>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
        <meta-value>© The Author(s) 2019</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec id="Sec1">
    <title>Background</title>
    <p>Gene duplications are a major source of raw material for evolution and a likely contributor to the diversity of life on earth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Gene duplications are a special type of mutation resulting in the multiplication of intact functional components. These duplicate genes may either retain the ancestral function or individual portions of the gene’s ancestral function may be partitioned (i.e., subfunctionalize) or evolve new functions entirely (i.e., neofunctionalize) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Duplicate genes may evolve new functions either by changes in the primary coding sequence or altering where and when they are expressed. Previous work has indicated that changes to gene expression and their regulatory networks may be more important, rapid, or flexible than divergence of protein identities in the evolution of sub- and neofunctionlization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p>
    <p>There are multiple scenarios in which genes can be duplicated, ranging from small regional gene duplications to massive whole genome duplications (WGDs). The term polyploid refers to cells or organisms that have undergone a WGD event and contain more than two paired sets of chromosomes. Each complete set of chromosomes is referred to as a subgenome. Homologous genes located on separate subgenomes are referred to as hom<italic>e</italic>ologs.</p>
    <p>WGDs are especially common in plants; indeed, all extant angiosperms (i.e., flowering plants) have at least two rounds of WGD in common [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], and up to 15% of speciation events in angiosperms may have been the product of WGDs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Importantly, many major crops (corn, potato, wheat, etc.) are polyploid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. WGD events and the resulting polyploidy are not restricted to plants, but have occurred in both vertebrate and invertebrate lineages as well. For example, the African clawed frog, <italic>Xenopus</italic>, commonly used as an experimental model system and extensively studied in developmental biology, includes species ranging from diploid to dodecaploid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Other examples of polyploids with ancient WGD events include the zebrafish <italic>Danio rerio</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], several salmonids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], and some species of fungi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Interestingly, there exists at least one polyploid mammal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], a tetraploid rat from Argentina that mediates gene dosage by regulation of ribosomal RNA.</p>
    <p>The biological consequences of gene duplications and subfunctionalization are significant and include examples such as the evolution of eyes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], the evolution of hemoglobins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], development of heat resistance in plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], and insecticide resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Given the importance of duplicate genes in evolution, it is natural to ask how we might quantify differences in the activity or function of homeologous genes. One way to begin exploring this question is by analyzing gene expression levels.</p>
    <p>Genome-wide gene expression levels are commonly quantified using high throughput RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. In RNA-seq experiments, mRNA is extracted, purified, and reverse transcribed into cDNA. This cDNA is fragmented into smaller pieces and sequenced using next-generation technology. The resulting millions of sequence reads are then mapped to either a reference genome or reference transcriptome, and the number of sequences mapping to a particular gene is used as an indication of the expression level of that gene.</p>
    <p>In <italic>differential expression analysis</italic>, high-throughput RNA-seq data is used to determine if gene expression levels vary under different experimental conditions, or in distinct tissues, etc. Several different approaches to this statistical analysis exist [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], some of which use methods based on maximum likelihood estimation and likelihood ratio tests.</p>
    <p>Homeologous gene pairs frequently have distinguishing sequence differences. Therefore, sequencing reads derived from individual homeologs can be distinguished and expression levels can be determined for each homeolog. The term <italic>homeolog expression bias</italic> (HEB) refers to cases where homeologs are expressed at unequal levels in a single experimental condition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. The primary objective of this paper, development of a likelihood ratio test for statistical analysis of <italic>changes</italic> in homeolog expression bias (denoted <italic>Δ</italic>HEB) is a non-trivial extension of the statistical analysis of differential expression.</p>
    <p>The following sections begin with the derivation of a likelihood ratio test for HEB. This is our starting point for the development of a likelihood ratio test for <italic>Δ</italic>HEB, i.e. changes in relative expression levels between homeologous genes in two conditions. We apply this method to RNA-seq data of homeologous gene expression in petals and leaves of the allotetraploid <italic>Mimulus luteus</italic>. Finally, using simulated data, we show that the likelihood ratio test for <italic>Δ</italic>HEB derived here is the best choice among several alternative methods.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec2">
    <title>Methods</title>
    <sec id="Sec3">
      <title>Quantifying homeolog expression bias (HEB)</title>
      <p>We will write <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic> to denote a homeologous gene pair from which RNA-seq data is generated in <italic>n</italic> biological replicates. Typically, the mean expression levels of the homeologs (denoted <inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\bar {a}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mi>ā</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\bar {b}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq2.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) are normalized by gene length and sequencing depth, as when reported in units of RPKM (reads per kilobase of coding sequence per million mapped reads). We define the homeolog expression bias (HEB) of the <italic>n</italic> replicates as 
<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\text{HEB} = \log (\bar{b} / \bar{a}) = \log \bar{b} - \log \bar{a} \,, $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>HEB</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>ā</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:mi>ā</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula> a dimensionless quantity with HEB=0 indicating no bias. If one uses the base 2 logarithm, HEB=−3 indicates 8-fold bias towards homeolog <italic>A</italic>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4">
      <title>Likelihood ratio test for HEB</title>
      <p>After accounting for the possibility of different gene lengths, the statistical test for HEB is essentially a likelihood ratio test for differential expression of a pair of homeologous genes. The goal is to determine whether there is sufficient evidence to reject the null hypothesis (<italic>H</italic><sub>0</sub>) that there is no bias (i.e., equal expression levels for homeologous genes) in favor of the alternative hypothesis (<italic>H</italic><sub>1</sub>) that bias is present, i.e., different expression levels for homeologous genes. In mathematical terms, the null hypothesis <italic>H</italic><sub>0</sub> corresponds to the parameters (denoted by <italic>θ</italic>) of a probability model for generating the data being in a specified subset <italic>Θ</italic><sub>0</sub> of the parameter space <italic>Θ</italic>, that is, 
<disp-formula id="Equb"><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{array}{@{}rcl@{}} &amp;&amp; H_{0} \colon \; \theta \in \Theta_{0}  \\ &amp;&amp; H_{1} \colon \; \theta \in \Theta \backslash \Theta_{0}  \,. \end{array} $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left center right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="2.77626pt"/><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="2.77626pt"/><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>Θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∖</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equb.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>Let <italic>θ</italic>=(<italic>λ</italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup>,<italic>λ</italic><sup><italic>b</italic></sup>) denote the true but unknown expression levels (physical units of length <sup>−1</sup>, e.g., RPKM). Assuming positive, i.e. non-zero, expression, the parameter space is <inline-formula id="IEq3"><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\Theta = \left \{\theta : {{\lambda }^{a}},{{\lambda }^{b}} \in \mathbb {R}_{+} \right \}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mi>Θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="}" open="{" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℝ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq3.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. The null (<italic>H</italic><sub>0</sub>) and alternative (<italic>H</italic><sub>1</sub>) hypotheses for the likelihood ratio test for homeolog expression bias are formalized as follows, 
<disp-formula id="Equc"><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{array}{@{}rcl@{}} &amp;&amp; H_{0} \colon \; \left({{\lambda}^{a}}, {{\lambda}^{b}}\right) \in \left\{{{\lambda}^{a}},{{\lambda}^{b}} \in \mathbb{R}_{+} : {{\lambda}^{a}} = {{\lambda}^{b}}\right\}  \\ &amp;&amp; H_{1} \colon \; \left({{\lambda}^{a}}, {{\lambda}^{b}}\right) \in \left\{{{\lambda}^{a}},{{\lambda}^{b}} \in \mathbb{R}_{+} : {{\lambda}^{a}} \neq {{\lambda}^{b}} \right\}  \,. \end{array} $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M12"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left center right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="2.77626pt"/><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="}" open="{" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℝ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="2.77626pt"/><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="}" open="{" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℝ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>≠</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equc.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>Equivalently, let <italic>ω</italic>=<italic>λ</italic><sup><italic>b</italic></sup>/<italic>λ</italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup> denote the ratio of expression levels and drop the superscript indicating the reference homeolog (<italic>λ</italic>=<italic>λ</italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup>). In that case, <italic>λ</italic><sup><italic>b</italic></sup>=<italic>ω</italic><italic>λ</italic> and the hypotheses are written as follows, 
<disp-formula id="Equd"><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{array}{@{}rcl@{}} H_{0} \colon &amp;&amp; ({\lambda}, {\omega}) \in \{ {\lambda}, {\omega} \in \mathbb{R}_{+} : {\omega} = 1 \}  \\ H_{1} \colon &amp;&amp; ({\lambda}, {\omega}) \in \{ {\lambda}, {\omega} \in \mathbb{R}_{+} : {\omega} \neq 1 \}  \,. \end{array} $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M14"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left center right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℝ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℝ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi><mml:mo>≠</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>}</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equd.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>Once we specify a probability model for the data <inline-formula id="IEq4"><alternatives><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\mathcal {X}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M16"><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq4.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, likelihood functions for each hypothesis, <inline-formula id="IEq5"><alternatives><tex-math id="M17">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\mathcal {L}_{0}(\theta | \mathcal {X})$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M18"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq5.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq6"><alternatives><tex-math id="M19">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\mathcal {L}_{1}(\theta | \mathcal {X})$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M20"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq6.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, can be derived (see next section). For composite hypotheses, the appropriate likelihood ratio test statistic is 
<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M21">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ W(\mathcal{X})= -2 \ln \frac{ \hat{\mathcal{L}}_{0}}{ \hat{\mathcal{L}}_{1}} = 2 \left(\ln \hat{\mathcal{L}}_{1} - \ln \hat{\mathcal{L}}_{0} \right) \,,   $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M22"><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>where <inline-formula id="IEq7"><alternatives><tex-math id="M23">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\hat {\mathcal {L}}_{1} $\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M24"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq7.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq8"><alternatives><tex-math id="M25">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\hat {\mathcal {L}}_{0}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M26"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq8.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> are the maximized likelihoods, 
<disp-formula id="Eque"><alternatives><tex-math id="M27">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{array}{@{}rcl@{}} \hat{\mathcal{L}}_{1} &amp;= &amp; \sup\{\,\mathcal{L}(\theta | \mathcal{X}) : \theta\in\Theta\,\}  \\ \hat{\mathcal{L}}_{0} &amp;=&amp; \sup\{\mathcal{L}(\theta | \mathcal{X}):\theta\in\Theta_{0}\,\} \,.  \end{array} $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M28"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left center right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:mo>sup</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>Θ</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:mo>sup</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mo>}</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Eque.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>A critical value of the test statistic (<italic>W</italic><sub>∗</sub>) is obtained from the Chi-squared distribution with significance level <italic>α</italic>=0.05. The number of degrees of freedom <italic>δ</italic> is the difference in the number of free parameters in <italic>Θ</italic> and <italic>Θ</italic><sub>0</sub> (here <italic>δ</italic>=1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. The null hypothesis <italic>H</italic><sub>0</sub> is rejected in favor of the alternative <italic>H</italic><sub>1</sub> when <inline-formula id="IEq9"><alternatives><tex-math id="M29">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$W(\mathcal {X}) &gt; W_{*}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M30"><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq9.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec5">
      <title>Probability model for RNA-seq read counts</title>
      <p>Denote the lengths of homeologous genes <italic>a</italic> and <italic>b</italic> as <italic>ℓ</italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup> and <italic>ℓ</italic><sup><italic>b</italic></sup> (e.g., in kilobases) and let <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> be the sequencing depth (e.g., in millions of mapped reads) of replicate <italic>i</italic>. The expected number of RNA-seq reads for gene <italic>a</italic> and replicate <italic>i</italic> is 
<disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M31">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ {{\mu}^{a}_{i}} = {{\lambda}^{a}} {{\ell}^{a}} {{d}_{i}} = {\lambda} {{\ell}^{a}} {{d}_{i}} \,,   $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M32"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>where in the second equality we have dropped the superscript for the reference homeolog (<italic>λ</italic>=<italic>λ</italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup>). Similarly, the expected number of RNA-seq reads for gene <italic>b</italic> and replicate <italic>i</italic> is 
<disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M33">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ {{\mu}^{b}_{i}} = {{\lambda}^{b}} {{\ell}^{b}} {{d}_{i}} = {\omega} {\lambda} {{\ell}^{b}} {{d}_{i}} \,   $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M34"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ωλ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ3.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>where <italic>ω</italic>=<italic>λ</italic><sup><italic>b</italic></sup>/<italic>λ</italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup>=<italic>λ</italic><sup><italic>b</italic></sup>/<italic>λ</italic>.</p>
      <p>In order to model the overdispersion commonly observed in RNA-seq data, the probability model assumes that the count data for each gene is drawn from a negative binomial distribution, 
<disp-formula id="Equ4"><alternatives><tex-math id="M35">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ f(x ; {\mu},r) = \frac{\Gamma(r+x)}{\Gamma(r)x!} \left(\frac{{\mu}}{{\mu}+r}\right)^{x} \left(\frac{r}{{\mu}+r}\right)^{r}\,,   $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M36"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>!</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ4.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>where <italic>μ</italic> is the appropriate mean (<inline-formula id="IEq10"><alternatives><tex-math id="M37">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}${{\mu }^{a}_{i}}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M38"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq10.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> or <inline-formula id="IEq11"><alternatives><tex-math id="M39">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}${{\mu }^{b}_{i}}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M40"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq11.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> in Eqs. <xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="">2</xref> and <xref rid="Equ3" ref-type="">3</xref>). That is, if <inline-formula id="IEq12"><alternatives><tex-math id="M41">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$X^{a}_{i}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M42"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq12.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq13"><alternatives><tex-math id="M43">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$X^{b}_{i}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M44"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq13.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> are random variables representing the count data for replicate <italic>i</italic> of homeologous genes A and B, 
<disp-formula id="Equf"><alternatives><tex-math id="M45">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{array}{@{}rcl@{}} \Pr\left\{X^{a}_{i} = {{a}_{i}}\right\} &amp;=&amp; f\left({{a}_{i}} ; {\lambda} {{\ell}^{a}} {{d}_{i}},{{r}_{i}}\right)  \\ \Pr\left\{X^{b}_{i} = {{b}_{i}}\right\} &amp;=&amp; f\left({{b}_{i}} ; {\omega} {\lambda} {{\ell}^{b}} {{d}_{i}},{{r}_{i}}\right)  \,, \end{array} $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M46"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left center right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"><mml:mo>Pr</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="}" open="{" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:munderover accent="false" accentunder="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"><mml:mo>Pr</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="}" open="{" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:munderover accent="false" accentunder="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mi>ωλ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equf.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>where we have used <inline-formula id="IEq14"><alternatives><tex-math id="M47">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}${{\mu }^{a}_{i}} = {\lambda } {{\ell }^{a}} {{d}_{i}}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M48"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq14.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq15"><alternatives><tex-math id="M49">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}${{\mu }^{b}_{i}} = {\omega } {\lambda } {{\ell }^{b}} {{d}_{i}}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M50"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ωλ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq15.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. In these expressions, the aggregation parameter <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> is obtained from the observed mean-variance relation for all homeolog pairs of the <italic>i</italic>th experimental replicate (see Appendix 1).</p>
      <p>Assuming independence of experimental replicates, the likelihood functions <inline-formula id="IEq16"><alternatives><tex-math id="M51">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\mathcal {L}_{1}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M52"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq16.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq17"><alternatives><tex-math id="M53">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\mathcal {L}_{0}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M54"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq17.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> are products of the likelihood functions for each observation, that is, 
<disp-formula id="Equ5"><alternatives><tex-math id="M55">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ \mathcal{L}_{1}(\mathcal{X}) = \textstyle \prod_{i=1}^{n} \mathcal{L}_{1}^{i} (\mathcal{X})  \,,  $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M56"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∏</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ5.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>and similarly for <inline-formula id="IEq18"><alternatives><tex-math id="M57">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\mathcal {L}_{0}(\mathcal {X})$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M58"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq18.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula id="IEq19"><alternatives><tex-math id="M59">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\mathcal {X}_{i} = \{{{a}_{i}},{{b}_{i}}\}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M60"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq19.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> indicates the observed read counts for replicate <italic>i</italic> and <inline-formula id="IEq20"><alternatives><tex-math id="M61">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\mathcal {X} = \cup _{i=1}^{n} \mathcal {X}_{i}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M62"><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∪</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq20.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. The likelihood function for the alternative hypothesis and the <italic>i</italic>th replicate is 
<disp-formula id="Equ6"><label>4</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M63">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{array}{@{}rcl@{}} &amp;&amp; \mathcal{L}_{1}^{i}(\mathcal{X})= \frac{\Gamma({{r}_{i}}+{{a}_{i}})}{\Gamma({{r}_{i}}){{a}_{i}}!}\frac{\Gamma({{r}_{i}}+{{b}_{i}})}{\Gamma({{r}_{i}}){{b}_{i}}!}  \\ &amp;&amp;\times \left(\frac{{\lambda} {{\ell}^{a}} {{d}_{i}}}{{\lambda} {{\ell}^{a}} {{d}_{i}}+{{r}_{i}}}\right)^{{{a}_{i}}} \left(\frac{{\omega} {\lambda} {{\ell}^{b}} {{d}_{i}}}{{\omega} {\lambda} {{\ell}^{b}} {{d}_{i}}+{{r}_{i}}}\right)^{{{b}_{i}}}  \\ &amp;&amp; \times \left(\frac{{{r}_{i}}}{{\lambda} {{\ell}^{a}} {{d}_{i}} +{{r}_{i}}}\right)^{{{r}_{i}}} \left(\frac{{{r}_{i}}}{{\omega} {\lambda} {{\ell}^{b}} {{d}_{i}} + {{r}_{i}}}\right)^{{{r}_{i}}} \, . \end{array} $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M64"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left center right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>!</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>!</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ωλ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ωλ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ωλ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ6.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>The likelihood function for the null hypothesis and the <italic>i</italic>th replicate, <inline-formula id="IEq21"><alternatives><tex-math id="M65">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\mathcal {L}_{0}^{i}(\mathcal {X})$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M66"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq21.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, is given by Eq. <xref rid="Equ6" ref-type="">4</xref> with <italic>ω</italic>=1.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec6">
      <title>Maximum likelihood estimation</title>
      <p>Maximum likelihood estimation is performed using the the log-likelihood function corresponding to Eq. <xref rid="Equ6" ref-type="">4</xref>, namely, 
<disp-formula id="Equ7"><label>5</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M67">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ {\ln \mathcal{L}}_{1}(\mathcal{X}) = \textstyle \sum_{i} {\ln \mathcal{L}}_{1}^{i} (\mathcal{X}) \,,   $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M68"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ7.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>where 
<disp-formula id="Equ8"><label>6</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M69">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{array}{@{}rcl@{}} {\ln \mathcal{L}}_{1}^{i}(\mathcal{X}) &amp;=&amp; \gamma({{r}_{i}}+{{a}_{i}}) + \ln\left({{a}_{i}}!\right)  \\ &amp;+&amp;\gamma\left({{r}_{i}}+{{b}_{i}}\right) + \ln\left({{b}_{i}}!\right)  \\ &amp;+&amp; 2 {{r}_{i}} \ln {{r}_{i}} - 2 \gamma\left({{r}_{i}}\right)  \\ &amp;+&amp; {{a}_{i}} \ln\left({\lambda} {{\ell}^{a}} {{d}_{i}} \right) +{{b}_{i}} \ln\left({\omega} {\lambda} {{\ell}^{b}} {{d}_{i}} \right)  \\ &amp; -&amp; \left({{a}_{i}} + {{r}_{i}} \right) \ln \left({\lambda} {{\ell}^{a}} {{d}_{i}} + {{r}_{i}}\right)  \\ &amp; -&amp; \left. \left({{b}_{i}} + {{r}_{i}} \right) \ln \left({\omega} {\lambda} {{\ell}^{b}} {{d}_{i}} + {{r}_{i}}\right) \right]  \end{array} $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M70"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left center right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>!</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>!</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ωλ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:mfenced close="]" open="" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ωλ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ8.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>and <italic>γ</italic>(·)= ln<italic>Γ</italic>(·). The log-likelihood function for the null hypothesis (<inline-formula id="IEq22"><alternatives><tex-math id="M71">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}${\ln \mathcal {L}}_{0}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M72"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq22.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) is given by Eq. <xref rid="Equ8" ref-type="">6</xref> with <italic>ω</italic>=1.</p>
      <p>The log-likelihood function <inline-formula id="IEq23"><alternatives><tex-math id="M73">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}${\ln \mathcal {L}}_{1}(\mathcal {X})$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M74"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq23.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is maximized by numerically solving for <inline-formula id="IEq24"><alternatives><tex-math id="M75">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\hat {\lambda }$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M76"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq24.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq25"><alternatives><tex-math id="M77">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\hat {\omega }$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M78"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq25.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> leading to zero partial derivatives, 
<disp-formula id="Equ9"><label>7</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M79">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{array}{@{}rcl@{}} 0 &amp;=&amp; \left. \frac{{\partial \ln \mathcal{L}}_{1}}{\partial \lambda} \right|_{\hat{\lambda},\hat{\omega}}  \end{array} $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M80"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left center right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="|" open="" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ9.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>
        <disp-formula id="Equ10">
          <label>8</label>
          <alternatives>
            <tex-math id="M81">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{array}{@{}rcl@{}} 0 &amp;=&amp; \left.\frac{{\partial \ln \mathcal{L}}_{1}}{\partial \omega}\right|_{\hat{\lambda},\hat{\omega}} \,,  \end{array} $$ \end{document}</tex-math>
            <mml:math id="M82">
              <mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left center right">
                <mml:mtr>
                  <mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1">
                    <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                  </mml:mtd>
                  <mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2">
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  </mml:mtd>
                  <mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3">
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mfenced close="|" open="" separators="">
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mfrac>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:msub>
                                  <mml:mrow>
                                    <mml:mi>∂</mml:mi>
                                    <mml:mo>ln</mml:mo>
                                    <mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi>
                                  </mml:mrow>
                                  <mml:mrow>
                                    <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                                  </mml:mrow>
                                </mml:msub>
                              </mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mi>∂ω</mml:mi>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:mfrac>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mfenced>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mover accent="true">
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
                        </mml:mover>
                        <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mover accent="true">
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>ω</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
                        </mml:mover>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mspace width="0.3em"/>
                    <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                  </mml:mtd>
                </mml:mtr>
              </mml:mtable>
            </mml:math>
            <graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ10.gif" position="anchor"/>
          </alternatives>
        </disp-formula>
      </p>
      <p>as described in Appendix 2. The log-likelihood function <inline-formula id="IEq26"><alternatives><tex-math id="M83">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}${\ln \mathcal {L}}_{0}(\mathcal {X})$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M84"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq26.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is maximized by solving for <inline-formula id="IEq27"><alternatives><tex-math id="M85">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\hat {\lambda }$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M86"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq27.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> leading to 
<disp-formula id="Equ11"><label>9</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M87">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ 0 = \left. \frac{{\partial \ln \mathcal{L}}_{0}}{\partial \lambda} \right|_{\hat{\lambda}}  \,.  $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M88"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="|" open="" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ11.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>The optimal parameter values <inline-formula id="IEq28"><alternatives><tex-math id="M89">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\hat {\lambda }$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M90"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq28.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq29"><alternatives><tex-math id="M91">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\hat {\omega }$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M92"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq29.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> are used to evaluate <inline-formula id="IEq30"><alternatives><tex-math id="M93">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\ln \hat {\mathcal {L}}_{0} (\mathcal {X} ; \hat {\lambda })$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M94"><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq30.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq31"><alternatives><tex-math id="M95">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\ln \hat {\mathcal {L}}_{1}(\mathcal {X} ; \hat {\lambda },\hat {\omega })$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M96"><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq31.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, and the test statistic <italic>W</italic> (see Eq. <xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="">1</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec7">
      <title>Quantifying changes in homeolog expression bias (<italic>Δ</italic>HEB)</title>
      <p>Let <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic> represent homeologous genes and RNA-seq data is generated under conditions 1 and 2 in <italic>n</italic> biological replicates, leading to mean expression levels <inline-formula id="IEq32"><alternatives><tex-math id="M97">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}${\bar {a}_{1}}, {\bar {a}_{2}}, {\bar {b}_{1}}, {\bar {b}_{2}}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M98"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ā</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ā</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq32.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. The change in homeolog expression bias (<italic>Δ</italic>HEB) is defined as 
<disp-formula id="Equ12"><label>10</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M99">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ {\Delta {\text{HEB}}} = \text{HEB}_{2} - \text{HEB}_{1} = \log \left(\frac{{\bar{b}_{2}}/{\bar{a}_{2}}}{{\bar{b}_{1}} / {\bar{a}_{1}}}\right) \,,   $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M100"><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mtext>HEB</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>HEB</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>HEB</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ā</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ā</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ12.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>where the last equality uses <inline-formula id="IEq33"><alternatives><tex-math id="M101">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\text {HEB}_{1} = \log {\bar {b}_{1}}/{\bar {a}_{1}}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M102"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>HEB</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ā</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq33.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq34"><alternatives><tex-math id="M103">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\text {HEB}_{2}= \log {\bar {b}_{2}}/{\bar {a}_{2}}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M104"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>HEB</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ā</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq34.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec8">
      <title>Likelihood ratio test for <italic>Δ</italic>HEB</title>
      <p>The likelihood ratio test for <italic>Δ</italic>HEB is designed to determine whether there is sufficient evidence to reject the null hypothesis (<italic>H</italic><sub>0</sub>) that homeolog expression bias is the same under two experimental conditions (<italic>Δ</italic>HEB=0) in favor of the alternative hypothesis (<italic>H</italic><sub>1</sub>) that there is a difference in bias (<italic>Δ</italic>HEB≠0). Following notation similar to the previous section, our hypotheses are 
<disp-formula id="Equg"><alternatives><tex-math id="M105">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{array}{@{}rcl@{}} &amp;&amp; H_{0} \colon \theta \in \Theta_{0} = \left\{\lambda^{a|b}_{1|2} \in \mathbb{R}_{+} : {{\lambda}^{b}_{1}}/{{\lambda}^{a}_{1}} = {{\lambda}^{b}_{2}}/{{\lambda}^{a}_{2}}\right\}  \\ &amp;&amp; H_{1} \colon \theta \in \Theta \backslash \Theta_{0} =\left\{\lambda^{a|b}_{1|2} \in \mathbb{R}_{+} : {{\lambda}^{b}_{1}}/{{\lambda}^{a}_{1}} \neq {{\lambda}^{b}_{2}}/{{\lambda}^{a}_{2}}\right\}  \,, \end{array} $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M106"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left center right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="}" open="{" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℝ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>Θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∖</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="}" open="{" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℝ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>≠</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equg.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>where <inline-formula id="IEq35"><alternatives><tex-math id="M107">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\lambda ^{a|b}_{1|2}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M108"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq35.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is an abbreviation for <inline-formula id="IEq36"><alternatives><tex-math id="M109">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}${{\lambda }^{a}_{1}},{{\lambda }^{b}_{1}}, {{\lambda }^{b}_{1}},{{\lambda }^{b}_{2}}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M110"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq36.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. Equivalently, 
<disp-formula id="Equh"><alternatives><tex-math id="M111">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{array}{@{}rcl@{}} H_{0} \colon &amp; \theta \in \Theta_{0} = \{ {{\lambda}_{1|2}}, {{\omega}_{1|2}} \in \mathbb{R}_{+} : {{\omega}_{1}} = {{\omega}_{2}} \}  \\ H_{1} \colon &amp; \theta \in \Theta\backslash \Theta_{0} = \{ {{\lambda}_{1|2}}, {{\omega}_{1|2}} \in \mathbb{R}_{+} : {{\omega}_{1}} \ne {{\omega}_{2}} \}  \,, \end{array} $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M112"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left center right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℝ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"/><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>Θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∖</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℝ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≠</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"/><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equh.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>where <inline-formula id="IEq37"><alternatives><tex-math id="M113">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}${{\omega }_{1}} = {{\lambda }^{b}_{1}}/{{\lambda }^{a}_{1}}, {{\omega }_{2}} = {{\lambda }^{b}_{2}}/{{\lambda }^{a}_{2}}, {{\lambda }_{1}} = {{\lambda }^{a}_{1}}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M114"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq37.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq38"><alternatives><tex-math id="M115">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}${{\lambda }_{2}} = {{\lambda }^{a}_{2}}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M116"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq38.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. The difference in degrees of freedom of the alternative and null hypotheses is <italic>δ</italic>=4−3=1.</p>
      <p>The likelihood functions for the <italic>Δ</italic>HEB test are similar to those for HEB, though the two different experimental conditions lead to twice as many terms (cf. Eq. <xref rid="Equ6" ref-type="">4</xref>). The likelihood function for <italic>H</italic><sub>1</sub> is 
<disp-formula id="Equ13"><label>11</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M117">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ \mathcal{L}_{1}(\mathcal{X})= \prod_{k=1}^{2} \prod_{i=1}^{n} \mathcal{L}_{1}^{k,i}(\mathcal{X})  $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M118"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∏</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∏</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ13.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>where <inline-formula id="IEq39"><alternatives><tex-math id="M119">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\mathcal {L}_{1}^{k,i}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M120"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq39.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, the likelihood function for the <italic>i</italic>th replicate of the <italic>k</italic>th condition, has the form of Eq. <xref rid="Equ6" ref-type="">4</xref> with parameters indexed by condition <inline-formula id="IEq40"><alternatives><tex-math id="M121">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\left (a_{k,i}, b_{k,i}, r_{k,i}^{a}, r_{k,i}^{b}, {\omega }_{k}\right)$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M122"><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq40.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. The log-likelihood function for <italic>H</italic><sub>1</sub> is thus 
<disp-formula id="Equ14"><label>12</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M123">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ {\ln \mathcal{L}}_{1}(\mathcal{X}) = \sum_{k=1}^{2} \sum_{i=1}^{n} {\ln \mathcal{L}}_{1}^{k,i} (\mathcal{X})   $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M124"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ14.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>where 
<disp-formula id="Equ15"><label>13</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M125">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{array}{@{}rcl@{}} {\ln \mathcal{L}}_{1}^{k,i}(\mathcal{X}) &amp;=&amp; \gamma\left({{r}_{k,i}}+{{a}_{k,i}}\right) + \ln\left({{a}_{k,i}}!\right)  \\ &amp;+&amp;\gamma\left({{r}_{k,i}}+{{b}_{k,i}}\right) + \ln\left({{b}_{k,i}}!\right)  \\ &amp;+&amp; 2 {{r}_{k,i}} \ln {{r}_{k,i}} - 2 \gamma\left({{r}_{k,i}}\right)  \\ &amp;+&amp; {{a}_{k,i}} \ln\left({\lambda} {{\ell}^{a}} {{d}_{i}} \right) +{{b}_{k,i}} \ln\left({\omega}_{k} {\lambda} {{\ell}^{b}} {{d}_{i}} \right)  \\ &amp; -&amp; \left({{a}_{k,i}} + {{r}_{k,i}} \right) \ln \left({\lambda} {{\ell}^{a}} {{d}_{i}} + {{r}_{k,i}}\right)  \\ &amp; -&amp; \left. \left({{b}_{k,i}} + {{r}_{i}} \right) \ln \left({\omega}_{k} {\lambda} {{\ell}^{b}} {{d}_{i}} + {{r}_{k,i}}\right) \right]  \end{array} $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M126"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left center right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>!</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>!</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:mfenced close="]" open="" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ15.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>and <italic>γ</italic>(·)= ln<italic>Γ</italic>(·). The log-likelihood function for the null hypothesis (<inline-formula id="IEq41"><alternatives><tex-math id="M127">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}${\ln \mathcal {L}}_{0}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M128"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq41.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) is given by the above expressions with <italic>ω</italic><sub>1</sub>=<italic>ω</italic><sub>2</sub>=<italic>ω</italic>. The aggregation parameters (<italic>r</italic><sub><italic>k</italic>,<italic>i</italic></sub>) are determined from the data with experimental conditions <italic>k</italic>=1 and 2 considered separately (cf. Eqs. <xref rid="Equ19" ref-type="">17</xref>–<xref rid="Equ21" ref-type="">19</xref>).</p>
      <p>The log-likelihood function <inline-formula id="IEq42"><alternatives><tex-math id="M129">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}${\ln \mathcal {L}}_{1}(\mathcal {X})$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M130"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq42.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> used in the analysis of <italic>Δ</italic>HEB is maximized by numerically solving uncoupled systems of the form of Eqs. <xref rid="Equ9" ref-type="">7</xref> and <xref rid="Equ10" ref-type="">8</xref> for <inline-formula id="IEq43"><alternatives><tex-math id="M131">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\left (\hat {\lambda }_{1},\hat {\omega }_{1}\right)$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M132"><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq43.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq44"><alternatives><tex-math id="M133">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\left (\hat {\lambda }_{2},\hat {\omega }_{2}\right)$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M134"><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq44.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. The log-likelihood function <inline-formula id="IEq45"><alternatives><tex-math id="M135">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}${\ln \mathcal {L}}_{0}(\mathcal {X})$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M136"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq45.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is maximized by solving for <inline-formula id="IEq46"><alternatives><tex-math id="M137">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\hat {\lambda }_{1}, \hat {\lambda }_{2}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M138"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq46.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq47"><alternatives><tex-math id="M139">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\hat {\omega }$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M140"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq47.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> that lead to zero partial derivatives, 
<disp-formula id="Equ16"><label>14</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M141">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{array}{@{}rcl@{}} 0 &amp;=&amp; \left. \frac{{\partial \ln \mathcal{L}}_{0}}{\partial {{\lambda}_{1}} } \right|_{\hat{\lambda}_{1},\hat{\lambda}_{2},\hat{\omega}}  \end{array} $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M142"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left center right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="|" open="" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ16.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>
        <disp-formula id="Equ17">
          <label>15</label>
          <alternatives>
            <tex-math id="M143">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{array}{@{}rcl@{}} 0 &amp;=&amp; \left. \frac{{\partial \ln \mathcal{L}}_{0}}{\partial {{\lambda}_{2}}} \right|_{\hat{\lambda}_{1},\hat{\lambda}_{2},\hat{\omega}} \end{array} $$ \end{document}</tex-math>
            <mml:math id="M144">
              <mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left center right">
                <mml:mtr>
                  <mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1">
                    <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                  </mml:mtd>
                  <mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2">
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  </mml:mtd>
                  <mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3">
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mfenced close="|" open="" separators="">
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mfrac>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:msub>
                                  <mml:mrow>
                                    <mml:mi>∂</mml:mi>
                                    <mml:mo>ln</mml:mo>
                                    <mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi>
                                  </mml:mrow>
                                  <mml:mrow>
                                    <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                                  </mml:mrow>
                                </mml:msub>
                              </mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mi>∂</mml:mi>
                                <mml:msub>
                                  <mml:mrow>
                                    <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
                                  </mml:mrow>
                                  <mml:mrow>
                                    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                                  </mml:mrow>
                                </mml:msub>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:mfrac>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mfenced>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mover accent="true">
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
                              </mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
                            </mml:mover>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:msub>
                        <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mover accent="true">
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
                              </mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
                            </mml:mover>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:msub>
                        <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mover accent="true">
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>ω</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
                        </mml:mover>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                  </mml:mtd>
                </mml:mtr>
              </mml:mtable>
            </mml:math>
            <graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ17.gif" position="anchor"/>
          </alternatives>
        </disp-formula>
      </p>
      <p>
        <disp-formula id="Equ18">
          <label>16</label>
          <alternatives>
            <tex-math id="M145">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{array}{@{}rcl@{}} 0 &amp;=&amp; \left. \frac{\partial \ln \mathcal{L}_{0}}{\partial{\omega}} \right|_{\hat{\lambda}_{1},\hat{\lambda}_{2},\hat{\omega}} \,.  \end{array} $$ \end{document}</tex-math>
            <mml:math id="M146">
              <mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left center right">
                <mml:mtr>
                  <mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1">
                    <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                  </mml:mtd>
                  <mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2">
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  </mml:mtd>
                  <mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3">
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mfenced close="|" open="" separators="">
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mfrac>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mi>∂</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mo>ln</mml:mo>
                                <mml:msub>
                                  <mml:mrow>
                                    <mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi>
                                  </mml:mrow>
                                  <mml:mrow>
                                    <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                                  </mml:mrow>
                                </mml:msub>
                              </mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mi>∂ω</mml:mi>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:mfrac>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mfenced>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mover accent="true">
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
                              </mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
                            </mml:mover>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:msub>
                        <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mover accent="true">
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
                              </mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
                            </mml:mover>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:msub>
                        <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mover accent="true">
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>ω</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
                        </mml:mover>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mspace width="0.3em"/>
                    <mml:mi>.</mml:mi>
                  </mml:mtd>
                </mml:mtr>
              </mml:mtable>
            </mml:math>
            <graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ18.gif" position="anchor"/>
          </alternatives>
        </disp-formula>
      </p>
      <p>The optimal parameter values are used to evaluate the likelihoods, <inline-formula id="IEq48"><alternatives><tex-math id="M147">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\hat {\mathcal {L}}_{0} (\mathcal {X} ; \hat {\lambda }_{1},\hat {\lambda }_{2},\hat {\omega })$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M148"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq48.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq49"><alternatives><tex-math id="M149">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\hat {\mathcal {L}}_{1}(\mathcal {X} ; \hat {\lambda }_{1},\hat {\lambda }_{2},\hat {\omega }_{1}, \hat {\omega }_{2})$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M150"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq49.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, and the test statistic <italic>W</italic> (see Eq. <xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="">1</xref>).</p>
      <p>The numerical solution of these equations was facilitated by transforming these equations in a manner that ensured both parameters are positive and symmetric with respect to the mean expression levels of homeolog <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic> (see Appendix 2).</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec9" sec-type="results">
    <title>Results</title>
    <sec id="Sec10">
      <title>The likelihood ratio test for HEB applied to allotetraploid <italic>Mimulus luteus</italic></title>
      <p>To demonstrate the application of the likelihood ratio test for HEB, five biological replicates of RNA-seq data were generated from petals of the tetraploid <italic>Mimulus luteus</italic> (monkeyflower), and another five replicates were generated from the leaves (see Appendix 3 for details). We have chosen <italic>M. luteus</italic> because it is a tetraploid with two distinct subgenomes, denoted <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic> (mean synonymous divergence is ∼ 11.1<italic>%</italic>; for details on genome assembly, see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]). In this section, we use the likelihood ratio test for HEB to find homeologous gene pairs where one homeolog is expressed at significantly different levels than the other, one tissue at a time. In the section on <italic>Δ</italic>HEB we develop a likelihood ratio test to determine whether there is a significant difference in the bias between the two tissues.</p>
      <sec id="Sec11">
        <title>Homeolog expression bias in <italic>Mimulus luteus</italic> petals</title>
        <p>Figure <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> (top panel) shows the result of applying the likelihood ratio test for HEB to the petal data. There are 1853 homeologous gene pairs in <italic>M. luteus</italic> that can be identified as coming from separate subgenomes. Of these 1853 homoeologous pairs, 1560 were testable (measurable expression from each individual homeolog). Of testable pairs, a total of 676 gene pairs show significant bias (using a significance level of <italic>α</italic>=0.05, and applying the Benjamini-Hochberg correction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] to account for multiple testing error). In the 334 pairs biased towards the <italic>A</italic> homeolog the mean HEB is − 2.49 (5.6-fold change). In the 342 pairs biased towards the <italic>B</italic> homeolog, the mean HEB is 2.39 (5.2-fold change).
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Likelihood ratio test for HEB in petals (top) and leaves (bottom) of <italic>M. luteus</italic>. (<bold>Top</bold>) Of 1560 testable homeologous gene pairs in the petals (gray), a total of 676 show significant bias. Of these, 334 pairs are biased towards the <italic>A</italic> homeolog (yellow), with a mean HEB of − 2.49 (5.6 ×). 342 pairs are biased towards the <italic>B</italic> homeolog (blue), with a mean HEB of 2.39 (about 5.2 ×). (<bold>Bottom</bold>) Of 1560 testable homeologous gene pairs (gray), a total of 676 show significant bias. Of these, 334 pairs are biased towards the <italic>A</italic> homeolog (yellow), with a mean HEB of − 2.49 (5.6 ×). 342 pairs are biased towards the <italic>B</italic> homeolog (blue), with a mean HEB of 2.39 (about 5.2 ×). The Benajamini-Hochberg correction for multiple testing was applied at significance level <italic>α</italic>=0.05 (and also in Figs. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
        <p>These results may be indicative of a number of evolutionary processes. For example, one of the homeologs may have become sub- or neofunctionalized in this tissue, or one of the homeologs may simply be losing its function.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec12">
        <title>Homeolog expression bias in <italic>Mimulus luteus</italic> leaves</title>
        <p>Next, the likelihood ratio test for HEB was applied to the leaf data (results shown in Fig <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, bottom panel). Of 1853 homoeologous pairs, 1498 were testable and a total of 399 gene pairs show significant bias. In the 199 pairs biased towards the <italic>A</italic> homeolog the mean HEB is − 2.83 (7.1-fold change). In the 200 pairs biased towards the <italic>B</italic> homeolog, the mean HEB is 2.80 (7.0-fold change).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec13">
      <title>The likelihood ratio test for <italic>Δ</italic>HEB applied to allotetraploid <italic>Mimulus luteus</italic></title>
      <p>The likelihood ratio test for <italic>Δ</italic>HEB requires each homeolog to have at least one read in each condition. Returning to the leaf and petal data from the previous sections on HEB, this gives 1448 testable pairs. Figure <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> shows the results of the likelihood ratio test for <italic>Δ</italic>HEB. We find a total of 76 gene pairs show significant <italic>Δ</italic>HEB. Of these, 35 are more biased towards the <italic>A</italic> homeolog in the leaf than they are in the petal. The remaining 41 gene pairs are more biased towards the <italic>B</italic> homeolog in the leaf than in the petal.
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Likelihood ratio test for <italic>Δ</italic>HEB in the leaves vs. petals of <italic>M. luteus</italic>. Of 1448 testable homeologous gene pairs (gray), 76 show significant <italic>Δ</italic>HEB. Of these, 35 are more biased towards the <italic>A</italic> homeolog in the leaves than in the petals (yellow). 41 gene pairs are more biased towards the <italic>B</italic> homeolog in the leaf than in the petal (blue)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
      <p>Figure <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> shows a scatter plot of homeolog expression bias (HEB) in leaf and petal. Colored marks indicate gene pairs with statistically significant changes in homeolog expression bias (<italic>Δ</italic>HEB) (these points correspond to the colored bars in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Data points in the top-left and bottom-right quadrants of Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> represent homeologous pairs where one homeolog is more highly expressed in one tissue and its partner is more highly expressed in the other tissue. The top-right and bottom-left quadrants correspond to homeologous pairs where the difference in bias favors the same homeolog but has become more extreme. Finally, all of the marks that are colored blue or yellow show significant change in bias and are candidates for tissue specific sub- or neofunctionalization.
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Statistical significance of <italic>Δ</italic>HEB compared to homeolog expression bias (HEB) in leaf and petal. Yellow and blue indicates homeolog gene pairs with significant <italic>Δ</italic>HEB. The likelihood ratio test for <italic>Δ</italic>HEB is distinct from HEB tests in leaf and petal (see text)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
      <p>Although the change in homeolog expression bias is defined by Eq. <xref rid="Equ12" ref-type="">10</xref> as the log-fold change in homeolog expression bias, the intercalation of significant (yellow and blue) and not significant (gray) <italic>Δ</italic>HEB in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> makes it clear that statistical evidence for <italic>Δ</italic>HEB is not reducible to the difference between HEB<sub>leaf</sub> and HEB<sub>petal</sub> (the vertical or horizontal distance to the line of slope 1 where HEB<sub>leaf</sub>=HEB<sub>petal</sub>).</p>
      <p>Whether or not <italic>Δ</italic>HEB is statistically significant also depends on differences in sequencing depths, mean expression levels (e.g., lowly expressed genes are more likely to be influenced by shot noise), and ratios of gene lengths. All of these factors are considered simultaneously in the likelihood ratio test presented here. Assessing the statistical significance of <italic>Δ</italic>HEB using sequential HEB analysis would almost certainly result in a different set of genes being called significant.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec14">
      <title>Validation of the likelihood ratio tests using simulated data</title>
      <p>A natural question to ask about HEB and <italic>Δ</italic>HEB is, “How large does the change in expression levels between homeologs across conditions need to be before we can detect <italic>Δ</italic>HEB most of the time?” Unsurprisingly, this depends largely on the number of biological replicates.</p>
      <p>To explore this question, we generated simulated data with one expression level fixed at a constant value, <italic>μ</italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup>=100, and varied the other expression level, <italic>μ</italic><sup><italic>b</italic></sup>=2<sup><italic>x</italic></sup><italic>μ</italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup>, with <italic>x</italic>∈[0,2] in steps of 0.1. For each value of <italic>x</italic>, we generated 10,000 sets of data from a negative binomial distribution for <italic>N</italic>=3,6,12 and 24 replicates. We fixed the parameter <italic>r</italic>=10 for simplicity; this is within the range of values typically observed in RNA-seq data.</p>
      <p>Figure <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> shows the results of the likelihood ratio test for HEB on this simulated data set. We find that a 4-fold change is almost always detectable, regardless of the number of replicates. However, detecting a 2-fold change at least 95% of the time requires at least 12 replicates.
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Ability of the likelihood ratio test for HEB to detect different levels of bias. Simulation results show the fraction of times <italic>H</italic><sub>0</sub> was rejected for 10,000 trials with the given values of <italic>x</italic> and <italic>n</italic> (parameters: <italic>α</italic>=0.05, <italic>μ</italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup>=100, <italic>r</italic>=10). With <italic>n</italic>≥3 replicates, a 4-fold change is detectable over 95% of the time. Detecting a 2-fold change greater than 95% of the time requires at least 6 replicates</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p>
      <p>To assess the sensitivity of <italic>Δ</italic>HEB to different levels of bias shift, we created a similar data set. This time, we set 3 of the expression levels equal <inline-formula id="IEq50"><alternatives><tex-math id="M151">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\left (\mu ^{a}_{1} = \mu ^{b}_{1} = \mu ^{a}_{2} =100\right)$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M152"><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq50.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, and varied the fourth; <inline-formula id="IEq51"><alternatives><tex-math id="M153">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\mu ^{b}_{2} = 2^{x}\mu ^{a}_{2}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M154"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq51.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, with <italic>x</italic>∈[0,2] in steps of 0.1. The aggregation parameter was again fixed at <italic>r</italic>=10. For each value of <italic>x</italic>, 10,000 sets of data were generated from a negative binomial distribution for <italic>N</italic>=3,6,12 and 24 replicates.</p>
      <p>Figure <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> shows the results of the likelihood ratio test for <italic>Δ</italic>HEB on this simulated data set. The results are similar to those for HEB, with the test for <italic>Δ</italic>HEB being slightly less sensitive than the test for HEB. For <italic>Δ</italic>HEB, a 4-fold change in bias is detected more than 95% of the time when <italic>N</italic>≥6. As with the test for HEB, the ability to detect smaller changes increases significantly with the number of replicates.
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Ability of the likelihood ratio test for <italic>Δ</italic>HEB to detect different levels of change in bias. Simulation results show the fraction of times <italic>H</italic><sub>0</sub> was rejected for 10,000 trials with given values of <italic>x</italic> and <italic>n</italic> (parameters: <italic>α</italic>=0.05, <inline-formula id="IEq52"><alternatives><tex-math id="M155">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\mu ^{a}_{1}=\mu ^{b}_{1}=\mu ^{a}_{2} = 100$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M156"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq52.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <italic>r</italic>=10). With <italic>n</italic>≥6 replicates, a 4-fold change is detectable over 95% of the time. However, detecting a 2-fold change more than 95% of the time requires at least 12 replicates</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec15" sec-type="discussion">
    <title>Discussion</title>
    <sec id="Sec16">
      <title>Alternative methods</title>
      <p>Our method is transparent, derived specifically for the analysis of <italic>Δ</italic>HEB, and requires a minimal number of assumptions; nevertheless we wished to investigate whether other methods could achieve similar results. Because we found only one method analogous to ours in the literature (Homeoroq, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]), we developed three additional ad hoc methods. To compare these methods we generated simulated data sets and analyzed ROC curves. Each data set contained 10,000 gene pairs, half of which had <italic>Δ</italic>HEB fixed at a constant value (2, 8, and 16). Three replicates were generated from negative binomial distributions, and this was repeated 50 times for each value of <italic>Δ</italic>HEB (150 simulations total).</p>
      <p>First, we took a naive approach and performed t-tests and z-tests on the ratio of log<sub>2</sub>-fold changes between conditions 1 and 2. Next, we ran DESeq2 and extracted the estimated shrunken log<sub>2</sub>-fold changes and their standard errors, and performed a z-test (we call this method ‘DEZ’). Unsurprisingly, the naive methods (standard t- and z- tests) underperformed the LRT, with area under the ROC curve (ROC area) typically less than the LRT by ≈0.05 to 0.36.</p>
      <p>The LRT outperformed DEZ for <italic>Δ</italic>HEB=8 and 16 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>, top region). For <italic>Δ</italic>HEB=2, both methods performed poorly with mean ROC area =0.58080 for the LRT, while DEZ came out slightly ahead with mean ROC area =0.58083 (not shown). In all cases, the Homeoroq method significantly underperformed both alternatives.</p>
      <p>The test with largest ROC area is not necessarily the best choice, for example, when an ROC curve accumulates a small area for low FPR, and a large area for high FPR. To address this, we evaluated partial ROC area for false positive rates between 0 and 0.1, as researchers typically don’t accept FPR &gt; 0.1. An example truncated ROC curve is shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>. By this metric, the LRT outperforms DEZ for <italic>Δ</italic>HEB=8 and 16, while for <italic>Δ</italic>HEB=2 both methods performed poorly, with DEZ marginally better (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>, bottom region). Homeoroq significantly underperformed both alternatives at all levels of <italic>Δ</italic>HEB.
<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Example of a truncated ROC curve Comparison of the LRT, DEZ, and Homeoroq (HRO) using partial area under their ROC curves. For this comparison, 3 replicates of 10,000 homeolog pairs were simulated, half of which with <italic>Δ</italic>HEB=8. For most false positive rates, the LRT achieves a higher true positive rate than DEZ and HRO. This analysis was repeated 50 times for different levels of <italic>Δ</italic>HEB, and the area under the partial and full ROC curves are summarized in Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Comparison of the LRT, DEZ and Homeoroq (HRO) The top part of the plot shows the distribution of area under ROC curves for 100 trials of simulated data. Each trial contained 20,000 genes, half of which had <italic>Δ</italic>HEB fixed at a constant value. Results for <italic>Δ</italic>HEB=2 are not shown as they were too low (mean area for LRT =0.5616, for DEZ=0.5620). The bottom part of the plot shows ROC area constrained to false positive rates less than 0.1. In both regions, boxes indicate interquartile ranges, whiskers indicate 5th and 95th percentiles, and black lines indicate medians</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec17">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Gene duplication and polyploidy are extremely important factors in generating the diversity of life on earth. As Ohno stated in his seminal work on gene duplication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], “Natural selection merely modified while redundancy created” the raw materials necessary for the diversification of life on earth.</p>
      <p>In this paper we have developed a robust statistical framework specifically designed for the comparison of duplicate gene expression patterns. Importantly, this technique is consistent and reproducible. Through analysis of simulated data we have shown that these methods perform well, especially given the small sample sizes typical of RNA-seq experiments. We have shown that the ability to detect small differences in expression levels increases as a function of sample size, a fact that can be used to aid experimental design. Other authors have noted this in the context of traditional differential expression analysis and made similar recommendations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Moreover, we demonstrate the usefulness of the likelihood ratio test for <italic>Δ</italic>HEB using homeolog expression RNA-seq data derived from a polyploid plant. While we have developed this test for the purpose of analyzing changes in expression patterns of homeologous genes, we emphasize that the method is suitable for the expression analysis of any two genes (they need not be homeologs) across any two conditions.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec18">
    <title>Appendix 1: Estimation of aggregation parameters</title>
    <p>Due to the typically small number of replicates in RNA-seq experiments, accurate estimation of the aggregation parameter is not realistic on a gene-by-gene basis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Instead, we use the mean-variance relation of a negative binomial distribution, namely, 
<disp-formula id="Equ19"><label>17</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M157">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ \sigma^{2} = \mu + \frac{1}{r}\mu^{2} \,,   $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M158"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ19.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
    <p>to compute an aggregation parameter <italic>r</italic> for each experimental replicate, after rescaling to account for each replicates sequencing depth.</p>
    <p>In brief, let <inline-formula id="IEq53"><alternatives><tex-math id="M159">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$x_{j}^{i}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M160"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq53.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> denote the count data for the <italic>j</italic>th pair of homeologous genes obtained for experimental replicate <italic>i</italic>∈{1,2,…,<italic>n</italic>}. For each of the <italic>n</italic> replicates, we produce an auxiliary data set <inline-formula id="IEq54"><alternatives><tex-math id="M161">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\left (y_{k,j}^{i}\right)$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M162"><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq54.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> by rescaling the count data for all replicates as though each were obtained in an experiment with the sequencing depth of replicate <italic>k</italic>, 
<disp-formula id="Equ20"><label>18</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M163">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ y_{k,j}^{i} = \frac{{d}_{k}}{{{d}_{i}}}x_{j}^{i} \,.   $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M164"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ20.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
    <p>For each gene (<italic>j</italic>), we compute a scaled mean (<italic>μ</italic><sub><italic>k</italic>,<italic>j</italic></sub>) and variance <inline-formula id="IEq55"><alternatives><tex-math id="M165">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\left (\sigma ^{2}_{k,j}\right)$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M166"><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq55.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> of <inline-formula id="IEq56"><alternatives><tex-math id="M167">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$y_{k,j}^{i}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M168"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq56.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> over replicates (<italic>i</italic>). To obtain the aggregation parameter <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub>, we perform a nonlinear least squares fit of the observed mean-variance relation across all genes. That is, <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> minimizes the sum of squares error, 
<disp-formula id="Equ21"><label>19</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M169">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ E = \sum_{j} \left(\sigma^{2}_{k,j} -\mu_{k,j} - \frac{1}{r_{k}}\mu^{2}_{k,j} \right)^{2}  \,.  $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M170"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ21.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec19">
    <title>Appendix 2: Numerical scheme for maximum likelihood estimation</title>
    <p>For the analysis of both HEB and <italic>Δ</italic>HEB, parameter values maximizing the likelihood functions <inline-formula id="IEq57"><alternatives><tex-math id="M171">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\hat {\mathcal {L}}_{0}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M172"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq57.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq58"><alternatives><tex-math id="M173">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$\hat {\mathcal {L}}_{1}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M174"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq58.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> were obtained using the built-in MATLAB command fsolve applied to Eqs. <xref rid="Equ9" ref-type="">7</xref>–<xref rid="Equ11" ref-type="">9</xref> and <xref rid="Equ16" ref-type="">14</xref>–<xref rid="Equ18" ref-type="">16</xref>. In both cases, the numerical procedure was facilitated by changing variables from (<italic>λ</italic>,<italic>ω</italic>) to (<italic>v</italic>,<italic>y</italic>) through 
<disp-formula id="Equi"><alternatives><tex-math id="M175">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{array}{@{}rcl@{}} \lambda &amp;=&amp; e^{v-y}  \\ \omega &amp;=&amp; e^{2y}  \,, \end{array} $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M176"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left center right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equi.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
    <p>that is, <italic>v</italic>= ln<italic>λ</italic>+<italic>y</italic> and <italic>y</italic>=(ln<italic>ω</italic>)/2. This ensures positivity of <italic>λ</italic> and <italic>ω</italic> and leads to a system of equations that is symmetric in <italic>λ</italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup>⇔<italic>λ</italic><sup><italic>b</italic></sup>. The new variable <italic>v</italic> is the logarithm of the geometric mean of the expression levels <italic>λ</italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup>=<italic>λ</italic> and <italic>λ</italic><sup><italic>b</italic></sup>=<italic>ω</italic><italic>λ</italic>, 
<disp-formula id="Equ22"><alternatives><tex-math id="M177">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ v = \ln \sqrt{{{\lambda}^{a}}{{\lambda}^{b}}} = \ln \sqrt{\lambda \cdot \omega \lambda }  \,,  $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M178"><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>ωλ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ22.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
    <p>that is, <italic>λ</italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup>=<italic>λ</italic>=<italic>e</italic><sup><italic>v</italic>−<italic>y</italic></sup> and <italic>λ</italic><sup><italic>b</italic></sup>=<italic>ω</italic><italic>λ</italic>=<italic>e</italic><sup><italic>v</italic>+<italic>y</italic></sup>. The transformed partial derivatives used to maximize the log-likelihood <inline-formula id="IEq59"><alternatives><tex-math id="M179">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}${\ln \mathcal {L}}_{1}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M180"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq59.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> (Eqs. <xref rid="Equ9" ref-type="">7</xref>–<xref rid="Equ10" ref-type="">8</xref>) are 
<disp-formula id="Equ23"><label>20</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M181">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{array}{@{}rcl@{}} 0 &amp;=&amp; \frac{{\partial \ln \mathcal{L}}_{1}}{\partial v} = \sum_{i} {B}_{i}({v},{y}) + {A}_{i}({v},{y})  \end{array} $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M182"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left center right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ23.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
    <p>
      <disp-formula id="Equ24">
        <label>21</label>
        <alternatives>
          <tex-math id="M183">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{array}{@{}rcl@{}} 0 &amp;=&amp; \frac{{\partial \ln \mathcal{L}}_{1}}{\partial y} = \sum_{i} {B}_{i}({v},{y}) - {A}_{i}({v},{y})  \end{array} $$ \end{document}</tex-math>
          <mml:math id="M184">
            <mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left center right">
              <mml:mtr>
                <mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1">
                  <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                </mml:mtd>
                <mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2">
                  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                </mml:mtd>
                <mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3">
                  <mml:mfrac>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>∂</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mo>ln</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>∂y</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  <mml:munder>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:munder>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>B</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                </mml:mtd>
              </mml:mtr>
            </mml:mtable>
          </mml:math>
          <graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ24.gif" position="anchor"/>
        </alternatives>
      </disp-formula>
    </p>
    <p>where 
<disp-formula id="Equ25"><label>22</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M185">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{array}{@{}rcl@{}} {A}_{i}(v,y) = {{a}_{i}} - \frac{({{a}_{i}} + {{r}_{i}})e^{v-y} {{\ell}^{a}} {{d}_{i}} }{e^{v-y} {{\ell}^{a}} {{d}_{i}} +{{r}_{i}} } \end{array} $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M186"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left center right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ25.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
    <p>
      <disp-formula id="Equ26">
        <label>23</label>
        <alternatives>
          <tex-math id="M187">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{array}{@{}rcl@{}} {B}_{i}(v,y) = {{b}_{i}} - \frac{({{b}_{i}} + {{r}_{i}})e^{v+y} {{\ell}^{b}} {{d}_{i}} }{e^{v+y} {{\ell}^{b}} {{d}_{i}} +{{r}_{i}}}  \,. \end{array} $$ \end{document}</tex-math>
          <mml:math id="M188">
            <mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left center right">
              <mml:mtr>
                <mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1">
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>B</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mfrac>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                      <mml:msup>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msup>
                      <mml:msup>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msup>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:msup>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msup>
                      <mml:msup>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msup>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mfrac>
                  <mml:mspace width="0.3em"/>
                  <mml:mi>.</mml:mi>
                </mml:mtd>
              </mml:mtr>
            </mml:mtable>
          </mml:math>
          <graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ26.gif" position="anchor"/>
        </alternatives>
      </disp-formula>
    </p>
    <p>The transformed partial derivative used to maximize <inline-formula id="IEq60"><alternatives><tex-math id="M189">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}${\ln \mathcal {L}}_{0}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M190"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq60.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> are found by substituting <italic>y</italic>=0 in Eq. <xref rid="Equ23" ref-type="">20</xref>, 
<disp-formula id="Equj"><alternatives><tex-math id="M191">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{array}{@{}rcl@{}} 0 &amp; = &amp; \frac{{\partial \ln \mathcal{L}}_{0}}{\partial {v}} =\sum_{i} {B}_{i}(v,0) + {A}_{i}(v,0) \,.  \end{array} $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M192"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left center right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equj.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
    <p>For the analysis of <italic>Δ</italic>HEB, the partial derivatives used to maximize <inline-formula id="IEq61"><alternatives><tex-math id="M193">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}${\ln \mathcal {L}}_{1}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M194"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_IEq61.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> are two uncoupled systems of the form of Eq. <xref rid="Equ23" ref-type="">20</xref>–<xref rid="Equ26" ref-type="">23</xref>, one for each experimental condition (<italic>k</italic>=1 and 2), 
<disp-formula id="Equk"><alternatives><tex-math id="M195">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{array}{@{}rcl@{}} 0 &amp;=&amp; \frac{{\partial \ln \mathcal{L}}_{1}} {\partial v_{k}} = \sum_{i} {B}_{k,i}({v}_{k},{y}_k) + {A}_{k,i}({v}_{k},{y}_k)  \\ 0 &amp;=&amp; \frac{{\partial \ln \mathcal{L}}_{1}} {\partial y_{k}} = \sum_{i} {B}_{k,i}({v}_{k},{y}_k) - {A}_{k,i}({v}_{k},{y}_k)  \end{array} $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M196"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left center right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equk.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
    <p>where 
<disp-formula id="Equl"><alternatives><tex-math id="M197">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$\begin{array}{@{}rcl@{}} {A}_{k,i}(v,y) = {{a}_{k,i}} - \frac{({{a}_{k,i}} + {{r}_{k,i}})e^{v-y} {{\ell}^{a}} {{d}_{i}} }{e^{v-y} {{\ell}^{a}} {{d}_{i}} +{{r}_{k,i}}}  \\ {B}_{k,i}(v,y) = {{b}_{k,i}} - \frac{({{b}_{k,i}} + {{r}_{k,i}})e^{v+y} {{\ell}^{b}} {{d}_{i}} }{e^{v+y} {{\ell}^{b}} {{d}_{i}} +{{r}_{k,i}}}  \,. \end{array} $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M198"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left center right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"/><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-1"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-2"/><mml:mtd class="eqnarray-3"/><mml:mtd><mml:mtext/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equl.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
    <p>For the null hypothesis <italic>y</italic><sub>2</sub>=<italic>y</italic><sub>1</sub>=<italic>y</italic> we numerically solve a system of three equations, including 
<disp-formula id="Equ27"><alternatives><tex-math id="M199">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ 0 = \frac{{\partial \ln \mathcal{L}}_{0}} {\partial v_{k}} = \sum_{i} {B}_{k,i}({v}_{k},{y}) + {A}_{k,i}({v}_{k},{y})   $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M200"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ27.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
    <p>for <italic>k</italic>=1 and 2. These are coupled via 
<disp-formula id="Equ28"><alternatives><tex-math id="M201">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document} $$ 0 = \frac{{\partial \ln \mathcal{L}}_{0}} {\partial {y}} = \sum_{k} \sum_{i} {B}_{k,i}({v}_{k},{y}) - {A}_{k,i}({v}_{k},{y})  \,.  $$ \end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M202"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">ℒ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi>.</mml:mi></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2019_2709_Article_Equ28.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec20">
    <title>Appendix 3: Experimental methods</title>
    <p>Plant tissues were collected from second generation inbred <italic>Mimulus luteus</italic>. All plants were grown in a greenhouse under a 16 h light regiment at 21°C and 30% humidity. Petal tissue was collected from the corolla of a flower bud near blooming, and leaf tissue came from young leaves adjacent to the stem apical meristem. Five replicates of each tissue type were collected, at the same time of day, from different individuals. Approximately 100–200 mg of plant tissue was immediately placed into liquid nitrogen. RNA was extracted by grinding frozen tissue with pestles in PureLink Plant RNA Reagent from Ambion. Column isolation of RNA was subsequently performed using Direct-zol RNA MiniPrep Plus Kit from Zymo Research. Libraries were constructed using KAPA Stranded mRNA-Seq Kit. During library construction, sequence specific Illumina TruSeq <italic>Â</italic><italic>Ⓡ</italic> adapters were added to distinguish each library. Using an Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer, average fragment lengths were determined to be between 230 and 300 bp. Libraries were then pooled and sequenced by the Duke Center for Genomic and Computational Biology on an Illumina HiSeq 2500 instrument. The resulting reads (50 base pair, single end) were mapped to the <italic>M. luteus</italic> genome using bowtie2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>] with the –very-sensitive-local option. Reads to exonic regions were counted using htseq-count [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>] with the default settings (minimum alignment quality of 10 on the phred scale).</p>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <glossary>
    <title>Abbreviations</title>
    <def-list>
      <def-item>
        <term>FPR</term>
        <def>
          <p>False positive rate</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>HEB</term>
        <def>
          <p>Homeolog expression bias</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>LRT</term>
        <def>
          <p>Likelihood ratio test</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>ROC</term>
        <def>
          <p>Receiver operating characteristic</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>WGD</term>
        <def>
          <p>Whole genome duplication</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
    </def-list>
  </glossary>
  <ack>
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <p>The work was supported in part by National Science Foundation Grant DMS 1121606 to GDCS, the Biomathematics Initiative at The College of William &amp; Mary, and a W&amp;M Summer Research grant to JRP.</p>
    <sec id="d29e8145" sec-type="data-availability">
      <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
      <p>Sample MATLAB code and the data used in <italic>Δ</italic>HEB analysis can be found on the Mathworks file exchange, submission number 62502: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.mathworks.com/matlabcentral/fileexchange/62502">https://www.mathworks.com/matlabcentral/fileexchange/62502</ext-link>. Raw sequence reads are available on the NCBI SRA under accession number PRJNA380107: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov//bioproject/PRJNA380107">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov//bioproject/PRJNA380107</ext-link>.;</p>
    </sec>
  </ack>
  <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
    <title>Authors’ contributions</title>
    <p>All four co-authors were involved in conception of the work; data analysis and interpretation; and drafting, critical review and final approval of the article. Data collection (TJK and JRP). Mathematical framework and numerical scheme (RDS and GDCS). TJK supervised by JRP. RDS was jointly supervised by JRP and GDCS. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
  </notes>
  <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
    <sec>
      <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
      <p>Not applicable.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Publisher’s Note</title>
      <p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
    </sec>
  </notes>
  <ref-list id="Bib1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="CR1">
      <label>1</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ohno</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Evolution by Gene Duplication</source>
        <year>1970</year>
        <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
        <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR2">
      <label>2</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Otto</surname>
            <given-names>SP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Whitton</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Polyploid incidence and evolution</article-title>
        <source>Annu Rev Genet</source>
        <year>2000</year>
        <volume>34</volume>
        <fpage>401</fpage>
        <lpage>37</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.genet.34.1.401</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11092833</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR3">
      <label>3</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wendel</surname>
            <given-names>JF</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Genome evolution in polyploids</article-title>
        <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>
        <year>2000</year>
        <volume>42</volume>
        <fpage>225</fpage>
        <lpage>49</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1006392424384</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10688139</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR4">
      <label>4</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Crow</surname>
            <given-names>KD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wagner</surname>
            <given-names>GP</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>What is the role of genome duplication in the evolution of complexity and diversity?</article-title>
        <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
        <year>2006</year>
        <volume>23</volume>
        <issue>5</issue>
        <fpage>887</fpage>
        <lpage>92</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msj083</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16368775</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR5">
      <label>5</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Proulx</surname>
            <given-names>SR</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Multiple routes to subfunctionalization and gene duplicate specialization</article-title>
        <source>Genetics</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>190</volume>
        <fpage>737</fpage>
        <lpage>51</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.111.135590</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22143920</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR6">
      <label>6</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>McLysaght</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hokamp</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wolfe</surname>
            <given-names>KH</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Extensive genomic duplication during early chordate evolution</article-title>
        <source>Nat Genet</source>
        <year>2002</year>
        <volume>31</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <fpage>200</fpage>
        <lpage>4</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng884</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12032567</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR7">
      <label>7</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dehal</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Boore</surname>
            <given-names>JL</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Two rounds of whole genome duplication in the ancestral vertebrate</article-title>
        <source>PLoS Biol</source>
        <year>2005</year>
        <volume>3</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <fpage>314</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0030314</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR8">
      <label>8</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Spring</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Genome duplication strikes back</article-title>
        <source>Nat Genet</source>
        <year>2002</year>
        <volume>31</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <fpage>128</fpage>
        <lpage>30</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng0602-128</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12040374</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR9">
      <label>9</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chao</surname>
            <given-names>D-Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dilkes</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Luo</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Douglas</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yakubova</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lahner</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Salt</surname>
            <given-names>DE</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Polyploids exhibit higher potassium uptake and salinity tolerance in arabidopsis</article-title>
        <source>Science</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>341</volume>
        <issue>6146</issue>
        <fpage>658</fpage>
        <lpage>9</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1240561</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23887874</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR10">
      <label>10</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sémon</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wolfe</surname>
            <given-names>KH</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Preferential subfunctionalization of slow-evolving genes after allopolyploidization in <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic></article-title>
        <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>105</volume>
        <issue>24</issue>
        <fpage>8333</fpage>
        <lpage>8</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0708705105</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18541921</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR11">
      <label>11</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rastogi</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liberles</surname>
            <given-names>DA</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Subfunctionalization of duplicated genes as a transition state to neofunctionalization</article-title>
        <source>BMC Evol Biol</source>
        <year>2005</year>
        <volume>5</volume>
        <fpage>28</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2148-5-28</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15831095</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR12">
      <label>12</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Taylor</surname>
            <given-names>JS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Raes</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Duplication and divergence: The evolution of new genes and old ideas</article-title>
        <source>Annu Rev Genet</source>
        <year>2004</year>
        <volume>38</volume>
        <fpage>615</fpage>
        <lpage>43</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.genet.38.072902.092831</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15568988</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR13">
      <label>13</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Smet</surname>
            <given-names>RD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>de Peer</surname>
            <given-names>YV</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Redundancy and rewiring of genetic networks following genome-wide duplication events</article-title>
        <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>15</volume>
        <fpage>168</fpage>
        <lpage>76</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2012.01.003</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22305522</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR14">
      <label>14</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Blanc</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wolfe</surname>
            <given-names>KH</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Functional divergence of duplicated genes formed by polyploidy during <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> evolution</article-title>
        <source>The Plant Cell</source>
        <year>2004</year>
        <volume>16</volume>
        <issue>7</issue>
        <fpage>1679</fpage>
        <lpage>91</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.021410</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15208398</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR15">
      <label>15</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kassahn</surname>
            <given-names>KS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dang</surname>
            <given-names>VT</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wilkins</surname>
            <given-names>SJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Perkins</surname>
            <given-names>AC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ragan</surname>
            <given-names>MA</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Evolution of gene function and regulatory control after whole-genome duplication: Comparative analyses in vertebrates</article-title>
        <source>Genome Res</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>19</volume>
        <issue>8</issue>
        <fpage>1404</fpage>
        <lpage>18</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.086827.108</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19439512</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR16">
      <label>16</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Huminiecki</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wolfe</surname>
            <given-names>KH</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Divergence of spatial gene expression profiles following species-specific gene duplications in human and mouse</article-title>
        <source>Genome Res</source>
        <year>2004</year>
        <volume>14</volume>
        <issue>10a</issue>
        <fpage>1870</fpage>
        <lpage>9</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.2705204</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15466287</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR17">
      <label>17</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Makova</surname>
            <given-names>KD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>W-H</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Divergence in the spatial pattern of gene expression between human duplicate genes</article-title>
        <source>Genome Res</source>
        <year>2003</year>
        <volume>13</volume>
        <issue>7</issue>
        <fpage>1638</fpage>
        <lpage>45</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.1133803</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12840042</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR18">
      <label>18</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gu</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nicolae</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>HH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>W-H</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Rapid divergence in expression between duplicate genes inferred from microarray data</article-title>
        <source>Trends Genet</source>
        <year>2002</year>
        <volume>18</volume>
        <issue>12</issue>
        <fpage>609</fpage>
        <lpage>13</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-9525(02)02837-8</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12446139</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR19">
      <label>19</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Qiu</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>S-L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Adams</surname>
            <given-names>KL</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Frequent changes in expression profile and accelerated sequence evolution of duplicated imprinted genes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol Evol</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <issue>7</issue>
        <fpage>1830</fpage>
        <lpage>42</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evu144</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25115008</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR20">
      <label>20</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jiao</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wickett</surname>
            <given-names>NJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ayyampalayam</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chanderbali</surname>
            <given-names>AS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Landherr</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ralph</surname>
            <given-names>PE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tomsho</surname>
            <given-names>LP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liang</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Soltis</surname>
            <given-names>PS</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Ancestral polyploidy in seed plants and angiosperms</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>473</volume>
        <issue>7345</issue>
        <fpage>97</fpage>
        <lpage>100</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature09916</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21478875</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR21">
      <label>21</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wood</surname>
            <given-names>TE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Takebayashi</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Barker</surname>
            <given-names>MS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mayrose</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Greenspoon</surname>
            <given-names>PB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rieseberg</surname>
            <given-names>LH</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The frequency of polyploid speciation in vascular plants</article-title>
        <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>106</volume>
        <issue>33</issue>
        <fpage>13875</fpage>
        <lpage>9</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0811575106</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19667210</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR22">
      <label>22</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Renny-Byfield</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wendel</surname>
            <given-names>JF</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Doubling down on genomes: Polyploidy and crop plants</article-title>
        <source>Am J Bot</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>101</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <fpage>1711</fpage>
        <lpage>25</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3732/ajb.1400119</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25090999</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR23">
      <label>23</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kobel</surname>
            <given-names>HR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pasquier</surname>
            <given-names>LD</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Genetics of polyploid <italic>Xenopus</italic></article-title>
        <source>Trends Genet</source>
        <year>1986</year>
        <volume>2</volume>
        <fpage>310</fpage>
        <lpage>5</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0168-9525(86)90286-6</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR24">
      <label>24</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wolfe</surname>
            <given-names>KH</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Yesterday’s polyploids and the mystery of diploidization</article-title>
        <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>
        <year>2001</year>
        <volume>2</volume>
        <fpage>333</fpage>
        <lpage>41</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35072009</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11331899</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR25">
      <label>25</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Albertin</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Marullo</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Polyploidy in fungi: evolution after whole-genome duplication</article-title>
        <source>Proc R Soc B</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>279</volume>
        <fpage>2497</fpage>
        <lpage>509</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2012.0434</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR26">
      <label>26</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gallardo</surname>
            <given-names>MH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>González</surname>
            <given-names>CA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cebrián</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Molecular cytogenetics and allotetraploidy in the red vizcacha rat Tympanoctomys barrerae (Rodentia, Octodontidae)</article-title>
        <source>Genomics</source>
        <year>2006</year>
        <volume>88</volume>
        <fpage>214</fpage>
        <lpage>21</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ygeno.2006.02.010</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16580173</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR27">
      <label>27</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rivera</surname>
            <given-names>AS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pankey</surname>
            <given-names>MS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Plachetzki</surname>
            <given-names>DC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Villacorta</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Syme</surname>
            <given-names>AE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Serb</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Omilian</surname>
            <given-names>AR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Oakley</surname>
            <given-names>TH</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Gene duplication and the origins of morphological complexity in pancrustacean eyes, a genomic approach</article-title>
        <source>BMC Evol Biol</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>123</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2148-10-123</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20433736</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR28">
      <label>28</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hardison</surname>
            <given-names>RC</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Evolution of hemoglobin and its genes</article-title>
        <source>Cold Spring Harb Perspect Med</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>2</volume>
        <issue>12</issue>
        <fpage>011627</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a011627</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR29">
      <label>29</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>S-y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chi</surname>
            <given-names>W-t</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Charng</surname>
            <given-names>Y-y</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Recent gene duplication and subfunctionalization produced a mitochondrial GrpE, the nucleotide exchange factor of the Hsp70 complex, specialized in thermotolerance to chronic heat stress in <italic>arabidopsis</italic></article-title>
        <source>Plant Physiol</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>158</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <fpage>747</fpage>
        <lpage>58</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.111.187674</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22128139</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR30">
      <label>30</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Remnant</surname>
            <given-names>EJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Good</surname>
            <given-names>RT</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schmidt</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lumb</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Robin</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Daborn</surname>
            <given-names>PJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Batterham</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Gene duplication in the major insecticide target site, rdl, in <italic>drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title>
        <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>110</volume>
        <issue>36</issue>
        <fpage>14705</fpage>
        <lpage>10</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1311341110</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23959864</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR31">
      <label>31</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gerstein</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Snyder</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>RNA-Seq: a revolutionary tool for transcriptomics</article-title>
        <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <fpage>57</fpage>
        <lpage>63</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg2484</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19015660</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR32">
      <label>32</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Soneson C, Delorenzi M. A comparison of methods for differential expression analysis of RNA-seq data. BMC Bioinformatics. 2013;14(91).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR33">
      <label>33</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Love</surname>
            <given-names>MI</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huber</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Anders</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA-seq data with DESeq2</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>15</volume>
        <issue>12</issue>
        <fpage>550</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-014-0550-8</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25516281</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR34">
      <label>34</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Anders</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huber</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Differential expression analysis for sequence count data</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <fpage>R106</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2010-11-10-r106</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20979621</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR35">
      <label>35</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Grover</surname>
            <given-names>CE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gallagher</surname>
            <given-names>JP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Szadkowski</surname>
            <given-names>EP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yoo</surname>
            <given-names>MJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Flagel</surname>
            <given-names>LE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wendel</surname>
            <given-names>JF</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Homoeolog expression bias and expression level dominance in allopolyploids</article-title>
        <source>New Phytol</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>196</volume>
        <fpage>966</fpage>
        <lpage>71</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2012.04365.x</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23033870</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR36">
      <label>36</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wilks</surname>
            <given-names>SS</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The large sample distribution of the likelihood ratio test for testing composite hypotheses</article-title>
        <source>Ann Math Statist</source>
        <year>1938</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>60</fpage>
        <lpage>62</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1214/aoms/1177732360</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR37">
      <label>37</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Edger</surname>
            <given-names>PP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Smith</surname>
            <given-names>RD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McKain</surname>
            <given-names>MR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cooley</surname>
            <given-names>AM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vallejo-Marin</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yuan</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bewick</surname>
            <given-names>AJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ji</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Platts</surname>
            <given-names>AE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bowman</surname>
            <given-names>MJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Subgenome dominance in an interspecific hybrid, synthetic allopolyploid, and a 140 year old naturally established neo-allopolyploid monkeyflower</article-title>
        <source>The Plant Cell</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>29</volume>
        <issue>9</issue>
        <fpage>2150</fpage>
        <lpage>67</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.17.00010</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28814644</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR38">
      <label>38</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Benjamini</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hochberg</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</article-title>
        <source>J R Stat Soc Ser B Methodol</source>
        <year>1995</year>
        <volume>57</volume>
        <fpage>289</fpage>
        <lpage>300</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR39">
      <label>39</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Groppe DM. Benjamini &amp; Hochberg/Yekutieli false discovery rate control procedure for a set of statistical tests. 2015. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.mathworks.com/matlabcentral/fileexchange/27418-fdr-bh">https://www.mathworks.com/matlabcentral/fileexchange/27418-fdr-bh</ext-link>. Accessed 6 Dec 2017.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR40">
      <label>40</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Akama</surname>
            <given-names>Satoru</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shimizu-Inatsugi</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shimizu</surname>
            <given-names>KK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sese</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Genome-wide quantification of homeolog expression ratio revealed nonstochastic gene regulation in synthetic allopolyploid <italic>arabidopsis</italic></article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>42</volume>
        <issue>6</issue>
        <fpage>e46</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt1376</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24423873</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR41">
      <label>41</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhou</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>White</surname>
            <given-names>KP</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>RNA-seq differential expression studies: more sequence or more replication?</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>30</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <fpage>301</fpage>
        <lpage>4</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt688</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24319002</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR42">
      <label>42</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Schurch</surname>
            <given-names>NJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schofield</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gierlinski</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cole</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sherstnev</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Singh</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wrobel</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gharbi</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Simpson</surname>
            <given-names>GG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Owen-Hughes</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Blaxter</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Barton</surname>
            <given-names>GJ</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>How many biological replicates are needed in an RNA-seq experiment and which differential expression tool should you use?</article-title>
        <source>RNA</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>22</volume>
        <issue>6</issue>
        <fpage>839</fpage>
        <lpage>51</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1261/rna.053959.115</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27022035</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR43">
      <label>43</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Roulin</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Auer</surname>
            <given-names>PL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Libault</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schlueter</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Farmer</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>May</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stacey</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Doerge</surname>
            <given-names>RW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jackson</surname>
            <given-names>SA</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The fate of duplicated genes in a polyploid plant genome</article-title>
        <source>The Plant J</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>73</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>143</fpage>
        <lpage>53</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.12026</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22974547</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR44">
      <label>44</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Robinson</surname>
            <given-names>MD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Smyth</surname>
            <given-names>GK</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Small-sample estimation of negative binomial dispersion, with applications to SAGE data</article-title>
        <source>Biostatistics</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <fpage>321</fpage>
        <lpage>32</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/biostatistics/kxm030</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17728317</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR45">
      <label>45</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Langmead</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Salzberg</surname>
            <given-names>SL</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2</article-title>
        <source>Nat Methods</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <fpage>357</fpage>
        <lpage>9</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1923</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22388286</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR46">
      <label>46</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Anders</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pyl</surname>
            <given-names>PT</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huber</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>HTSeq–a Python framework to work with high-throughput sequencing data</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>31</volume>
        <fpage>638</fpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
