<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1367-4803</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1367-4811</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7703781</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31603498</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btz770</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">btz770</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Applications Note</subject>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading">
          <subject>Databases and Ontologies</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>dbInDel: a database of enhancer-associated insertion and deletion variants by analysis of H3K27ac ChIP-Seq</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5543-9334</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Huang</surname>
          <given-names>Moli</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btz770-aff1">1</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btz770-aff2">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Wang</surname>
          <given-names>Yunpeng</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btz770-aff1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Yang</surname>
          <given-names>Manqiu</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btz770-aff1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Yan</surname>
          <given-names>Jun</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btz770-aff3">3</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Yang</surname>
          <given-names>Henry</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btz770-aff4">4</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Zhuang</surname>
          <given-names>Wenzhuo</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btz770-aff1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Xu</surname>
          <given-names>Ying</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btz770-aff2">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Koeffler</surname>
          <given-names>H Phillip</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btz770-aff4">4</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btz770-aff5">5</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Lin</surname>
          <given-names>De-Chen</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btz770-aff5">5</xref>
        <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="btz770-cor1"/>
        <!--<email>dchlin11@gmail.com</email>-->
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Chen</surname>
          <given-names>Xi</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btz770-aff6">6</xref>
        <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="btz770-cor1"/>
        <!--<email>chenx9@sustech.edu.cn</email>-->
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name>
          <surname>Kelso</surname>
          <given-names>Janet</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Associate Editor</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <aff id="btz770-aff1">
      <label>1</label>
      <institution>Department of Bioinformatics, School of Biology and Basic Medical Sciences</institution>
    </aff>
    <aff id="btz770-aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Cambridge-Suda Genomic Research Center, Soochow University</institution>, Suzhou 215123, <country country="CN">China</country></aff>
    <aff id="btz770-aff3"><label>3</label><institution>MOE Key Laboratory of Model Animal for Disease Study, Nanjing University</institution>, Nanjing 210061, <country country="CN">China</country></aff>
    <aff id="btz770-aff4"><label>4</label><institution>Cancer Science Institute of Singapore, National University of Singapore</institution>, Singapore 119074, <country country="SG">Singapore</country></aff>
    <aff id="btz770-aff5"><label>5</label><institution>Department of Medicine, Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</institution>, Los Angeles, CA 90048, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
    <aff id="btz770-aff6"><label>6</label><institution>Department of Biology, Southern University of Science and Technology</institution>, Shenzhen 518055, <country country="CN">China</country></aff>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="btz770-cor1">To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email>dchlin11@gmail.com</email> or <email>chenx9@sustech.edu.cn</email></corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
      <month>3</month>
      <year>2020</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2019-10-11">
      <day>11</day>
      <month>10</month>
      <year>2019</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>11</day>
      <month>10</month>
      <year>2019</year>
    </pub-date>
    <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
    <volume>36</volume>
    <issue>5</issue>
    <fpage>1649</fpage>
    <lpage>1651</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>17</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2019</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>24</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2019</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>08</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2019</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2019. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
      <license license-type="cc-by-nc" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xlink:href="btz770.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <sec id="s1">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <p>Cancer hallmarks rely on its specific transcriptional programs, which are dysregulated by multiple mechanisms, including genomic aberrations in the DNA regulatory regions. Genome-wide association studies have shown many variants are found within putative enhancer elements. To provide insights into the regulatory role of enhancer-associated non-coding variants in cancer epigenome, and to facilitate the identification of functional non-coding mutations, we present dbInDel, a database where we have comprehensively analyzed enhancer-associated insertion and deletion variants for both human and murine samples using ChIP-Seq data. Moreover, we provide the identification and visualization of upstream TF binding motifs in InDel-containing enhancers. Downstream target genes are also predicted and analyzed in the context of cancer biology. The dbInDel database promotes the investigation of functional contributions of non-coding variants in cancer epigenome.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2">
        <title>Availability and implementation</title>
        <p>The database, dbInDel, can be accessed from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://enhancer-indel.cam-su.org/">http://enhancer-indel.cam-su.org/</ext-link>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3">
        <title>Supplementary information</title>
        <p><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary data</xref> are available at <italic>Bioinformatics</italic> online.</p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>National Key R&amp;D Program of China</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>2018YFA0801100</award-id>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100001809</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>31971117</award-id>
        <award-id>81672873</award-id>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="3"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec>
    <title>1 Introduction</title>
    <p>Human cancer genome contains millions of non-coding mutations of either germline or somatic origins, including single-nucleotide substitutions, small and large insertions and deletions (<xref rid="btz770-B5" ref-type="bibr">Groschel <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). Since estimation of region-specific background mutational rates in tumor samples can be particularly challenging, it is extremely difficult to systematically and unbiasedly assess the selection pressure of non-coding mutations in a genome-wide manner (<xref rid="btz770-B7" ref-type="bibr">Polak <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="btz770-B8" ref-type="bibr">Schuster-Bockler and Lehner, 2012</xref>). As a result, to date, only a few non-coding variants have been characterized and the functional contribution of non-coding mutations is underappreciated (<xref rid="btz770-B4" ref-type="bibr">Garraway and Lander, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="btz770-B12" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>). Recent genome-wide association studies (GWAS) have shown that many cancer-related variants tend to appear in putative enhancer elements (<xref rid="btz770-B10" ref-type="bibr">Sur and Taipale, 2016</xref>), which can be systematically investigated via techniques such as ChIP-Seq of histone marks or ATAC-Seq. By focusing on mutations in putative enhancers, one can profoundly reduce surveying space and increase statistical power. In this way, we not only capture bona fide InDels, but also detect low frequency variants in the regulatory regions (<xref rid="btz770-B1" ref-type="bibr">Abraham <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). In addition, we could efficiently link candidate variants to target transcripts. More importantly, we have further developed this method to incorporate transcription factor binding motif analysis, which considerably facilitates the identification of potential upstream transcriptional regulators involved.</p>
    <p>Here, we present dbInDel, the first comprehensive and interactive database cataloging enhancer-associated insertion and deletion variants for both human and murine samples. Unlike the COSMIC (<xref rid="btz770-B11" ref-type="bibr">Tate <italic>et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>), an established database centered on the annotation of existing somatic mutations, our database focuses on the construction of bona fide enhancer-associated InDels captured from H3K27ac ChIP-Seq experiments, leveraging recent advances in alignment algorithms (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S1A</xref>). To facilitate the analysis of target transcripts of InDel-containing enhancers, we integrate mRNA expression profiles and survival analysis in both tumor and normal samples across all human cancer types (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S1B</xref>). Moreover, our method identifies the potential recruitment of transcription factors as a result of enhancer-associated InDels, promoting the investigation of functional contributions of this important class of non-coding variants (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S1C</xref>).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>2 Materials and methods and results</title>
    <p>To identify small InDels (defined as &lt;50 bp) in putative enhancer elements across a broad spectrum of cancers, we computationally reconstructed the published method described in <xref rid="btz770-B1" ref-type="bibr">Abraham <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref> and analyzed H3K27ac ChIP-Seq datasets from over 250 samples representing 26 cancer types. The detailed workflow is summarized in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>. Briefly, we first mapped ChIP-Seq reads to the reference genome to establish putative enhancer landscapes. Then, from the unmapped reads of ChIP-Seq, we identified and verified enhancer-associated InDels with multiple alignment procedures. Currently, our database contains 640 432 insertions and 157 554 deletions in 593 655 putative enhancers detected in 275 samples (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table S1</xref>). Within all the InDels, there are 274 995 unique insertions and 71 603 unique deletions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S3</xref>). Notably, our results showed that many well-established cancer type-specific drivers harbored unique enhancer-associated InDels in the respective cancer types. For example, AR, a unique prostate cancer oncogene, was detected to have enhancer-associated InDels exclusively in prostate cancer samples. Similarly, TAL1 had enhancer-associated InDels only in leukemia and lymphoma samples (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S4</xref>). These data strongly suggest that some of the enhancer-associated InDels detected by our pipeline are under selection pressure, and they confer growth/survival advantages to specific types of cells because of the unique functions of the target genes that they regulate.</p>
    <p>We next performed integrative and comprehensive analysis focusing on the predicted downstream genes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S1B</xref>). Specifically, in the context of cancer biology, we performed survival analysis, tumor/normal differential expression using TCGA/GTEx data and mRNA expression of target genes in cancer cell lines from CCLE, considering this information is particularly relevant for understanding tumor cell biology. Moreover, putative cancer drivers were predicted using Cancer Gene Consensus of Sanger. Notably, 26 out of 100 genes with the highest numbers of enhancer-associated InDels are categorized as cancer drivers; in stark contrast, none of the genes with the lowest numbers of enhancer-associated InDels are designated as drivers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S5</xref>). This finding may partially indicate that a faction of predicted InDels were under positive selection pressure during tumor development. In addition, we provided their potential roles in cancers (<xref rid="btz770-B2" ref-type="bibr">Bailey <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>), drug-gene interaction (<xref rid="btz770-B3" ref-type="bibr">Cotto <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>) and GWAS publications, further facilitating the analysis of putative cancer genes for our users.</p>
    <p>To facilitate exploration of the potential mechanism of InDels on regulating the activity of their hosting enhancers, we incorporated motif analysis to predict the TF binding motifs which are generated by the detected InDels. Briefly, using FIMO we scanned canonic TF binding motifs in each InDel-containing sequence, and compared that with results obtained from the reference genome. Motifs and associated TFs that were specific to InDel-containing sequences were compiled and visualized in our database (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S1C</xref>). Using this method, we successfully recovered the MYB motif, which is generated by the insertions in the super-enhancer region of TAL1 gene in Jurkat cells, as shown previously (<xref rid="btz770-B6" ref-type="bibr">Mansour <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). More importantly, numerous additional recruitments of potentially important TFs were predicted by our method. A particularly notable case was found in the super-enhancer region downstream of FOXA1 in a prostate cancer cell line 22Rv1 (<xref rid="btz770-B9" ref-type="bibr">Shukla <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). We predicted that a CTT deletion generated a canonical HNF4G motif (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S6A</xref>, P 5.67e-05; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Tables S2 and S3</xref>). Importantly, in 22Rv1 cells, ChIP-Seq data revealed prominent HNF4G binding precisely in our predicted InDel locus within this FOXA1 super-enhancer. In contrast, in the wild-type cell line LnCaP, no such HNF4G binding was observed and FOXA1 had a much weaker H3K27ac signal (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S6A</xref>). Even forced over-expression of HNF4G in LnCaP cells did not lead to its occupancy to this FOXA1 enhancer region. Interestingly, the FOXA1 expressions are comparable in this two cell lines (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S6B</xref>). Supportively, FOXA1 was expressed uniquely high in prostate cancer in a pan-cancer analysis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S6C</xref>). High FOXA1 level was also associated with poor prognosis in this cancer, albeit without reaching statistical significance (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S6D</xref>). Our data thus implies that this CTT deletion introduces a canonical HNF4G motif, which may recruit HNF4G binding to the downstream of FOXA1 locus in 22Rv1 cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S6E</xref>). This indicates the mechanisms causing the high expression of FOXA1 may vary in different samples.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>3 Discussion</title>
    <p>With the field of epigenome advancing rapidly, non-coding mutations identified directly from epigenomic feature is one of the most investigated area. There exists a great need among cancer researchers to understand the functional significance of these variants. To the best of our knowledge, dbInDel is the first database that allows users to perform interactive analysis of non-coding InDels, upstream TF prediction and enhancer features. In addition, we incorporated many cancer-centric analysis of candidate InDel-associated genes, including differential expression between matched normal and tumor samples, survival analysis, function predictions, drug-gene interactions and potential upstream TF binding analysis. Those features greatly facilitate the investigations by cancer researchers. This would result in the identification of important mutations and fast forward novel therapeutics to target the non-coding genome.</p>
    <p>A few databases exist curating non-coding somatic mutations (e.g. COSMIC, ICGC, DoCM, IntOGen) or germline variants (ClinVar) in human cancers. However, none of these resources associates non-coding mutations with distal cis-regulatory elements (such as enhancers or other TF binding sites). Therefore, it is extremely difficult to prioritize the functional potential of the large number of non-coding variants in the cancer genome. Our database directly tackles this problem. In addition, with the ever-increasing number of cancer samples profiled by epigenome sequencing (such as ChIP-Seq and ATAC-Seq), the catalog of non-coding InDel variants associated with functional epigenomic domains will be expanding rapidly and we will continue adding the newly identified variants in our database.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup1">
      <label>btz770_Supplementary_Data</label>
      <media xlink:href="btz770_supplementary_data.zip">
        <caption>
          <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
        </caption>
      </media>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack id="ack1">
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <p>The authors would like to thank Richard A. Young for sharing calling InDel variants pipeline to this work. They also thank Kar-tong Tan and HPK lab members for the kind help.</p>
    <sec>
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p>The work was supported by National Key R&amp;D Program of China (2018YFA0801100), National Natural Science Foundation of China (31971117, 81672873) and the Priority Academic Program Development of Jiangsu Higher Education Institutions.</p>
      <p><italic>Conflict of Interest</italic>: none declared.</p>
    </sec>
  </ack>
  <ref-list id="ref1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="btz770-B1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) 
<article-title>Small genomic insertions form enhancers that misregulate oncogenes</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun</source>., <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>14385</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28181482</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz770-B2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) 
<article-title>Comprehensive characterization of cancer driver genes and mutations</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>174</volume>, <fpage>1034</fpage>–<lpage>1035</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30096302</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz770-B3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cotto</surname><given-names>K.C.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) 
<article-title>DGIdb 3.0: a redesign and expansion of the drug-gene interaction database</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>D1068</fpage>–<lpage>D1073</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29156001</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz770-B4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garraway</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) 
<article-title>Lessons from the cancer genome</article-title>. <source>Cell</source><volume>153</volume>, <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23540688</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz770-B5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Groschel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) 
<article-title>A single oncogenic enhancer rearrangement causes concomitant EVI1 and GATA2 deregulation in leukemia</article-title>. <source>Cell</source><volume>157</volume>, <fpage>369</fpage>–<lpage>381</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24703711</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz770-B6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mansour</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) 
<article-title>Oncogene regulation. An oncogenic super-enhancer formed through somatic mutation of a noncoding intergenic element</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>346</volume>, <fpage>1373</fpage>–<lpage>1377</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25394790</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz770-B7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Polak</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) 
<article-title>Reduced local mutation density in regulatory DNA of cancer genomes is linked to DNA repair</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biotechnol</source>., <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24336318</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz770-B8">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuster-Bockler</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lehner</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>Chromatin organization is a major influence on regional mutation rates in human cancer cells</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>488</volume>, <fpage>504</fpage>–<lpage>507</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22820252</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz770-B9">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) 
<article-title>Aberrant activation of a gastrointestinal transcriptional circuit in prostate cancer mediates castration resistance</article-title>. <source>Cancer Cell</source>, <volume>32</volume>, 792–806.e7.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz770-B10">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sur</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taipale</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) 
<article-title>The role of enhancers in cancer</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Cancer</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>483</fpage>–<lpage>493</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27364481</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz770-B11">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tate</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>) 
<article-title>COSMIC: the catalogue of somatic mutations in cancer</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>D941</fpage>–<lpage>D947</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30371878</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz770-B12">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) 
<article-title>A global transcriptional network connecting noncoding mutations to changes in tumor gene expression</article-title>. <source>Nat. Genet</source>., <volume>50</volume>, <fpage>613</fpage>–<lpage>620</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29610481</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
