<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1367-4803</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1367-4811</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7703748</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31562766</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btz732</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">btz732</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Applications Notes</subject>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading">
          <subject>Structural Bioinformatics</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>The CroCo cross-link converter: a user-centred tool to convert results from cross-linking mass spectrometry experiments</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3316-9999</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Bender</surname>
          <given-names>Julian</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btz732-aff1"/>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9410-1424</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Schmidt</surname>
          <given-names>Carla</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="btz732-cor1"/>
        <!--<email>carla.schmidt@biochemtech.uni-halle.de</email>-->
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="btz732-aff1"/>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name>
          <surname>Valencia</surname>
          <given-names>Alfonso</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Associate Editor</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <aff id="btz732-aff1"><institution>Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg, Institute for Biochemistry and Biotechnology, Interdisciplinary Research Center HALOmem</institution>, Charles Tanford Protein Center, 06120 Halle (Saale), <country country="DE">Germany</country></aff>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="btz732-cor1">To whom correspondence should be addressed. <email>carla.schmidt@biochemtech.uni-halle.de</email></corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
      <day>15</day>
      <month>2</month>
      <year>2020</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2019-09-28">
      <day>28</day>
      <month>9</month>
      <year>2019</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>28</day>
      <month>9</month>
      <year>2019</year>
    </pub-date>
    <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
    <volume>36</volume>
    <issue>4</issue>
    <fpage>1296</fpage>
    <lpage>1297</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2019</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>09</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2019</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2019</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2019. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
      <license license-type="cc-by" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xlink:href="btz732.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <sec id="s1">
        <title>Motivation</title>
        <p>A variety of search engines exists for the identification of peptide spectrum matches after cross-linking mass spectrometry experiments. The resulting diversity in output formats complicates data validation and visualization as well as exchange with collaborators, particularly from other research areas.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2">
        <title>Results</title>
        <p>Here, we present CroCo, a user-friendly standalone executable to convert cross-linking results to a comprehensive spreadsheet format. Using this format, CroCo can be employed to generate input files for a selection of the commonly utilized validation and visualization tools.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3">
        <title>Availability and implementation</title>
        <p>The source-code is freely available under a GNU general public license at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/cschmidtlab/croco">https://github.com/cschmidtlab/croco</ext-link>. The standalone executable is available and documented at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cschmidtlab.github.io/CroCo">https://cschmidtlab.github.io/CroCo</ext-link>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4">
        <title>Supplementary information</title>
        <p><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary data</xref> are available at <italic>Bioinformatics</italic> online.</p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <named-content content-type="funder-name">Federal Ministry for Education and Research</named-content>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>03Z22HN22</award-id>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <named-content content-type="funder-name">European Regional Development Funds</named-content>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>ZS/2016/04/78115</award-id>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <named-content content-type="funder-name">Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes</named-content>
        </funding-source>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="2"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec>
    <title>1 Introduction</title>
    <p>Chemical cross-linking and mass spectrometry (XL-MS) are often combined to gain low-resolution structural information on protein–protein interactions (<xref rid="btz732-B13" ref-type="bibr">Rappsilber, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="btz732-B15" ref-type="bibr">Sinz, 2014</xref>). For this, a protein or protein complex is treated with a chemical cross-linker that covalently links amino acid residues in close proximity. The proteins are then enzymatically hydrolyzed and cross-linked di-peptides are identified by MS.</p>
    <p>As the combination of potential covalently linked peptide sequences significantly increases the database search space, specialized software tools have been developed for the analysis of XL-MS experiments. The most commonly used tools for identification of covalently linked di-peptides include xQuest (<xref rid="btz732-B14" ref-type="bibr">Rinner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>), StavroX (<xref rid="btz732-B3" ref-type="bibr">Gotze <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>), pLink (<xref rid="btz732-B16" ref-type="bibr">Yang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>), Kojak (<xref rid="btz732-B6" ref-type="bibr">Hoopmann <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>) and XiSearch (<xref rid="btz732-B12" ref-type="bibr">Mendes <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>). After identification of cross-linked residues, spectral annotation can manually be validated using tools such as pLabel (<xref rid="btz732-B11" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>) or xiSPEC (<xref rid="btz732-B9" ref-type="bibr">Kolbowski <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>). Identified cross-links can further be explored by mapping them on three-dimensional structures using xWalk (<xref rid="btz732-B8" ref-type="bibr">Kahraman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>) or XlinkAnalyzer (<xref rid="btz732-B10" ref-type="bibr">Kosinski <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>) or by generating network plots using xiNet (<xref rid="btz732-B1" ref-type="bibr">Combe <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>) or xVis (<xref rid="btz732-B4" ref-type="bibr">Grimm <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). DynamXL integrates conformational ensembles of proteins with cross-linking (<xref rid="btz732-B2" ref-type="bibr">Degiacomi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>).</p>
    <p>However, each software tool requires specific input formats and, therefore, most laboratories developed an individual data processing pipeline. Community standards are consequently missing (<xref rid="btz732-B7" ref-type="bibr">Iacobucci <italic>et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>). Here, we introduce CroCo, a software tool to convert results of the most commonly used cross-link search engines to a common text format that simplifies data handling and management. The text file can then be converted to input files for the post-processing tools described.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>2 Implementation</title>
    <p>CroCo is written in Python 3.6 and relies on the pandas library for handling data tables. The graphical user-interface (GUI) is based on wxPython. CroCo is designed as a standalone executable that allows fast and easy distribution; a Python module for integration into existing workflows is also available. It is centred on collection of scripts to parse the output formats of the commonly used cross-linking search engines Kojak, StavroX, Xi, pLink and xQuest. During data conversion, the input file is internally transformed into a pandas data frame object with defined column headers. The data frame can be exported in comma-separated .csv format (called xTable) to simplify manual validation of the identified cross-links as well as data filtering. As an example, using the xTable, an input file for the pLabel spectral annotation software can be created. During manual inspection using pLabel, peptide-spectrum matches of lower quality can be removed from the xTable. The reduced table containing high-confidence cross-links can then be converted to an input file for cross-link visualization tools. A list of output formats available is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="btz732-F1">Figure 1</xref>.
</p>
    <fig id="btz732-F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>CroCo workflow. The user can select one of the available input formats (<bold>A</bold>) in the graphical user-interface (<bold>B</bold>). After selecting one of the post-processing tools compatible with CroCo (<bold>C</bold>) and providing the respective input and output paths, conversion can be started. If additional information is required for conversion (e.g. additional input files), CroCo will ask the user in a pop-up window</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="btz732f1"/>
    </fig>
    <p>Using the standalone GUI, the user can select the appropriate input and output formats as well as the required file paths followed by data conversion. Additional information needed to generate the xTable is requested in an additional window, if necessary. As CroCo relies on the xTable intermediate data file, it can easily be extended including additional software tools while maintaining full compatibility with the already established tools and formats.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>3 Results</title>
    <p>To demonstrate the use of CroCo, we chemically cross-linked homomeric pyruvate kinase from rabbit. The cross-linked protein complex was analysed following established standard protocols (<xref rid="btz732-B5" ref-type="bibr">Haupt <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). Potential cross-links were then identified employing the various search engines compatible with CroCo. Examples of the input files and converted xTable files and a description of the column headers used are presented in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref>. Note, that CroCo will generate columns containing additional database search results present in the corresponding input file. The addition of the original search results not required to generate the xTable can optionally be turned off during data conversion. The conversion of a selected xTable to the available output formats for data validation and visualization was tested (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref>).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>4 Conclusion</title>
    <p>We developed CroCo, a user-friendly conversion tool for cross-linking data management. Manual inspection followed by conversion to the xTable simplifies data exchange within the cross-linking community. The generated xTable could serve as a common data structure paving the way to reach a common reporting standard. We aim to integrate a community-based standardized reporting data-format as soon as it is defined.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup1">
      <label>btz732_Supplementary_Data</label>
      <media xlink:href="btz732_supplementary_data.zip">
        <caption>
          <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
        </caption>
      </media>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack id="ack1">
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <p>The authors thank Sabine Wittig, Marie Barth, Julia Hesselbarth and Patrick Pieczyk for extensive testing of CroCo and Marie Barth for providing a test file. They also thank Iva Pritišanac for comments on the Python script.</p>
    <sec>
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p>This work was supported by the Federal Ministry for Education and Research (BMBF, ZIK programme, 03Z22HN22), the European Regional Development Funds (EFRE, ZS/2016/04/78115), the German Research Foundation (DFG, RTG 2467) and the MLU Halle-Wittenberg. J.B. acknowledges funding from the Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes.</p>
      <p><italic>Conflict of Interest</italic>: none declared.</p>
    </sec>
  </ack>
  <ref-list id="ref1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="btz732-B1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Combe</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) 
<article-title>xiNET: cross-link network maps with residue resolution</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell. Proteomics</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>1137</fpage>–<lpage>1147</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25648531</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz732-B2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Degiacomi</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) 
<article-title>Accommodating protein dynamics in the modeling of chemical crosslinks</article-title>. <source>Structure</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>1751</fpage>–<lpage>1757</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28966018</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz732-B3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gotze</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>StavroX–a software for analyzing crosslinked products in protein interaction studies</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Soc. Mass Spectrom</source>., <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22038510</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz732-B4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimm</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) 
<article-title>xVis: a web server for the schematic visualization and interpretation of crosslink-derived spatial restraints</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>W362</fpage>–<lpage>W369</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25956653</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz732-B5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haupt</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) 
<article-title>Combining chemical cross-linking and mass spectrometry of intact protein complexes to study the architecture of multi-subunit protein assemblies</article-title>. <source>J. Vis. Exp.</source>, <bold>129</bold>, e56747.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz732-B6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoopmann</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) 
<article-title>Kojak: efficient analysis of chemically cross-linked protein complexes</article-title>. <source>J. Proteome Res</source>., <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>2190</fpage>–<lpage>2198</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25812159</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz732-B7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iacobucci</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>) 
<article-title>First community-wide, comparative cross-linking mass spectrometry study</article-title>. <source>Anal. Chem</source>., <volume>91</volume>, <fpage>6953</fpage>–<lpage>6961</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31045356</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz732-B8">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kahraman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) 
<article-title>Xwalk: computing and visualizing distances in cross-linking experiments</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>2163</fpage>–<lpage>2164</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21666267</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz732-B9">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolbowski</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) 
<article-title>xiSPEC: web-based visualization, analysis and sharing of proteomics data</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>W473</fpage>–<lpage>W478</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29741719</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz732-B10">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kosinski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) 
<article-title>Xlink Analyzer: software for analysis and visualization of cross-linking data in the context of three-dimensional structures</article-title>. <source>J. Struct. Biol</source>., <volume>189</volume>, <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>183</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25661704</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz732-B11">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) 
<article-title>pFind: a novel database-searching software system for automated peptide and protein identification via tandem mass spectrometry</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>3049</fpage>–<lpage>3050</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15817687</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz732-B12">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) 
<article-title>An integrated workflow for cross-linking/mass spectrometry</article-title>. <source>bioRxiv</source><volume>355396</volume>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz732-B13">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rappsilber</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) 
<article-title>The beginning of a beautiful friendship: cross-linking/mass spectrometry and modelling of proteins and multi-protein complexes</article-title>. <source>J. Struct. Biol</source>., <volume>173</volume>, <fpage>530</fpage>–<lpage>540</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21029779</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz732-B14">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rinner</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) 
<article-title>Identification of cross-linked peptides from large sequence databases</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>315</fpage>–<lpage>318</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18327264</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz732-B15">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sinz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) 
<article-title>The advancement of chemical cross-linking and mass spectrometry for structural proteomics: from single proteins to protein interaction networks</article-title>. <source>Expert Rev. Proteomics</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>733</fpage>–<lpage>743</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25227871</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btz732-B16">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>Identification of cross-linked peptides from complex samples</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>904</fpage>–<lpage>906</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22772728</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
