<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ACS//DTD ACS Journal DTD v1.02 20061031//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName ACSJournal-v102.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.02?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName acs2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">ACS Omega</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">ACS Omega</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ao</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="coden">acsodf</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>ACS Omega</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">2470-1343</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>American Chemical Society</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7557219</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsomega.0c02564</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group>
        <subject>Article</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>proteiNorm – A User-Friendly Tool for Normalization
and Analysis of TMT and Label-Free Protein Quantification</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath1">
        <name>
          <surname>Graw</surname>
          <given-names>Stefan</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">†</xref>
        <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">‡</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath2">
        <name>
          <surname>Tang</surname>
          <given-names>Jillian</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">†</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath3">
        <name>
          <surname>Zafar</surname>
          <given-names>Maroof K</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">†</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath4">
        <name>
          <surname>Byrd</surname>
          <given-names>Alicia K</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">†</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath5">
        <name>
          <surname>Bolden</surname>
          <given-names>Chris</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">§</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath6">
        <name>
          <surname>Peterson</surname>
          <given-names>Eric C.</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">§</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="ath7">
        <name>
          <surname>Byrum</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie D</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="other">*</xref>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">†</xref>
        <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">‡</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>†</label>Department
of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, <institution>University
of Arkansas for Medical Sciences</institution>, Little Rock, Arkansas, 72205 <country>United States</country></aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>‡</label><institution>Arkansas
Children’s Research Institute</institution>, Little Rock, Arkansas, 72202 <country>United States</country></aff>
      <aff id="aff3"><label>§</label>Department
of Pharmacology and Toxicology, <institution>University
of Arkansas for Medical Sciences</institution>, Little Rock, Arkansas, 72205 <country>United States</country></aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Email: <email>sbyrum@uams.edu</email>.</corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>30</day>
      <month>09</month>
      <year>2020</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <day>13</day>
      <month>10</month>
      <year>2020</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>5</volume>
    <issue>40</issue>
    <fpage>25625</fpage>
    <lpage>25633</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>05</month>
        <year>2020</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>14</day>
        <month>08</month>
        <year>2020</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement/>
      <copyright-year>2020</copyright-year>
      <copyright-holder>American Chemical Society</copyright-holder>
      <license>
        <license-p>This is an open access article published under a Creative Commons Attribution (CC-BY) <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/page/policy/authorchoice_ccby_termsofuse.html">License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the author and source are cited.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract>
      <p content-type="toc-graphic">
        <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao0c02564_0005" id="ab-tgr1"/>
      </p>
      <p>The
technological advances in mass spectrometry allow us to collect
more comprehensive data with higher quality and increasing speed.
With the rapidly increasing amount of data generated, the need for
streamlining analyses becomes more apparent. Proteomics data is known
to be often affected by systemic bias from unknown sources, and failing
to adequately normalize the data can lead to erroneous conclusions.
To allow researchers to easily evaluate and compare different normalization
methods via a user-friendly interface, we have developed “proteiNorm”.
The current implementation of proteiNorm accommodates preliminary
filters on peptide and sample levels followed by an evaluation of
several popular normalization methods and visualization of the missing
value. The user then selects an adequate normalization method and
one of the several imputation methods used for the subsequent comparison
of different differential expression methods and estimation of statistical
power. The application of proteiNorm and interpretation of its results
are demonstrated on two tandem mass tag multiplex (TMT6plex and TMT10plex)
and one label-free spike-in mass spectrometry example data set. The
three data sets reveal how the normalization methods perform differently
on different experimental designs and the need for evaluation of normalization
methods for each mass spectrometry experiment. With proteiNorm, we
provide a user-friendly tool to identify an adequate normalization
method and to select an appropriate method for differential expression
analysis.</p>
    </abstract>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>document-id-old-9</meta-name>
        <meta-value>ao0c02564</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>document-id-new-14</meta-name>
        <meta-value>ao0c02564</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>ccc-price</meta-name>
        <meta-value/>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec id="sec1">
    <label>1</label>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <p>With the latest technological advances in the development of mass
spectrometers, the detection accuracy of the instruments and the speed
with which data is being produced have drastically increased. The
amount of data generated by these high-throughput devices increases
rapidly, making the need for tools that allow users to streamline
analyses more and more apparent.</p>
    <p>In a single mass spectrometry
run, peptide levels of thousands
of proteins can be measured for several patients. However, mass spectrometry
data is often affected by systemic bias, variations caused by non-biological
sources, which can lead to erroneous conclusions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref></sup> These sources of variation can include sample preparation
and handling, device calibration, changes in temperature, and other
unknown sources.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref></sup> Unlike the effect of
batching, these sources of variation are either not measured or simply
cannot be measured and therefore cannot be controlled for during the
statistical analysis. Normalization is a technique that aims to account
for these systematic biases and make samples more comparable while
preserving the signal. Many normalization methods have been proposed,
with most of them being adopted from DNA microarray technology.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref></sup> Välikangas et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref></sup> systemically evaluated normalization methods used in quantitative
label-free proteomics. While there are certain normalization methods
that consistently rank among the top performing methods (i.e., variance
stabilizing normalization (VSN), linear regression normalization,
and local regression normalization), it is crucial to select a suitable
normalization method for a specific data set.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></sup> The
need for tools that identify proper methods for normalization was
recognized and addressed by Webb-Robertson et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></sup> and Chawade et al.,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref></sup> with their
tools SPAN and Normalyzer, respectively. SPAN combines eight peptide
selection methods to select peptides subsequently used during the
normalization and five methods for normalization.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></sup> Normalyzer includes popular normalization methods such
as linear regression, local regression, total intensity, average intensity,
median intensity, VSN, and quantile normalization. The performance
of each normalization method is individually evaluated by comparing
its pooled coefficient of variance (PCV), pooled median absolute deviation
(PMAD), and pooled estimate of variance (PEV).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref></sup> However, there remains an outstanding need for a user-friendly and
publicly available tool that provides a systematic evaluation of normalization
methods and also facilitates imputation of missing data and compares
different methods to assess differential abundance of proteins and/or
peptides.</p>
    <p>Here, we present proteiNorm, a user-friendly tool
for a systematic
evaluation of normalization methods for mass spectrometric data sets
that do not have a protein standard or spike-in proteins for reference,
imputation of missing values, and comparisons of different differential
abundance methods. Our tool provides a point-and-click R-Shiny interface
for researchers that are less comfortable or unfamiliar with the R
programming environment. However, the functions are run in R and can
be easily modified to include additional normalization methods.</p>
    <p>After loading the raw peptide data from the database search results
into the peptide input box in the “data” tab in the
Shiny interface, the user can choose to filter the peptide data using
the “Top3” method,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref></sup> where
the three most intense peptides of a protein are averaged to calculate
a stable protein intensity and create a filtered protein file. Next,
either the filtered protein file or the original/raw protein file
from the database search results is uploaded in the protein input
box in the “data” tab. The tool is designed to normalize
the data using the protein relative abundance directly from MaxQuant,
which is generated by summing the peptide intensities. The Top3 method
provided in the “data” upload for peptide data is used
when outlier peptides are present that then skew the relative protein
abundance values provided by MaxQuant. The ultimate goal is to perform
downstream differential abundance analysis to identify significantly
differentiating proteins between sample conditions. However, if someone
is interested in performing an analysis at the peptide level, then
a matrix of peptides as rows and peptide intensities for each sample
as columns can be loaded into the protein input box in the “data”
tab in the Shiny interface.</p>
    <p>The meta-data (i.e., custom sample
names, group labels, and batch
labels) can be specified in the user-interface after loading protein
data. The custom sample names will be used for labeling all subsequent
plots in the tool. On the next “filter” tab in the Shiny
interface, any unwanted samples such as blanks, samples with poor
quality, or pooled samples can be removed from subsequent steps. The
remaining data is then subjected to different normalization methods,
which are compared among each other in the “Normalization”
tab. Once a suitable normalization method is identified, missing values
can be imputed (optional) and the normalized protein data can be saved
from the “DAtest” tab in the Shiny interface. In addition,
different methods for differential abundance analysis can be evaluated
for a selected normalization method (“DAtest” tab),
and the statistical power of a given test of differential abundance
can be assessed (“DApower” tab).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2">
    <label>2</label>
    <title>Results</title>
    <p>Our tool “proteiNorm” is implemented in R statistical
language (<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://r-project.org">http://r-project.org</uri>, version 3.6) using the package “shiny”<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref></sup> to provide a user-friendly user interface. It
is publicly available at <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://sbyrum.shinyapps.io/proteiNorm/">https://sbyrum.shinyapps.io/proteiNorm/</uri> and can also be downloaded from GitHub (<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://github.com/ByrumLab/proteiNorm">https://github.com/ByrumLab/proteiNorm</uri>). <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></xref> shows
its workflow and illustrates an overview involving the following steps:
upload peptide-level data, filter peptides to create new filtered
protein-level data (optional), upload protein-level data (original
or filtered), provide meta-data (e.g., batch and treatment groups),
normalize data with different normalization methods and evaluate their
performances, select appropriate normalization methods, select an
appropriate imputation method (optional), and export normalized (and
imputed) protein-level data. If the user is uncertain about the choice
of method for the differential abundance analysis, proteiNorm provides
the option to compare different methods for differential abundance
analysis provided by the R package “DAtest”.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref></sup></p>
    <fig id="fig1" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Overview of proteiNorm’s workflow, inputs, and
outputs.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao0c02564_0002" id="gr1" position="float"/>
    </fig>
    <p>To demonstrate the application
of proteiNorm and the interpretation
of results in different scenarios, we analyzed the following proteomics
data sets: mouse data set with a weak signal, breast cancer cell lines
with a strong signal, and spike-in data set with weak to strong known
signals (described in <xref rid="sec2.1" ref-type="other">Sections <xref rid="sec2.1" ref-type="other">2.1</xref></xref>–<xref rid="sec2.3" ref-type="other">2.3</xref>).</p>
    <sec id="sec2.1">
      <label>2.1</label>
      <title>Mouse
Data Set</title>
      <p>First, the raw peptide
file (“peptides.txt”) produced by MaxQuant is uploaded
and filtered using the “Top3” method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref></sup> and then exported as the filtered proteinGroups file (e.g.,
“proteinGroups_filtered.txt”). Next, the newly created
and filtered proteinGroups file is uploaded (alternatively, the unfiltered
raw “proteinGroups.txt” file generated by MaxQuant can
be uploaded), and the corresponding meta-data is specified, such as
treatment group, batch number, and an optional custom name (as shown
in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">1</xref></xref>). In this
example, we focus on the striatum samples (“S_T_1” –
“S_T_3” and “S_1” – “S_3”)
and therefore unselected all nucleus accumbens samples (“NA_T_1”
– “NA_T_3” and “NA_1” –
“NA_3”) within the “Filter” tab. No additional
samples were excluded as no sample was identified as an outlier sample
or a sample with poor quality based on the intensity distributions
and the PCA plot (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564/suppl_file/ao0c02564_si_001.pdf">Figures S1–S2</ext-link>). Next, the performance of each normalization method is evaluated
at the protein level. Therefore, the following figures are inspected
(<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>)</xref>: (A) total
intensity, (B) PCA, (D) PCV, (E) PEV, (F) PMAD, (G) intragroup correlation,
(H) correlation heatmap, and (I) LogRatio density. Panels (A), (B),
and (H) visualize the total intensity, PCA, and correlation heatmap
of VSN, respectively (panels (A), (B), and (H) of the remaining normalization
are shown in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564/suppl_file/ao0c02564_si_001.pdf">Figures S3–S5</ext-link>, respectively).</p>
      <fig id="fig2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Evaluation
of normalization and missing values. (A) Sum of normalized
intensities using VSN by sample. (B) Principal component analysis
plot based on data normalized by VSN. (C) Sample-clustered heatmap
of missing values. (D) Pooled intragroup coefficient of variance comparing
different normalization methods. (E) Pooled intragroup estimate of
variance comparing different normalization methods. (F) Pooled intragroup
median absolute deviation comparing different normalization methods.
(G) Pairwise sample correlations within a group for different normalization
methods. (H) Correlation heatmap (all pairwise samples). (I) Distribution
of log2-ratios (all two-group combinations) for different normalization
methods.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao0c02564_0003" id="gr2" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float">
        <label>Table 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Meta-Data for the
Mouse Data Set<xref rid="t1fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></title>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0">
          <colgroup>
            <col align="left"/>
            <col align="left"/>
            <col align="left"/>
            <col align="left"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th style="border:none;" align="center">Protein.Sample.Names</th>
              <th style="border:none;" align="center">Custom.Sample.Names</th>
              <th style="border:none;" align="center">group</th>
              <th style="border:none;" align="center">batch</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.1.TMT1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">NA_T_1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">NA_T</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.2.TMT1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">NA_T_2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">NA_T</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.3.TMT1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">NA_T_3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">NA_T</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.4.TMT1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">NA_1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">NA</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.5.TMT1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">NA_2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">NA</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.6.TMT1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">NA_3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">NA</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.1.TMT2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">S_T_1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">S_T</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.2.TMT2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">S_T_2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">S_T</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.3.TMT2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">S_T_3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">S_T</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.4.TMT2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">S_1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">S</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.5.TMT2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">S_2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">S</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.6.TMT2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">S_3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">S</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">2</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="t1fn1">
            <label>a</label>
            <p>“Protein.Sample.Names”
care automatically generated from the proteinGroups file. “Custom.Sample.Names”
is optional and replaces protein sample names when provided (needs
to be a unique name). “Group” specifies individual treatment
groups. “Batch” is optional and indicates the batch
for each sample.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>With regard
to the total intensity, the samples are nearly indistinguishable
after applying VSN (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>A) and the remaining normalization methods produced very similar
results (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564/suppl_file/ao0c02564_si_001.pdf">Figure S3</ext-link>). Unless the treatment
between groups, such as in a knock out experiment, is expected to
have a major impact on a subset of the most abundant proteins, it
can be expected that the sums of the intensities by sample are similar
within a batch (small changes or changes in low abundant proteins
will be dominated by highly abundant proteins; differences between
total intensities comparing multiple batches are not unusual). Also,
in cases where a sample did not sequence well on the instrument, the
total intensity for that sample will be lower than the rest and can
indicate a bad sequencing run, especially in the case of label-free
designs. Panel (B) of <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref> shows the PCA figure of VSN (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564/suppl_file/ao0c02564_si_001.pdf">Figure S2</ext-link> for the PCA plot before normalization and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564/suppl_file/ao0c02564_si_001.pdf">Figure S4</ext-link> for remaining normalization methods) and demonstrates
an unclear separation among the sample groups. In <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>C, a clustered heatmap of missing
values for each sample is shown. Only proteins with at least one measured
value and one missing value are shown (proteins with complete measurement
or only missing values are not shown). The purpose of this heatmap
is to assist researchers to identify patterns of missing values (i.e.,
MAR or MNAR) and guide the choice of imputation method, if desired.
Here, the missing values seem to not demonstrate an obvious pattern. <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>D–F compares
different measurements of intragroup variations (PCV, PEV, and PMAD,
respectively) for different normalization methods. Small values are
desirable here as they indicate limited variation of sample replicates.
It can be observed that VSN seems to perform the best in reducing
the intragroup variation throughout all three metrics. <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>G compares the pairwise correlation
within the treatment groups of the normalization methods. High intragroup
correlation values indicate high correlation of replicates within
a treatment group and are desirable. All pairwise correlations using
VSN are presented in a clustered correlation heatmap (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>H; clustered correlation heatmaps
of the remaining normalization methods in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564/suppl_file/ao0c02564_si_001.pdf">Figure S5</ext-link>). It can be observed that the untreated and treated samples
from the same specimen cluster together. This could indicate that
the differences between sample specimens outweigh the treatment effect.
In panel (I) of <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>, the density distributions of log2-ratios of all pairwise treatment
combinations are compared for each normalization method. Unless an
unbalanced regulation (primarily up- or downregulation) in the data
is to be expected, the densities should be centered around zero. The
density distributions of most normalization are more or less off center
and could potentially indicate a bias in the normalized data. Only
the density distributions of “VSN” and “RLR”
normalization are centered around zero, with “VSN” demonstrating
the highest peak.</p>
      <p>Based on the evaluation and comparison of
normalization methods
and the heatmap of missing values, the user can choose an adequate
normalization method and has the choice to select an imputation method.
Here, we have selected VSN for the mouse data set. Because some statistical
methods do not require complete data (e.g., limma<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref></sup>), imputation is not always necessary, and we have decided
not to impute our example data set. Following the selection of normalization
and imputation method (“no imputation” is an imputation
choice), the normalized protein data was exported from the “DAtest”
tab in the Shiny interface.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.2">
      <label>2.2</label>
      <title>Breast Cancer Cell Lines</title>
      <p>Analogously,
the raw peptide file (“peptides.txt”) of the breast
cancer cell lines is first uploaded, filtered using the “Top3”
method,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref></sup> and then exported as the filtered
proteinGroups file. Next, the newly created and filtered “proteinGroups.txt”
file is uploaded, and the corresponding meta-data is specified (as
shown in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">Table <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">2</xref></xref>).
Next, pooled samples are unselected and excluded from the subsequent
evaluation. The pool sample helps to evaluate TMT batch effects in
the PCA plot. The pool also serves as a mixture of all proteins present
in all samples so that mass spectrometry has the potential to switch
on those proteins in both TMT batches and limit the number of missing
values across two TMT runs. However, the pool is not part of the differential
abundance analysis and should be removed from the final normalized
protein data that will be utilized for differential abundance analysis.</p>
      <table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float">
        <label>Table 2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Meta-Data for the Breast Cancer Data
Set<xref rid="t2fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></title>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0">
          <colgroup>
            <col align="left"/>
            <col align="left"/>
            <col align="left"/>
            <col align="left"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th style="border:none;" align="center">Protein.Sample.Names</th>
              <th style="border:none;" align="center">Custom.Sample.Names</th>
              <th style="border:none;" align="center">group</th>
              <th style="border:none;" align="center">batch</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.1.TMT3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">ER/PR+
MCF7_UT_19</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">ERPR</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.2.TMT3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">ER/PR+ MCF7_UT_20</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">ERPR</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.3.TMT3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">ER/PR+ MCF7_UT_21</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">ERPR</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.4.TMT3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">MCF 10A_UT_22</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">control</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.5.TMT3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">MCF 10A_UT_23</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">control</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.6.TMT3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">MCF 10A_UT_24</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">control</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.7.TMT3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">HER2+
HCC 1954_UT_25</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">HER2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.8.TMT3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">HER2+ HCC
1954_UT_26</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">HER2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.9.TMT3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">HER2+ HCC 1954_UT_27</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">HER2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.10.TMT3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">pool_3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">pool</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.1.TMT4</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">MCF 10A_TR_28</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">ERPR_TR</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.2.TMT4</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">MCF 10A_TR_29</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">ERPR_TR</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.3.TMT4</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">MCF
10A_TR_30</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">ERPR_TR</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.4.TMT4</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">ER/PR+ MCF7_TR_31</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">control_TR</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.5.TMT4</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">ER/PR+ MCF7_TR_32</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">control_TR</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.6.TMT4</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">ER/PR+ MCF7_TR_33</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">control_TR</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.7.TMT4</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">HER2+ HCC 1954_TR_34</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">HER2_TR</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.8.TMT4</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">HER2+ HCC 1954_TR_35</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">HER2_TR</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.9.TMT4</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">HER2+ HCC 1954_TR_36</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">HER2_TR</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Reporter.intensity.corrected.10.TMT4</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">pool_4</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">pool</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">4</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="t2fn1">
            <label>a</label>
            <p>“Protein.Sample.Names”
are automatically generated from the proteinGroups file. “Custom.Sample.Names”
is optional and replaces protein sample names when provided (needs
to be a unique name). “Group” specifies individual treatment
groups. “Batch” is optional and indicates the batch
for each sample.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>No additional
samples were excluded as no sample was identified
as an outlier sample or a sample with poor quality based on the intensity
distributions and the PCA plot (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564/suppl_file/ao0c02564_si_001.pdf">Figures S6–S7</ext-link>). It can be observed that the batch effect is more prevalent in
the raw peptide data than in the filtered protein data (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564/suppl_file/ao0c02564_si_001.pdf">Figure S7</ext-link>). Next, the performance of each normalization
method is evaluated by inspecting the following figures (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564/suppl_file/ao0c02564_si_001.pdf">Figure S8</ext-link>): (A) total intensity, (B) PCA, (D)
PCV, (E) PEV, (F) PMAD, (G) intragroup correlation, (H) correlation
heatmap, and (I) LogRatio density. We selected the cyclic loess normalization
to normalize this data set. Panels (A), (B), and (H) visualize the
total intensity, PCA, and correlation heatmap of the cyclic loess
normalization, respectively (panels (A), (B), and (H) of the remaining
normalization methods produced similar results; <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564/suppl_file/ao0c02564_si_001.pdf">Figures S9–S11</ext-link>).</p>
      <p>With regard to total intensity,
the samples are nearly indistinguishable
after applying cyclic loess normalization (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564/suppl_file/ao0c02564_si_001.pdf">Figure S8A</ext-link>) and the remaining normalization methods produced very
similar results (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564/suppl_file/ao0c02564_si_001.pdf">Figure S9</ext-link>). Panel (B)
of <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564/suppl_file/ao0c02564_si_001.pdf">Figure S8</ext-link> shows the PCA figure after
cyclic loess normalization (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564/suppl_file/ao0c02564_si_001.pdf">Figure S10</ext-link> for remaining normalization methods) and demonstrates a stronger
separation of cell lines after normalization, while the cell-line-treatment
combinations cluster tighter than before normalizing. In <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564/suppl_file/ao0c02564_si_001.pdf">Figure S8C</ext-link>, a clustered heatmap of missing values
for each sample is shown. It can be observed that samples cluster
primarily by batch and secondarily by cell-line-treatment combination.
It is apparent that measurements are not missing at random, but rather
the missingness of values is influenced by batch and cell-line-treatment
combination. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564/suppl_file/ao0c02564_si_001.pdf">Figure S8D</ext-link>–F compares
different measurements of intragroup variations (PCV, PEV, and PMAD,
respectively) for different normalization methods. It can be observed
that all evaluated normalization methods produced similar results,
with cyclic loess normalization ranking among the better performing
methods. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564/suppl_file/ao0c02564_si_001.pdf">Figure S8G</ext-link> compares the pairwise
correlation within cell-line-treatment combinations of the normalization
methods. All pairwise correlations using cyclic normalization are
presented in a clustered heatmap (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564/suppl_file/ao0c02564_si_001.pdf">Figure S8H</ext-link>; correlation heatmaps of remaining normalization methods in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564/suppl_file/ao0c02564_si_001.pdf">Figure S11</ext-link>). The highest correlations are observed
among samples from the same cell-line with either no treatment or
treatment. The next strongest correlations are demonstrated between
treated and untreated samples from the same cell-line. The second
weakest correlations are produced by samples from different cell-lines
with the same treatment, which are also samples within the same batch.
Samples originating from different cell-lines with different treatments
(in different batches) exhibited the weakest correlation. In panel
(H) of <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564/suppl_file/ao0c02564_si_001.pdf">Figure S8</ext-link>, the density distributions
of log2-ratios of all treatment combinations are compared for each
normalization method. No differences are apparent among the different
normalization methods.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.3">
      <label>2.3</label>
      <title>Spike-in</title>
      <p>For the
spiked-in data,
the raw peptide files (“peptides.txt”) from MaxQuant
are uploaded and filtered using the “Top3” method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref></sup> before exporting the filtered “proteinGroups_filtered.txt”
file. Next, the filtered “proteinGroups_filtered.txt”
file is uploaded, the corresponding meta-data is specified (as shown
in <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="other">Table <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="other">3</xref></xref>), and no
samples are excluded. Analogously using <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564/suppl_file/ao0c02564_si_001.pdf">Figure S14</ext-link> to evaluate the different normalization methods, it can
be observed that the methods perform similarly. For the spike-in data
set, “VSN” was selected because of the slightly lower
intragroup variations and slightly higher intragroup correlation.
The advantage of this spike-in data set is that the true signal is
known and the performance of the normalization can be evaluated by
comparing the intensity ratios of the spiked-in proteins.</p>
      <table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float">
        <label>Table 3</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Meta-Data for the Spiked-in Data Set<xref rid="t3fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></title>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0">
          <colgroup>
            <col align="left"/>
            <col align="left"/>
            <col align="left"/>
            <col align="left"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th style="border:none;" align="center">Protein.Sample.Names</th>
              <th style="border:none;" align="center">Custom.Sample.Names</th>
              <th style="border:none;" align="center">group</th>
              <th style="border:none;" align="center">batch</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.12500amol_R1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">12500amol_R1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">12500</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.12500amol_R2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">12500amol_R2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">12500</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.12500amol_R3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">12500amol_R3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">12500</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.125amol_R1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">125amol_R1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">125</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.125amol_R2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">125amol_R2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">125</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.125amol_R3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">125amol_R3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">125</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.25000amol_R1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">25000amol_R1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">25000</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.25000amol_R2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">25000amol_R2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">25000</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.25000amol_R3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">25000amol_R3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">25000</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.2500amol_R1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">2500amol_R1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">2500</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.2500amol_R2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">2500amol_R2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">2500</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.2500amol_R3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">2500amol_R3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">2500</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.250amol_R1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">250amol_R1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">250</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.250amol_R2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">250amol_R2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">250</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.250amol_R3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">250amol_R3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">250</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.50000amol_R1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">50000amol_R1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">50000</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.50000amol_R2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">50000amol_R2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">50000</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.50000amol_R3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">50000amol_R3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">50000</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.5000amol_R1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">5000amol_R1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">5000</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.5000amol_R2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">5000amol_R2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">5000</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.5000amol_R3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">5000amol_R3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">5000</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.500amol_R1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">500amol_R1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">500</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.500amol_R2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">500amol_R2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">500</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.500amol_R3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">500amol_R3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">500</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.50amol_R1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">50amol_R1</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">50</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.50amol_R2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">50amol_R2</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">50</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">Intensity.50amol_R3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">50amol_R3</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">50</td>
              <td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="t3fn1">
            <label>a</label>
            <p>“Protein.Sample.Names”
are automatically generated from the proteinGroups file. “Custom.Sample.Names”
is optional and replaces protein sample names when provided (needs
to be a unique name). “Group” specifies individual treatment
groups. “Batch” is optional and indicates the batch
for each sample.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <p><xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref></xref> shows the
ratios between different concentrations of the spiked-in protein averages
across replicates comparing the normalized protein data to the raw
protein data. It can be observed that normalized data is performing
better in the estimation of the true concentration ratio (gray dashed
line), especially when the concentration and consequently the intensities
increase.</p>
      <fig id="fig3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Distribution ratios of spiked-in proteins (averages across replicates)
of different spike-in concentrations for raw and normalized protein
intensities. Intensities of spiked-in proteins were averaged across
concentration replicates to calculate the ratio of averaged proteins
between different spike-in concentrations. The distributions of ratios
of the measured proteins are compared between raw and normalized protein
data. Spiked-in concentrations of 50–500amol were excluded
due to the absence of most measurements.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao0c02564_0004" id="gr3" position="float"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec3">
    <label>3</label>
    <title>Discussion</title>
    <p>In our example data sets, we evaluated
different popular normalization
methods. While most methods performed very similarly, we decided to
use the VSN or cyclic loess normalization for our data sets based
on their performance. In addition, both normalization methods rank
consistently among the top performing methods.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref></sup> While it is important to identify an adequate normalization method
for the data set at hand, Välikangas et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref></sup> have demonstrated that most normalization methods result
in better performance than a simple log2 transformation.</p>
    <p>In
experimental designs where there are expected to be thousands
of significantly differentiating proteins, such as the case for the
breast cancer cell lines, the choice of normalization method does
not have a big impact on the final results. However, in the case of
the mouse data where it is expected to have small protein changes,
then the normalization method can make an impact on the final significant
protein lists as shown in the log2 ratio plots. Each data set should
be evaluated based on its own metrics.</p>
    <p>The current implementation
of proteiNorm is limited to the evaluation
of normalization methods utilizing intragroup variance and correlation.
A more suitable form of evaluations for normalization methods is the
assessment of true spike-in signals and/or proteomics standards. However,
this requires additional steps during the sample preparation and might
not always be possible. In future versions of proteiNorm, we intend
to include the option of evaluating normalization methods by assessing
spike-in signals and/or proteomic standards. Further extensions include
a broader spectrum of the input file, additional peptide filter methods,
and additional normalization and imputation methods.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec4">
    <label>4</label>
    <title>Conclusions</title>
    <p>When analyzing proteomics data measured using
mass spectrometers,
normalization of the data is an integral data processing step to adjust
unwanted systematic biases. Failing to acknowledge such issues can
lead to erroneous results and inferences, which limits reproducibility
and scientific progress and increases the cost of science.</p>
    <p>With
proteiNorm, we present a user-friendly tool with the goal
of assisting researchers in the evaluation of popular normalization
methods and of identifying an adequate normalization method suited
for their data sets. Researchers also have the option to impute missing
values and/or compare different differential abundance methods and
their power for a range of effect sizes. Once the data has been evaluated
in proteiNorm, the normalized output is now ready for differential
abundance analysis using other available tools such as limma.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref></sup></p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec5">
    <label>5</label>
    <title>Methods</title>
    <sec id="sec5.1">
      <label>5.1</label>
      <title>Data
Requirements</title>
      <p>As input, proteiNorm
expects tab-separated peptide (optional) and protein data (not on
logarithmic scale) as produced by software such as MaxQuant,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref></sup> where each row represents a peptide or protein
and the column names of the measured intensities (samples) beginning
with “Reporter intensity corrected” followed by an integer
and an optional label (e.g., “Reporter intensity corrected
5 TMT2”) for TMT experiments. The column names for samples
in label-free experiments should begin with “Intensity”
followed by an integer (“Intensity 01”). Data from both
mass spectrometry quantitation methods, tandem mass tag (TMT) and
label-free mass spectrometry, are supported. The TMT reporter intensities
should be corrected using the error correction factors provided by
Thermo Fisher for the specific TMT lot that was used during the sample
preparation. These correction factors are imported into MaxQuant when
setting up the database search parameters. The MaxQuant “proteinGroups.txt”
output file will then contain column names for each TMT reporter ion
labeled as “Reporter intensity corrected” and “Reporter
intensity”. In the following examples, we are using the “Reporter
intensity corrected” columns from MaxQuant since these intensities
apply the TMT correction factors. The reporter ion isotopic distributions
(−2, −1, +1, +2) are primarily for carbon isotopes with
reporter ion interference for each mass tag. ProteiNorm automatically
detects these column names and determines if the data is TMT or label-free
data type. ProteiNorm also removes proteins flagged as common contaminants
and reverse sequences in the MaxQuant output using the column names
“Potential contaminant” and “Reverse”
provided in the proteinGroups.txt MaxQuant output file. If you prefer
to load in a different matrix of data, then the column labels for
the samples will need to be modified to match the naming structure
provided here. An example of the data input files is hosted on Github
for both TMT and label-free data sets.</p>
      <p>Due to the detection
limits of mass spectrometry instruments, many measurements of peptides
or proteins result in intensity levels of zero. These values will
be considered as missing values (denoted as NA) and can be imputed
with precaution. A modified heatmap of missing values (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>C) from the DEP Bioconductor
package<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref></sup> helps to determine if data is
missing at random (MAR) or missing not at random (MNAR), and the MSnbase
vignette describes different imputation methods used for different
types of missing data.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref></sup></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec5.2">
      <label>5.2</label>
      <title>Normalization Methods</title>
      <p>The current
implementation of proteiNorm includes several popular normalization
methods, including log2 (Log2) (a data transformation method), median
normalization (Median), mean normalization (Mean), variance stabilizing
normalization (VSN),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref></sup> quantile normalization
(Quantile),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref></sup> cyclic loess normalization
(Cyclic Loess),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref></sup> global robust linear regression
normalization (RLR),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref></sup> and global intensity
normalization (Global Intensity).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref></sup> The
individual performance of each method can be evaluated by comparing
the following metrics: total intensity (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>A), principal component analysis (PCA; <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>B), pooled intragroup
coefficient of variation (PCV; <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>D), pooled intragroup estimate of variance (PEV; <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>E), pooled intragroup
median absolute deviation (PMAD; <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>F); intragroup correlation (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>G), correlation heatmap (Pearson; <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>H), and log2-ratio
distributions (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>I). These plots are automatically generated and can be viewed on
the “Normalization” tab. When samples are unselected
on the “Filters”
tab, the normalization plots automatically update to include only
the selected samples. The overall goal is to select the normalization
method with the lowest variance and the highest correlation within
the replicates within a group. The plots included in proteiNorm display
a boxplot of each sample group where each dot represents a group so
the variance effects of the normalization method can easily be evaluated
by examining the metrics on the <italic>y</italic>-axis. The correlation
plots include multiple dots per group for all the pairwise intragroup
correlations. The log2 ratio plot helps to evaluate if the normalization
method introduces skewing of the fold change values when comparing
the sample group conditions. The log2-ratios are calculated from all
two-group combinations. The log2 ratio should be centered on zero
and not introduce bias toward up- or downregulation of proteins. All
of the plots in proteiNorm can be saved by clicking on the “Save
Figures” button in the “Normalization” tab in
the interface.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec5.3">
      <label>5.3</label>
      <title>Differential Abundance
Analysis</title>
      <p>If
the user is undecided about the statistical method for the differential
abundance analysis, methods can be compared using the incorporated
functions of the R package DAtest<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref></sup> using
the “DAtest” tab in the Shiny interface. As the DAtest
package requires complete data (no missing values), the user can select
an appropriate method for normalization and imputation for the differential
abundance analysis. This choice should be guided by the comparison
of the normalization methods and the heatmap visualizing patterns
of missing values (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>C). The current implementation of proteiNorm provides the
following imputation methods: k-nearest neighbors (KNN),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref></sup> Quantile Regression Imputation of Left-Censored
(QRILC),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref></sup> deterministic minimal value
imputation (MinDet),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref></sup> stochastic minimal
value imputation (MinProb),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref></sup> minimal value
imputation (Min), and zero imputation (Zero).</p>
      <p>In addition, proteiNorm
provides the opportunity to adjust the DAtest-specific parameters
(i.e., number of times to run the tests, effect size for the spike-ins
(on a natural intensity scale), and number of cores to use for parallel
computing) and to exclude certain statistical tests. The latter option
can be beneficial as the exclusion of tests with high computation
demand (such as the permutation-based test) will drastically reduce
the run-time.</p>
      <p>DAtest automatically selects appropriate statistical
tests, depending
on the data type (count versus intensities) from the pool of tests
and repeatedly evaluates their performance. To do so, the data is
shuffled and spiked-in by multiplying the values in one group by the
selected effect size in the “spike-in” parameter box
on the “DAtest” Shiny tab for randomly chosen features
within the normalized protein data set. For instance, if you are interested
in a differential analysis method that can detect a 2-fold change,
then the spike-in parameter can be set to 2. DAtest then assesses
whether the spiked-in features are correctly identified by each test
and if the false discovery rate is controlled. The results are summarized
in a table and figures comparing and ranking the performance of each
individual test. Additionally, proteiNorm provides the opportunity
to investigate the performance of each individual test by estimating
statistical power (probability of correctly detecting the true signal)
over a range of effect sizes (centered around the previously specified
effect size for the spike-ins), utilizing the “powerDA”
function from the “DAtest” package. This DA power analysis
is run on the “DAtest Power” tab in the Shiny interface.
Once the differential analysis method is determined, then the saved
normalized protein data file will need to be uploaded into a downstream
tool or R to perform the differential analysis. ProteiNorm is used
to evaluate normalization methods and save the normalized matrix using
the “Save file” button after selecting the normalization
method on the “DAtest” data tab.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec5.4">
      <label>5.4</label>
      <title>Data</title>
      <p>Our examples consist of three
data sets: (1) a TMT6plex mouse data set, where proteins were extracted
from the striatum of the brain after treating the mice with methamphetamine
or saline; (2) three breast cancer cell lines (MCF10A non-tumorigenic
epithelial cell line, MCF7 ER/PR+ cells, and HCC1954 HER2+ cells)
with and without hydroxyurea treatment; (3) a publicly available yeast
lysate with known spiked-in UPS1 concentrations (ProteomeXchange ID:
PXD001819).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> The sample preparation and
mass spectrometry methods for each data set are included in the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564/suppl_file/ao0c02564_si_001.pdf">Supporting Information</ext-link> Methods section.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <notes id="notes4" notes-type="si">
    <title>Supporting Information Available</title>
    <p>The Supporting
Information is
available free of charge at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564?goto=supporting-info">https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564</ext-link>.<list id="silist" list-type="simple"><list-item><p>Diagnostic plots from
the three data sets and the sample
preparation and mass spectrometry methods (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564/suppl_file/ao0c02564_si_001.pdf">PDF</ext-link>)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Generated proteiNorm for the three
data sets (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c02564/suppl_file/ao0c02564_si_002.zip">ZIP</ext-link>)</p></list-item></list></p>
  </notes>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sifile1">
      <media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao0c02564_si_001.pdf">
        <caption>
          <p>ao0c02564_si_001.pdf</p>
        </caption>
      </media>
    </supplementary-material>
    <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sifile2">
      <media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ao0c02564_si_002.zip">
        <caption>
          <p>ao0c02564_si_002.zip</p>
        </caption>
      </media>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
  <notes notes-type="" id="notes1">
    <title>Author Contributions</title>
    <p>S.G., J.T.,
and S.D.B. performed tool development, manuscript writing, and editing.
M.K.Z. and A.K.B. performed the sample preparation for the breast
cancer data set and editing. E.C.P. and C.B. performed the sample
preparation for the mouse data set and editing.</p>
  </notes>
  <notes notes-type="funding-statement" id="notes2">
    <p>This study was
supported by the Arkansas Children’s Research Institute, the
Arkansas Biosciences Institute, the Little Rock Envoys Seeds of Science,
and the Center for Translational Pediatric Research funded under the
National Institutes of Health National Institute of General Medical
Sciences (NIH/NIGMS) grant P20GM121293, the UAMS Barton Pilot Study
Grant, and National Institutes of Health National Institute of Drug
Abuse (NIH/NIDA) R21 DA041822.</p>
  </notes>
  <notes notes-type="COI-statement" id="NOTES-d7e1265-autogenerated">
    <p>The authors declare
no
competing financial interest.</p>
  </notes>
  <notes notes-type="" id="notes3">
    <title>Notes</title>
    <p>All of the mass spectrometry data is available
via ProteomeXchange with identifier PXD018152. ProteiNorm and example
data is freely available at <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://github.com/ByrumLab/ProteiNorm">https://github.com/ByrumLab/ProteiNorm</uri>.</p>
  </notes>
  <ack>
    <title>Acknowledgments</title>
    <p>The authors
would like to acknowledge the University
of Arkansas for Medical Sciences Proteomics Core Facility.</p>
  </ack>
  <glossary id="dl1">
    <def-list>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <def-item>
        <term>VSN</term>
        <def>
          <p>variance stabilizing normalization</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>PCV</term>
        <def>
          <p>pooled coefficient
of variance</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>PMAD</term>
        <def>
          <p>pooled median absolute deviation</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>PEV</term>
        <def>
          <p>pooled estimate of variance</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>TMT</term>
        <def>
          <p>tandem mass tag</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>MAR</term>
        <def>
          <p>missing at random</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>MNAR</term>
        <def>
          <p>missing not at random</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>RLR</term>
        <def>
          <p>robust linear regression</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>PCA</term>
        <def>
          <p>principal component
analysis</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>KNN</term>
        <def>
          <p>k-nearest
neighbors</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>QRILC</term>
        <def>
          <p>Quantile Regression Imputation of Left-Censored</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
    </def-list>
  </glossary>
  <ref-list>
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="ref1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit1"><name><surname>Chawade</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Alexandersson</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Levander</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><article-title>Normalyzer: a tool for rapid evaluation
of normalization methods for omics data sets</article-title>. <source>J. Proteome Res.</source><year>2014</year>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>3114</fpage>–<lpage>3120</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/pr401264n</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24766612</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit2"><name><surname>Välikangas</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Suomi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Elo</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name><article-title>A systematic
evaluation of normalization
methods in quantitative label-free proteomics</article-title>. <source>Briefings Bioinf.</source><year>2018</year>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bib/bbw095</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit3"><name><surname>Karpievitch</surname><given-names>Y. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dabney</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name><article-title>Normalization
and missing value imputation
for label-free LC-MS analysis</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinf.</source><year>2012</year>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>S5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-13-S16-S5</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit4"><name><surname>Webb-Robertson</surname><given-names>B.-J. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Matzke</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pounds</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><article-title>A statistical
selection strategy for normalization procedures in LC-MS proteomics
experiments through dataset-dependent ranking of normalization scaling
factors</article-title>. <source>Proteomics</source><year>2011</year>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>4736</fpage>–<lpage>4741</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pmic.201100078</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22038874</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit5"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gorenstein</surname><given-names>M. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G.-Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vissers</surname><given-names>J. P. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Geromanos</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><article-title>Absolute
quantification of proteins by LCMSE - A virtue of parallel MS acquisition</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell. Proteomics</source><year>2006</year>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>144</fpage>–<lpage>156</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/mcp.M500230-MCP200</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16219938</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit6"><source>Easy
web applications in R</source>; <publisher-name>RStudio, Inc.</publisher-name>:<year>2013</year></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit7"><name><surname>Russel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Thorsen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Brejnrod</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bisgaard</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sørensen</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Burmølle</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><article-title>DAtest: a
framework for choosing differential abundance
or expression method</article-title>. <source>bioRxiv</source><year>2018</year>, <fpage>241802</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/241802</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref8">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit8"><name><surname>Ritchie</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Phipson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>G. K.</given-names></name><article-title>limma powers differential
expression analyses for RNA-sequencing
and microarray studies</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2015</year>, <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>e47</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkv007</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25605792</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref9">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit9"><name><surname>Tyanova</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Temu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><article-title>The MaxQuant computational platform
for mass spectrometry-based shotgun proteomics</article-title>. <source>Nat. Protoc.</source><year>2016</year>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>2301</fpage>–<lpage>2319</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2016.136</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27809316</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref10">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit10"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Smits</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>van Tilburg</surname><given-names>G. B. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ovaa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vermeulen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><article-title>Proteome-wide
identification of ubiquitin interactions
using UbIA-MS</article-title>. <source>Nat. Protoc.</source><year>2018</year>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>530</fpage>–<lpage>550</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2017.147</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29446774</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref11">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit11"><name><surname>Gatto</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lilley</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name><article-title>MSnbase-an R/Bioconductor package for isobaric tagged
mass spectrometry data visualization, processing and quantitation</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2012</year>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>288</fpage>–<lpage>289</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr645</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22113085</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref12">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit12"><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>von Heydebreck</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sültmann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Poustka</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vingron</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><article-title>Variance stabilization
applied to microarray data calibration and to the quantification of
differential expression</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2002</year>, <fpage>S96</fpage>–<lpage>S104</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/18.suppl_1.S96</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12169536</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref13">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="undeclared" id="cit13"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Bolstad</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><source>preprocessCore: A collection
of pre-processing functions</source>; <year>2019</year>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref14">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="undeclared" id="cit14"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Hastie</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tibshirani</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Narasimhan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><source>impute: impute: Imputation for microarray
data</source>; <year>2018</year>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref15">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="undeclared" id="cit15"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Lazar</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><source>imputeLCMD: A collection
of methods for left-censored missing data imputation</source>; <year>2015</year>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref16">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit16"><name><surname>Ramus</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hovasse</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Marcellin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hesse</surname><given-names>A.-M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mouton-Barbosa</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bouyssié</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vaca</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Carapito</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chaoui</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bruley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Garin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cianférani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ferro</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Van Dorssaeler</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Burlet-Schiltz</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Schaeffer</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Couté</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>de Peredo</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name><article-title>Spiked
proteomic standard dataset for testing label-free quantitative software
and statistical methods</article-title>. <source>Data Brief</source><year>2016</year>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>286</fpage>–<lpage>294</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dib.2015.11.063</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26862574</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
