<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?origin publisher?>
<?FILEmeta_IDM202 xml ?>
<?FILEmain xml ?>
<?FILEmain pdf ?>
<?FILEgr1 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr2 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr3 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr4 jpg ?>
<?FILEgr5 jpg ?>
<?FILEmmc1 docx ?>
<?FILEsi1 svg ?>
<?FILEsi2 svg ?>
<?FILEsi3 svg ?>
<?FILEsi4 svg ?>
<?FILEsi5 svg ?>
<?FILEsi6 svg ?>
<?FILEsi7 svg ?>
<?FILEsi8 svg ?>
<?FILEsi9 svg ?>
<?FILEsi10 svg ?>
<?FILEsi11 svg ?>
<?FILEsi12 svg ?>
<?FILEsi13 svg ?>
<?FILEsi14 svg ?>
<?FILEsi15 svg ?>
<?FILEsi16 svg ?>
<?FILEsi17 svg ?>
<?FILEsi18 svg ?>
<?FILEsi19 svg ?>
<?FILEsi20 svg ?>
<?FILEsi21 svg ?>
<?FILEsi22 svg ?>
<?FILEsi23 svg ?>
<?FILEsi24 svg ?>
<?FILEsi25 svg ?>
<?FILEsi26 svg ?>
<?FILEsi27 svg ?>
<?FILEsi28 svg ?>
<?FILEsi29 svg ?>
<?FILEsi30 svg ?>
<?FILEsi31 svg ?>
<?FILEsi32 svg ?>
<?FILEsi33 svg ?>
<?FILEsi34 svg ?>
<?FILEsi35 svg ?>
<?FILEsi36 svg ?>
<?FILEsi37 svg ?>
<?FILEsi39 svg ?>
<?FILEsi40 svg ?>
<?FILEsi41 svg ?>
<?FILEsi42 svg ?>
<?FILEsi43 svg ?>
<?FILEsi44 svg ?>
<?FILEsi45 svg ?>
<?FILEsi46 svg ?>
<?FILEsi47 svg ?>
<?FILEsi48 svg ?>
<?FILEsi49 svg ?>
<?FILEsi50 svg ?>
<?FILEsi51 svg ?>
<?FILEsi52 svg ?>
<?FILEsi53 svg ?>
<?FILEsi54 svg ?>
<?FILEsi55 svg ?>
<?FILEsi56 svg ?>
<?FILEsi58 svg ?>
<?FILEsi59 svg ?>
<?FILEsi60 svg ?>
<?FILEsi61 svg ?>
<?FILEsi62 svg ?>
<?FILEsi63 svg ?>
<?FILEsi64 svg ?>
<?FILEsi65 svg ?>
<?FILEsi66 svg ?>
<?FILEsi68 svg ?>
<?FILEsi69 svg ?>
<?FILEsi70 svg ?>
<?FILEsi71 svg ?>
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Infect Dis Model</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Infect Dis Model</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Infectious Disease Modelling</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">2468-2152</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">2468-0427</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>KeAi Publishing</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7897994</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2468-0427(21)00013-0</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.idm.2021.01.010</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Original Research Article</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>SCHISTOX: An individual based model for the epidemiology and control of schistosomiasis</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1">
        <name>
          <surname>Graham</surname>
          <given-names>Matthew</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
        <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
        <xref rid="PC_fnQKkIXaIrbn" ref-type="fn">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2">
        <name>
          <surname>Ayabina</surname>
          <given-names>Diepreye</given-names>
        </name>
        <email>diepreye.ayabina@bdi.ox.ac.uk</email>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
        <xref rid="PC_fnQKkIXaIrbn" ref-type="fn">1</xref>
        <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3">
        <name>
          <surname>Lucas</surname>
          <given-names>Tim CD.</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
        <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4">
        <name>
          <surname>Collyer</surname>
          <given-names>Benjamin S.</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5">
        <name>
          <surname>Medley</surname>
          <given-names>Graham F.</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6">
        <name>
          <surname>Hollingsworth</surname>
          <given-names>T. Deirdre</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
        <xref rid="PC_fnejWEyxrjKZ" ref-type="fn">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7">
        <name>
          <surname>Toor</surname>
          <given-names>Jaspreet</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
        <xref rid="PC_affK7c0wAuMPM" ref-type="aff">e</xref>
        <xref rid="PC_fnejWEyxrjKZ" ref-type="fn">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Big Data Institute, Li Ka Shing Centre for Health Information and Discovery, University of Oxford, Oxford, United Kingdom</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Centre for Mathematical Modelling of Infectious Disease, London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, London, United Kingdom</aff>
      <aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Centre for Environment and Health, Imperial College London, London, United Kingdom</aff>
      <aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology, School of Public Health, Faculty of Medicine, St Mary’s Campus, Imperial College London, United Kingdom</aff>
      <aff id="PC_affK7c0wAuMPM"><label>e</label>MRC Centre for Global Infectious Disease Analysis; and the Abdul Latif Jameel Institute for Disease and Emergency Analytics (J-IDEA), School of Public Health, Imperial College London, London, W2 1PG, United Kingdom</aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>Corresponding author. <email>diepreye.ayabina@bdi.ox.ac.uk</email></corresp>
      <fn id="PC_fnQKkIXaIrbn">
        <label>1</label>
        <p id="notep3305">Joint first authors.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="PC_fnejWEyxrjKZ">
        <label>2</label>
        <p id="notep7715">Joint last authors.</p>
      </fn>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>04</day>
      <month>2</month>
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>04</day>
      <month>2</month>
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>6</volume>
    <fpage>438</fpage>
    <lpage>447</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2020</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>21</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© 2021 The Authors</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
      <license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
        <license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract id="abs0010">
      <p>A stochastic individual based model, SCHISTOX, has been developed for the study of schistosome transmission dynamics and the impact of control by mass drug administration. More novel aspects that can be investigated include individual level adherence and access to treatment, multiple communities, human sex population dynamics, and implementation of a potential vaccine. Many of the model parameters have been estimated within previous studies and have been shown to vary between communities, such as the age-specific contact rates governing the age profiles of infection. However, uncertainty remains as there are wide ranges for certain parameter values and a few remain relatively unknown. We analyse the model dynamics by parameterizing it with published parameter values. We also discuss the development of SCHISTOX in the form of a publicly available open-source GitHub repository. The next key development stage involves validating the model by calibrating to epidemiological data.</p>
    </abstract>
    <kwd-group id="kwrds0010">
      <title>Keywords</title>
      <kwd>Schistosomiasis</kwd>
      <kwd>Individual based model</kwd>
      <kwd>Mass drug administration</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
  </article-meta>
  <notes>
    <p id="misc0010">Handling Editor: Dr Y. Shao</p>
  </notes>
</front>
<body>
  <sec id="sec1">
    <label>1</label>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <p id="p0010">Schistosomiasis is a parasitic disease caused by trematode blood flukes of the genus Schistosoma. It is currently endemic in 52 countries with over 290 million people requiring treatment in 2018 (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2020a</xref>). The target for schistosomiasis has been recently drafted as elimination as a public health problem in the 2030 roadmap for neglected tropical diseases (NTDs) by the World Health Organization (WHO) (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2020b</xref>). Although morbidity and mortality as a result of schistosomiasis has declined over the years, effective control of schistosomiasis remains a challenge for populations living in endemic areas of the tropical and subtropical regions of the world (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Verjee, 2020</xref>). Two of the major species found in Africa are <italic>Schistosoma mansoni</italic> (intestinal) and <italic>S. haematobium</italic> (urogenital).</p>
    <p id="p0015">An important element of the transmission of schistosomiasis is human contact with cercariae-infested bodies of water. The life cycle requires freshwater in which the eggs excreted from infected humans will hatch into miracidia. The miracidia penetrate suitable snail hosts where they mature into cercariae. The cercariae are shed by their snail host and penetrate the human skin where they develop inside the body to adult worms. Adult worms live in couples, pairing with the opposite sex, copulating and ovipositing which starts the whole cycle again (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Allen &amp; Victory, 2003</xref> ; <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">LoVerde, 2019</xref>, pp. 45–70).</p>
    <p id="p0020">In addition to the contamination of water by human faeces or urine (depending on the species of schistosome), the production of cercariae requires the presence of suitable snail hosts. As such water from safe sources will likely be schistosome free and reduce the chances of exposure (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Grimes et al., 2015</xref>). Additionally, good sanitation and hygiene have been shown to be associated with lower odds of infection with <italic>S. mansoni</italic> and <italic>S. haematobium</italic> (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Freeman et al., 2017</xref>). However, more data are needed to determine the impact of improved water, sanitation and hygiene (WASH) measures on schistosomiasis control.</p>
    <p id="p0025">The main approach applied to control schistosomiasis is mass drug administration (MDA) with the anthelmintic drug, praziquantel. This aims to lessen the morbidity and mortality due to infection and to prevent new infection by limiting transmission through reduction of the overall prevalence in the population (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Li, Gurarie, Lo, Zhu, &amp; King, 2019</xref>). MDA generally leads to a reduction of schistosome worms in the human host, which in turn reduces the quantity of schistosome eggs excreted and ultimately reduces the level of contamination in the environment and infection of the snail population. School aged children (SAC; 5–14 years) typically have a higher likelihood of being infected with <italic>Schistosoma</italic> parasites than other age groups mainly as a result of age-related water contact activities. Therefore, treatment is usually focused on SAC to minimise morbidity in this important stage of development with delivery through school-based programmes. Treatment of at-risk adults is also important and recommended by WHO, particularly in higher prevalence settings (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2006</xref>). Infected individuals that are not covered by MDA may still spread the infection (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">King, 2009</xref>). Hence, in settings with high adult burdens of infection or low school enrolment levels, community-wide treatment can be more effective for achieving elimination as a public health problem (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Toor et al., 2019</xref>).</p>
    <p id="p0030">Studies of the transmission dynamics of the <italic>Schistosoma</italic> infections date as far back as 1965 when the first mathematical model of schistosome epidemiology was developed by George Macdonald (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Macdonald, 1965</xref>). His model, which was based on differential equations, describes the evolution of the mean worm burden in the human host whilst accounting for the dioecious nature of the schistosome worms. Many different models have been published since then, using more advanced mathematical approaches and accounting for more complexities known to be present in real life, as outlined in a recent extensive review (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Anderson, Turner, Farrell, &amp; Truscott, 2016</xref>). Individual based models (IBMs) of schistosomiasis transmission evolved from differential equation models, capturing several heterogeneous factors such as variations in local demographics and exposure patterns which contribute to the persistence of schistosomiasis (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Wang &amp; Spear, 2015</xref>). These models track every individual in the population and their interaction with the environment.</p>
    <p id="p0035">Schistosomiasis IBMs are important as they can be used to inform policymakers and programme managers on priority questions, such as recommendations for treatment guidelines and surveillance criteria for detecting elimination. Several IBMs of schistosome infection exist in the literature (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Collyer et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Hu et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Kura, Truscott, Toor, &amp; Anderson, 2019</xref>, <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Vlas et al., 1996</xref>, <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Spear, 2015</xref>), though they are not readily available for public use. As such, there is a need for an individual based framework for schistosomiasis that is publicly accessible.</p>
    <p id="p0040">In this paper, we describe the development of an open source individual based model, SCHISTOX, for the dynamics of infection, transmission and control of schistosomiasis. The model comprises the life history of the <italic>Schistosoma</italic> parasite, its transmission and the impact of control. The effects of MDA control strategies on the burden of infection can be evaluated, thereby allowing for model-based predictions on control strategies being implemented and recommendations for optimal treatment strategies. The model is designed such that it can be parameterised for either <italic>S. mansoni or S. haematobium</italic>.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2">
    <label>2</label>
    <title>Methods</title>
    <sec id="sec2.1">
      <label>2.1</label>
      <title>Model structure and parameters</title>
      <p id="p0045">Models of schitosomiasis transmission typically include the different aspects of the life cycle of schistosomes to different degrees of detail depending on the questions the model seeks to explore (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">supplementary table S1</xref>). The factors included within SCHISTOX can be grouped into four parts: human population, parasite population (the two larval stages of the schistosome parasite: miracidia and cercariae), transmission and control. Briefly, humans uptake cercariae from the environment, which become worms within the host, leading to excretion of eggs which become miracidia larvae in the environment. The miracidia then transitions through the intermediate snail host resulting in cercariae (schematic of the model shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). It is implemented in a synchronous stochastic simulation. Details on the simulation approach are given below, but first we describe the biological processes and provide an event table (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Schematic representation of the structure of the model.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Events in SCHISTOX simulation.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Event</th><th>Probability</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Birth of individuals</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">The birth rate is set per 1000 individuals, and at each time point, the number of births is randomly selected from a binomial distribution with population size <inline-formula><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and birth rate (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Death of an individual</td><td align="left">Time of death is pre-determined for each individual.</td><td align="left">Time of death is set at birth and is dependent on death rates per 1000 in each age bracket.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Egg production</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si71.svg"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">Number of eggs in individuals <inline-formula><mml:math id="M5" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> follow a negative binomial distribution with mean. It depends on the maximum fecundity <inline-formula><mml:math id="M6" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, worm pairs <inline-formula><mml:math id="M7" altimg="si6.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, number of female worms <inline-formula><mml:math id="M8" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> , exponential decay constant <inline-formula><mml:math id="M9" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and aggregation parameter for egg production <italic>(r)</italic>.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Worm maturity</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M10" altimg="si9.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo><mml:mn>365</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M11" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the worm stage,<inline-formula><mml:math id="M12" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the time step and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M13" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the average lifespan of the worms.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Miracidia production</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M14" altimg="si13.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>max</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">Eggs from each individual (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M15" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> will be released into the environment relative to the maximum age dependent contact rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M16" altimg="si15.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>max</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cercarial maturity</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M17" altimg="si16.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>μ</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">Number of days for miracidia to mature into cercarcia (life expectancy in the intermediate snail host used as a proxy).</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Uptake of cercariae</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M18" altimg="si17.svg"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">Depends on overall contact rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M19" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, age dependent contact rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M20" altimg="si19.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> , individual predisposition <inline-formula><mml:math id="M21" altimg="si20.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and the available number cercariae in the environment <inline-formula><mml:math id="M22" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. It is density dependent as otherwise if the population grows, then the relative rate of uptake increases proportional to population size.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Intervention implementation (MDA or vaccination)</td><td align="left">Coverage levels, frequency and timing of intervention is pre-set.</td><td/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
      <p id="p0050">There are published values for many of the SCHISTOX input parameters (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). However, some of these have wide ranges and a few have limited information. Certain parameter values, such as the age dependent contact rates, will vary for different settings. Currently in the model, all these values can be explicitly specified. However, these would need to be calibrated to epidemiological data to provide more robust estimates.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Parameter values from some published studies have been outlined, some of these would vary from one population to another and a few would need to be estimated from epidemiological data as there is limited information about them.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Parameter</th><th>Values/ranges</th><th>Source</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Maximum fecundity <inline-formula><mml:math id="M23" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left"><italic>S. mansoni:</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M24" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.05</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.34</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>eggs</mml:mtext><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>worm pair</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><break/><italic>S. haematobium:</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M25" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5.2</mml:mn><mml:mtext> eggs</mml:mtext><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>worm</mml:mtext><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">/</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mtext>ml specimen</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">(<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Anderson &amp; May 1982</xref>; <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">de Vlas, Nagelkerke, &amp; Habbema, 1993</xref>; <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">De Vlas, Van Oortmarssen, Habbema, Gryseels, &amp; Polderman, 1992</xref>; <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Truscott et al., 2017</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Aggregation parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="M26" altimg="si24.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M27" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.04</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.24</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">( <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Anderson &amp; May 1982</xref>; <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Anderson, Turner, Farrell, &amp; Truscott, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Chan et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Toor et al., 2019</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Density dependent fecundity <inline-formula><mml:math id="M28" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left"><italic>S. mansoni</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M29" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.0007</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>/female worm<break/><italic>S. haematobium</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M30" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.0006</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>/female worm</td><td align="left">(<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Anderson &amp; May 1982</xref>; <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Anderson, Turner, Farrell, &amp; Truscott, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Turner et al., 2017</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mean adult worm life span <inline-formula><mml:math id="M31" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left"><italic>S. mansoni:</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M32" altimg="si28.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.7</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>10.5</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>years<break/><italic>S. haematobium:</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M33" altimg="si29.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>years</td><td align="left">(<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Anderson &amp; May 1985</xref>; <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Anderson &amp; May, 1991</xref>; <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Sturrock &amp; Butterworth, 1995</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Drug efficacy</td><td align="left"><italic>S. mansoni:</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M34" altimg="si30.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>79</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mn>92.5</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><break/><italic>S. haematobium:</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M35" altimg="si31.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>63</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">(<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Kihara et al., 2007</xref>, <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Utzinger et al., 2000</xref>)<break/>(<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Ojurongbe et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Tchuem Tchuenté et al., 2004</xref>, <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Utzinger et al., 2000</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mean parasite life expectancy in snail host <inline-formula><mml:math id="M36" altimg="si32.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>μ</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left"><italic>S. mansoni</italic> in <italic>Biomphalaria glabarata</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M37" altimg="si33.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>7</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mn>42</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>days</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><break/><italic>S. haematobium</italic> in <italic>Bulinus globusus</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M38" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>14</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>28</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>days</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">(<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Anderson &amp; May, 1991</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td>Egg production aggregation parameter <italic>(r)</italic></td><td>0 - 0.1</td><td>(<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Gurarie, King, Yoon, &amp; Li, 2016</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Contact rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M39" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">Varies according to study population</td><td align="left">–</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Age dependent contact rates <inline-formula><mml:math id="M40" altimg="si19.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">Varies according to study population</td><td align="left">–</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Number of worms, miracidia and cercaria</td><td align="left">Relatively unknown</td><td align="left">–</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Proportion of miracidia which become cercariae</td><td align="left">Relatively unknown.</td><td align="left">–</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Proportion of cercariae that survive each time step</td><td align="left">Relatively unknown.</td><td align="left">–</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
      <sec id="sec2.1.1">
        <label>2.1.1</label>
        <title>Human population</title>
        <p id="p0055">The dynamics of the human population are determined by its birth and death rates. We assume that some individuals are more predisposed to uptaking larvae, with individuals randomly assigned a level of predisposition, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M41" altimg="si35.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> , from a gamma distribution with shape <inline-formula><mml:math id="M42" altimg="si36.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and scale <inline-formula><mml:math id="M43" altimg="si37.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> at birth (where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M44" altimg="si36.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the aggregation parameter). The aggregation parameter varies inversely with the degree of parasite aggregation in the population. Therefore, a large <inline-formula><mml:math id="M45" altimg="si36.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> value will result in all people having the same predisposition hence picking up approximately the same number of larvae (dependent on their age). With a low value, the level of aggregation will be large, and hence a few individuals will pick up high numbers of larvae, whilst many individuals will pick up very few or no larvae. In scenarios with lower prevalence, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M46" altimg="si36.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> also tends to be smaller (corresponding to a higher level of aggregation) as a the infection is concentrated in a few individuals with a high number of worms (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>).<fig id="fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Plots of equilibrium levels of total population prevalence using different values for the aggregation parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="M47" altimg="si24.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The simulation was run using N = 1000, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M48" altimg="si39.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>= (0.032, 0.61, 1, 0.06) for 0–5 year olds, 5–10 year olds, 10–16 year olds and 16+ year olds, respectively (corresponding to a moderate adult burden of infection setting) (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Turner et al., 2017</xref>), <inline-formula><mml:math id="M49" altimg="si40.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.065</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M50" altimg="si41.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>0.24 and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M51" altimg="si42.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>5.7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>years.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p>
        <p id="p0060">Exposure to infection depends on an individual’s risk and their age. The uptake of cercariae occurs at a rate which is age dependent, with the rate generally highest in SAC. Specific age profiles of infection (patterns of contact rates by age) can be considered by specifying the age parameter values, which describe the relationship between the level of contact in non-SAC age groups (i.e. infants, pre-SAC, SAC and adults) relative to SAC. As the age profile of infection is setting specific (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>), the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M52" altimg="si39.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> values will vary for different settings.<fig id="fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Observed age intensity profiles of infection for <italic>S. mansoni</italic> and <italic>S. haematobium</italic> showing Kenyan data from Iietune village (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Sturrock &amp; Butterworth, 1995</xref>), Matithini village (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Sturrock &amp; Butterworth, 1995</xref>), Katheka village (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">King et al., 2003</xref>), and 12 villages in the Msambweni region of Coastal Kenya (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Gurarie et al., 2016</xref>). Figure adapted from (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Turner et al., 2020</xref>).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p>
        <p id="p0065">As individuals may have varying levels of adherence and access to intervention programmes (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Adriko et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Inobaya et al., 2018</xref>), these aspects can be considered within the model. Adherence refers to whether an individual who is given an intervention will actually adhere to the treatment. On the other hand, access to treatment describes whether an individual is covered by MDA, as individuals in hard-to-reach areas may be missed.</p>
        <p id="p0070">When an individual is “born”, their age of death (based on the probability of death within each age group of the population) and predisposition is chosen, along with their adherence and access to intervention, all of which are fixed for the remainder of their life in the population. At each time step any individuals older than their age of death are removed from the population.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2.1.2">
        <label>2.1.2</label>
        <title>Parasite population</title>
        <p id="p0075">To generate erlang distributed worm lifespans, the worms within a human host are split into a specified number of stages, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M53" altimg="si43.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1,2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and are aged through all these stages before they die. For example, if the number of stages is set to 1, then the first step of maturity would be death. The worms are assumed to age through each of the stages at the same rate with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M54" altimg="si44.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> denoting the mean adult worm lifespan. Hence, the probability of aging out of each worm stage at each step forward in time is given by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M55" altimg="si9.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo><mml:mn>365</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M56" altimg="si45.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the time step. The number of worms aging out of each stage follows a binomial distribution, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M57" altimg="si46.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M58" altimg="si47.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> denoting the number of worms currently in that stage and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M59" altimg="si48.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo><mml:mn>365</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
        <p id="p0080">The worms are assumed to reproduce monogamously (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Beltran &amp; Boissier, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Steinauer, 2009</xref>), hence the total number of potential worm pairs within an individual is simply the minimum of the number of female and male worm pairs, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M60" altimg="si49.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The expected number of eggs, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M61" altimg="si50.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, is assumed to be density dependent, where an increase in the number of worms does not lead to a linear increase in the expected number of eggs, due to overcrowding (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Medley &amp; Anderson, 1985</xref>). The expected number of eggs is defined as<disp-formula id="ufd1"><mml:math id="M62" altimg="si70.svg"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo><mml:mspace linebreak="newline"/></mml:math></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M63" altimg="si51.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>is the maximum fecundity of the female worms, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M64" altimg="si52.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the exponential decay and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M65" altimg="si53.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the number of female worms. The number of eggs produced in humans is assumed to follow a negative binomial distribution with this mean and aggregation assumed to be <inline-formula><mml:math id="M66" altimg="si54.svg"><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
        <p id="p0085">We do not explicitly model the intermediate snail host but consider a single shared environmental reservoir of infection which includes the miracidial and cercarial stages. For miracidia production, we assume that each individual can contribute up to the number of eggs that their worms have produced, which is then scaled relative to the age dependent contact rate of each individual. For example, if an individual has 40 eggs, and belongs to the highest contact age group, then they will produce 40 miracidia. If they are in an age group with half the level of age dependent contact, then they will produce 20 miracidia. The number of infective cercariae in the environment, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M67" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, is updated based on the number of miracidia which are shed in the environment <inline-formula><mml:math id="M68" altimg="si56.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>days earlier. The parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="M69" altimg="si56.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is used as a proxy for the lifespan of the parasite in the intermediate snail host.</p>
        <p id="p0090">As free-living miracidia and cercariae are relatively short-lived (ranging from 4 to 20 h ( <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Anderson, Turner, Farrell, &amp; Truscott, 2016</xref>), these stages are not explicitly included within the model (i.e. we assume these are uptaken by their host immediately or do not survive). The initial number of worms, miracidia and cercariae can be specified in the model. Although it is unlikely to know what these initial numbers are, they do not affect the equilibrium level of infection. However, the smaller these initial numbers, the longer the model takes to reach equilibrium.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2.1.3">
        <label>2.1.3</label>
        <title>Transmission</title>
        <p id="p0095">Humans become infected when exposed to water bodies infested with cercariae. The number of cercariae uptaken by an individual each time step, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M70" altimg="si58.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, is modelled as<disp-formula id="ufd2"><mml:math id="M71" altimg="si59.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M72" altimg="si60.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M73" altimg="si39.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are the scaling contact rate for every individual in the population and an age dependent contact rate, respectively, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M74" altimg="si61.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the population size. Dividing by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M75" altimg="si61.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ensures that as the population grows, the rate of uptake of cercariae for everyone does not increase at a proportional rate. When cercariae are uptaken, this is performed for every individual in the population in a random order and each uptaken cercariae is removed from the environmental pool.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2.1.4">
        <label>2.1.4</label>
        <title>Treatment and control</title>
        <p id="p0100">Control of infection is administered through MDA and/or vaccination. This is set to occur at given times in the simulation, hence at each time step we check whether we have reached the specified time for the MDA or vaccination to take place. When we perform MDA or vaccination, the process is very similar. A lower and upper age limit, the coverage level, the timing and frequency for the intervention are specified (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). Additionally, as described earlier, everyone in the population has two characteristics: adherence and access, which determine whether they partake in any intervention. Adherence is only applicable for MDA and not vaccination as this is administered by a healthcare individual in a way that cannot be avoided.</p>
        <p id="p0105">To select individuals for an intervention, we firstly identify all the individuals in the specified age bracket who have access to the intervention. Then we narrow this down to only cover the population at the coverage level selected, and then for each person who adheres to the intervention (all individuals in the case of vaccination), we administer the intervention. If there is full adherence and access, then individuals (falling within the specified age group) are selected at random at each round of treatment. Note that if there is an access constraint, the specified level of coverage is not actually achieved, for example, if 100% coverage rate is specified but only 50% of the population have access to the intervention, then only 50% of the population will receive the intervention.</p>
        <p id="p0110">Interventions are assumed to reduce the worm burden in individuals. For MDA, this is a one-time decrease in these burdens, whilst for vaccination, there is lasting protection (for a specified length of time) against rebuilding these burdens, enacted as a reduction in the rate of uptaking larvae.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.2">
      <label>2.2</label>
      <title>Implementation and simulations</title>
      <p id="p0115">Running a simulation of the model starts by creating an initial human population with specified size, age and sex distribution. Human characteristics such as age at death, access and adherence to treatment are chosen at random by the appropriate distributions. The initial number of worms, miracidia and cercariae can also be specified. In a simulation, we step forward by a specified number of days at a time. To ensure that an epidemiological equilibrium is reached, the model is generally run for several decades (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>).<fig id="fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Distribution of worms in the population and prevalence when SCHISTOX is run to equilibrium over 100 years assuming a moderate adult burden of infection setting (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M76" altimg="si62.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.032</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.61</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.06</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>for 0–5 year olds, 5–10 year olds, 10–16 year olds and 16+ year olds, respectively (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Turner et al., 2017</xref>)). Here <inline-formula><mml:math id="M77" altimg="si63.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1000</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.0423</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>N = 1000, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M78" altimg="si64.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.007</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for the moderate transmission setting and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M79" altimg="si65.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.24</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for the high transmission setting. A) and C) show the probability of having a specified worm burden (with bins 0, 1–5, 6–10, 11–15, …, 96–100, 100+) for the simulation in moderate and high transmission settings, respectively. B) and D) show the prevalence in school-aged children (SAC; 5–14 years old) and adults (15+ years old) over time for moderate and high transmission settings, respectively.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig><fig id="fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>The impact of annual mass drug administration (MDA) on SAC and adult prevalence for <italic>S. mansoni</italic> with a moderate adult burden of infection setting (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M80" altimg="si62.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.032</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.61</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.06</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>for 0–5 year olds, 5–10 year olds, 10–16 year olds and 16+ year olds, respectively (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Turner et al., 2017</xref>)) with coverage levels of A) 75% SAC and B) 75% SAC and 30% adults. The plot shows the mean prevalence for 100 realizations of the model assuming 100% adherence,<inline-formula><mml:math id="M81" altimg="si66.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.055</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, drug efficacy = 86% and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M82" altimg="si42.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>5.7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Fig. 5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig></p>
      <p id="p0120">The code is written in Julia programming language but we also provide an R-interface which is available from (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/mattg3004/SchistoIndividual" id="intref0010">https://github.com/mattg3004/SchistoIndividual</ext-link>). To provide a benchmark for performance, to run a single realization of the model with population size <inline-formula><mml:math id="M83" altimg="si68.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to equilibrium and then implement 10 annual rounds of MDA in a high prevalence setting requires ~ 4.96 seconds to run on a laptop with 1.7 GHz intel core i5 processor and 8 Gb of memory (note: for lower prevalence settings a simulation would run relatively quicker).</p>
      <p id="p0125">The model can be adapted to different transmission settings by varying the input parameters. The aggregation parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="M84" altimg="si36.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and contact rates <inline-formula><mml:math id="M85" altimg="si60.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M86" altimg="si69.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>which both affect the uptake rate, can be adjusted to obtain different transmission settings. Computational simulations of SCHISTOX are shown in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>, <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>. The model output can be presented with several degrees of detail depending on the purpose of the simulation. In its most detailed form, epidemiological information can be obtained for each individual or grouped by sex and/or age.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.3">
      <label>2.3</label>
      <title>Computational specialties of using SCHISTOX</title>
      <p id="p0130">SCHISTOX is publicly available on GitHub with options of being run in julia (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/mattg3004/Schistoxpkg.jl" id="intref0015">https://github.com/mattg3004/Schistoxpkg.jl</ext-link>) or by using the R user-interface (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/mattg3004/SchistoIndividual" id="intref0020">https://github.com/mattg3004/SchistoIndividual</ext-link>). Both Julia and R are free programming languages. Using Julia means the model is quick to run computationally (due to Julia’s combination of multiple-dispatch and just in time compilation) without relying on a lower level language such as C. The added option of the user-friendly R interface allows for the model to be accessible to R-users.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.4">
      <label>2.4</label>
      <title>Model validation and fitting to data</title>
      <p id="p0135">Although there are published estimates for most of the SCHISTOX parameters, some of these parameters have a wide range and vary according to the <italic>Schistosoma</italic> spp and/or study population (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). Important on-going next steps are model validation by fitting to epidemiological data. This requires good longitudinal data on the intensity of infection across all ages from a variety of transmission settings. Two of the parameters, the proportion of cercariae and miracidia uptaken from the environment, have limited information in published data. The impact of varying these parameters on the transmission dynamics can also be investigated to determine their importance.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2.5">
      <label>2.5</label>
      <title>Further model aspects for investigation</title>
      <p id="p0140">SCHISTOX has been designed to incorporate several features depending on the question being investigated. The model framework currently allows for implementation of multiple communities, with a shared environmental reservoir of infection. The number of communities is specified by the user alongside the contact rates for each community. Another aspect that can be investigated is gender. The simulations can be set up in such a way that one human sex has a lower or higher predisposition to infection or adherence to treatment. This provides the opportunity to study the effects of gender on schistosomiasis burden (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Ayabina et al., 2020</xref>).</p>
      <p id="p0145">Aside from MDA programmes, other forms of schistosomiasis control can be implemented in the model. As discussed, the framework allows the implementation of vaccines, with vaccine coverage and effectiveness set up by the user at the start of the simulation. Although SCHISTOX does not explicitly model the snail population, snail control can be implemented via the parameters that govern miracidia and cercariae maturity and uptake in the environment.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec3">
    <label>3</label>
    <title>Discussion</title>
    <p id="p0150">We have presented an individual based modelling framework for the study of schistosomiasis transmission and control. This is not the first individual based model designed for the study of schistosomiasis transmission and control. However, SCHISTOX offers the advantage of being publicly available on github with options of being run in Julia or through the R user-interface. We have analysed its dynamics using published parameter values and shown that SCHISTOX can produce expected disease dynamics and describe the impact of MDA.</p>
    <p id="p0155">Many of the parameters in SCHISTOX are used to describe the characteristics of a specific population and control programme. As such, it can be easily adapted to make predictions in a variety of transmission settings. In the hope that SCHISTOX will contribute to the planning and evaluation of control programmes, model validation and data fitting are currently underway.</p>
    <p id="p0160">To conclude, SCHISTOX is a flexible framework that can be used to investigate the impact of control strategies and to produce model-based recommendations for treatment programmes. Control strategies can be specified in a detailed way as level of adherence and access, coverage, treatment and vaccine effectiveness are specified by the user. Its flexible design and public availability make SCHISTOX a helpful tool to researchers and stakeholders in the control of schistosomiasis.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec4">
    <title>Funding statement</title>
    <p id="p0165">All authors gratefully acknowledge funding of the NTD Modelling Consortium by the <funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000865</institution-id><institution>Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> [OPP1184344].</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec5">
    <title>Author contributions</title>
    <p id="p0170"><bold>Matthew Graham:</bold> Writing - original draft, Conceptualization, Methodology, Software, Investigation, Visualization; <bold>Diepreye Ayabina:</bold> Writing - review &amp; editing, Conceptualization, Methodology, Visualization; <bold>Tim CD Lucas:</bold> Writing - review &amp; editing, Conceptualization, Software; <bold>Benjamin S Collyer</bold>: Methodology and Software; <bold>Graham F Medley:</bold> Conceptualization; <bold>T. Deirdre Hollingsworth:</bold> Writing - review &amp; editing, Funding acquisition, Supervision; <bold>Jaspreet Toor:</bold> Writing - review &amp; editing, Conceptualization, Methodology, Software, Visualization, Supervision.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
    <title>Declaration of competing interest</title>
    <p id="p0175">We have no conflicts of interest.</p>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ref-list id="cebib0010">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="bib1">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Adriko</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Faust</surname>
            <given-names>C.L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Carruthers</surname>
            <given-names>L.V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Moses</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tukahebwa</surname>
            <given-names>E.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lamberton</surname>
            <given-names>P.H.L.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Low praziquantel treatment coverage for schistosoma mansoni in mayuge district, Uganda, due to the absence of treatment opportunities, rather than systematic non-compliance</article-title>
        <source>Tropical Medicine and Infectious Disease</source>
        <volume>3</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <year>2018</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/tropicalmed3040111</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="oref2">Allen, E. J., &amp; Victory, H. D. (2003). Modelling and simulation of a schistosomiasis infection with biological control. doi:10.1016/S0001-706X(03)00065-2.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib3">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Anderson</surname>
            <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>May</surname>
            <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Population dynamics of human helminth infections: Control by chemotherapy</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <volume>297</volume>
        <issue>5867</issue>
        <year>1982</year>
        <fpage>557</fpage>
        <lpage>563</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/297557a0</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7088139</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib4">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Anderson</surname>
            <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>May</surname>
            <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Helminth infections of humans: Mathematical models, population dynamics, and control</article-title>
        <source>Advances in Parasitology</source>
        <volume>24</volume>
        <year>1985</year>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <lpage>101</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0065-308x(08)60561-8</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3904343</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib5">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Anderson</surname>
            <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Turner</surname>
            <given-names>H.C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Farrell</surname>
            <given-names>S.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Truscott</surname>
            <given-names>J.E.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Studies of the transmission dynamics, mathematical model development and the control of schistosome parasites by mass drug administration in human communities</article-title>
        <source>Advances in Parasitology</source>
        <volume>94</volume>
        <year>2016</year>
        <fpage>199</fpage>
        <lpage>246</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/bs.apar.2016.06.003</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27756455</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib6">
      <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref6">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ayabina</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Clark</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Toor</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <chapter-title>Gender related differences in infection intensity, prevalence and risk of schistosoma mansoni and schistosoma haematobium: A systematic review protocol</chapter-title>
        <year>2020</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib7">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Beltran</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Boissier</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Schistosome monogamy: Who, how, and why?</article-title>
        <source>Trends in Parasitology</source>
        <volume>24</volume>
        <issue>9</issue>
        <year>2008</year>
        <fpage>386</fpage>
        <lpage>391</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pt.2008.05.009</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18674968</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib8">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chan</surname>
            <given-names>M.S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Guyatt</surname>
            <given-names>H.L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bundy</surname>
            <given-names>D.A.P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Booth</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fulford</surname>
            <given-names>A.J.C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Medley</surname>
            <given-names>G.F.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The development of an age structured model for schistosomiasis transmission dynamics and control and its validation for Schistosoma mansoni</article-title>
        <source>Epidemiology and Infection</source>
        <volume>115</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <year>1995</year>
        <fpage>325</fpage>
        <lpage>344</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0950268800058453</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7589272</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib9">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Collyer</surname>
            <given-names>B.S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Turner</surname>
            <given-names>H.C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hollingsworth</surname>
            <given-names>T.D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Keeling</surname>
            <given-names>M.J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Vaccination or mass drug administration against schistosomiasis: A hypothetical cost-effectiveness modelling comparison</article-title>
        <source>Parasites &amp; Vectors</source>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <year>2019</year>
        <fpage>499</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-019-3749-4</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31647019</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib10">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>De Vlas</surname>
            <given-names>S.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Van Oortmarssen</surname>
            <given-names>G.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Habbema</surname>
            <given-names>J.D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gryseels</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Polderman</surname>
            <given-names>A.M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A model for variations in single and repeated egg counts in schistosoma mansoni infections</article-title>
        <source>Parasitology</source>
        <volume>104</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <year>1992</year>
        <fpage>451</fpage>
        <lpage>460</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S003118200006371X</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1641245</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib11">
      <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref11">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Freeman</surname>
            <given-names>M.C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Garn</surname>
            <given-names>J.V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sclar</surname>
            <given-names>G.D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Boisson</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Medlicott</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Alexander</surname>
            <given-names>K.T.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <source>The impact of sanitation on infectious disease and nutritional status: A systematic review and meta-analysis</source>
        <volume>Vol. 220</volume>
        <year>2017</year>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier GmbH</publisher-name>
        <fpage>928</fpage>
        <lpage>949</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib12">
      <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref12">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Grimes</surname>
            <given-names>J.E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Croll</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Harrison</surname>
            <given-names>W.E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Utzinger</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Freeman</surname>
            <given-names>M.C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Templeton</surname>
            <given-names>M.R.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <source>The roles of water, sanitation and hygiene in reducing schistosomiasis: A review</source>
        <volume>Vol. 8</volume>
        <year>2015</year>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central Ltd</publisher-name>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib13">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gurarie</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>King</surname>
            <given-names>C.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yoon</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Refined stratified-worm-burden models that incorporate specific biological features of human and snail hosts provide better estimates of Schistosoma diagnosis, transmission, and control</article-title>
        <source>Parasites &amp; Vectors</source>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <year>2016</year>
        <fpage>428</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-016-1681-4</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27492409</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib14">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gong</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Spatially explicit agent-based modelling for schistosomiasis transmission: Human-environment interaction simulation and control strategy assessment</article-title>
        <source>Epidemics</source>
        <volume>2</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <year>2010</year>
        <fpage>49</fpage>
        <lpage>65</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.epidem.2010.03.004</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21352776</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib15">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Inobaya</surname>
            <given-names>M.T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chau</surname>
            <given-names>T.N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ng</surname>
            <given-names>S.K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>MacDougall</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Olveda</surname>
            <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tallo</surname>
            <given-names>V.L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ross</surname>
            <given-names>A.G.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Mass drug administration and the sustainable control of schistosomiasis: An evaluation of treatment compliance in the rural Philippines</article-title>
        <source>Parasites &amp; Vectors</source>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <year>2018</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-018-3022-2</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib16">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kihara</surname>
            <given-names>J.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Muhoho</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Njomo</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mwobobia</surname>
            <given-names>I.K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Josyline</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mitsui</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mwandawiro</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Drug efficacy of praziquantel and albendazole in school children in Mwea Division, Central Province, Kenya</article-title>
        <source>Acta Tropica</source>
        <volume>102</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <year>2007</year>
        <fpage>165</fpage>
        <lpage>171</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actatropica.2007.04.017</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17572368</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib17">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>King</surname>
            <given-names>C.H.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Global health: Toward the elimination of schistosomiasis</article-title>
        <source>New England Journal of Medicine</source>
        <volume>360</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <year>2009</year>
        <fpage>106</fpage>
        <lpage>109</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMp0808041</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib18">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>King</surname>
            <given-names>C.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Magak</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Salam</surname>
            <given-names>E.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ouma</surname>
            <given-names>J.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kariuki</surname>
            <given-names>H.C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Blanton</surname>
            <given-names>R.E.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Measuring morbidity in schistosomiasis mansoni: Relationship between image pattern, portal vein diameter and portal branch thickness in large-scale surveys using new WHO coding guidelines for ultrasound in schistosomiasis</article-title>
        <source>Tropical Medicine and International Health</source>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <year>2003</year>
        <fpage>109</fpage>
        <lpage>117</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-3156.2003.00994.x</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12581434</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib40">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="optwBc1QmwwVK">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kura</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Truscott</surname>
            <given-names>J.E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Toor</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Anderson</surname>
            <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Modelling the impact of a <italic>Schistosoma mansoni</italic> vaccine and mass drug administration to achieve morbidity control and transmission elimination</article-title>
        <source>PLOS neglected tropical diseases</source>
        <volume>13</volume>
        <issue>6</issue>
        <year>2019</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib19">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>E.Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gurarie</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lo</surname>
            <given-names>N.C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>X.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>King</surname>
            <given-names>C.H.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Improving public health control of schistosomiasis with a modified WHO strategy: A model-based comparison study</article-title>
        <source>The Lancet Global Health</source>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <year>2019</year>
        <fpage>e1414</fpage>
        <lpage>e1422</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2214-109X(19)30346-8</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31537371</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib20">
      <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref20">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>LoVerde</surname>
            <given-names>P.T.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <chapter-title>Schistosomiasis</chapter-title>
        <volume>Vol. 1154</volume>
        <year>2019</year>
        <publisher-name>Springer New York LLC</publisher-name>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib21">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Macdonald</surname>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The dynamics of helminth infections, with special reference to schistosomes</article-title>
        <source>Transactions of the Royal Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</source>
        <volume>59</volume>
        <issue>5</issue>
        <year>1965</year>
        <fpage>489</fpage>
        <lpage>506</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0035-9203(65)90152-5</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5860312</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib22">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Medley</surname>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Anderson</surname>
            <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Density-dependent fecundity in schistosoma mansoni infections in man</article-title>
        <source>Transactions of the Royal Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</source>
        <volume>79</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <year>1985</year>
        <fpage>532</fpage>
        <lpage>534</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0035-9203(85)90087-2</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3936242</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib23">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ojurongbe</surname>
            <given-names>O.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sina-Agbaje</surname>
            <given-names>O.R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Busari</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Okorie</surname>
            <given-names>P.N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ojurongbe</surname>
            <given-names>T.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Akindele</surname>
            <given-names>A.A.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Efficacy of praziquantel in the treatment of Schistosoma haematobium infection among school-age children in rural communities of Abeokuta, Nigeria</article-title>
        <source>Infectious Diseases of Poverty</source>
        <volume>3</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <year>2014</year>
        <fpage>30</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2049-9957-3-30</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25215186</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib24">
      <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref24">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Anderson</surname>
            <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>May</surname>
            <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <chapter-title>Infectious diseases of humans: Dynamics and control</chapter-title>
        <edition>1st ed.</edition>
        <year>1991</year>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib25">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Steinauer</surname>
            <given-names>M.L.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The sex lives of parasites: Investigating the mating system and mechanisms of sexual selection of the human pathogen schistosoma mansoni</article-title>
        <source>International Journal for Parasitology</source>
        <volume>39</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <year>2009</year>
        <fpage>1157</fpage>
        <lpage>1163</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpara.2009.02.019</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19298820</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib26">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sturrock</surname>
            <given-names>R.F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Butterworth</surname>
            <given-names>A.E.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A statistical approach to schistosome population dynamics and estimation of the life-span of schistosoma mansoni in man</article-title>
        <source>Parasitology</source>
        <volume>110</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <year>1995</year>
        <fpage>307</fpage>
        <lpage>316</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182000080896</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7724238</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib27">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tchuem Tchuenté</surname>
            <given-names>L.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shaw</surname>
            <given-names>D.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Polla</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cioli</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vercruysse</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Efficacy of praziquantel against Schistosoma haematobium infection in children</article-title>
        <source>The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</source>
        <volume>71</volume>
        <issue>6</issue>
        <year>2004</year>
        <fpage>778</fpage>
        <lpage>782</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.2004.71.778</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15642971</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib28">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Toor</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rollinson</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Turner</surname>
            <given-names>H.C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gouvras</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>King</surname>
            <given-names>C.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Medley</surname>
            <given-names>G.F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <x>…</x>
          <name>
            <surname>Anderson</surname>
            <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Achieving elimination as a public health problem for schistosoma mansoni and S. haematobium: When is community-wide treatment required?</article-title>
        <source>The Journal of Infectious Diseases</source>
        <volume>221</volume>
        <issue>Supplement_5</issue>
        <year>2019</year>
        <fpage>S525</fpage>
        <lpage>S530</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiz609</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib29">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Truscott</surname>
            <given-names>J.E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gurarie</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Alsallaq</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Toor</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yoon</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Farrell</surname>
            <given-names>S.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <x>…</x>
          <name>
            <surname>Anderson</surname>
            <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A comparison of two mathematical models of the impact of mass drug administration on the transmission and control of schistosomiasis</article-title>
        <source>Epidemics</source>
        <volume>18</volume>
        <year>2017</year>
        <fpage>29</fpage>
        <lpage>37</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.epidem.2017.02.003</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28279453</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib30">
      <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref30">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Turner</surname>
            <given-names>H.C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>French</surname>
            <given-names>M.D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Montresor</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>King</surname>
            <given-names>C.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rollinson</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Toor</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Economic evaluations of human schistosomiasis interventions: A systematic review and identification of associated research needs</source>
        <volume>5</volume>
        <year>2020</year>
        <publisher-name>F1000 Research Ltd</publisher-name>
        <fpage>45</fpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib31">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Turner</surname>
            <given-names>H.C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Truscott</surname>
            <given-names>J.E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bettis</surname>
            <given-names>A.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Farrell</surname>
            <given-names>S.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Deol</surname>
            <given-names>A.K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Whitton</surname>
            <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <x>…</x>
          <name>
            <surname>Anderson</surname>
            <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Evaluating the variation in the projected benefit of community-wide mass treatment for schistosomiasis: Implications for future economic evaluations</article-title>
        <source>Parasites &amp; Vectors</source>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <year>2017</year>
        <fpage>213</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-017-2141-5</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28454578</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib32">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Utzinger</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>N’Goran</surname>
            <given-names>E.K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>N’Dri</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lengeler</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tanner</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Efficacy of praziquantel against Schistosoma mansoni with particular consideration for intensity of infection</article-title>
        <source>Tropical Medicine and International Health</source>
        <volume>5</volume>
        <issue>11</issue>
        <year>2000</year>
        <fpage>771</fpage>
        <lpage>778</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-3156.2000.00646.x</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11123824</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib33">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Verjee</surname>
            <given-names>M.A.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Schistosomiasis: Still a cause of significant morbidity and mortality&lt;/p&gt;</article-title>
        <source>Research and Reports in Tropical Medicine</source>
        <volume>ume 10</volume>
        <year>2020</year>
        <fpage>153</fpage>
        <lpage>163</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/rrtm.s204345</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib34">
      <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref34">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>de Vlas</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nagelkerke</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Habbema</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Statistical models for estimating prevalence and incidence of parasitic diseases</source>
        <volume>Vol. 2</volume>
        <year>1993</year>
        <publisher-name>Stat Methods Med Res</publisher-name>
        <fpage>3</fpage>
        <lpage>21</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib35">
      <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref35">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Vlas</surname>
            <given-names>S.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>J</surname>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>O</surname>
            <given-names>V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gryseels</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Polderman</surname>
            <given-names>A.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Plaisier</surname>
            <given-names>A.P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Habbema</surname>
            <given-names>J.D.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <chapter-title>SCHISTOSIM: A microsimulation model for the epidemiology and control of schistosomiasis › research explorer</chapter-title>
        <year>1996</year>
        <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pure.itg.be/en/publications/schistosim-a-microsimulation-model-for-the-epidemiology-and-control-of-schistosomiasis(266b34e4-da47-465f-84a7-b24ba1c4120a)/export.html" id="intref0025">https://pure.itg.be/en/publications/schistosim-a-microsimulation-model-for-the-epidemiology-and-control-of-schistosomiasis(266b34e4-da47-465f-84a7-b24ba1c4120a)/export.html</ext-link></comment>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib36">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Spear</surname>
            <given-names>R.C.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Exploring the contribution of host susceptibility to epidemiological patterns of Schistosoma japonicum infection using an individual-based model</article-title>
        <source>The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</source>
        <volume>92</volume>
        <issue>6</issue>
        <year>2015</year>
        <fpage>1245</fpage>
        <lpage>1252</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.14-0691</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25870427</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib37">
      <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref37">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>WHO</surname>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <person-group person-group-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Organization</surname>
            <given-names>W.H.</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <series>Preventive in human helminthiasis chemotherapy</series>
        <volume>Vol. 2020</volume>
        <year>2006</year>
        <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>France</publisher-loc>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib38">
      <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref38">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>WHO</surname>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <chapter-title>Schistosomiasis</chapter-title>
        <year>2020</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="bib39">
      <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref39">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>WHO</surname>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <chapter-title>Ending the neglect to attain the sustainable development goals</chapter-title>
        <year>2020</year>
        <comment>Retrieved from</comment>
        <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/70809" id="intref0030">https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/70809</ext-link>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
  <sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <label>Appendix A</label>
    <title>Supplementary data</title>
    <p id="p0215">The following is the Supplementary data to this article:<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1"><caption><title>Multimedia component 1</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.docx"><alt-text>Multimedia component 1</alt-text></media></supplementary-material></p>
  </sec>
  <fn-group>
    <fn id="d34e1110">
      <p id="ntpara0010">Peer review under responsibility of KeAi Communications Co., Ltd.</p>
    </fn>
    <fn id="appsec2" fn-type="supplementary-material">
      <label>Appendix A</label>
      <p id="p7220">Supplementary data to this article can be found online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.idm.2021.01.010" id="intref7015">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.idm.2021.01.010</ext-link>.</p>
    </fn>
  </fn-group>
</back>
