<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>BMC Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1471-2105</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8285884</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34271851</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">4287</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-021-04287-1</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Methodology</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>MSCFS: inferring circRNA functional similarity based on multiple data sources</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Shu</surname>
          <given-names>Liang</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>solar1222@csu.edu.cn</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Zhou</surname>
          <given-names>Cheng</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>zhoucheng_zc@csu.edu.cn</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Yuan</surname>
          <given-names>Xinxu</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>xinxu.yuan@vcuhealth.org</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Zhang</surname>
          <given-names>Jingpu</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>zhangjp@csu.edu.cn</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <name>
          <surname>Deng</surname>
          <given-names>Lei</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>leideng@csu.edu.cn</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.216417.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0379 7164</institution-id><institution>School of Computer Science and Engineering, </institution><institution>Central South University, </institution></institution-wrap>Lushangnan Road, Changsha, China </aff>
      <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.224260.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0458 8737</institution-id><institution>Department of Chemical and Life Science Engineering, </institution><institution>Virginia Commonwealth University, </institution></institution-wrap>Richmond, VA 23284 USA </aff>
      <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.440740.3</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1757 7092</institution-id><institution>School of Computer and Data Science, </institution><institution>Henan University of Urban Construction, </institution></institution-wrap>Longxiang Road, Pingdingshan, 467000 China </aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>16</day>
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>16</day>
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>22</volume>
    <issue>Suppl 10</issue>
    <issue-sponsor>Publication of this supplement has not been supported by sponsorship. Information about the source of funding for publication charges can be found in the individual articles. The articles have undergone the journal's standard peer review process for supplements. The Supplement Editors declare that they have no competing interests.</issue-sponsor>
    <elocation-id>371</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>20</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>6</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2021</copyright-statement>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract id="Abs1">
      <sec>
        <title>Background</title>
        <p id="Par1">More and more evidence shows that circRNA plays an important role in various biological processes and human health. Therefore, inferring the circRNA’s potential functions and obtaining circRNA functional similarity has become more and more significant. However, there is no effective approach to explore the functional similarity of circRNAs.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Methods</title>
        <p id="Par2">In this paper, we propose a new approach, called MSCFS, to calculate the functional similarity of circRNA by integrating multiple data sources. We combine circRNA-disease association, circRNA-gene-Gene Ontology association, and circRNA sequence information to explore the functional similarity of circRNA. Firstly, we employ different learning representation methods from three data sources to establish three circRNA functional similarity networks. Then we integrate the three networks to obtain the final circRNA functional similarity.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Results</title>
        <p id="Par3">We utilize circRNA–miRNA association similarity and circRNA co-expression similarity to evaluate the performance of MSCFS. The results show a positive correlation with miRNA association (<inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$R=0.213$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.213</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) and circRNA co-expression similarity (<inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$R=0.8991$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.8991</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq2.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>). Finally, we construct a circRNA functional similarity network and perform case analysis. The result shows our method can be applied to infer new potential functions of circRNA and other associations.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Conclusions</title>
        <p id="Par4">MSCFS combines multiple data sources related to circRNA functions. Correlation analysis and case analyses prove that MSCFS is a useful method to explore circRNA functional similarity.</p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
      <title>Keywords</title>
      <kwd>CircRNA functional similarity</kwd>
      <kwd>Multiple data sources</kwd>
      <kwd>Multiple representations</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group>
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id>
            <institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China (CN)</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>61672541</award-id>
        <award-id>61972422</award-id>
        <principal-award-recipient>
          <name>
            <surname>Deng</surname>
            <given-names>Lei</given-names>
          </name>
        </principal-award-recipient>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <conference xlink:href="http://www.binfo.ncku.edu.tw/APBC2021/index.html">
      <conf-name>The 19th Asia Pacific Bioinformatics Conference (APBC 2021)</conf-name>
      <conf-acronym>APBC 2021</conf-acronym>
      <conf-loc>Tainan, Taiwan</conf-loc>
      <conf-date>3-5 February 2021</conf-date>
    </conference>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
        <meta-value>© The Author(s) 2021</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec id="Sec1">
    <title>Background</title>
    <p id="Par12">Circular RNAs, a class of endogenous non-coding RNAs, are characterized by their covalently closed-loop structures without a 5<inline-formula id="IEq3"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^{\prime }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq3.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> cap or a 3<inline-formula id="IEq4"><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^{\prime }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq4.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> Poly A tail [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Sanger et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] first found CircRNAs in 1976. However, the circRNAs were thought to be splicing artifact; and were continuously considered as “junk” RNAs for about two decades [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. More and more researches have corroborated that circRNAs play an essential role in many cell activities, affecting arteriosclerosis and participating in mRNA expression variable splicing regulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. In recent years, circRNAs have been identified as biomarkers and therapeutic targets for various acute diseases. CircRNA is associated with a variety of chronic diseases, such as lung cancer, Alzheimer’s disease, diabetes, cardiovascular disease and other [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. The emerging experimental results have corroborated that circRNA molecules have abundant miRNA binding sites and act as miRNA sponges in cells to releasing the inhibitory effect of miRNA on their target genes and improving the expression level of target genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Identifying the targets of circRNAs helps to understand the functions of circRNAs. Several efforts have been developed to identify circRNA targets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. For example, Lin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] designed Analysis of common targets (ACT) to facilitate the identification of potential circRNA targets.</p>
    <p id="Par13">Functional similarity can be defined as an association, such as co-expression similarity, co-Gene Ontology (GO) term similarity, co-similar disease similarity, and co-literature similarity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Analogous to the methods of studying the functional similarity of microRNA, Wang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] obtained the functional similarity of miRNA through the DAG of disease and microRNA-disease association. The Gene Ontology (GO) project provides the most comprehensive resource currently available for computable knowledge regarding the functions of genes and gene products. Gene Ontology provides the logical structure of the biological functions (‘terms’) and their relationships to one another, manifested as a directed acyclic graph [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Yang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] obtained the functional similarity of microRNA by calculating GO semantic similarity and miRNA-GO association. There are many methods to acquire the semantic similarity of GO, such as the measures proposed by Resnik et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], Jiang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], Lin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], Wang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], and Wu et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Obtaining the functional similarity of RNA can also be obtained through sequence information. Sequence similarity can be calculated by methods such as K-mer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] or LSTM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>].</p>
    <p id="Par14">However, there is no valid method to calculate the functional similarity of circRNA, and a single circRNA data source can’t effectively explore the circRNA functional similarity. In this paper, we propose a novel method called MSCFS by integrating multiple biological data sources to calculate the functional similarity between circRNAs. Firstly, we obtain the circRNA functional similarity matrix by using the DAG graph and association information of the disease. Secondly, we construct the corpus through circRNA-gene-GO associations and GO annotations and employ word2vec to obtain the circRNA functional similarity matrix. Thirdly, we adopt chaos game representation to get circRNA functional similarity by circRNA sequence information. Finally, the circRNA functional similarity is obtained by integrating the three networks. The results show that MSCFS is efficacious and accurate, and it can infer the potential functions of circRNA. The flowchart of our proposed model is shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Overview of MSCFS demonstrating the basic ideas of measuring circRNAs functional similarity</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec2">
    <title>Methods</title>
    <sec id="Sec3">
      <title>Dataset</title>
      <p id="Par15">We downloaded the MeSH descriptor from the National Library of Medicine (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nlm.nih.gov/">http://www.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. MeSH descriptors are divided into 16 categories: category A is anatomical terms, category B is organisms, category C is diseases, category D is drugs and chemicals, etc. Then, we obtained the relationship of various diseases based on DAG diseases from the MeSH descriptor of category C.</p>
      <p id="Par16">Many benchmark databases contain circRNA-disease association data, such as circR2Disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>], circRNADisease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], circFunBase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>], and Circ2Disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], which contain experimentally verified associations between circRNAs and diseases. We utilize circR2Disease as the benchmark data set. Circ2Disease is a database that can manually manage human circRNA supported by experiments and provide the association between circRNA and human diseases. We obtained 418 confirmed circRNA-disease associations consisting of 365 circRNA and 71 diseases after removing the circRNAs in which the gene symbol could not be found.</p>
      <p id="Par17">We downloaded the Gene Ontology (GO) in OWL format from the Gene Ontology Consortium (GOC) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] and GO annotations in the Gene Ontology Annotation (GOA) Database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. We used the OWL API version 4.2.6 to process the GO in OWL format.</p>
      <p id="Par18">We extracted 321 genes associated with circRNA and the circRNA sequence information from the circBase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. We obtained 7321 GO-gene associations from multiple versions of the database bioDBnet [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4">
      <title>Overview of MSCFS</title>
      <p id="Par19">In this article, we combine the three data sources of circRNA to calculate the functional similarity of circRNA. Specifically, we obtain three circRNA functional similarity matrices from the circRNA-disease association, circRNA-gene-GO association, and circRNA sequence information. Finally, we integrate three networks to obtain the final circRNAs functional similarity, and the formula is as follows:<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} \left\{ \begin{array}{lr} \mathrm {FS}=\alpha * \mathrm {CDFS}+\beta * \mathrm {GOFS}+\gamma * \mathrm {SQFS} \\ \alpha +\beta +\gamma = 1 \end{array} \right. \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mfenced open="{"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">FS</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">CDFS</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">GOFS</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">SQFS</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where CDFS, GOFS, SQFS are circRNA functional similarity matrices obtained through circRNA-disease association, circRNA-gene-GO association, and circRNA sequence information, respectively. <inline-formula id="IEq5"><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\alpha$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M12"><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq5.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq6"><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\beta$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M14"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq6.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula id="IEq7"><alternatives><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\gamma$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M16"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq7.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> are the weighting coefficients of the three networks severally.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec5">
      <title>Functional similarity based on circRNA-disease association</title>
      <p id="Par20">Genes with similar functions are known to be associated with similar diseases. A structure of a directed acyclic graph (DAG) can represent the relationship between different diseases. Therefore, we can calculate the functional similarity of circRNA through circRNA-disease association. The process is shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Calculating circRNA functional similarity based on circRNA-disease association</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Fig2_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
      <p id="Par21">In the MeSH database, the relationship between diseases is described in the form of a directed acyclic graph (<italic>DAG</italic>), where nodes represent diseases and edges represent relationships between diseases. Given a disease <italic>D</italic>, we have defined a DAG graph <inline-formula id="IEq8"><alternatives><tex-math id="M17">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$DAG_{D}=\left( D, T_{a}, E_{a}\right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M18"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq8.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> based on the other diseases it is associated with and related edges, where <inline-formula id="IEq9"><alternatives><tex-math id="M19">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$T_{a}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M20"><mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq9.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the set of ancestor nodes containing itself, and <inline-formula id="IEq10"><alternatives><tex-math id="M21">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$E_{a}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M22"><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq10.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the set of corresponding edges connecting these diseases. If disease <italic>d</italic> is in the <italic>DAG</italic>, its contribution to disease <italic>A</italic> can be calculated as follows:<disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M23">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} \left\{ \begin{array}{ll} D_{D}(D)=1 \\ D_{D}(d)=\max \left\{ \Delta * D_{A}\left( d^{\prime }\right) \mid d^{\prime } \in { children\ of } \ d \, \right\} \ if \ d \ne A \end{array} \right. \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M24" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mfenced open="{"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo movablelimits="true">max</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="}" open="{"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mml:mi><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:msup><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>≠</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <inline-formula id="IEq11"><alternatives><tex-math id="M25">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\Delta$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M26"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq11.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the semantic contribution factor of disease d and its child nodes. In DAG, the semantic value of disease D itself is defined as 1. Therefore, through the following formula, we calculate the semantic value <italic>DV</italic>(<italic>D</italic>) of disease <italic>D</italic>:<disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M27">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} {\mathrm {DV}}({\mathrm {D}})=\sum _{d \in T_{A}} D_{A}(d). \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M28" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">DV</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">D</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_Equ3.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p id="Par22">Here, we assume that the more <italic>DAG</italic> shared parts of the two diseases, the higher the semantic similarity, so according to the position of the two diseases in the <italic>DAG</italic> graph and the semantic relationship with the ancestral diseases, the formula for calculating the semantic similarity of the two diseases <italic>M</italic> and <italic>N</italic> is as follows:<disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M29">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} S(M, N)=\frac{\sum _{d \in T_{M \cap } T_{N}}\left( D_{M}(d)+D_{N}(d)\right) }{D V(M)+D V(N)}, \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M30" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>∩</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_Equ4.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <inline-formula id="IEq12"><alternatives><tex-math id="M31">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$D_{M}(d)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M32"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq12.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the semantic value of disease d related to disease <italic>M</italic>, and <inline-formula id="IEq13"><alternatives><tex-math id="M33">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$D_{N}(d)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M34"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq13.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the semantic value of disease d related to disease <italic>N</italic>.<disp-formula id="Equ5"><label>5</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M35">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} S d(d, D T)=\max _{u \in D T} S(d, D T(u)), \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M36" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo movablelimits="true">max</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_Equ5.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>DT</italic> is a group of diseases, <italic>u</italic> is any disease in <italic>DT</italic>. After obtaining the semantic similarity of disease combinations, we use circRNA-disease correlation to obtain the functional similarity of circRNA, CDFS.<disp-formula id="Equ6"><label>6</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M37">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} {CDFS}(i, j)=\frac{\sum _{d \in D(i)} S d(d, d(j))+\sum _{d \in D(j)} S d(d, d(i))}{|D(i)|+|D(j)|}, \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M38" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CDFS</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_Equ6.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>CDFS</italic>(<italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic>) is the similarity between the <italic>i</italic>th circRNA and the <italic>j</italic>th circRNA, <italic>D</italic>(<italic>i</italic>) is the <italic>i</italic>th circRNA associated disease set.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec6">
      <title>Functional similarity based on circRNA-gene-GO association</title>
      <p id="Par23">Onto2Vec is a measure that combines formal ontology axioms and annotation axioms in ontology metadata to generate a vector representation of biological entities in the ontology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Gene Ontology contains the representation of the essence of the knowledge system in the field of biology. Ontologies are usually composed of a set of categories (or terms or concepts) with relationships between them. In order to explore the functional similarity of circRNA, we use the circRNA-gene-GO association. We add circRNA as new entities and apply the <inline-formula id="IEq14"><alternatives><tex-math id="M39">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$has{-function}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M40"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq14.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> relationship to connect them with their functions to generate a corpus. Then we use Onto2Vec to generate a vector representation for each class (using a corpus to only be based on axioms), and further, generate a joint representation of circRNA and classes (using a corpus-based axiom and circRNA and its annotations).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Using word2vec to get circRNA functional similarity based on circRNA-gene-GO association and GO annotations</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Fig3_HTML" id="MO9"/></fig></p>
      <p id="Par24">In the end, we constructed 230,699 corpus, with 50,409 categories, using the Skip-gram model in word2vec. Word2Vec is a set of neural network-based tools that can generate vector representations of words from a large corpus. There are two models: the continuous bag of word (CBOW), which uses a context to predict a target word, and the Skip-gram model that tries to maximize the classification of a word based on another word from the same sentence. Figure <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> shows the flow of this section.</p>
      <p id="Par25">The Skip-gram model is chosen because the Skip-gram model generates higher quality rare word representations in the corpus. The Skip-gram model learns more detailed word vectors and has a large number of low-frequency words in the corpus to produce high-quality representations of all biological entities occurring in our large corpus, including uncommon ones. Given a set of training word sequences <inline-formula id="IEq15"><alternatives><tex-math id="M41">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${w}_1, {w}_2\ldots , {w}_N$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M42"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq15.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, Skip-gram the goal is to maximize the following average logarithmic likelihood values:<disp-formula id="Equ7"><label>7</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M43">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} \frac{1}{N} \sum _{t=1}^{N} \sum _{-s \le i \le s, j \ne 0} \log p\left( \omega _{t+j} \mid \omega _{t}\right) , \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M44" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>≠</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mo>log</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:msub><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_Equ7.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>s</italic> means the size of the training context, <italic>N</italic> means the size of the set of the training words, and <inline-formula id="IEq16"><alternatives><tex-math id="M45">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${w}_i$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M46"><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq16.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the <italic>i</italic>th training word in the sequence. In our research, the parameters of word2vec used are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Parameters of Word2Vec model</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Parameter</th><th align="left">Definition</th><th align="left">Default value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>sg</italic></td><td align="left">Choice of training algorithm (sg = 1:skip gram; sg = 0:CBOW)</td><td char="." align="char">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq17"><alternatives><tex-math id="M47">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$min\_count$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M48"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>_</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq17.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">Words with frequency lower than this value will be ignored</td><td char="." align="char">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>size</italic></td><td align="left">Dimension of the obtained vectors</td><td char="." align="char">200</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>window</italic></td><td align="left">Maximum distance between the current and the predicted word</td><td char="." align="char">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>iter</italic></td><td align="left">Number of iterations</td><td char="." align="char">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>negative</italic></td><td align="left">Whether negative sampling will be used and how many ’noise words’ would be drawn</td><td char="." align="char">4</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
      <p id="Par26">Through the training, we get the similarity of the genes, and then through the circRNA-gene relationship GOFS, the calculation formula is as follows:<disp-formula id="Equ8"><label>8</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M49">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} {\mathrm {GOFS}}(i, j)=\frac{\sum _{g \in G(i)} S(g, g(j))+\sum _{g \in G(j)} S(g, g(i))}{|g(i)|+|g(j)|}, \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M50" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">GOFS</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_Equ8.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>g</italic>(<italic>i</italic>) is the set of genes associated with the <italic>i</italic>th circRNA, and <italic>g</italic>(<italic>j</italic>) is the set of genes associated with the <italic>j</italic>th circRNA.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec7">
      <title>Functional similarity based on circRNA sequence</title>
      <p id="Par27">Different from the K-mer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], PSSM method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], chaos game representation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] combines position information and nonlinear relationship to obtain vector representation of sequences. Finally, the Pearson correlation is used to quantify their correlation. The advantage of the algorithm is that the original information of the sequence is completely restored in the coordinate system, and the information will not be lost in the mapping. Secondly, the position information will be retained as a mapping. Figure <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> shows the workflow of this section.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Utilizing Chaos game representation to obtain circRNA functional similarity though circRNA sequence information</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Fig4_HTML" id="MO12"/></fig></p>
      <p id="Par28">The position of each nucleotide in the plane:<disp-formula id="Equ9"><label>9</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M51">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} P_{i}=0.5*\left( P_{i-1}+S_{i}\right) \quad i=1\ldots N , \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M52" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_Equ9.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <inline-formula id="IEq18"><alternatives><tex-math id="M53">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${P}_0$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M54"><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq18.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is any given starting point <inline-formula id="IEq19"><alternatives><tex-math id="M55">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$(P_{0}=(0.5,0.5))$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M56"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq19.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <italic>N</italic> represents the length of the sequence. <inline-formula id="IEq20"><alternatives><tex-math id="M57">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${S}_i$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M58"><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq20.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> represents the <italic>i</italic>th nucleotide in the sequence, which corresponds to the fixed vertex coordinates of <inline-formula id="IEq21"><alternatives><tex-math id="M59">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$A=(0,0)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M60"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq21.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq22"><alternatives><tex-math id="M61">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$C=(1,0)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M62"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq22.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq23"><alternatives><tex-math id="M63">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$G=(1,1)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M64"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq23.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq24"><alternatives><tex-math id="M65">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$U=(0,1)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M66"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq24.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> respectively.</p>
      <p id="Par29">In this way, the CGR graph is transformed into a <inline-formula id="IEq25"><alternatives><tex-math id="M67">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$N_{g}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M68"><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq25.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> grid <inline-formula id="IEq26"><alternatives><tex-math id="M69">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\left( N_{g}=2^{s} \times 2^{s}, \mathrm {s}=3\right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M70"><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mfenced></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq26.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> digital matrix, which is called the frequency matrix of CGR graph (FCGR). And grid can be represented as follows:<disp-formula id="Equ10"><label>10</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M71">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} {grid}_{i}=\left( X_{i}, Y_{i}, Z_{i}\right) \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M72" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">grid</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_Equ10.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p id="Par30">We use the x-axis, y-axis direction and their digital features to construct the feature vector of the sequence, the calculation formula is as follows: the abscissa point.x and ordinate point.y in each grid are accumulated respectively to quantify position information.<disp-formula id="Equ11"><label>11</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M73">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} \left\{ \begin{array}{ll} X_{i}=\sum {point.x }&amp;{} \quad {if \ points \ in\ grid }_{i}\\ Y_{i}=\sum {point. y}&amp;{} \quad {if \ points \ in\ grid }_{i} \end{array}. \right. \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M74" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mfenced open="{"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:msub><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_Equ11.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p id="Par31">Then, we obtain the <italic>z</italic>-scores of each grid <inline-formula id="IEq27"><alternatives><tex-math id="M75">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$Z_{i}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M76"><mml:msub><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq27.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> to quantify potential features.<disp-formula id="Equ12"><label>12</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M77">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} \left\{ \begin{array}{ll} Z_{i}=\frac{ {Num}_{i}-\frac{\sum _{m=1}^{N_{g}} N u m_{m}}{N_{g}}}{\sqrt{\frac{1}{N_{g}} \sum _{k=1}^{N_{g}}\left( {Num}_{k} -\frac{\sum _{n=1}^{N_{g}} N u m_{n}}{N_{g}}\right) ^{2}}}\\ \\ { Num }_{i}= number \ of \ points\ in \ grid_{i} \end{array} \right. \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M78" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mfenced open="{"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">Num</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:msubsup><mml:msup><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">Num</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">Num</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_Equ12.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>Finally, each grid can be represented as three attributes, and we fused the attributes to construct the vectors <italic>vector</italic>(<italic>c</italic>(<italic>i</italic>)) to define the sequence functional similarity of circRNAs <italic>SQFS</italic>(<italic>c</italic>(<italic>i</italic>), <italic>c</italic>(<italic>j</italic>)) by Pearson correlation coefficient. Where <italic>c</italic>(<italic>i</italic>) represents the <italic>A</italic>
<italic>i</italic>th cricRNA.<disp-formula id="Equ13"><label>13</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M79">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} \left\{ \begin{array}{ll} {SQFS(c(i),c(j))}=\frac{ {vector}({c(i))} \cdot {vector}({c(j))}}{\Vert {vector}({c(i))}\Vert \Vert {vector}({c(j))}\Vert }\\ { vevtor }(c(i))=\left( {grid}_{1}, {grid}_{2}, \ldots , {grid}_{\mathrm {N}_{g}}\right) \end{array}, \right. \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M80" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mfenced open="{"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">vector</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">vector</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">‖</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">vector</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">‖</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">‖</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">vector</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">‖</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">vevtor</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">grid</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">grid</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">grid</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:msub></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_Equ13.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>vector</italic>(<italic>c</italic>(<italic>i</italic>)) means the sequence feature vector of the <italic>i</italic>th circRNA, <inline-formula id="IEq28"><alternatives><tex-math id="M81">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${vector(c(i))}\cdot {vector(c(i))}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M82"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq28.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the dot product of <italic>vector</italic>(<italic>c</italic>(<italic>i</italic>)) and <italic>vector</italic>(<italic>c</italic>(<italic>i</italic>)).</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec8">
    <title>Results</title>
    <sec id="Sec9">
      <title>Parameters selection</title>
      <p id="Par32">circRNA can be used as the sponge of microRNA to play a role in biological processes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. We downloaded circRNA–miRNA association data from the starbase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. There are 267 types of circRNAs that match the 365 types of circRNA we calculated. We obtained 267 pairs of circRNA–miRNA association similarities through the Jaccard similarity method, which were compared with the functional similarities we calculated. Denote <italic>CMS</italic> as the circRNA–miRNA similarity matrix, and its entry <italic>CMS</italic>(<italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic>) can be obtained by the following formula:<disp-formula id="Equ14"><label>14</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M83">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} CMS\left( i,j\right) =\frac{\left| {CM}_i\cap {CM}_j\right| }{\left| {CM}_i\cup {CM}_j\right| }, \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M84" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CM</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∩</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CM</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfenced><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CM</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∪</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CM</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfenced></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_Equ14.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <inline-formula id="IEq29"><alternatives><tex-math id="M85">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${CM}_i$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M86"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CM</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq29.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the set of microRNAs associated with the <italic>i</italic>th circRNA, and <inline-formula id="IEq30"><alternatives><tex-math id="M87">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${CM}_j$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M88"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CM</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq30.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the set of microRNAs associated with the <italic>j</italic>th circRNA.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Parameters selection</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Fig5_HTML" id="MO19"/></fig></p>
      <p id="Par33">We set the parameter step size to 0.1. Because circRNA has little data associated with diseases, we set <inline-formula id="IEq31"><alternatives><tex-math id="M89">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\alpha$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M90"><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq31.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> the value range from 0 to 0.2, and the value range for <inline-formula id="IEq32"><alternatives><tex-math id="M91">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\beta$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M92"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq32.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq33"><alternatives><tex-math id="M93">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\gamma$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M94"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq33.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> from 0 to 1.We used the grid search method to obtain the optimal parameters through 30 sets of experiments and selected two groups for display. The results are shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>. The experimental results with parameters of 0.1, 0.4, 0.5 and 0.1, 0.3, 0.6 are <inline-formula id="IEq34"><alternatives><tex-math id="M95">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$({R=0.205}, {P=8.2e^{-3})}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M96"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.205</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>8.2</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq34.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq35"><alternatives><tex-math id="M97">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$({R=0.213}, {P=4.6e^{-4}})$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M98"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.213</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>4.6</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq35.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. The results prove that our circRNA functional similarity is related to microRNA similarity. We selected the optimal value of the parameter <inline-formula id="IEq36"><alternatives><tex-math id="M99">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\alpha ,\beta ,\gamma$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M100"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq36.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> are 0.1, 0.3, 0.6. Figure <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> shows the heat map of circRNA functional similarity calculated with parameters of 0.1, 0.3 and 0.6.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>CircRNA functional similarity heatmap shows the functional similarity of 365 kinds of circRNAs</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Fig6_HTML" id="MO20"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec10">
      <title>CircRNA functional similarity is correlated with expression similarity</title>
      <p id="Par34">CircRNAs with semblable functions squint towards participate in semblable biological processes and interact with semblable cellular components. To verify circRNAs with similar functions may squint towards having similar expression profiles, we seeked the relationship between circRNA functional similarity calculated by MSCFS and expression similarity. In this study, we used the absolute Pearson’s correlation coefficient (PCC) to measure circRNA expression similarity.</p>
      <p id="Par35">We finally obtain circRNA expression profiling data from Peng et al.’s work [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], which consists of expression profiles of 2932 circRNAs. Then, we calculated the conducted a comprehensive analysis of circRNA expression in papillary thyroid carcinoma PCC score as the co-expression similarity of each pair of circRNA expression profiles and obtained the co-expression similarity of 8049 pairs of circRNAs, and then performed the correlation analysis of circRNA expression similarity and circRNA functional similarity. As a result, the functional similarity of circRNA confirmed positive correlation with circRNA co-expression similarity (<inline-formula id="IEq37"><alternatives><tex-math id="M101">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${R=0.076, P=9.05e^{-4}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M102"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.076</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>9.05</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq37.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, Pearson correlation). We grouped 8049 pairs of circRNAs into different groups according to functional similarity in steps of 0.1 and calculated the average expression similarity and functional similarity of each group. Clearly, the functional similarity of circRNA is positively correlated with the expression similarity (<inline-formula id="IEq38"><alternatives><tex-math id="M103">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${R=0.8991, P=9.73e^{-4}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M104"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.8991</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>9.73</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Article_IEq38.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). Results inform that circRNA functional similarity obtained by our method is correlated with circRNA expression similarity, which is well known to be associated with circRNA functional similarity.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>The relationship between circRNA MSCFS functional similarity and their expression similarity</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Fig7_HTML" id="MO21"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec11">
      <title>A circRNA functional similarity network</title>
      <p id="Par36">Figure <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref> shows the distribution of circRNA functional similarity scores. We have structured a partial graph of the circRNA network with a threshold of 0.7 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>). Some circRNAs are less associated with other circRNAs, while some circRNAs are more associated with other circRNAs. We can do more research on those circRNAs that are more related and explore the potential functions of circRNAs related to them.<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>The circRNA funtional similarity score distribution</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Fig8_HTML" id="MO22"/></fig><fig id="Fig9"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>A circRNA functional network based on the functional similarity of MSCFS. Each node and edge connecting any two nodes (circRNAs) indicates that the functional similarity of the two circRNAs is equal to or greater than the similarity cutoff value</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2021_4287_Fig9_HTML" id="MO23"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec12">
      <title>Case study</title>
      <p id="Par37">To verify our results, we executed case analysis on the circRNA function annotation in the CircFunBase database. CircFunBase is a web-accessible database that aims to provide a high-quality functional circRNA resource, including experimentally validated and computationally predicted functions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p>
      <p id="Par38">Amongst the 365 kinds of circRNAs, hsa_circ_0000140 has the highest correlation score with hsa_circ_0001946 in other 364 circRNAs. In the CircFunBase database, the functional annotations of these two circRNAs are related to gastric cancer. Then we select circRNA pairs with high similarity scores for analysis. For example, the functional similarity score of hsa_circ_0043278 and hsa_circ_0006220 is 0.82, and it can be found in the CircFunBase database that both are related to hypertension [differential expression (hypertensive patients and healthy controls)]. The functional similarity score of hsa_circ_0005927 and hsa_circ_0138960 is 0.83, both of which are related to gastric cancer. Through case analysis, we can know the practicality and accuracy of the MSCFS method.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec13">
    <title>Discussion and conclusion</title>
    <p id="Par39">CircRNAs have peculiar biological structures and have proven to play essential roles in biological processes and human health. Inferring the functional similarity of circRNAs can help analyze the function of circRNAs and predict the association of circRNA-disease. However, due to the lack of functional annotations for circRNAs in public databases, it is not straightforward to calculate the functional similarity of circRNAs using existing single data sources.</p>
    <p id="Par40">This paper proposes a new algorithm, MSCFS, to calculate the functional similarity of circRNA by integrating multiple circRNA associated biological data. The results showed that the circRNAs associated with the same miRNA have a high similarity score. The circRNA co-expression similarity was positively correlated with our calculated results. We also found that circRNAs with a high similarity score were also similar in the function of the disease. By calculating the functional similarity of circRNAs, we can explore more potential functions and associations of circRNAs.</p>
    <p id="Par41">We have integrated multiple biological data sources related to circRNAs, and the results will be somewhat biased due to the quality of some data sources. In the future, we will integrate more and more reliable data to further improve the accuracy of circRNA functional similarity calculations.</p>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <glossary>
    <title>Abbreviations</title>
    <def-list>
      <def-item>
        <term>circRNAs</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par5">Circular RNAs</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>GO</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par6">Gene Ontology</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>RBPs</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par7">RNA binding proteins</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>DAG</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par8">Directed acyclic graphs</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>PSSM</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par9">Position specific scoring matrix</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>CMS</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par10">CircRNA–miRNA similarity matrix</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>PCC</term>
        <def>
          <p id="Par11">Pearson’s correlation coefficient</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
    </def-list>
  </glossary>
  <fn-group>
    <fn>
      <p>
        <bold>Publisher's Note</bold>
      </p>
      <p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
    </fn>
  </fn-group>
  <ack>
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <p>The authors are very grateful to the anonymous reviewers for their constructive comments which have helped significantly in revising this work. We would like to thank the Experimental Center of School of Computer Science and Engineering of Central South University, for providing computing resources.</p>
    <sec id="d32e3268">
      <title>About this supplement</title>
      <p id="Par42">This article has been published as part of BMC Bioinformatics Volume 22 Supplement 10 2021: Selected articles from the 19th Asia Pacific Bioinformatics Conference (APBC 2021): bioinformatics. The full contents of the supplement are available at
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bmcbioinformatics.biomedcentral.com/articles/supplements/volume-22-supplement-10">https://bmcbioinformatics.biomedcentral.com/articles/supplements/volume-22-supplement-10</ext-link>.</p>
    </sec>
  </ack>
  <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
    <title>Authors’ contributions</title>
    <p>LS, CZ, XY, LD and JP designed the study and conducted experiments. LS, CZ, LD and JP performed statistical analyses. LS, XY and JP drafted the manuscript. JP and LD prepared the experimental materials and benchmarks. All authors have read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
  </notes>
  <notes notes-type="funding-information">
    <title>Funding</title>
    <p>This work was supported by National Natural Science Foundation of China under Grant No. 61972422. The funding body has not played any roles in the design of the study and collection, analysis and interpretation of data in writing the manuscript.</p>
  </notes>
  <notes notes-type="data-availability">
    <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
    <p>The Python source codes and the datasets in this work are freely available in the GitHub (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/CJNabla/MultiSourcCFS">https://github.com/CJNabla/MultiSourcCFS</ext-link>).</p>
  </notes>
  <notes>
    <title>Declarations</title>
    <notes id="FPar2">
      <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
      <p id="Par43">Not applicable.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes id="FPar3">
      <title>Consent for publication</title>
      <p id="Par44">Not applicable.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes id="FPar4" notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p id="Par45">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
    </notes>
  </notes>
  <ref-list id="Bib1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="CR1">
      <label>1.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Meng</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhou</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Feng</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tang</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>CircRNA: functions and properties of a novel potential biomarker for cancer</article-title>
        <source>Mol Cancer.</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>16</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <lpage>8</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12943-016-0568-5</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28093071</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR2">
      <label>2.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sanger</surname>
            <given-names>HL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Klotz</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Riesner</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gross</surname>
            <given-names>HJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kleinschmidt</surname>
            <given-names>AK</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Viroids are single-stranded covalently closed circular RNA molecules existing as highly base-paired rod-like structures</article-title>
        <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci.</source>
        <year>1976</year>
        <volume>73</volume>
        <issue>11</issue>
        <fpage>3852</fpage>
        <lpage>6</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.73.11.3852</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 1069269?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1069269</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR3">
      <label>3.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xiao</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Circular RNAs: promising biomarkers for human diseases</article-title>
        <source>EBioMedicine.</source>
        <year>2018</year>
        <volume>34</volume>
        <fpage>267</fpage>
        <lpage>74</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ebiom.2018.07.036</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 30078734?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30078734</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR4">
      <label>4.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Du</surname>
            <given-names>WW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fang</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Awan</surname>
            <given-names>FM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>BB</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Induction of tumor apoptosis through a circular RNA enhancing Foxo3 activity</article-title>
        <source>Cell Death Differ.</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>24</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <fpage>357</fpage>
        <lpage>70</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cdd.2016.133</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 27886165?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27886165</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR5">
      <label>5.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Armakola</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Higgins</surname>
            <given-names>MJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Figley</surname>
            <given-names>MD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Barmada</surname>
            <given-names>SJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Scarborough</surname>
            <given-names>EA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Diaz</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fang</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shorter</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Krogan</surname>
            <given-names>NJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Finkbeiner</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Inhibition of RNA lariat debranching enzyme suppresses TDP-43 toxicity in ALS disease models</article-title>
        <source>Nat Genet.</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>44</volume>
        <issue>12</issue>
        <fpage>1302</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2434</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 23104007?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23104007</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR6">
      <label>6.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bao</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhong</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dai</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Exon-intron circular RNAs regulate transcription in the nucleus</article-title>
        <source>Nat Struct Mol Biol.</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>22</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <fpage>256</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nsmb.2959</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25664725?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25664725</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR7">
      <label>7.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>X-O</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xiang</surname>
            <given-names>J-F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yin</surname>
            <given-names>Q-F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xing</surname>
            <given-names>Y-H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>L-L</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Circular intronic long noncoding RNAs</article-title>
        <source>Mol Cell.</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>51</volume>
        <issue>6</issue>
        <fpage>792</fpage>
        <lpage>806</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2013.08.017</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24035497?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24035497</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR8">
      <label>8.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Guo</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The circular RNA Cdr1as, via miR-7 and its targets, regulates insulin transcription and secretion in islet cells</article-title>
        <source>Sci Rep.</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>5</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <lpage>12</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR9">
      <label>9.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Deng</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zheng</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>An</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhou</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Circular RNA ITCH has inhibitory effect on ESCC by suppressing the WNT/<italic>β</italic>-catenin pathway</article-title>
        <source>Oncotarget.</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <issue>8</issue>
        <fpage>6001</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.3469</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25749389?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25749389</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR10">
      <label>10.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lukiw</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Circular RNA (circRNA) in Alzheimer’s disease (AD)</article-title>
        <source>Front Genet.</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <fpage>307</fpage>
        <?supplied-pmid 24427167?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24427167</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR11">
      <label>11.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Greene</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Baird</surname>
            <given-names>A-M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Brady</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lim</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gray</surname>
            <given-names>SG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McDermott</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Finn</surname>
            <given-names>SP</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Circular RNAs: biogenesis, function and role in human diseases</article-title>
        <source>Front Mol Biosci.</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <fpage>38</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmolb.2017.00038</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 28634583?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28634583</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR12">
      <label>12.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hansen</surname>
            <given-names>TB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jensen</surname>
            <given-names>TI</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Clausen</surname>
            <given-names>BH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bramsen</surname>
            <given-names>JB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Finsen</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Damgaard</surname>
            <given-names>CK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kjems</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Natural RNA circles function as efficient microRNA sponges</article-title>
        <source>Nature.</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>495</volume>
        <issue>7441</issue>
        <fpage>384</fpage>
        <lpage>8</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11993</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 23446346?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23446346</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR13">
      <label>13.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Thomas</surname>
            <given-names>LF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sætrom</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Circular RNAs are depleted of polymorphisms at microRNA binding sites</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics.</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>30</volume>
        <issue>16</issue>
        <fpage>2243</fpage>
        <lpage>6</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu257</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24764460?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24764460</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR14">
      <label>14.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kulcheski</surname>
            <given-names>FR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Christoff</surname>
            <given-names>AP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Margis</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Circular RNAs are miRNA sponges and can be used as a new class of biomarker</article-title>
        <source>J Biotechnol.</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>238</volume>
        <fpage>42</fpage>
        <lpage>51</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbiotec.2016.09.011</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 27671698?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27671698</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR15">
      <label>15.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dudekula</surname>
            <given-names>DB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Panda</surname>
            <given-names>AC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Grammatikakis</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>De</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Abdelmohsen</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gorospe</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>CircInteractome: a web tool for exploring circular RNAs and their interacting proteins and microRNAs</article-title>
        <source>RNA Biol.</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>13</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>34</fpage>
        <lpage>42</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15476286.2015.1128065</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 26669964?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26669964</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR16">
      <label>16.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dori</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bicciato</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Integration of bioinformatic predictions and experimental data to identify circRNA–miRNA associations</article-title>
        <source>Genes.</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <issue>9</issue>
        <fpage>642</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/genes10090642</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR17">
      <label>17.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>Y-C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Y-C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chang</surname>
            <given-names>K-L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hsiao</surname>
            <given-names>K-Y</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Analysis of common targets for circular RNAs</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinform.</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>20</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>372</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-019-2966-3</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR18">
      <label>18.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wan</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shi</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhou</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cui</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>MISIM v2.0: a web server for inferring microRNA functional similarity based on microRNA-disease associations</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>47</volume>
        <issue>W1</issue>
        <fpage>536</fpage>
        <lpage>41</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkz328</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR19">
      <label>19.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Song</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cui</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Inferring the human microRNA functional similarity and functional network based on microRNA-associated diseases</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics.</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>26</volume>
        <issue>13</issue>
        <fpage>1644</fpage>
        <lpage>50</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq241</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 20439255?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20439255</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR20">
      <label>20.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ashburner</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ball</surname>
            <given-names>CA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Blake</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Botstein</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Butler</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cherry</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Davis</surname>
            <given-names>AP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dolinski</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dwight</surname>
            <given-names>SS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Eppig</surname>
            <given-names>JT</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Gene ontology: tool for the unification of biology</article-title>
        <source>Nat Genet.</source>
        <year>2000</year>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>25</fpage>
        <lpage>9</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/75556</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 3037419?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10802651</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR21">
      <label>21.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fu</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Qu</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xiao</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shen</surname>
            <given-names>H-B</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>MiRGOFS: a GO-based functional similarity measurement for miRNAs, with applications to the prediction of miRNA subcellular localization and miRNA-disease association</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics.</source>
        <year>2018</year>
        <volume>34</volume>
        <issue>20</issue>
        <fpage>3547</fpage>
        <lpage>56</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bty343</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 29718114?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29718114</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR22">
      <label>22.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Resnik</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Semantic similarity in a taxonomy: an information-based measure and its application to problems of ambiguity in natural language</article-title>
        <source>J Artif Intell Res.</source>
        <year>1999</year>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <fpage>95</fpage>
        <lpage>130</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1613/jair.514</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR23">
      <label>23.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jiang JJ, Conrath DW. Semantic similarity based on corpus statistics and lexical taxonomy. arXiv preprint <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://arxiv.org/abs/cmp-lg/9709008">arXiv:cmp-lg/9709008</ext-link>. 1997.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR24">
      <label>24.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>An information-theoretic definition of similarity</article-title>
        <source>Icml.</source>
        <year>1998</year>
        <volume>98</volume>
        <fpage>296</fpage>
        <lpage>304</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR25">
      <label>25.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>JZ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Du</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Payattakool</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>PS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>C-F</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A new method to measure the semantic similarity of GO terms</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics.</source>
        <year>2007</year>
        <volume>23</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <fpage>1274</fpage>
        <lpage>81</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btm087</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 17344234?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17344234</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR26">
      <label>26.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Su</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mao</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Olman</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Prediction of functional modules based on comparative genome analysis and gene ontology application</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <year>2005</year>
        <volume>33</volume>
        <issue>9</issue>
        <fpage>2822</fpage>
        <lpage>37</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gki573</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 15901854?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15901854</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR27">
      <label>27.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Fletez-Brant</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McCallion</surname>
            <given-names>AS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Beer</surname>
            <given-names>MA</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>kmer-SVM: a web server for identifying predictive regulatory sequence features in genomic data sets</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>41</volume>
        <issue>W1</issue>
        <fpage>544</fpage>
        <lpage>56</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt519</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR28">
      <label>28.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hochreiter</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schmidhuber</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Long short-term memory</article-title>
        <source>Neural Comput.</source>
        <year>1997</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <issue>8</issue>
        <fpage>1735</fpage>
        <lpage>80</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/neco.1997.9.8.1735</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 9377276?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9377276</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR29">
      <label>29.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lord</surname>
            <given-names>PW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stevens</surname>
            <given-names>RD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Brass</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Goble</surname>
            <given-names>CA</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Investigating semantic similarity measures across the gene ontology: the relationship between sequence and annotation</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics.</source>
        <year>2003</year>
        <volume>19</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <fpage>1275</fpage>
        <lpage>83</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btg153</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 12835272?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12835272</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR30">
      <label>30.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fan C, Lei X, Fang Z, Jiang Q, Wu F-X. CircR2Disease: a manually curated database for experimentally supported circular RNAs associated with various diseases. Database. 2018;2018:bay044.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR31">
      <label>31.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jiang</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>circRNA disease: a manually curated database of experimentally supported circRNA-disease associations</article-title>
        <source>Cell Death Dis.</source>
        <year>2018</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <issue>5</issue>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <lpage>2</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41419-018-0503-3</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29298988</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR32">
      <label>32.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Meng X, Hu D, Zhang P, Chen Q, Chen M. CircFunBase: a database for functional circular RNAs. Database. 2019;2019:baz003.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR33">
      <label>33.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yao</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zheng</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Circ2Disease: a manually curated database of experimentally validated circRNAs in human disease</article-title>
        <source>Sci Rep.</source>
        <year>2018</year>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <lpage>6</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29311619</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR34">
      <label>34.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <collab>Consortium GO</collab>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Gene ontology consortium: going forward</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>43</volume>
        <issue>D1</issue>
        <fpage>1049</fpage>
        <lpage>56</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gku1179</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR35">
      <label>35.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Camon</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Magrane</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Barrell</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dimmer</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Maslen</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Binns</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Harte</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lopez</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Apweiler</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The gene ontology annotation (GOA) database: sharing knowledge in uniprot with gene ontology</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <year>2004</year>
        <volume>32</volume>
        <issue>suppl–1</issue>
        <fpage>262</fpage>
        <lpage>6</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkh021</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR36">
      <label>36.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Glažar</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Papavasileiou</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rajewsky</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>circBase: a database for circular RNAs</article-title>
        <source>RNA.</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>20</volume>
        <issue>11</issue>
        <fpage>1666</fpage>
        <lpage>70</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1261/rna.043687.113</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25234927?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25234927</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR37">
      <label>37.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mudunuri</surname>
            <given-names>U</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Che</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yi</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stephens</surname>
            <given-names>RM</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>biodbnet: the biological database network</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics.</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <fpage>555</fpage>
        <lpage>6</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btn654</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 19129209?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19129209</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR38">
      <label>38.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Smaili</surname>
            <given-names>FZ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gao</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hoehndorf</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Onto2vec: joint vector-based representation of biological entities and their ontology-based annotations</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics.</source>
        <year>2018</year>
        <volume>34</volume>
        <issue>13</issue>
        <fpage>52</fpage>
        <lpage>60</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bty259</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR39">
      <label>39.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kelley</surname>
            <given-names>LA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>MacCallum</surname>
            <given-names>RM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sternberg</surname>
            <given-names>MJ</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Enhanced genome annotation using structural profiles in the program 3D-PSSM</article-title>
        <source>J Mole Biol.</source>
        <year>2000</year>
        <volume>299</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <fpage>501</fpage>
        <lpage>22</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jmbi.2000.3741</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR40">
      <label>40.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jeffrey</surname>
            <given-names>HJ</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Chaos game representation of gene structure</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <year>1990</year>
        <volume>18</volume>
        <issue>8</issue>
        <fpage>2163</fpage>
        <lpage>70</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/18.8.2163</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 2336393?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2336393</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR41">
      <label>41.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>J-H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhou</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Qu</surname>
            <given-names>L-H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>J-H</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>starBase v2.0: decoding miRNA–ceRNA, miRNA–ncRNA and protein–RNA interaction networks from large-scale CLIP-Seq data</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic acids Res.</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>42</volume>
        <issue>D1</issue>
        <fpage>92</fpage>
        <lpage>7</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt1248</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR42">
      <label>42.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Peng</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shi</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ye</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Microarray profiling of circular RNAs in human papillary thyroid carcinoma</article-title>
        <source>PLoS One.</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <fpage>0170287</fpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
