<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?properties open_access?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1367-4803</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1367-4811</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8723139</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34320637</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btab549</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">btab549</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Applications Notes</subject>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading">
          <subject>Data and Text Mining</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01060</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>rPanglaoDB: an R package to download and merge labeled single-cell RNA-seq data from the PanglaoDB database</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <name>
          <surname>Osorio</surname>
          <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="btab549-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
        <aff><institution>Centre for Molecular Medicine Norway (NCMM), University of Oslo</institution>, 0349 Oslo, <country country="NO">Norway</country></aff>
        <!--daniecos@uio.no-->
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6280-3130</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Kuijjer</surname>
          <given-names>Marieke L</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Centre for Molecular Medicine Norway (NCMM), University of Oslo</institution>, 0349 Oslo, <country country="NO">Norway</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>Department of Pathology, Leiden University Medical Center</institution>, Leiden, <country country="NL">The Netherlands</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8081-6725</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Cai</surname>
          <given-names>James J</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Department of Veterinary Integrative Biosciences, Texas A&amp;M University</institution>, College Station, TX 77843, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>Department of Electrical &amp; Computer Engineering, Texas A&amp;M University</institution>, College Station, TX 77843, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>Interdisciplinary Program of Genetics, Texas A&amp;M University</institution>, College Station, TX 77843, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>Center for Statistical Bioinformatics, Texas A&amp;M University</institution>, College Station, TX 77843, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name>
          <surname>Kendziorski</surname>
          <given-names>Christina</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Associate Editor</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="btab549-cor1">To whom correspondence should be addressed. <email>daniecos@uio.no</email></corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <day>15</day>
      <month>1</month>
      <year>2022</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2021-07-28">
      <day>28</day>
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>28</day>
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>38</volume>
    <issue>2</issue>
    <fpage>580</fpage>
    <lpage>582</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>01</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>14</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="editorial-decision">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>26</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="corrected-typeset">
        <day>06</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2021. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xlink:href="btab549.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <sec id="s1">
        <title>Motivation</title>
        <p>Characterizing cells with rare molecular phenotypes is one of the promises of high throughput single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNA-seq) techniques. However, collecting enough cells with the desired molecular phenotype in a single experiment is challenging, requiring several samples preprocessing steps to filter and collect the desired cells experimentally before sequencing. Data integration of multiple public single-cell experiments stands as a solution for this problem, allowing the collection of enough cells exhibiting the desired molecular signatures. By increasing the sample size of the desired cell type, this approach enables a robust cell type transcriptome characterization.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2">
        <title>Results</title>
        <p>Here, we introduce rPanglaoDB, an R package to download and merge the uniformly processed and annotated scRNA-seq data provided by the PanglaoDB database. To show the potential of rPanglaoDB for collecting rare cell types by integrating multiple public datasets, we present a biological application collecting and characterizing a set of 157 fibrocytes. Fibrocytes are a rare monocyte-derived cell type, that exhibits both the inflammatory features of macrophages and the tissue remodeling properties of fibroblasts. This constitutes the first fibrocytes’ unbiased transcriptome profile report. We compared the transcriptomic profile of the fibrocytes against the fibroblasts collected from the same tissue samples and confirm their associated relationship with healing processes in tissue damage and infection through the activation of the prostaglandin biosynthesis and regulation pathway.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3">
        <title>Availability and implementation</title>
        <p>rPanglaoDB is implemented as an R package available through the CRAN repositories <ext-link xlink:href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=rPanglaoDB" ext-link-type="uri">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=rPanglaoDB</ext-link>.</p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>European Union’s Horizon 2020</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Marie Sklodowska-Curie</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>801133</award-id>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Norwegian Research Council</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100005416</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>University of Oslo through the Centre for Molecular Medicine Norway (NCMM</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>187615</award-id>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="3"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec>
    <title>1 Introduction</title>
    <p>Merging and integrating the count matrices derived from multiple independent public single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNA-seq) experiments allows for better evaluation of the biological patterns in cell composition of tissues, as well as the identification of patterns of gene expression and gene regulation that are consistent across cells of the same cell type obtained from independent samples (<xref rid="btab549-B17" ref-type="bibr">Swamy <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>). A good quality integration of multiple datasets allowing comparison and contrasting of the data across different projects begins with a consistent preprocessing of the samples, using the same reference genome and the same quantification method to generate the count matrices (<xref rid="btab549-B11" ref-type="bibr">Lachmann <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>). These steps are then followed by the batch effect removal, normalization, cell type annotation and characterization of samples and cell types (<xref rid="btab549-B2" ref-type="bibr">Butler <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="btab549-B8" ref-type="bibr">Hie <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="btab549-B10" ref-type="bibr">Korsunsky <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="btab549-B13" ref-type="bibr">Luecken <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="btab549-B16" ref-type="bibr">Stuart <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>).</p>
    <p>PanglaoDB is a secondary scRNA-seq database that reports the annotated count matrices for thousands of human and mice scRNA-seq experiments deposited in the sequence read archive (SRA) database of the National Center for Biotechnology Information. Samples available in the PanglaoDB database are uniformly processed with the ‘alona’ package and made available in a web-based unified framework at <ext-link xlink:href="https://panglaodb.se/" ext-link-type="uri">https://panglaodb.se/</ext-link> (<xref rid="btab549-B5" ref-type="bibr">Franzen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="btab549-B4" ref-type="bibr">Franzen and Bjorkegren, 2020</xref>). However, the PanglaoDB database reports each sample on a single web page and does not offer options to automatically download or merge multiple available datasets based on molecular phenotypes or specific cell-type composition of the samples.</p>
    <p>For that reason, here, we introduce rPanglaoDB, an R package to download and merge the uniformly processed and annotated scRNA-seq data provided by the PanglaoDB database. The package contains a comprehensive set of functions for filtering samples by organism and tissue from which the cells were collected, for cell type and signature marker genes expressed by the cells, as well as for the quality control and merging of the downloaded datasets. The final output of rPanglaoDB is a Seurat object, facilitating the downstream analysis and characterization of the data as well as the integration of datasets not available in PanglaoDB after being processed through ‘alona’ (<xref rid="btab549-B5" ref-type="bibr">Franzen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>2 Material and methods</title>
    <p>rPanglaoDB includes four main functions, two for querying the list of samples available in the database, one to query the cell-type composition of the samples and one to download the samples’ count matrices and associated annotations.</p>
    <p><italic toggle="yes">Querying samples in the database</italic>: Currently available samples can be accessed through two functions: ‘getSampleList’ which returns the list of all samples included in the database together with their associated annotations, such as the SRA database identifiers, the species and tissue from which the cells were collected, the protocol used and the number of cells included in the sample, and ‘getMarkers’ which returns the list of clusters of cells in which a user-defined set of markers is expressed.</p>
    <p><italic toggle="yes">Querying samples’ composition information from the database</italic>: Cell-type and number of cells by cell-type for the samples included in the database can be accessed through the ‘getSampleComposition’ function. It allows filtering of the results by the metadata associated with the sample returned by the ‘getSampleList’ function.</p>
    <p><italic toggle="yes">Downloading samples’ count matrices and associated annotations</italic>: Once identified the samples, as well as the count matrices and the associated annotations can be downloaded using the ‘downloadSamples’ function. This function includes an option to return each sample as an independent Seurat object or to merge all samples into one Seurat object.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>3 Results</title>
    <p>Using the ‘getMarkers’ function, we identified a cluster of cells in the SRS3121028 sample derived from skin wound tissues (3 days after scab detachment) expressing <italic toggle="yes">CD34</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">ACTA2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">FN1</italic>, Collagen V, <italic toggle="yes">FAP</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">SIRPA</italic> and the lack of expression of <italic toggle="yes">CSF1R</italic> (<xref rid="btab549-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>). Such combinatorial expression of genes differentiate fibrocytes from macrophages and fibroblasts (<xref rid="btab549-B12" ref-type="bibr">Lim <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="btab549-B14" ref-type="bibr">Pilling <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="btab549-B15" ref-type="bibr">Reilkoff <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>).</p>
    <fig position="float" id="btab549-F1">
      <label>Fig. 1.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Characterization of the fibrocytes transcriptome. (<bold>A</bold>) Identification of cells expressing marker genes that differentiate fibrocytes’ identity from macrophages and fibroblasts (<italic toggle="yes">CD34</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">ACTA2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">FN1</italic>, Collagen V, <italic toggle="yes">FAP and SIRPA</italic>). (<bold>B</bold>) Cross validation of the identified cells expressing <italic toggle="yes">CD34</italic><inline-formula id="IE1"><mml:math id="IM1" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <italic toggle="yes">ACTA2</italic><inline-formula id="IE2"><mml:math id="IM2" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <italic toggle="yes">COL5A1</italic><inline-formula id="IE3"><mml:math id="IM3" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <italic toggle="yes">COL5A2</italic><inline-formula id="IE4"><mml:math id="IM4" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <italic toggle="yes">COL5A3</italic><inline-formula id="IE5"><mml:math id="IM5" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <italic toggle="yes">FN1</italic><inline-formula id="IE6"><mml:math id="IM6" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <italic toggle="yes">FAP</italic><inline-formula id="IE7"><mml:math id="IM7" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <italic toggle="yes">SIRPA</italic><inline-formula id="IE8"><mml:math id="IM8" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <italic toggle="yes">PTPRC</italic><inline-formula id="IE9"><mml:math id="IM9" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <italic toggle="yes">MME</italic><inline-formula id="IE10"><mml:math id="IM10" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <italic toggle="yes">SEMA7A</italic><inline-formula id="IE11"><mml:math id="IM11" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> by kernel density estimation through the Nebulosa package. (<bold>C</bold>) Volcano plot displaying the differential expression between fibrocytes and the fibroblasts collected in the same merged samples. (<bold>D</bold>) Enrichment of the prostaglandin biosynthesis and regulation pathway using GSEA through the fgsea package. (<bold>E</bold>) Enrichment of the prostaglandin biosynthesis and regulation pathway using ssGSEA through the GSVA package</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="btab549f1" position="float"/>
    </fig>
    <p>Fibrocytes are associated with fibrosis, autoimmunity, cardiovascular disease and asthma, among other pathologies (<xref rid="btab549-B15" ref-type="bibr">Reilkoff <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Since, fibrocytes are marrow-derived cells that differentiate into fibroblasts-like phenotypes, they are usually wrongly labeled as fibroblasts. Thus, using the ‘getSamples’ function in rPanglaoDB, we downloaded all fibroblasts available from dermis samples in the database (SRA accessions: SRS3121028 and SRS3121030) (<xref rid="btab549-B12" ref-type="bibr">Lim <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>). We merged a total of 2172 cells and processed the associated scRNA-seq data using the Seurat package recommended pipeline (<xref rid="btab549-B16" ref-type="bibr">Stuart <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>). Datasets were integrated using Harmony and further corroboration of the marker genes defining their identity as fibrocytes (<italic toggle="yes">CD34</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">ACTA2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">COL5A1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">COL5A2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">COL5A3</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">FN1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">FAP</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">SIRPA</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">PTPRC</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">MME</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">SEMA7A</italic>) was assessed using the Nebulosa package (<xref rid="btab549-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>) (<xref rid="btab549-B1" ref-type="bibr">Alquicira-Hernandez and Powell, 2021</xref>; <xref rid="btab549-B10" ref-type="bibr">Korsunsky <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="btab549-B15" ref-type="bibr">Reilkoff <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>).</p>
    <p>Differential expression analysis of the cluster 8, which contained 157 fibrocytes (<xref rid="btab549-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>), against all the fibroblasts in the samples was performed using the MAST package (<xref rid="btab549-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1C</xref>); returning 50 upregulated genes in fibrocytes associated with the <italic toggle="yes">TGF-beta regulation of extracellular matrix</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">ECM-receptor interaction</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Prostaglandin biosynthesis and regulation</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Notch signaling pathway</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Interleukin-5 regulation of apoptosis</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Integrin beta-5 pathway</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Oncostatin M</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Hematopoietic cell lineage</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Inflammatory response pathway</italic> (FDR &lt; 0.05 using the hypergeometric-test through the enrichR package) (<xref rid="btab549-B3" ref-type="bibr">Finak <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="btab549-B18" ref-type="bibr">Xie <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>). We cross-validated the enrichment of the genes associated with the <italic toggle="yes">Prostaglandin biosynthesis and regulation pathway</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">ANXA3</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">S100A10</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">ANXA5</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">ANXA2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">PTGIS</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">ANXA1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">S100A6</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">PTGS1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HPGD</italic>) using the Gene Set Enrichment Analysis (GSEA) approach included in the fgsea package (FDR <inline-formula id="IE12"><mml:math id="IM12" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.01</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <xref rid="btab549-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1D</xref>) and the single-sample Gene Set Enrichment Analysis (ssGSEA) included in the GVSA package (FDR = <inline-formula id="IE13"><mml:math id="IM13" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2.18</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>18</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <xref rid="btab549-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1E</xref>) (<xref rid="btab549-B7" ref-type="bibr">Hanzelmann <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="btab549-B9" ref-type="bibr">Korotkevich <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>). All other associations did not pass the FDR threshold in all the other approaches applied (GSEA and ssGSEA). Our results show the potential of rPanglaoDB as a tool to collect cells with rare molecular phenotypes from the PanglaoDB database. We anticipate its use in the construction of atlases to characterize the different molecular phenotypes exhibited by different cell types in different tissues and organisms. We also provide the first unbiased, highly specific characterization of the fibrocyte transcriptome in skin wound tissues and confirm their association with healing processes in tissue damage and infection through the activation of the <italic toggle="yes">Prostaglandin Biosynthesis and Regulation Pathway</italic> (<xref rid="btab549-B6" ref-type="bibr">Grieb <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="btab549-B19" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>Funding</title>
    <p>D.O. was supported by the European Union’s Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme under the Marie Sklodowska-Curie grant agreement [801133]. M.L.K. was supported by the Norwegian Research Council, Helse Sør-Øst, and University of Oslo through the Centre for Molecular Medicine Norway (NCMM, 187615). </p>
    <p><italic toggle="yes">Conflict of Interest</italic>: none declared. </p>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ref-list id="ref1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="btab549-B1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Alquicira-Hernandez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Nebulosa recovers single cell gene expression signals by kernel density estimation</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>2485</fpage>–<lpage>2487</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab549-B2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Integrating single-cell transcriptomic data across different conditions, technologies, and species</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biotechnol</source>., <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>411</fpage>–<lpage>420</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29608179</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab549-B3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Finak</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Mast: a flexible statistical framework for assessing transcriptional changes and characterizing heterogeneity in single-cell RNA sequencing data</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>., <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>278</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26653891</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab549-B4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Franzen</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bjorkegren</surname><given-names>J.L.M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>alona: a web server for single-cell RNA-Seq analysis</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>3910</fpage>–<lpage>3912</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32324845</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab549-B5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Franzen</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>PanglaoDB: a web server for exploration of mouse and human single-cell RNA sequencing data</article-title>. <source>Database (Oxford)</source>, <volume>2019</volume>, <fpage>baz046</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30951143</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab549-B6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Grieb</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Circulating fibrocytes—biology and mechanisms in wound healing and scar formation</article-title>. <source>Int. Rev. Cell Mol. Biol</source>., <volume>291</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22017972</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab549-B7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hanzelmann</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>GSVA: gene set variation analysis for microarray and RNA-Seq data</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>7</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23323831</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab549-B8">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hie</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Efficient integration of heterogeneous single-cell transcriptomes using scanorama</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biotechnol</source>., <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>685</fpage>–<lpage>691</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31061482</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab549-B9">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Korotkevich</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2021</year>) Fast gene set enrichment analysis. <italic toggle="yes">bioRxiv</italic>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab549-B10">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Korsunsky</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Fast, sensitive and accurate integration of single-cell data with harmony</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>1289</fpage>–<lpage>1296</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31740819</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab549-B11">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lachmann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Massive mining of publicly available RNA-Seq data from human and mouse</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun</source>., <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>1366</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29636450</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab549-B12">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Hedgehog stimulates hair follicle neogenesis by creating inductive dermis during murine skin wound healing</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun</source>., <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>4903</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30464171</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab549-B13">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Luecken</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2020</year>) Benchmarking atlas-level data integration in single-cell genomics. <italic toggle="yes">bioRxiv</italic>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab549-B14">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pilling</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Identification of markers that distinguish monocyte-derived fibrocytes from monocytes, macrophages, and fibroblasts</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>e7475</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19834619</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab549-B15">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Reilkoff</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Fibrocytes: emerging effector cells in chronic inflammation</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Immunol</source>., <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>435</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21597472</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab549-B16">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Comprehensive integration of single-cell data</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>177</volume>, <fpage>1888</fpage>–<lpage>1902.e21</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31178118</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab549-B17">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Swamy</surname><given-names>V.S.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2021</year>) Building the mega single cell transcriptome ocular meta-atlas. <italic toggle="yes">bioRxiv</italic>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab549-B18">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Gene set knowledge discovery with enrichr</article-title>. <source>Curr. Protoc</source>., <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>e90</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33780170</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab549-B19">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Prostaglandin e2 hydrogel improves cutaneous wound healing via m2 macrophages polarization</article-title>. <source>Theranostics</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>5348</fpage>–<lpage>5361</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30555551</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
