<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?properties open_access?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1367-4803</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1367-4811</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8545346</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33974004</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btab317</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">btab317</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Original Papers</subject>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading">
          <subject>Data and Text Mining</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01060</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>Omics community detection using multi-resolution clustering</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9710-0248</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Rahnavard</surname>
          <given-names>Ali</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="btab317-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
        <aff><institution>Department of Biostatistics and Bioinformatics, Computational Biology Institute, Milken Institute School of Public Health, The George Washington University</institution>, Washington, DC 20052, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
        <!--rahnavard@gwu.edu-->
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
          <given-names>Suvo</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Epidemiology Branch, Division of Intramural Population Health Research, Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development, National Institutes of Health</institution>, Bethesda, MD 20892, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1187-0848</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Sayoldin</surname>
          <given-names>Bahar</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>School of Systems Biology, College of Science, George Mason University</institution>, Fairfax, VA 22030, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0836-3389</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Crandall</surname>
          <given-names>Keith A</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Department of Biostatistics and Bioinformatics, Computational Biology Institute, Milken Institute School of Public Health, The George Washington University</institution>, Washington, DC 20052, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Tekola-Ayele</surname>
          <given-names>Fasil</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Epidemiology Branch, Division of Intramural Population Health Research, Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development, National Institutes of Health</institution>, Bethesda, MD 20892, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4956-2429</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Mallick</surname>
          <given-names>Himel</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="btab317-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
        <aff><institution>Biostatistics and Research Decision Sciences, Merck &amp; Co., Inc</institution>, Rahway, NJ 07065, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
        <!--himel.mallick@merck.com-->
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name>
          <surname>Wren</surname>
          <given-names>Jonathan</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Associate Editor</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="btab317-cor1">To whom correspondence should be addressed. <email>rahnavard@gwu.edu</email> or <email>himel.mallick@merck.com</email></corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <day>15</day>
      <month>10</month>
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2021-05-11">
      <day>11</day>
      <month>5</month>
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>11</day>
      <month>5</month>
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>37</volume>
    <issue>20</issue>
    <fpage>3588</fpage>
    <lpage>3594</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>02</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>23</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="editorial-decision">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>26</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2021. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xlink:href="btab317.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <sec id="s1">
        <title>Motivation</title>
        <p>The discovery of biologically interpretable and clinically actionable communities in heterogeneous omics data is a necessary first step toward deriving mechanistic insights into complex biological phenomena. Here, we present a novel clustering approach, <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic>, for community detection in omics profiles by simultaneously incorporating similarities among measurements and the overall complex structure of the data.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2">
        <title>Results</title>
        <p>We show that <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> outperforms published methods in inferring the true community structure as measured by both sensitivity and misclassification rate on simulated datasets. We further validated <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> in diverse, multiple omics datasets, revealing new communities and functionally related groups in microbial strains, cell line gene expression patterns and fetal genomic variation. We also derived enrichment scores attributable to putatively meaningful biological factors in these datasets that can serve as hypothesis generators facilitating new sets of testable hypotheses.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3">
        <title>Availability and implementation</title>
        <p><italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> is open-source software, and the implementation is available online at <ext-link xlink:href="http://github.com/omicsEye/omeClust" ext-link-type="uri">http://github.com/omicsEye/omeClust</ext-link>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s5">
        <title>Supplementary information</title>
        <p><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary data</xref> are available at <italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic> online.</p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>National Science Foundation</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100000001</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>DEB-2028280</award-id>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>National Institute of Child Health and Human Development</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100000071</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>National Institutes of Health including American Recovery and Reinvestment Act</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>HHSN275200800013C</award-id>
        <award-id>HHSN275200800002I</award-id>
        <award-id>HHSN27500006</award-id>
        <award-id>HHSN275200800003IC</award-id>
        <award-id>HHSN275200800014C</award-id>
        <award-id>HHSN275200800012C</award-id>
        <award-id>HHSN275200800028C</award-id>
        <award-id>HHSN275201000009C</award-id>
        <award-id>HHSN27500008</award-id>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="7"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec>
    <title>1 Introduction</title>
    <p>Finding biologically meaningful groups exhibiting coherent within-group similarities and between-group differences is often the first critical step in any analysis of modern high-throughput data. An interesting characteristic that real biological networks represent is the clustering or community structure, under which the network topology is organized into modules commonly known as communities or clusters. While clustering and community discovery differ in their representation of detected group entities, they share many commonalities and our use case in this study is based on biological questions benefiting both finding clusters and detecting communities.</p>
    <p>Despite being a highly researched unsupervised problem supported by a myriad of algorithms from diverse scientific disciplines, clustering and community structure detection remains computationally and biologically challenging. This is particularly due to the technical nature of the associated data, which are typically noisy and high dimensional with confounding effects unique to individual technology (e.g. platform-specific batch effects). With ever-increasing multi-omics efforts and the associated technology-specific challenges, there is a need for more data-driven methods that are capable of finding biologically meaningful communities in a technology-agnostic manner.</p>
    <p>In addition to the omics-specific challenges, there are some long standing issues shared by most existing clustering (<xref rid="btab317-B1" ref-type="bibr">Altman, 1992</xref>; <xref rid="btab317-B34" ref-type="bibr">Sibson, 1973</xref>) and community detection algorithms (<xref rid="btab317-B4" ref-type="bibr">Blondel <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="btab317-B5" ref-type="bibr">Bohlin <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). Clear challenges remain to determine the most appropriate number of clusters as well as the most appropriate distance metric for a particular dataset. For example, a problem akin to hierarchical clustering is the careful tuning of the resolution parameter as well as the selection of appropriate evaluation criteria. When applied in high-throughput biology contexts, these are exacerbated by sparse and highly variable measurements with additional challenges introduced by the heterogeneity of the associated features. For instance, in metabolomics, some groups of metabolites have greater inter-feature distances than others or in microbial communities, distance between species is often related to sample environment (<xref rid="btab317-B24" ref-type="bibr">Lloyd-Price <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). These, together with the inter-individual differences introduced by the potential confounding factors (e.g. gender and age), calls for an algorithm that detects communities and attributes putatively meaningful biological factors to the detected community structure.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>2 Materials and methods</title>
    <p>Multi-resolution clustering (<italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic>) identifies communities within datasets potentially consisting of heterogeneous ‘features’. Features can be biomarkers from omics molecular profiles (e.g. taxa, genes, pathways, chemicals, etc.) potentially accompanied by the associated metadata (e.g. epidemiological variables, clinical, pharmaceutical and environmental covariates, among others). The relevant features are therefore, specifically defined in a study-specific manner relative to the data and research question posed by the individual study. To achieve generality of our approach, a key <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> input is a distance matrix of features. For an input dataset containing values from samples alongside a pre-calculated distance matrix between points (measurements) (<xref rid="btab317-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1a</xref>), the <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> algorithm proceeds by (i) building a representation of the overall structure of point distances (a hierarchy) using hierarchical clustering (zoom out) (<xref rid="btab317-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1b</xref>), (ii) descending the hierarchy to find heterogeneous clusters (zoom in) using a <bold>binary-silhouette score</bold>, (iii) calculating resolution scores (defined as the harmonic mean of the number of cluster members and the similarity between cluster members) for each cluster to prioritize important clusters and <bold>enrichment scores</bold> including normalized mutual information (NMI) and frequency-based scores for each metadata to rank the influence of the variable on the detected communities (if provided) and (iv) finally, generating graphic visualizations (<xref rid="btab317-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1c</xref> and <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S1</xref>) and reporting interpretable clustering results (<xref rid="btab317-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1d</xref>). We cover each of these key workflow elements in more detail below.</p>
    <p>
      <inline-graphic xlink:href="btab317ilf1.jpg"/>
    </p>
    <fig position="float" id="btab317-F1">
      <label>Fig. 1.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>omeClust overview workflow. (<bold>a)</bold> A distance matrix is used as input. The distance matrix can be obtained using any appropriate metric, such as Bray–Curtis distance for microbiome data or nucleotide-based distance for DNA sequence data. (<bold>b</bold>) Two-stage cluster detection applies (i) hierarchical clustering to find the hierarchical distance structure among features and (ii) trace up-down using a binary-silhouette score to find cluster nodes. (<bold>c</bold>) omeClust provides several ordination plots to represent the clustering results. The color represents cluster membership; the shape is used to present the most influential metadata in the detected clusters. (<bold>d)</bold> A tab-delimited file with clusters as rows and feature members, resolution scores for all metadata sorted by the mean of resolution scores for all clusters, and enrichment scores for each metadata are returned in columns</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="btab317f1" position="float"/>
    </fig>
    <p>In summary, <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> finds communities by generating an overall structure of relationships between points (samples or features) in the form of a hierarchical cluster based on a user-defined distance matrix, and then descends the hierarchy to find communities of homogeneous features. This approach uses two unique algorithms: (i) Algorithm 1 is designed to descend a hierarchy and return intermediate nodes in the hierarchy that represent communities, and (ii) Algorithm 2 is similarly designed to find heterogeneous clusters using a binary-silhouette score.</p>
    <sec>
      <title>2.1 Binary-silhouette score</title>
      <p>Binary-silhouette, defined in Algorithm 2, is a measurement to quantify how well members within a branch are related compared to the sibling branch in a hierarchy. A hierarchy is a binary tree, and each node has two children nodes. We calculate a binary-silhouette score, which is similar to a silhouette score (<xref rid="btab317-B30" ref-type="bibr">Ogbuabor and Ugwoke, 2018</xref>) except that, in binary-silhouette scoring, we only consider two clusters, left and right, rather than all clusters, when the score is measured. When we measure the binary-silhouette score for the left child (<italic toggle="yes">from</italic>: a) in a node, we use the immediate right child as another cluster (<italic toggle="yes">to</italic>: b) and vice-versa.</p>
      <p>
        <inline-graphic xlink:href="btab317ilf2.jpg"/>
      </p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>2.2 Enrichment score</title>
      <p>To measure the influence of each metadatum on the community structure, <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> implements two approaches, <bold><italic toggle="yes">freq</italic></bold> and <bold><italic toggle="yes">nmi</italic></bold>. While <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> by default, discretizes the continuous metadata, essentially any metadata that can be converted to a float data type can be used as an input to the <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> algorithm. For the <bold><italic toggle="yes">freq</italic></bold>approach, enrichment scores are computed by calculating the number of occurrences of the most frequent category of a metadata in a community, which is then scaled by dividing by the number of community members. The mean enrichment scores for each major cluster are then used to rank the influence of each metadatum on the detected community structure. Major clusters with &gt;0.05 enrichment scores are highlighted and returned. The <bold><italic toggle="yes">nmi</italic></bold> approach, on the other hand, directly uses the NMI (<xref rid="btab317-B11" ref-type="bibr">Estévez <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="btab317-B21" ref-type="bibr">Kvålseth, 2017</xref>) between the community labels and the metadata values as enrichment scores. NMI is a measure to evaluate the dependency between two variables, and it is a variant of mutual information from information theory which provides an interpretable quantification. If two variables are completely independent (no association) the NMI will be 0, whereas, for two identical variables, the NMI will be 1.</p>
      <p>At a deeper level, <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> uses hierarchical clustering to build an overall structure of potentially heterogeneous features and subsequently detects communities of related features. For hierarchical clustering, by default, <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> uses a complete-linkage approach (<xref rid="btab317-B17" ref-type="bibr">Großwendt and Röglin, 2017</xref>); however, the algorithm is robust to the specification of the linkage method (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S2</xref>) as other well-used approaches, such as <italic toggle="yes">single</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">average</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">complete</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">weighted</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">centroid</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">median</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">ward</italic> can be provided as options by the user. Specifically, for community detection, <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> undertakes a top-down recursive approach beginning at the root of the hierarchical tree and descending to a set of nodes within the tree. For descent, <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> compares a node’s binary-silhouette score with its two direct children. This procedure is repeated until termination, i.e. when the selected nodes represent single features in their respective data trees or the current nodes’ binary-silhouette score is larger than its children. All tips under a node in the hierarchy are considered a cluster if the node has a greater score than its children. Philosophically, <italic toggle="yes">omeClust’</italic>s approach is similar to a static tree cut (e.g. <italic toggle="yes">the cutree</italic> function in R) that creates groups from hierarchical clustering using an arbitrary cut threshold and returns groups in branches under the cut level (<xref rid="btab317-B22" ref-type="bibr">Langfelder <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). However, <italic toggle="yes">omeClust’</italic>s approach differs fundamentally from <italic toggle="yes">cutree</italic> in that <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> finds the cut levels adaptively at various distance levels, whereas <italic toggle="yes">cutree</italic> cuts all the hierarchy at an arbitrary and constant level provided by the user.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>3 <italic toggle="yes">OmeClust</italic> increases community detection power in omics data</title>
    <p>When applied to datasets with no clear cluster structure, <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> reports singleton clusters, as expected, ruling out the possibility of data artifacts and false positive findings (results not shown). To determine <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic>’s ability to recapitulate true positive clusters, we further validated <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> on datasets with known cluster structure (detailed in Section 3.1). Since <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> coherently looks at multiple resolution levels of the underlying hierarchical structure, it is expected to discover clusters (communities) above and beyond those detectable only by computing average distances between clusters. This is particularly relevant for omics data, where large groups of molecular features (e.g. expression values for genes in a metabolic pathway) form communities with variable mean distances between members and it is desirable to incorporate the entire resolution spectrum of the intra-cluster distances into the clustering algorithm.</p>
    <sec>
      <title>3.1 Synthetic data validation of <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic></title>
      <p>To evaluate <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic>, we tested our algorithm along with existing state-of-the-art approaches (<xref rid="btab317-B39" ref-type="bibr">You and You, 2018</xref>) in a variety of synthetic datasets containing built-in known communities (‘ground truth’) and evaluated their statistical and computational performance across a range of parameters. For generating synthetic clusters with ‘ground truth’ membership information, we used <italic toggle="yes">clusterlab</italic> (<xref rid="btab317-B18" ref-type="bibr">John <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>), which is a recent method that allows simulation of Gaussian clusters (<xref rid="btab317-B26" ref-type="bibr">Maugis <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>) with controlled spacing, size and variance among the generated clusters. Specifically, we generated 135 synthetic datasets of varying capacity across a range of pairwise combinations of cluster size (4, 6, 8) and per-cluster sample size (10, 20, 40), while also varying the feature dimensions (500, 1000, 1500) and inter-cluster distances (0.05, 0.10, 0.25, 0.5, 1).</p>
      <p>We found that <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> vastly outperforms popular community detection methods, such as the Louvain approach (<xref rid="btab317-B4" ref-type="bibr">Blondel <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>) and Infomap (<xref rid="btab317-B5" ref-type="bibr">Bohlin <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>) in terms of (i) the adjusted Rand index (<xref rid="btab317-F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2a</xref>), (ii) Jaccard index (<xref rid="btab317-F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2b</xref>), (iii) Fowlkes–Mallows index (<xref rid="btab317-F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2c</xref>) and (iv) <italic toggle="yes">F</italic>1 score (<xref rid="btab317-F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2d</xref>). While these network community detection approaches tend to perform well in readily distinguishable communities, they suffer in the presence of inherent multicollinearity, noise and overlap as typically observed in omics samples and can in turn give rise to misleading communities (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S1</xref>). In addition to superseding these more sophisticated methods and improving community detection, <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> further exhibited improved performance as compared to several other state-of-the-art domain-agnostic clustering algorithms, such as the partitional [e.g. Sincell (<xref rid="btab317-B19" ref-type="bibr">Juliá <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>), pcaReduce (<xref rid="btab317-B42" ref-type="bibr">Žurauskienė and Yau, 2016</xref>) and Seurat (<xref rid="btab317-B32" ref-type="bibr">Satija <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>)], network-based [e.g. Infomap (<xref rid="btab317-B5" ref-type="bibr">Bohlin <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>) and Louvain (<xref rid="btab317-B4" ref-type="bibr">Blondel <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="btab317-B8" ref-type="bibr">Csardi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>)], model-based [e.g. Hcmodel (<xref rid="btab317-B13" ref-type="bibr">Fraley <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>)], density-based [e.g. DBSCAN (<xref rid="btab317-B23" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>)], subspace-based [e.g. Hddc (<xref rid="btab317-B6" ref-type="bibr">Bouveyron <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2007; Bergé <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2013</xref>)] and shared nearest neighbor-based [e.g. sNNclust (<xref rid="btab317-B10" ref-type="bibr">Ertöz <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>) and sscClust (<xref rid="btab317-B31" ref-type="bibr">Ren <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>)] community detection methods [<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Tables S1 and S2</xref> and <xref rid="btab317-F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2(a–d)]</xref>. The superior performance of <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> remained consistent across a range of feature dimensions, inter-cluster distances and linkage methods, which further highlights the flexibility and robustness of <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> in realistically unbalanced community structures. Taken together, these findings confirm that by taking into account the overall high-level structure of diverse features, in addition to feature-wise distances, which alone may not be sufficient to reproducibly recover biologically complex communities, <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> is able to capture biologically relevant communities, missed by other methods, across a broad range of realistically complex scenarios.</p>
      <fig position="float" id="btab317-F2">
        <label>Fig. 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> improves community detection power. 135 synthetic datasets were generated using <italic toggle="yes">clusterlab (</italic><xref rid="btab317-B18" ref-type="bibr">John <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>) with varying number of clusters (<italic toggle="yes">k</italic>=4, 6, 8), cluster sizes (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=10, 20, 30), feature dimensions (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=500, 1000 and 1500) and distances among clusters (alpha =0.05, 0.1, 0.25, 0.5, 1) measured against a variety of indices with scores from 0 to 1, with 0 indicating identical features and 1 indicating features with random similarity. (<bold>a</bold>) <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> has a higher adjusted Rand index as compared to nine other clustering methods displaying greater degree of agreement among partitions and/or clusters given the ground truth information. (<bold>b</bold>) <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> similarly has a higher Jaccard index as compared to existing methods displaying greater degree of similarity given the ground truth information. (<bold>c)</bold> In terms of Fowlkes–Mallows index, <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> is also one of the best-performing methods displaying greater degree of similarity between its clustering set and the ground truth information. (<bold>d)</bold> Finally, <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> has a higher <italic toggle="yes">F</italic>1 score as compared to all other clustering methods displaying a better weighted average between precision and recall given the ground truth information</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="btab317f2" position="float"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>3.2 Empirical validation and application of <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic></title>
      <sec>
        <title>3.2.1 Niche association of human microbial species and strains</title>
        <p>We first applied <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> to 2484 metagenomes from the expanded human microbiome project (HMP1-II) (<xref rid="btab317-B24" ref-type="bibr">Lloyd-Price <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). In this application, the ‘features’ included the microbial speices inferred from the metagenomic data (<xref rid="btab317-B14" ref-type="bibr">Franzosa <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>) as well as clinical metadata for each sample (including body area of the collection site). <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> identified body area as the most influential metadata (NMI=0.83) responsible for the clustering structure (<xref rid="btab317-F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> also reports four major clusters (resolution score &gt;0.05) each corresponding to a human body site from which samples were collected, confirming the compositional structure of microbial species and their niche associations. Two metadata, RANDSID (random ID for patients) and SNPRNT (specimen barcode ID), had the lowest frequency-based enrichment scores (&lt;0.05), as expected. The overlaps of color and shape explain how well our computational approach defines the underlying clustering structure, providing actionable interpretations of the detected clusters or communities. Several ordination plots, such as principal coordinates analysis, <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-distributed stochastic neighbor embedding and multidimensional scaling were used to visualize the results. We also combined HMP1-II samples with the iHMP (<xref rid="btab317-B25" ref-type="bibr">Lloyd-Price <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>) shotgun metagenomic data on the human stool samples, and profiled additional 1149 microbial strains that passed the strain conditions (<xref rid="btab317-B37" ref-type="bibr">Truong <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> detected three communities of <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus parainfluenzae</italic> with body site being the most influential metadata, also confirmed with an independent PERMANOVA analysis (<xref rid="btab317-B2" ref-type="bibr">Anderson, 2017</xref>) using the <italic toggle="yes">adonis</italic> R function in the <italic toggle="yes">vegan</italic> package (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value = 0.001 with 999 permutations). These communities largely correspond to two body sites, supragingival plaque (two communities) and tongue dorsum (one community) with NMI of 0.49 (<xref rid="btab317-F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3b</xref>). Our novel findings thus suggest that microbial species can have more than one strain in each sample. We detected similar patterns for oral microbial species, including <italic toggle="yes">Actinomyces johnsonii</italic> (<xref rid="btab317-F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3c</xref>), <italic toggle="yes">Rothia mucilaginosa</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter showae</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Porphyromonas sp oral taxon 279</italic>, and stool microbial species including <italic toggle="yes">Eubacterium siraeum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> that showed evidence of multiple subclades of strains consistent with the literature (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S3</xref>).</p>
        <fig position="float" id="btab317-F3">
          <label>Fig. 3.</label>
          <caption>
            <p><italic toggle="yes">omeClust reveals biologically meaningful clusters of omics features</italic>. (<bold>a</bold>) <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> detects four major communities based on Bray–Curtis dissimilarity in human-associated microbial species, finding strong segregation by body area (i.e. oral, gut, skin and vaginal) revealing site-specific subspecies clades and dynamics across major body site habitats. (<bold>b)</bold> <italic toggle="yes">H.parainfluenzae</italic> strain clades are detected as communities of microbial strains using a combination of HMP1-II and iHMP data using Kimura two-parameter distance (<xref rid="btab317-B20" ref-type="bibr">Kimura, 1980</xref>). This reveals that microbial species not only have different strain subclades in different niches, but also can have more than one strain in each sample. (<bold>c</bold>) <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> detected three communities of <italic toggle="yes">A.johnsonii</italic> mostly detected in supragingival plaque body site</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="btab317f3" position="float"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>3.2.2 Cross-tissue analysis of gene and protein expression in cell lines</title>
        <p>Cell line gene expression has been extensively used to investigate intracellular activities in diseases, such as cancer (<xref rid="btab317-B15" ref-type="bibr">Ghandi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>) and inflammatory bowel disease (<xref rid="btab317-B33" ref-type="bibr">Schulze <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). We applied <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> to gene expression datasets from three breast cancer studies (<xref rid="btab317-B27" ref-type="bibr">McCall <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>, <xref rid="btab317-B28" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; <xref rid="btab317-B41" ref-type="bibr">Zilliox and Irizarry, 2007</xref>). In this application, the omics ‘features’ are gene expression and the clinical metadata include cell line type (i.e. kidney versus cerebellum) and spatial information (whether the sample is collected from the left or right side). Cell line gene expression serves as a strong application to validate our technique as we hypothesized these samples to be clustered according to the kind of tissue from which they originated. <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic>, indeed, found that cells establish communities based on their drawn tissues. Using the high-resolution mode of <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic>, we detected nine communities from seven tissue cell lines with NMI of 0.84 (<xref rid="btab317-F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4a</xref>). Cell lines from the kidney and cerebellum formed two communities suggesting spatial heterogeneity of these organs (e.g. whether samples have been collected from the left or right side). Although we did not have spatial resolution data to validate this information, this leads to an interesting hypothesis of spatial gene expression patterns of the left and right side of the kidney and cerebellum, which has been indicated in previous animal studies (<xref rid="btab317-B12" ref-type="bibr">Evans <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="btab317-B29" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). This finding also highlights the versatility of <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic>'s clustering capabilities, suggesting that depending on the biological signal present in the dataset, the user may choose the appropriate resolution level. The ability to use multiple resolutions within <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> allows users the flexibility to interpret communities at multiple vantage points (e.g. specific communities associated with different sets of metadata at various resolution levels).</p>
        <fig position="float" id="btab317-F4">
          <label>Fig. 4.</label>
          <caption>
            <p><italic toggle="yes">omeClust with low resolution on gene expression reveals communities of genes that are related to sample tissues. omeClust</italic> provides different ordination plots as exploratory figures to help users visualize the underlying structure of omics data. (<bold>a</bold>) Number of detected communities matches with the number of cell lines with the exception of kidney and cerebellum, where two communities are detected, suggesting possible differences in gene expression between the left and right kidney and cerebellum. However, two communities from the same organs are more similar to each other compared to other organs. (<bold>b</bold>) Proteins are used to find communities of samples, and here we detected three communities with overlap in tissues. (<bold>c</bold>) Using host transcriptome (196 520 gene expression for 1019 samples) we found three communities that inference ethnicity was the most influential metadata; however, the structure in the data was not explained by any major metadata element</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="btab317f4" position="float"/>
        </fig>
        <p>We also used a dataset of 154 samples with 2845 proteins from the Human Protein Atlas database (<xref rid="btab317-B38" ref-type="bibr">Uhlén <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>) and found that samples for Cell RNA, Blood RNA and Brain RNA fall in separate communities, although, tissue RNA falls in two clusters: Blood RNA and Brain RNA (<xref rid="btab317-F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4b</xref>), suggesting that tissue RNA has a broader transcriptomic community and could potentially have similar communities as Blood RNA or Brain RNA. In addition, our results using gene expression from 196 520 genes for 1019 cell lines from the CCLE (Cancer Cell Line Encyclopedia) (<xref rid="btab317-B15" ref-type="bibr">Ghandi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>) show that not one major metadatum explains the structure underlying the data. In particular, inferred ethnicity (<xref rid="btab317-F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4c</xref>), histology, pathology and gender were the most influential metadata (in decreasing order) and the least enriched metadata in the communities corresponded to the ID variables (i.e. name and depMapID), as expected. This testing strategy is very similar in spirit to a standalone approach like PERMANOVA, where it is possible to attribute the percentage of variation in the distance matrix explained by a metadata of interest. However, unlike PERMANOVA, <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> explicitly uses the clustering and community results to derive the enrichment scores, providing a sophisticated and biologically balanced information for further follow-up experimentation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>3.2.3 Genetic relatedness in fetal growth outcomes</title>
        <p>Finally, we applied <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> to the NICHD Fetal Growth Studies-Singletons (<xref rid="btab317-B16" ref-type="bibr">Grewal <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>) data that included placental samples at delivery from 301 pregnant women from four race/ethnic groups including non-Hispanic white (25.6%), non-Hispanic black (23.9%), Hispanic (33.9%) and Asian/Pacific Islander (16.6%). The samples were genotyped to obtain fetal single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) using HumanOmni2.5 Beadchips (Illumina Inc, San Diego, CA) with ∼2 million SNPs (<xref rid="btab317-B9" ref-type="bibr">Delahaye <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>). In this application, the SNP data are the genomic ‘features’ and the associated clinical metadata include birth weight, prenatal environment, race, education, etc. Using genetic relationship information among the SNPs as a measure of distance, we set out to detect communities with higher affinity to babies with extremely small or large weight at birth. To this end, we considered several prenatal environments (e.g. maternal age, socio-economic status and parity, among others) as well as low birth weight status (defined as birth weight &lt;2500 g), small for gestational age defined as birth weight less than the 10th percentile for gestational age based on sex-specific birth weight references, and large-for-gestational age defined as birth weight greater than the 90th percentile for gestational age based on sex-specific birth weight references as metadata in the <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> analysis. <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> reported four major clusters primarily overlapping with self-identified race/ethnicity (<xref rid="btab317-F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5a</xref>). The top three most influential metadata were maternal demographic factor (race), socio-economic status (education) and cardiometabolic factors (gestational weight gain), consistent with previous evidence for population differences in size at birth (<xref rid="btab317-B7" ref-type="bibr">Buck Louis <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="btab317-B35" ref-type="bibr">Tekola-Ayele <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="btab317-B35" ref-type="bibr">Tekola‐Ayele <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>) [<xref rid="btab317-F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5(b–c)]</xref>. Specifically, the ordination plots revealed that babies born to self-identified Black mothers had disproportionately smaller weight at birth compared to other races. These findings demonstrate the ability of <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> to cluster samples based on genetic relatedness information and integrate clinical metadata yielding results consistent with findings from published epidemiological studies.</p>
        <fig position="float" id="btab317-F5">
          <label>Fig. 5.</label>
          <caption>
            <p><italic toggle="yes">omeClust reveals communities in fetal growth study.</italic> (<bold>a</bold>) Genome-wide autosomal SNP data were measured for 301 samples from pregnant women in the NICHD Fetal Growth Studies (<xref rid="btab317-B16" ref-type="bibr">Grewal <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>). The snpgdsGRM function implemented in SNPRelate (<xref rid="btab317-B40" ref-type="bibr">Zheng <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>) was used to calculate the genetic relationship matrix using the correlation method for SNP genotype data between the samples. <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> detected four communities and, Maternal Race is the most influential metadata (NMI=0.51) indicating differences in size of babies at birth for black mothers as compared to other races. (<bold>b</bold>) Maternal socio-economic status (education) was the second most influential metadata (NMI=0.16) indicating differences in the socio-economic status for mothers in the black community influencing the size of babies at birth as compared to other races. (<bold>c</bold>) Maternal cardiometabolic factors (gestational weight gain) was the third most influential metadata indicating differences in cardiometabolic activities of black mothers relating to disproportionate size of babies at birth as compared to other races (NMI=0.12)</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="btab317f5" position="float"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>4 Discussion</title>
    <p><italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> represents a newly developed method to detect clusters and communities in heterogeneous biological datasets. Its validation and applications show that <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> is well suited for finding biologically meaningful subsets of samples or features in a diverse range of omics studies. Key to our approach is the use of the overall structure of the feature-wise relationships in a dataset that allows capturing biologically relevant communities and clusters in different resolutions of similarity. We optimized and validated <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> using realistic synthetic datasets of known community structure, where our approach outperformed existing approaches across a range of scenarios. Notably, <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> remains one of the best-performing methods in the scRNASeq-specific evaluation despite not being optimized for the specific application domain.<italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> can also be used for specific downstream tasks, such as discretizing omics data, dimension reduction, microbial beta-diversity analysis and subclade finding in microbial strains using nucleotide-based distances, among others. Further, our approach can be paired with existing network analysis and community detection methods. For example, <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> can find an optimal threshold for sparse edge discovery that can be embedded in a network analysis approach, such as <italic toggle="yes">Infomap</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Louvain</italic> to improve their performance. Further, <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> outputs an enrichment score for each desired metadata that can be used to select the most influential features in any clustering analysis. This arguably leads to more interpretable communities that are potentially explainable by a few metadata, which can also be used as covariates in streamlined downstream discovery (e.g. differential expression and abundance analysis).</p>
    <p>Clearly, the development of robust computational and statistical methods for accurate community detection is an ongoing effort. We, therefore, hope that future work could further fine-tune the task of feature selection and dimensionality reduction based on detected communities (e.g. feature engineering and feature extraction for deep learning). Another opportunity for future extension of our method is allowing multiple omics simultaneously especially allowing multiple time points and tissues to comprehensively detect communities in tandem. Combined, such extensions will allow researchers to use other downstream methods in parallel with <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic>, moving toward a robust, unified framework for omics-driven biomarker discovery, development and validation. We believe that the <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> framework and the improved detection of communities represent an important step in this direction that can ultimately aid in better interpretation and understanding of omics data while also encouraging further methodological advances in this area. An open-source (Python) implementation of <italic toggle="yes">omeClust</italic> is freely available at <ext-link xlink:href="http://github.com/omicsEye/omeClust" ext-link-type="uri">http://github.com/omicsEye/omeClust</ext-link> along with documentation, demo datasets, real-world applications and a user forum.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>Author contributions</title>
    <p>A.R. conceived the method; A.R. implemented, packaged and provided online documents and software; S.C., A.R. and H.M. prepared synthetic data and evaluated the performance; B.S., A.R., S.C., and F.T.-A. applied the method on real-world applications. A.R., H.M. and S.C. wrote the manuscript. All authors discussed the results and commented on the article.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>Funding</title>
    <p>This work was supported by the National Science Foundation [grant DEB-2028280 to A.R. and K.A.C]. The NICHD Fetal Growth Studies was funded by the Intramural Research Program of the <italic toggle="yes">Eunice Kennedy Shriver</italic> National Institute of Child Health and Human Development, National Institutes of Health including American Recovery and Reinvestment Act funding via contract numbers HHSN275200800013C, HHSN275200800002I, HHSN27500006, HHSN275200800003IC, HHSN275200800014C, HHSN275200800012C, HHSN275200800028C, HHSN275201000009C and HHSN27500008.</p>
    <p><italic toggle="yes">Conflict of Interest</italic>: H.M. is employed by Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., Kenilworth, NJ, USA. The remaining authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
      <label>btab317_Supplementary_Data</label>
      <media xlink:href="btab317_supplementary_data.docx">
        <caption>
          <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
        </caption>
      </media>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ref-list id="ref1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="btab317-B1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>N.S.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>An introduction to kernel and nearest-neighbor nonparametric regression</article-title>. <source>Am. Stat</source>., <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>185</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <part-title>Permutational multivariate analysis of variance (PERMANOVA)</part-title>. <source>Wiley StatsRef: Statistics Reference Online</source>. pp. <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bergé</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) Hdclassif: high dimensional supervised classification and clustering. R Package Version, 1, 2.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Blondel</surname><given-names>V.D.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Fast unfolding of communities in large networks</article-title>. <source>J. Stat. Mech. Theory Exp</source>., <volume>2008</volume>, <fpage>P10008</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bohlin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <part-title>Community detection and visualization of networks with the map equation framework</part-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (eds) <source>Measuring Scholarly Impact: Methods and Practice</source>. 
<publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name>, 
<publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc>, pp. <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bouveyron</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>High-dimensional data clustering</article-title>. <source>Comput. Stat. Data Anal</source>., <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>502</fpage>–<lpage>519</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Buck Louis</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Racial/ethnic standards for fetal growth: the NICHD fetal growth studies</article-title>. <source>Am. J. Obstet. Gynecol</source>., <volume>213</volume>, <fpage>449.e1</fpage>–<lpage>449.e41</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B8">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Csardi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The igraph software package for complex network research</article-title>. <source>InterJ. Complex Syst</source>., <volume>1695</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B9">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Delahaye</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Genetic variants influence on the placenta regulatory landscape</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>., <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>e1007785</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30452450</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B10">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ertöz</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) Finding clusters of different sizes, shapes, and densities in noisy, high dimensional data. In: <source>Proceedings of the 2003 SIAM International Conference on Data Mining</source>. 
<publisher-name>Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics</publisher-name>, 
<publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B11">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Estévez</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Normalized mutual information feature selection</article-title>. <source>IEEE Trans. Neural Netw</source>., <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>201</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19150792</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B12">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>L.C.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Transcriptomic analysis reveals inflammatory and metabolic pathways that are regulated by renal perfusion pressure in the outer medulla of Dahl-S rats</article-title>. <source>Physiol. Genomics</source>, <volume>50</volume>, <fpage>440</fpage>–<lpage>447</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29602296</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B13">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Fraley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) mclust: normal mixture modeling for model-based clustering, classification, and density estimation. R Package Version, 4.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B14">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Franzosa</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Species-level functional profiling of metagenomes and metatranscriptomes</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>962</fpage>–<lpage>968</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30377376</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B15">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ghandi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Next-generation characterization of the Cancer Cell Line Encyclopedia</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>569</volume>, <fpage>503</fpage>–<lpage>508</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31068700</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B16">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Grewal</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Cohort profile: NICHD fetal growth studies-singletons and twins</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Epidemiol</source>., <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>25</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29025016</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B17">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Großwendt</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Röglin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Improved analysis of complete-linkage clustering</article-title>. <source>Algorithmica</source>, <volume>78</volume>, <fpage>1131</fpage>–<lpage>1150</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B18">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>John</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>M3C: monte Carlo reference-based consensus clustering</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep</source>., <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31913322</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B19">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Juliá</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Sincell: an R/Bioconductor package for statistical assessment of cell-state hierarchies from single-cell RNA-seq</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>3380</fpage>–<lpage>3382</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26099264</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B20">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>) <article-title>A simple method for estimating evolutionary rates of base substitutions through comparative studies of nucleotide sequences</article-title>. <source>J. Mol. Evol</source>., <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>120</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7463489</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B21">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kvålseth</surname><given-names>T.O.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>On normalized mutual information: measure derivations and properties</article-title>. <source>Entropy</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>631</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B22">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Langfelder</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Defining clusters from a hierarchical cluster tree: the Dynamic Tree Cut package for R</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>719</fpage>–<lpage>720</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18024473</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B23">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) VDBSCAN: varied density based spatial clustering of applications with noise. In: <source>2007 International Conference on Service Systems and Service Management</source>. Chengdu, China, pp. <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B24">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lloyd-Price</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Strains, functions and dynamics in the expanded Human Microbiome Project</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>551</volume>, <fpage>256</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B25">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lloyd-Price</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Multi-omics of the gut microbial ecosystem in inflammatory bowel diseases</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>569</volume>, <fpage>655</fpage>–<lpage>662</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31142855</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B26">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Maugis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Variable selection for clustering with Gaussian mixture models</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source>, <volume>65</volume>, <fpage>701</fpage>–<lpage>709</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19210744</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B27">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>McCall</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The Gene Expression Barcode: leveraging public data repositories to begin cataloging the human and murine transcriptomes</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>D1011</fpage>–<lpage>D1015</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21177656</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B28">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>McCall</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>The Gene Expression Barcode 3.0: improved data processing and mining tools</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>D938</fpage>–<lpage>D943</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24271388</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B29">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Stomach-selective gene transfer following the administration of naked plasmid DNA onto the gastric serosal surface in mice</article-title>. <source>Biol. Pharm. Bull</source>., <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>2082</fpage>–<lpage>2086</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17015955</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B30">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ogbuabor</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ugwoke</surname><given-names>F.N.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Clustering algorithm for a healthcare dataset using silhouette score value</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Comput. Sci. Inf. Technol</source>., <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B31">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>SSCC: a novel computational framework for rapid and accurate clustering large-scale single cell RNA-seq data</article-title>. <source>Genomics Proteomics Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31202000</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B32">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Satija</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Spatial reconstruction of single-cell gene expression data</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biotechnol</source>., <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>495</fpage>–<lpage>502</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25867923</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B33">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Schulze</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>From model cell line to in vivo gene expression: disease-related intestinal gene expression in IBD</article-title>. <source>Genes Immun</source>., <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>240</fpage>–<lpage>248</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18340362</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B34">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sibson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>SLINK: an optimally efficient algorithm for the single-link cluster method</article-title>. <source>Comput. J</source>., <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B35">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tekola-Ayele</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>High burden of birthweight-lowering genetic variants in Africans and Asians</article-title>. <source>BMC Med</source>., <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>70</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29792231</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B36">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tekola-Ayele</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Sex differences in the associations of placental epigenetic aging with fetal growth</article-title>. <source>Aging</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>5412</fpage>–<lpage>5432</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31395791</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B37">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Truong</surname><given-names>D.T.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Microbial strain-level population structure and genetic diversity from metagenomes</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>., <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>626</fpage>–<lpage>638</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28167665</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B38">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Uhlén</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Proteomics. Tissue-based map of the human proteome</article-title>. <source>Science</source>, <volume>347</volume>, <fpage>1260419</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25613900</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B39">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>You</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>You</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) Package ‘mclustcomp’.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B40">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A high-performance computing toolset for relatedness and principal component analysis of SNP data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>3326</fpage>–<lpage>3328</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23060615</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B41">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zilliox</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Irizarry</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A gene expression bar code for microarray data</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>911</fpage>–<lpage>913</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17906632</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab317-B42">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Žurauskienė</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yau</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>pcaReduce: hierarchical clustering of single cell transcriptional profiles</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>140</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27005807</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
