<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?properties open_access?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Database (Oxford)</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Database (Oxford)</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">databa</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Database: The Journal of Biological Databases and Curation</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1758-0463</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8607299</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34791104</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/database/baab073</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">baab073</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Database Tool</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI00960</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>Prototheca-ID: a web-based application for molecular identification of
Prototheca species</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5593-9432</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Dziurzyński</surname>
          <given-names>Mikołaj</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution content-type="department">Department of Environmental Microbiology and
Biotechnology, Institute of Microbiology, Faculty of Biology, University of
Warsaw</institution>, I. Miecznikowa 1, Warsaw 02-096, <country country="PL">Poland</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5621-7124</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Decewicz</surname>
          <given-names>Przemyslaw</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution content-type="department">Department of Environmental Microbiology and
Biotechnology, Institute of Microbiology, Faculty of Biology, University of
Warsaw</institution>, I. Miecznikowa 1, Warsaw 02-096, <country country="PL">Poland</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6927-514X</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Iskra</surname>
          <given-names>Mateusz</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution content-type="department">Department of Medical Microbiology, Institute of
Microbiology, Faculty of Biology, University of Warsaw</institution>, I. Miecznikowa
1, Warsaw 02-096, <country country="PL">Poland</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7560-2100</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Bakuła</surname>
          <given-names>Zofia</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution content-type="department">Department of Medical Microbiology, Institute of
Microbiology, Faculty of Biology, University of Warsaw</institution>, I. Miecznikowa
1, Warsaw 02-096, <country country="PL">Poland</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9553-5742</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Jagielski</surname>
          <given-names>Tomasz</given-names>
        </name>
        <!--t.jagielski@biol.uw.edu.pl-->
        <xref rid="COR0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        <aff><institution content-type="department">Department of Medical Microbiology, Institute of
Microbiology, Faculty of Biology, University of Warsaw</institution>, I. Miecznikowa
1, Warsaw 02-096, <country country="PL">Poland</country></aff>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="COR0001">*Corresponding author: Tel: +48 22 55 41427; Fax: +48 22 55 41010;
Email: <email xlink:href="t.jagielski@biol.uw.edu.pl">t.jagielski@biol.uw.edu.pl</email></corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2021-11-13">
      <day>13</day>
      <month>11</month>
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>13</day>
      <month>11</month>
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>2021</volume>
    <elocation-id>baab073</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>02</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>04</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>09</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="editorial-decision">
        <day>21</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="corrected-typeset">
        <day>13</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2021. Published by Oxford University
Press.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted
reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is
properly cited.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xlink:href="baab073.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <p>The genus <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> houses unicellular, achlorophyllous, yeast-like
algae, widely distributed in the environment. Protothecae are the only known plants that
have repeatedly been reported to infect vertebrates, including humans. Although rare,
protothecosis can be clinically demanding, with an unpredictable and treatment-resistant
behavior. Accurate identification of <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> species relies upon DNA
sequence-based typing of the mitochondrially encoded <italic toggle="yes">CYTB</italic> gene. However,
no bioinformatic tool for the processing and analyzing of protothecal sequence data
exists. Moreover, currently available sequence databases suffer from a limited number of
records and lack of or flawed sequence annotations, making <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic>
identification challenging and often inconclusive. This report introduces the
Prototheca-ID, a user-friendly, web-based application providing fast and reliable
speciation of <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> isolates. In addition, the application offers
the users the possibility of depositing their sequences and associated metadata in a fully
open Prototheca-ID database, developed to enhance research integrity and quality in the
field of Protothecae and protothecosis.</p>
      <p><bold>Database URL</bold>: The Prototheca-ID application is available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://prototheca-id.org" ext-link-type="uri">https://prototheca-id.org</ext-link></p>
    </abstract>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Uniwersytet Warszawski</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100006445</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>BOB-661-54/20</award-id>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="4"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <p>
    <bold>Key Points</bold>
  </p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>Prototheca-ID is a first, open-source, online toolbox for the molecular identification of
<italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> species.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Prototheca-ID collects sequences of <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> cytochrome b
(<italic toggle="yes">CYTB</italic>) and D1/D2 region of the large subunit of the rRNA genes—key
markers for <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> spp. identification.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Prototheca-ID contains 172 validated, high-quality sequences of 87
<italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> strains, representing all currently known species, including
their type strains.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Prototheca-ID users can analyze their sequences through the ‘Analyze’ subpage, which
provides the identification match, based on the highest alignment score, and generates a
dendrogram to illustrate the phylogenetic relationships of the subject to members of the
database.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <sec id="s1">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <p><italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> are unicellular, colorless, nonphotosynthetic microalgae,
ubiquitously distributed in nature. Although they normally live a saprophytic lifestyle,
occurring most abundantly in humid and organic-rich environments, they may, under certain
conditions, act as opportunistic pathogens, causing a variety of pathologies in both animals
and humans, collectively referred to as protothecosis (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> are the
only known plants that have repeatedly been reported to infect vertebrates, including men.
In animals, the disease most commonly affects dairy cattle, resulting in chronic,
drug-resistant mastitis. Bovine mammary protothecosis has recently become an emerging health
and economic problem to the veterinary sector worldwide (<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3–6</xref>). Next, to streptococci and staphylococci,
<italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> algae are the key mastitis pathogens. The prevalence of the
protothecal disease ranges from 5% to nearly 17% among dairy herds across the world (<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Human protothecosis is a rare condition, with a total
of 211 cases reported globally by 2017 (<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>).
Notwithstanding, the incidence of the disease has been on the rise over the past two decades
due to the growing population of elderly and otherwise immunocompromised individuals but
also due to improved clinical awareness and recent technological advancements in the
diagnostic approaches (<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). According to a new report updating the global caseload of human
protothecosis, there have been a total of 335 cases by 2020 (Jagielski T.
<italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, data unpublished).</p>
    <p>The <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> taxonomy has long been controversial and subject to several
revisions. The advent of molecular markers has greatly facilitated elucidating the
phylogenetic relationships of the <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> algae, leading to considerable
improvements in their identification.</p>
    <p>Until recently, the only target for the molecular taxonomic approaches has been the
ribosomal RNA gene cluster. Numerous studies have exploited sequence polymorphisms within
the small- and large-subunit (SSU, LSU) rRNA genes and the internal transcribed spacer (ITS)
region for investigating phylogenetic relatedness among <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> species
and allied taxa and for developing new typing schemes to achieve fast and accurate
identification of the algae (<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>).</p>
    <p>However, the rDNA markers do not provide sufficient discriminatory power to effectively
separate all <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> species currently recognized. What further impedes
the use of rDNA markers is a high level of intraspecific and intrastrain sequence variation
(<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9–11</xref>).</p>
    <p>Recently, we have proposed the mitochondrially encoded <italic toggle="yes">CYTB</italic> gene as a new
and powerful marker for diagnostics and phylogenetic studies of the
<italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> algae (<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). The
<italic toggle="yes">CYTB</italic> gene was shown superior to rDNA markers in terms of discriminatory
capacity and technical feasibility (i.e. PCR amplification, sequencing and sequence
analysis). Based on the <italic toggle="yes">CYTB</italic> gene marker, a new taxonomic classification
system of the <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> algae has been established (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Furthermore, a PCR-RFLP (polymerase chain reaction-restriction
fragments length polymorphism) assay targeting sequence polymorphisms within the
<italic toggle="yes">CYTB</italic> gene has been developed as a rapid and reliable means of
<italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> identification at the species level (<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Given, however, that some
<italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic><italic toggle="yes">ciferrii</italic> strains may produce PCR-RFLP patterns
characteristic for <italic toggle="yes">P. bovis</italic>, to distinguish between the two species, direct
sequencing of the <italic toggle="yes">CYTB</italic> gene is required (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Consequently, sequencing of the <italic toggle="yes">CYTB</italic> gene provides the
highest accuracy of <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> species delimitation. In fact, it is the
only approach, currently known, allowing for unambiguous identification of all 15
<italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> species described so far.</p>
    <p>In a clinical setting, the use of <italic toggle="yes">CYTB</italic> gene-based typing, and
<italic toggle="yes">CYTB</italic> sequencing in particular, is advocated as a new standard in
diagnostics of protothecal infections in both human and animal hosts.</p>
    <p>The success of any sequence-based taxonomic profiling depends critically on high-quality,
well-annotated reference sequence databases. However, the contamination of publicly
available sequence repositories with incorrectly annotated or otherwise poorly described
sequences is quite common, leading to either misidentification or no identification result
at all.</p>
    <p>Currently, the largest collection of <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic>-derived DNA sequences
provides the GenBank database. As of 1 May 2021, GenBank contained 8948
<italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic>-related sequences with seven assemblies for only five
<italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> species. One thousand five hundred thirty-nine (17%) out of
8948 sequences were for the rDNA loci, including the ITS region. Only 98 (1%) sequences
represented the <italic toggle="yes">CYTB</italic> gene, the bulk of which (87) was submitted by the
authors of this communication. Being not actively curated by taxonomic specialists, GenBank
often contains erroneous, outdated or misleading data, precluding the correct species
identification. Moreover, GenBank suffers from the lack of rigorous data collection and
structuring, potentially useful for comparative, analytical and interpretative purposes.
These pitfalls have been recognized for many GenBank deposited <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic>
sequences. Given the growing prevalence of Protothecae, and the ongoing discovery of new
species, databases such as GenBank are expected to be inflated by incorrectly or
insufficiently annotated entries.</p>
    <p>There is thus a need for an integrative and expert-curated database rendering a robust and
reliable identification of <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> species.</p>
    <p>To address this need, the Prototheca-ID project has been launched, introducing the
Prototheca-ID web application, a freely accessible, easy-to-use toolbox designed for
sequence-based, species-level identification of <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> isolates.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s2">
    <title>Prototheca-ID application</title>
    <p>The Prototheca-ID web-based application (<ext-link xlink:href="https://prototheca-id.org" ext-link-type="uri">https://prototheca-id.org</ext-link>) has a two-component construction. It comprises of a
manually curated database of <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic>-derived <italic toggle="yes">CYTB</italic> and
LSU marker sequences and a species-level taxonomy analysis tool. The database contains a set
of regularly updated and manually curated sequences of the two <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic>
markers, allowing for a fast and reliable identification of <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic>
isolates. Every sequence in the database is provided with metadata specifying the origin of
sequence or the strain details, including its source of isolation, year of deposition, names
of depositor(s) and appropriate reference if available. The users can not only search
through the database or download its content, upon request, but are welcome to deposit their
sequence(s), along with selected information on the strains so that the database can expand
easily, increasing the accuracy of sequence matching and thus successful identification. A
<italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> sequence of <italic toggle="yes">CYTB</italic> or LSU coding regions will
be considered for Prototheca-ID database if: (i) amplified using a high-fidelity polymerase
and primers previously reported by Jagielski <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>), (ii) deposited in the Genbank database, (iii) the following sequence
metadata are available: species name, strain number and Genbank accession number. The
optional, yet recommended, metadata include: source type, country and year of isolation.
This also enables investigators a more powerful exploration and analysis of the
datasets.</p>
    <p>The second module of the Prototheca-ID application consists of a sequence analysis and
classification tool (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). A user can perform the
identification of any of his <italic toggle="yes">CYTB</italic> or LSU nucleotide sequences in a fast and
simple manner. The identification process is based on nucleotide sequence search with BLASTn
against a selected group of reference genes, whereas the construction of the phylogenetic
trees is based on the multiple sequence alignment (<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). The initial search results are limited only to hits with at least 50% sequence
identity and 50% query coverage. These results are subsequently used to perform multiple
sequence alignment with mafft in auto mode (<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). The alignment is then curated with TrimAl by
applying <italic toggle="yes">-gapthreshold 0.3</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">-simthreshold 0.001</italic> flags
and passed to IQ-TREE (<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). The maximum likelihood phylogenetic tree is constructed based on the
model selected with jModelTest (<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Branch support
is calculated based on 1000 replicates of both ultrafast bootstrap and SH-like approximate
likelihood ratio. At the end, the resulting phylogenetic tree is presented to the user
through the phylotree.js library (<ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/veg/phylotree.js" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/veg/phylotree.js</ext-link>). The user can freely download the tree in
the Newick format and perform further adjustments.</p>
    <fig position="float" id="F1" fig-type="figure">
      <label>Figure 1.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Flowchart depicting all steps of the Prototheca-ID sequence analysis pipeline.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="baab073f1" position="float"/>
      <attrib>MSA—multiple sequence alignment.</attrib>
    </fig>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s3">
    <title>Conclusions</title>
    <p>This paper reports on the development and implementation of a user-friendly, web-based
analytical tool for fast and reliable identification of <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic>
species.</p>
    <p>The core idea of the project was not only to deliver a simple and robust platform for
<italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> identification but also to establish a comprehensive,
dedicated and fully open database of sequences of <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> isolates and
isolate-related information, well-annotated, carefully verified and rigorously structured in
a standardized and easily searchable manner.</p>
    <p>Prototheca-ID was conceived as a regularly updated and continuously expanding database to
include other taxonomic markers or markers associated with clinically and/or
epidemiologically relevant phenotypes, such as drug resistance, virulence and
transmissibility. The Prototheca-ID aims at integrating sequence data with provenance and
phenotypic information on Protothecae, allowing scientists to study the biology of these
organisms in the context of their genetic background. An important purpose of such studies
is to develop algorithms assessing risk factors predictive for human and animal
protothecosis.</p>
    <p>Prototheca-ID is still a project in <italic toggle="yes">statu nascendi</italic> and will be further
developed and refined by the authors in the next few years in order to enhance its data
collection capacities and to improve and streamline its analytical performance and general
functionality. Our near-term priority would be to install within the Prototheca-ID
application, a module for accommodating and filtering the whole-genome sequence datasets,
representing all <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> species. The <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic>
whole-genome sequencing project, initiated by our group in 2014, has already released a
complete sequence of the <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca wickerhamii</italic> genome (<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>).</p>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <sec id="s4">
    <title>Funding</title>
    <p>This work was supported in part by the internal grant of the University of Warsaw
(BOB-661-54/20).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s5">
    <title>Conflict of interest</title>
    <p>None declared.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s6">
    <title>Description of the authors</title>
    <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
        <p>Mikołaj Dziurzyński is a PhD student at the Department of Environmental Microbiology
and Biotechnology at the University of Warsaw. He specializes in bioinformatics analysis
of microbial genomes and metagenomes.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>Przemysław Decewicz is a postdoctoral researcher at the Institute of Microbiology at
the University of Warsaw. His research interests include bioinformatics in phage and
bacteria genomics.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>Mateusz Iskra is a PhD student, under the supervision of Dr Tomasz Jagielski, at the
Department of Medical Microbiology at the University of Warsaw.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>Zofia Bakuła is a postdoctoral researcher at the Department of Medical Microbiology,
University of Warsaw. In her research, she focuses on pathogens DNA in clinical
management and epidemiology of infectious diseases.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>Tomasz Jagielski is the head of Department of Medical Microbiology at the University of
Warsaw. He is one of the world’s top leaders in the field of <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic>
research.</p>
      </list-item>
    </list>
  </sec>
  <ref-list id="ref1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="R1">
      <label>1.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jagielski</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name> and
<string-name><surname>Lagneau</surname><given-names>P.-E.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
(<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Protothecosis. A pseudofungal
infection</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J. Mycol. Med.</italic></source>,
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>261</fpage>–<lpage>270</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R2">
      <label>2.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Masuda</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Jagielski</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Danesi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Protothecosis in dogs and cats -
new research directions</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Mycopathologia</italic></source>, <volume>186</volume>,
<fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>152</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33206310</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R3">
      <label>3.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jagielski</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Krukowski</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Bochniarz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Prevalence of
<italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> spp. on dairy farms in Poland - a cross-country
study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Microb. Biotechnol.</italic></source>,
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>556</fpage>–<lpage>566</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30891936</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R4">
      <label>4.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ricchi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De
Cicco</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Buzzini</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>First outbreak of bovine mastitis
caused by <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca blaschkeae</italic></article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet.
Microbiol.</italic></source>, <volume>162</volume>,
<fpage>997</fpage>–<lpage>999</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23201242</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R5">
      <label>5.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Kraft</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Bovine mastitis associated with
P<italic toggle="yes">rototheca blaschkeae</italic></article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J. Clin.
Microbiol.</italic></source>, <volume>46</volume>,
<fpage>1941</fpage>–<lpage>1945</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18434557</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R6">
      <label>6.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ricchi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Goretti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Branda</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Molecular characterization of
<italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> strains isolated from Italian dairy herds</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Dairy Sci.</italic></source>, <volume>93</volume>,
<fpage>4625</fpage>–<lpage>4631</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20854996</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R7">
      <label>7.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Todd</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Medical phycology
2017</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Med. Mycol.</italic></source>,
<volume>56</volume>, <fpage>S188</fpage>–<lpage>S204</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29767780</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R8">
      <label>8.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lass-Flörl</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name> and
<string-name><surname>Mayr</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
(<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Human protothecosis</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Clin. Microbiol. Rev.</italic></source>, <volume>20</volume>,
<fpage>230</fpage>–<lpage>242</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17428884</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R9">
      <label>9.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jagielski</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Gawor</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Bakuła</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>CYTB as a new genetic marker for
differentiation of <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> species</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Clin. Microbiol.</italic></source>, <volume>56</volume>,
e00584–18.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R10">
      <label>10.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hirose</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Inoue-Sakamoto</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Ribosomal internal transcribed
spacer of <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca wickerhamii</italic> has characteristic structure useful
for identification and genotyping</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS
One</italic></source>, <volume>8</volume>,
<page-range>e81223</page-range>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R11">
      <label>11.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hirose</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Molecular characterization of
<italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> strains isolated in China revealed the first cases of
protothecosis associated with <italic toggle="yes">Prototheca zopfii</italic> genotype
1</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Med. Mycol.</italic></source>, <volume>56</volume>,
<fpage>279</fpage>–<lpage>287</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28525645</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R12">
      <label>12.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jagielski</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Bakuła</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Gawor</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>The genus
<italic toggle="yes">Prototheca</italic> (Trebouxiophyceae, Chlorophyta) revisited: implications
from molecular taxonomic studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Algal
Res.</italic></source>, <volume>43</volume>,
<page-range>101639</page-range>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R13">
      <label>13.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Camacho</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Coulouris</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Avagyan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>BLAST+: architecture and
applications</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Bioinform.</italic></source>,
<volume>10</volume>, <page-range>421</page-range>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R14">
      <label>14.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Misawa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Kuma</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>MAFFT: a novel method for rapid
multiple sequence alignment based on fast Fourier transform</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res.</italic></source>, <volume>30</volume>,
<fpage>3059</fpage>–<lpage>3066</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12136088</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R15">
      <label>15.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name> and
<string-name><surname>Standley</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
(<year>2013</year>) <article-title>MAFFT multiple sequence alignment software version 7:
improvements in performance and usability</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol. Biol.
Evol.</italic></source>, <volume>30</volume>,
<fpage>772</fpage>–<lpage>780</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23329690</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R16">
      <label>16.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Capella-Gutiérrez</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Silla-Martínez</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></string-name>
and
<string-name><surname>Gabaldón</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
(<year>2009</year>) <article-title>trimAl: a tool for automated alignment trimming in
large-scale phylogenetic analyses</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic></source>, <volume>25</volume>,
<fpage>1972</fpage>–<lpage>1973</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505945</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R17">
      <label>17.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>L.-T.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>von
Haeseler</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>IQ-TREE: A fast and effective
stochastic algorithm for estimating maximum-likelihood phylogenies</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Mol. Biol. Evol.</italic></source>, <volume>32</volume>,
<fpage>268</fpage>–<lpage>274</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25371430</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R18">
      <label>18.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kalyaanamoorthy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Minh</surname><given-names>B.Q.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>T.K.F.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>ModelFinder: fast model selection
for accurate phylogenetic estimates</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat.
Methods</italic></source>, <volume>14</volume>,
<fpage>587</fpage>–<lpage>589</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28481363</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R19">
      <label>19.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bakuła</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Siedlecki</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Gromadka</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>A first insight into the genome of
<italic toggle="yes">Prototheca wickerhamii</italic>, a major causative agent of human
protothecosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Genomics</italic></source>,
<volume>22</volume>, <page-range>168</page-range>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
