<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?properties open_access?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1367-4803</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1367-4811</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8665759</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34260700</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btab514</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">btab514</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Original Papers</subject>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading">
          <subject>Genetics and Population Analysis</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01060</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>Openness weighted association studies: leveraging personal genome information to prioritize non-coding variants</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Song</surname>
          <given-names>Shuang</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Center for Statistical Science, Department of Industrial Engineering, Tsinghua University</institution>, 100084 Beijing, <country country="CN">China</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Shan</surname>
          <given-names>Nayang</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Center for Statistical Science, Department of Industrial Engineering, Tsinghua University</institution>, 100084 Beijing, <country country="CN">China</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Wang</surname>
          <given-names>Geng</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>University of Queensland Diamantina Institute, University of Queensland</institution>, 4102 Brisbane, <country country="AU">Australia</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Yan</surname>
          <given-names>Xiting</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Department of Internal Medicine, Section of Pulmonary, Critical Care, and Sleep Medicine, Yale School of Medicine</institution>, New Haven, CT 06519, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>Department of Biostatistics, Yale School of Public Health</institution>, New Haven, CT 06510, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Liu</surname>
          <given-names>Jun S</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Department of Statistics, Harvard University</institution>, Cambridge, MA 02138, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4283-8501</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Hou</surname>
          <given-names>Lin</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="btab514-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
        <aff><institution>Center for Statistical Science, Department of Industrial Engineering, Tsinghua University</institution>, 100084 Beijing, <country country="CN">China</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>MOE Key Laboratory of Bioinformatics, School of Life Sciences, Tsinghua University</institution>, 100084 Beijing, <country country="CN">China</country></aff>
        <!--houl@tsinghua.edu.cn-->
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name>
          <surname>Schwartz</surname>
          <given-names>Russell</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Associate Editor</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="btab514-cor1">To whom correspondence should be addressed. <email>houl@tsinghua.edu.cn</email></corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <day>15</day>
      <month>12</month>
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2021-07-14">
      <day>14</day>
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>14</day>
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>37</volume>
    <issue>24</issue>
    <fpage>4737</fpage>
    <lpage>4743</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>22</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="editorial-decision">
        <day>04</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>07</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="corrected-typeset">
        <day>01</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2021. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xlink:href="btab514.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <sec id="s1">
        <title>Motivation</title>
        <p>Identification and interpretation of non-coding variations that affect disease risk remain a paramount challenge in genome-wide association studies (GWAS) of complex diseases. Experimental efforts have provided comprehensive annotations of functional elements in the human genome. On the other hand, advances in computational biology, especially machine learning approaches, have facilitated accurate predictions of cell-type-specific functional annotations. Integrating functional annotations with GWAS signals has advanced the understanding of disease mechanisms. In previous studies, functional annotations were treated as static of a genomic region, ignoring potential functional differences imposed by different genotypes across individuals.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2">
        <title>Results</title>
        <p>We develop a computational approach, Openness Weighted Association Studies (OWAS), to leverage and aggregate predictions of chromosome accessibility in personal genomes for prioritizing GWAS signals. The approach relies on an analytical expression we derived for identifying disease associated genomic segments whose effects in the etiology of complex diseases are evaluated. In extensive simulations and real data analysis, OWAS identifies genes/segments that explain more heritability than existing methods, and has a better replication rate in independent cohorts than GWAS. Moreover, the identified genes/segments show tissue-specific patterns and are enriched in disease relevant pathways. We use rheumatic arthritis and asthma as examples to demonstrate how OWAS can be exploited to provide novel insights on complex diseases.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3">
        <title>Availability and implementation</title>
        <p>The R package OWAS that implements our method is available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/shuangsong0110/OWAS" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/shuangsong0110/OWAS</ext-link>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s5">
        <title>Supplementary information</title>
        <p><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary data</xref> are available at <italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic> online.</p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100001809</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>12071243</award-id>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Shanghai Municipal Science and Technology Major Project</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>2017SHZDZX01</award-id>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>National Science Foundation</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100000001</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>DMS-1903139</award-id>
        <award-id>DMS-2015411</award-id>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="7"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec>
    <title>1 Introduction</title>
    <p>In the past decade, genome-wide association studies (GWAS) have identified tens of thousands of genetic associations (<xref rid="btab514-B25" ref-type="bibr">Jostins and Barrett, 2011</xref>), which have led to new insights into etiologies of many diseases. Despite the success, how to interpret the functional relevance of detected loci remains a paramount challenge. The difficulties partly lie in that the causal genes mediating variant effects on the trait are rarely ascertainable from GWAS data alone (<xref rid="btab514-B59" ref-type="bibr">Wainberg <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>) without external information. Furthermore, the majority of GWAS loci (<inline-formula id="IE1"><mml:math id="IM1" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∼</mml:mo><mml:mn>89</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) lie within non-coding regions (<xref rid="btab514-B16" ref-type="bibr">Gusev <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). To understand biological mechanisms underlying these significant associations, it is necessary to incorporate function annotations in non-coding regions in the genome (<xref rid="btab514-B22" ref-type="bibr">Hou and Zhao, 2013</xref>).</p>
    <p>Most existing literature assumes that annotated SNPs are more likely to be causal and are enriched for heritability. For example, <xref rid="btab514-B7" ref-type="bibr">Chung <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2014)</xref> proposed a statistical approach to prioritize GWAS results by integrating pleiotropy and annotation. <xref rid="btab514-B38" ref-type="bibr">Lu <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2016)</xref> established GenoSkyline to integrate tissue-specific functional annotations to improve signal prioritization. DIVAN (<xref rid="btab514-B5" ref-type="bibr">Chen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>) identifies non-coding disease risk variants by integrating multiple genomic features. <xref rid="btab514-B61" ref-type="bibr">Watanabe <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2017)</xref> developed a convenient platform FUMA to facilitate functional annotations of GWAS results, gene prioritization and interactive visualization. In addition, transcriptome-wide association studies (TWAS) leverage genetically regulated gene expression information of each individual in the GWAS cohort to aggregate SNP-level effects into gene-level effects, and to further discover gene-trait associations (<xref rid="btab514-B17" ref-type="bibr">Gusev <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). These prioritization approaches provide novel insights into biological mechanism, enabling researchers to better understand gene regulation, as well as the pathogenesis of human diseases.</p>
    <p>In this article, we are particularly interested in understanding the role of chromatin accessibility in human complex diseases. Chromatin accessibility is the degree to which nuclear macromolecules are able to physically contact chromatinized DNA (<xref rid="btab514-B27" ref-type="bibr">Klemm <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>). As an important epigenetic change, chromatin accessibility is a conserved eukaryotic characteristic of active regulatory elements, including promoters, enhancers, silencers, insulators, transcription factor (TF) binding sites and active histone modifications. The accessible regions, which are also known as open regions, often work together with TFs, RNA polymerases and other cellular machines to regulate gene expression. Interestingly, 57% of the non-coding GWAS hits lie in open chromatin (spanning 42% of the genome), implying that chromatin accessibility will help understand the genetic mechanism of complex diseases (<xref rid="btab514-B12" ref-type="bibr">Finucane <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="btab514-B39" ref-type="bibr">Maurano <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="btab514-B47" ref-type="bibr">Ritchie <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>).</p>
    <p>Although several high-throughput biotechnologies, such as DNase-seq, FAIRE-seq and ATAC-seq (<xref rid="btab514-B42" ref-type="bibr">Min <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>), have been developed to measure chromatin accessibility, experimental measurement in large cohort is costly and not common. Therefore, computational approaches that predict chromatin accessibility from DNA sequences have been proposed. Notably, the method deltaSVM was developed based on gkm-SVM classifier and quantifies cell-type-specific effects of variants on DNase I sensitivity in their native genomic contexts (<xref rid="btab514-B32" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). A deep learning-based method was proposed for predicting assay-specific epigenetic consequences (<xref rid="btab514-B19" ref-type="bibr">Hoffman <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>). DeepCage incorporates cell type specific transcriptome profile to predict regulatory elements (<xref rid="btab514-B36" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>). Accurate <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> predictions of chromatin accessibility provide new opportunities for us to understand roles of non-coding variants in disease mechanisms. Some recent work leverages chromatin accessibility information to interpret GWAS variants (<xref rid="btab514-B33" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020a</xref>; <xref rid="btab514-B52" ref-type="bibr">Soskic <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>). Other representative work includes STAAR, which incorporates functional annotations to empower rare variant association analysis (<xref rid="btab514-B34" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020b</xref>), and GARFIELD, which integrates functional annotation in association models and classifies disease-relevant genomic features to bring novel biological insights (<xref rid="btab514-B24" ref-type="bibr">Iotchkova <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>). In addition, one can also leverage predicted regulatory information to split GWAS SNPs into functional units, and identify phenotype associations of SNPs in each functional unit (<xref rid="btab514-B1" ref-type="bibr">Arloth <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). However, existing approaches mainly treat functional annotations as an inherent attribute of a genomic segment, while their variations in personal genomes are ignored. In other words, these approaches assume that the epigenetic status of a genomic segment is homogeneous among all subjects. In fact, epigenetic studies in reference panels have shown a substantial variation in chromatin accessibility across individuals. We hypothesize that incorporating chromatin accessibility prediction in personal genomes in GWAS will further improve our understanding of the roles of non-coding variants in disease etiology.</p>
    <p>Here, we develop a systematic framework, Openness Weighted Association Studies (OWAS), which leverages <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> predictions of chromatin accessibility in personal genomes to prioritize GWAS SNPs. Individual-level openness, i.e. quantitative measure of chromatin accessibility, is predicted for each genomic segment and the openness scores are used as weights in subsequent association analysis. OWAS can be considered as a post-GWAS prioritization approach that integrates external information to prioritize disease-related genes/segments. Through extensive simulations and real data analyses, we find that OWAS identifies genes/segments that are more interpretable and reliable, and explains more heritability than existing methods. Furthermore, OWAS can take GWAS summary statistics as inputs and therefore does not require individual-level genotype data. Its computational framework can be easily extended to incorporate other epigenetic features. Overall, our results show that integrating functional predictions in personal genomes with GWAS can provide more precise interpretations of roles of non-coding variants in disease mechanism and shed insight on genetic architectures of complex traits.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>2 Materials and methods</title>
    <sec>
      <title>2.1 Method overview</title>
      <p>OWAS is a segment-based association approach, in which openness of a genomic segment is predicted for each personal genome, and subsequently tested for the association with the phenotype of interest (<xref rid="btab514-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). Importantly, we distinguish functions of non-coding genomic elements across different individuals by the genotype of SNPs embedded. In order to accommodate traits/diseases for which only GWAS summary statistics are available, we provide an analytical formula to approximate the OWAS statistics. In particular, we take 100 KB (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Note S1.1</xref>) up and down-stream from the transcription start sites of genes as regulatory regions, which covers most of the regulatory variants (<xref rid="btab514-B43" ref-type="bibr">Nasser <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>). We then divide the regions into segments of 5 KB, and calculate an openness score for each segment of each individual in a GWAS cohort. The openness score is a weighted aggregation of genotypes of SNPs in the segment, while the weight of an SNP is predicted by machine learning approaches in the literature.</p>
      <fig position="float" id="btab514-F1">
        <label>Fig. 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Schematic diagram of OWAS. Cell-type-specific predictions of individual-level chromosome accessibility (green part) and GWAS data (blue part) are integrated via statistical modeling to derive the test statistics of OWAS (red part)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="btab514f1" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Let <italic toggle="yes">X</italic> denote the genotype matrix of <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> individuals (rows) and <italic toggle="yes">m</italic> SNPs (columns), and let <italic toggle="yes">X<sub>ij</sub></italic> be the genotype of the <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>-th SNP of the <italic toggle="yes">i</italic>-th individual. The segment-level openness score <inline-formula id="IE2"><mml:math id="IM2" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> predicted for segment <italic toggle="yes">s</italic> in individual <italic toggle="yes">i</italic> is
<disp-formula id="E1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Ω</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where <italic toggle="yes">w<sub>j</sub></italic> is the predicted openness effect for the <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>-th SNP, and Ω<sub><italic toggle="yes">s</italic></sub> indicates the set of SNPs in segment <italic toggle="yes">s</italic>. To study the phenotypic association of each openness score, we posit the following linear phenotype model:
<disp-formula id="E2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M2" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>α</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>γ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>ϵ</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where γ<sub><italic toggle="yes">s</italic></sub> is called the effect size for segment <italic toggle="yes">s</italic>, and the error <italic toggle="yes">ϵ</italic> follows the normal distribution. The OWAS <italic toggle="yes">Z</italic>-score is simply
<disp-formula id="E3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M3" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>se(</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
      <p>When individual-level genotype data <italic toggle="yes">X</italic> is provided, <italic toggle="yes">O<sub>s</sub></italic> can be directly calculated with <xref rid="E1" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (1)</xref>, and OWAS <italic toggle="yes">Z</italic>-scores can be derived by fitting the linear regression model in <xref rid="E2" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (2)</xref>. When only GWAS summary statistics are available, we can approximate the OWAS <italic toggle="yes">Z</italic>-score as:
<disp-formula id="E4"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M4" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>se</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mo>Ω</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula>where <italic toggle="yes">z<sub>j</sub></italic> is the <italic toggle="yes">z</italic>-score for the <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>-th SNP in GWAS summary statistics; <inline-formula id="IE3"><mml:math id="IM3" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>σ^</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the sample variance of SNP <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> and <inline-formula id="IE4"><mml:math id="IM4" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>σ^</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is sample variance of the openness scores in segment <italic toggle="yes">s</italic>. The derivation of <xref rid="E4" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (4)</xref> is provided in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Note</xref> S1.2.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>2.2 Prediction of regulatory effect in personal genomes</title>
      <p>We derive the predicted openness effect (<italic toggle="yes">w<sub>j</sub></italic>) of each SNP with deltaSVM (<xref rid="btab514-B32" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>), which is a sequence-based computational method that predicts allelic regulatory effects of SNPs with cell-type specificity. We trained the model on DNase I-hypersensitive sites (DHSs) of 12 common cell types from the UW ENCODE Project (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.beerlab.org/deltasvm/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.beerlab.org/deltasvm/</ext-link>). A list of the cell types is provided in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>2.3 Cell type selection</title>
      <p>OWAS synthesizes openness scores trained from distinct cell types. We provide a strategy to automatically select a relevant cell type by GARFIELD (<xref rid="btab514-B24" ref-type="bibr">Iotchkova <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>), which identifies the cell type of which open chromatin marks are most enriched for trait-specific GWAS signals. The selected cell type is then used for downstream analyses.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>2.4 Simulations</title>
      <p>We first simulated GWAS <italic toggle="yes">z</italic>-scores. Associated SNPs were divided into three disjoint groups, <italic toggle="yes">C</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">C</italic><sub>2</sub> and <italic toggle="yes">C</italic><sub>3</sub>, with high, medium and low heritability, respectively, according to their ranks of openness scores. For an associated SNP in <italic toggle="yes">C<sub>k</sub></italic>, its effect size was simulated from a mean-zero normal distribution with variance τ<sub><italic toggle="yes">k</italic></sub>. Let <italic toggle="yes">C</italic><sub>0</sub> denote the set of unassociated SNPs, with proportion fixed at 0.9. Then we have <inline-formula id="IE5"><mml:math id="IM5" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>τ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula id="IE6"><mml:math id="IM6" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the number of SNPs in group <italic toggle="yes">C<sub>k</sub></italic>. We further simulated SNP-level <italic toggle="yes">z</italic>-scores according to:
<disp-formula id="E5"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="M5" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">z</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">R</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>β</mml:mo><mml:mo>∼</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msqrt><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">R</mml:mi><mml:mo>β</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">R</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where <inline-formula id="IE7"><mml:math id="IM7" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo>β</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> is the vector of SNP-level effect sizes, and <bold><italic toggle="yes">R</italic></bold> is the linkage disqeuilibrium (LD) matrix, which is estimated from 1000 Genomes Project European samples on chromosome 22. The sample size <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> was fixed at 10 000. The number of SNPs is 141 123. We set <inline-formula id="IE8"><mml:math id="IM8" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to be 50%, 20% and 10% for <italic toggle="yes">k </italic>=<italic toggle="yes"> </italic>1, 2, 3, which contain 0.5%, 1.5% and 8% of the total number of SNPs, respectively.</p>
      <p>As a comparison, we used an unweighted model regarding all SNPs in each segment equally. We compared the performance of OWAS with the unweighted model, by ranking the segments with the derived <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values and estimating the heritability explained by specific proportions of prioritized segments. The simulations were repeated for 100 times.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>2.5 Pathway enrichment analysis</title>
      <p>We tested the enrichment of OWAS genes in KEGG pathways (<xref rid="btab514-B26" ref-type="bibr">Kanehisa <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>) using the R package ‘clusterProfiler’ (<xref rid="btab514-B64" ref-type="bibr">Yu <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). For multiple testing error control, we used the Benjamini–Hochberg procedure to control the false discovery rate (FDR) at level 0.05 (<xref rid="btab514-B3" ref-type="bibr">Benjamini and Hochberg, 1995</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>2.6 Compared methods</title>
      <p>FUSION (<xref rid="btab514-B17" ref-type="bibr">Gusev <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>) is a TWAS method that studies transcriptome-phenotype associations. For FUSION-open, we extracted genes that have overlaps with the DNase-seq peaks in the corresponding cell type, and used FUSION to prioritized those genes. The CADD scores (<xref rid="btab514-B46" ref-type="bibr">Rentzsch <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>) supports prioritization of non-coding variants by integrating a range of annotations. We annotated the variant CADD scores by FUMA (<xref rid="btab514-B61" ref-type="bibr">Watanabe <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>) and ranked the SNPs accordingly, which is denoted by FUMA-CADD.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>2.7 Materials</title>
      <p>A detailed description of the GWAS datasets, the chromatin accessibility data and TWAS results is provided in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Materials</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>3 Results</title>
    <sec>
      <title>3.1 OWAS segments explain more heritability</title>
      <p>For real data experiments, we applied OWAS to three complex traits including Crohn’s disease (CD), hypertension (HT) and RA. The cell types selected for each trait is provided in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S2</xref>. In order to understand the influence of cell types, we applied OWAS with 12 common cell types from UW ENCODE Project and compared the prioritization results of each cell type to the selected cell type. OWAS identified most disease-relevant genes (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Note S1.3</xref> and <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S3</xref>), possibly due to the shared regulatory mechanism between cell types. Meanwhile, OWAS retains its superiority in explained heritability compared to other methods, even when the cell type is not optimal for the trait (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S1</xref>).</p>
      <p>As a comparison, we also prioritized genes/SNPs using FUSION, FUSION-open and FUMA-CADD (Section 2.6). The UK Biobank (UKB) summary statistics were used as the discovery cohort, and all the methods were evaluated with the WTCCC datasets (<xref rid="btab514-B10" ref-type="bibr">Consortium <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), which are independent from the discovery cohorts. We excluded the HLA region (chr6:28,477,797-33,448,354, hg19) in the heritability analysis due to the unusual LD structure and genetic architecture. For the compared methods, we ranked the SNPs/segments/genes according to their significance levels, and estimated the heritability explained by prioritized SNPs using the GCTA software (<xref rid="btab514-B63" ref-type="bibr">Yang <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). To avoid comparisons at arbitrary cutoffs, we varied the significance thresholds for all the methods, and calculated the proportion of SNPs and the explained heritability at each threshold (<xref rid="btab514-F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). With the same proportion of SNPs, OWAS segments explain more heritability compared to other methods, and the patterns are consistent across the three different traits. We also notice that the FUSION genes within the open chromatin regions are more enriched for heritability than those outside, which highlights that the integration of chromatin accessible information improves the heritability enrichment.</p>
      <fig position="float" id="btab514-F2">
        <label>Fig. 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>OWAS segments are more enriched for heritability compared to the FUSION genes, FUSION genes in open regions and SNPs prioritized by CADD scores annotated by FUMA, on CD, HT and rheumatic arthritis (RA). OWAS segments and the FUSION genes were ranked by their <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values, respectively, and the proportion of SNPs (x-axis) and the explained heritability (y-axis) at varying cutoffs are displayed. The error bar corresponds to the standard error of the heritability estimated by GCTA software. The discovery cohorts are derived using UKB summary statistics and the heritability was estimated with the WTCCC individual-level genotype data</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="btab514f2" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The improvement in explained heritability is also validated in simulations. We simulated GWAS <italic toggle="yes">z</italic>-scores from a genetic model with heritability enriched in SNPs with high openness effects (Section 2.4). The heritability of genomic segments detected by OWAS is significantly greater than that of the unweighted method (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S2</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>3.2 OWAS prioritized SNPs have higher replication rate</title>
      <p>We evaluated the replication rate of SNPs prioritized by the OWAS analysis in independent cohorts. For RA and prostate cancer (PrCa), we took the largest meta-analysis available as the discovery cohort and the UKB studies as the replication cohort. For high cholesterol (HC), we took UKB studies as the discovery cohort due to their large sample sizes (<italic toggle="yes">n </italic>=<italic toggle="yes"> </italic>361 141), and used the study by <xref rid="btab514-B56" ref-type="bibr">Teslovich <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2010)</xref> for the total cholesterol (<italic toggle="yes">n </italic>=<italic toggle="yes"> </italic>100 184) as the replication cohort. For each trait, we used a two-stage process. We first binned the SNPs by their GWAS <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values in the discovery cohort. Then, in each bin, we compared the replication rate of prioritized SNPs (i.e. SNPs harbored by significant segments in OWAS) to that of the other SNPs. OWAS prioritized SNPs had a greater replication rate, and the trend was consistent across different traits and different <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value bins (<xref rid="btab514-F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). The results indicate that OWAS effectively identifies truly associated SNPs in SNPs with moderate <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values, and the effect is more prominent for less significant SNPs.</p>
      <fig position="float" id="btab514-F3">
        <label>Fig. 3.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Replication of OWAS results. OWAS was performed with GWAS summary statistics from both the discovery cohort (with larger sample sizes) and the replication cohort on rheumatoid arthritis (RA), HC and PrCa. In the discovery cohort, GWAS SNPs were divided into 5 bins according to their <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values [I: (0, 1e–06), II: [1e–06, 1e–05), III: [1e–05, 1e–04), IV: [1e–04, 1e–03), V: [1e–03, 1e–02)]. In the replication cohort, GWAS significant SNPs were identified with a relaxed threshold (<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>&lt;<italic toggle="yes"> </italic>5e–02). In each bin, the SNPs were broken down into prioritized and not prioritized groups by the OWAS results (<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>&lt;<italic toggle="yes"> </italic>5e–08). The <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values were derived from the binomial test</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="btab514f3" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>We further compared the replicability of OWAS with that of DeepWAS (<xref rid="btab514-B1" ref-type="bibr">Arloth <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>) (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Note S1.4</xref>), a recently developed method that identifies genotype-phenotype associations by incorporating predicted regulatory information. DeepWAS requires individual-level genotype data for model training, thus we used the imputed WTCCC data as the discovery cohort and the UKB data for replication. OWAS segments achieved higher replication rates in most scenarios compared with DeepWAS (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S3</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>3.3 Functional analysis of OWAS segments illustrates disease mechanism</title>
      <p>We identified genes tagged by significant OWAS segments, and examined their tissue specificity and functional enrichment. In particular, OWAS identified 398, 313 and 211 genes with 4895, 1635 and 706 segments associated with RA, HC and PrCa, respectively. We performed SNPsea analysis (<xref rid="btab514-B50" ref-type="bibr">Slowikowski <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>) for segments identified by OWAS for each trait in order to quantify the enrichment of tissue-specific expressions (<xref rid="btab514-F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). OWAS segments for RA marked genes specifically expressed in CD4+ T cells (<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>=<italic toggle="yes"> </italic>3.0e–07) and CD19+ B cells (<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>=<italic toggle="yes"> </italic>7.0e–06), and these two cell types are both associated with autoimmune diseases (<xref rid="btab514-B30" ref-type="bibr">Konya <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="btab514-B54" ref-type="bibr">Suzuki <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Specifically, CD4+ T cells, including T helper (Th) and regulatory T (Treg) cells, play critical roles in pathogenesis of RA (<xref rid="btab514-B29" ref-type="bibr">Kondo <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>). In addition, increasing evidence suggests that B cells, which exclusively express CD19, participate in the pathogenesis of RA including autoantibody production and CD4+ T cell activation. Pre-clinical studies also propose CD19 as a promising therapeutic target for RA (<xref rid="btab514-B55" ref-type="bibr">Tedder, 2009</xref>). Similarly, our OWAS analyses on HC identified liver as the tissue with the most significant enrichment (<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>=<italic toggle="yes"> </italic>3.4e–05) for cell-type-specific gene expression relative to 78 other tissues in the Gene Atlas (<xref rid="btab514-B53" ref-type="bibr">Su <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). The pancreatic islets were identified as the most enriched (<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>=<italic toggle="yes"> </italic>2.5e–04) tissue for PrCa, and the prostate came second (<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>=<italic toggle="yes"> </italic>2.5e–03).</p>
      <fig position="float" id="btab514-F4">
        <label>Fig. 4.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>SNPsea analysis on OWAS identified segments. Empirical <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values for the enrichment of tissue-specific expression in profiles of 79 human tissues and cells (Gene Atlas), with the top 10 shown. Horizontal dashed and solid lines show <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value cutoffs at the 0.05 level (unadjusted and with Bonferroni correction). The heat maps show the Pearson correlation coefficients for pairs of expression profiles ordered by hierarchical clustering with UPGMA</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="btab514f4" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>We further investigated overlaps between OWAS segments and predicted chromatin states from the 15-state ChromHMM model (<xref rid="btab514-B11" ref-type="bibr">Ernst and Kellis, 2017</xref>). While OWAS segments are generally enriched in open chromatin regions, we still observe an enrichment of active chromatin states in PrCa (<inline-formula id="IE9"><mml:math id="IM9" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> 0.05 with Bonferroni correction) when the bias toward DNase-seq peaks is accounted for through a permutation test (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Note S1.5</xref> and <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S4</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>3.4 OWAS results in RA and ATH provide novel insights into the disease etiology</title>
      <p>We highlight two examples on RA and arthritis and asthma (ATH) to show how OWAS can provide novel insights into the disease etiology. We mapped the significant segments OWAS identified to the closest genes, which we simply refer to as the OWAS genes. For RA, 398 genes were identified by OWAS at the 0.05 significance level after the Bonferroni correction, among which 205 were outside HLA regions. The large number of OWAS genes located in HLA regions (48.49%) validates the significant role of HLA regions in the immune system. In fact, strong associations between HLA regions and autoimmune diseases have been well documented in the literature (<xref rid="btab514-B49" ref-type="bibr">Simmonds and Gough, 2007</xref>), thus we focus here on non-HLA genes in the discussion. The top 10 OWAS genes for RA are listed in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S4</xref>, among which <italic toggle="yes">PHTF1, HIPK1, PTPN22</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">RSBN1</italic> have been reported in GWAS of RA. Although not directly mapped to RA, <italic toggle="yes">AP4B1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">BCL2L15</italic> are located in RA-associated locus 1p13.2, and were reported to have interactions with enhancers (<xref rid="btab514-B13" ref-type="bibr">Gao and Qian, 2019</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">LAMA3</italic> has been previously associated with reticulocyte count, a blood biomarker for hematologic abnormalities, like anemia (<xref rid="btab514-B2" ref-type="bibr">Astle <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>), which is one of the most frequent extra-articular organ manifestations in RA (<xref rid="btab514-B28" ref-type="bibr">Komrokji <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">OLFML3</italic> serves as both a scaffold protein that recruits bone morphogenetic protein (BMP) to its substrate chordin in Xenopus (<xref rid="btab514-B23" ref-type="bibr">Inomata <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). BMPs have been demonstrated playing a key part in destructive and remodeling arthritis (<xref rid="btab514-B37" ref-type="bibr">Lories and Luyten, 2007</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">OLFML3</italic> also acts as a vascular tissue remodeler with pro-angiogenic properties by modulating critical signaling circuits such as Notch pathways (<xref rid="btab514-B58" ref-type="bibr">Tomarev and Nakaya, 2009</xref>), which underlies inflammation and pathology in RA (<xref rid="btab514-B62" ref-type="bibr">Wei <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). In addition, we provide a potential explanation that there exists common pathogenesis or causal relationship between cardiometabolic diseases (CMD) and RA with common genetic factors regulated by <italic toggle="yes">INHBC</italic> (<xref rid="btab514-F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). There have been studies revealing the connection between RA, CMD, serum uric acid (SUA) (<xref rid="btab514-B57" ref-type="bibr">Tin <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>) and lipid profile including triglyceride (TG), high density lipoprotein cholesterol (<xref rid="btab514-B20" ref-type="bibr">Hoffmann <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>) and <italic toggle="yes">INHBC</italic>. For example, RA has long been associated with coronary heart disease and gout, which has been strongly linked to CMD (<xref rid="btab514-B44" ref-type="bibr">Picavet and Hazes, 2003</xref>), and increasing prevalence and rate of progression of atherosclerosis. The <italic toggle="yes">INHBC</italic> has been previously associated with SUA and lipid profile (e.g. TG) (<xref rid="btab514-B15" ref-type="bibr">Gorski <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="btab514-B20" ref-type="bibr">Hoffmann <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>). A GWAS of uric acid in healthy controls, RA patients has revealed probable association between SNP rs3741414 <italic toggle="yes">INHBC</italic> and SUA level (<xref rid="btab514-B51" ref-type="bibr">Son <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). A recently developed latent causal variable model also showed that lipid related traits have partially causal effects on SUA (<xref rid="btab514-B57" ref-type="bibr">Tin <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>). In our study, we identified <italic toggle="yes">INHBC</italic> as an OWAS gene for RA, validating the common genetic mechanism between CMD and RA.</p>
      <fig position="float" id="btab514-F5">
        <label>Fig. 5.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Putative mechanism for RA, CMDs and gout. The connections confirmed by previous studies are linked with solid lines. OWAS identified the <italic toggle="yes">INHBC</italic> as the RA associated locus, validating the common genetic mechanism between CMDs and RA</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="btab514f5" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>We also examined the enrichment of OWAS genes identified for RA in KEGG pathways. We found 16 pathways were significantly enriched (FDR &lt; 0.05, <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S5</xref>), including the RA pathway, T cell receptor signaling, NF-κB signaling and JAK-STAT signaling pathways, which are known RA-related pathways. Notably, NF-<italic toggle="yes">κ</italic>B (<xref rid="btab514-B45" ref-type="bibr">Potter <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>) and JAK-STAT (<xref rid="btab514-B40" ref-type="bibr">McInnes and Schett, 2017</xref>) signaling pathways have been translated into therapeutic use (e.g. TNF-α antagonist and JAK inhibitor). Besides, toxoplasmosis has been previously associated with autoimmune diseases (<xref rid="btab514-B48" ref-type="bibr">Shapira <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Some infection related pathways are enriched, such as measles, human papillomavirus infection and hepatitis B pathways. RA is known to be associated with an increased risk of serious infection (<xref rid="btab514-B8" ref-type="bibr">Cobb <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1953</xref>). The elevated infection susceptibility of patients with RA is conceivably due to premature aging of the immune system, as RA contributes to weakened protection against infectious organisms, chronic comorbid conditions, as well as sequelae of immunosuppressive treatment (<xref rid="btab514-B35" ref-type="bibr">Listing <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). The analysis has highlighted important roles of genes in infection related pathways in RA, including <italic toggle="yes">AKT3, ATF6B, ATP6V1F, ATP6V1G2, BAK1, CD28, CD40, CDK2, CSNK2B, FADD, FOXO1, HES5, HSPA1A, HSPA1B, HSPA1L, ICAM1, IL2, LAMA3, NOTCH4, PSMD3, STAT1, STAT4, TAB1, TAP1, TAP2, TAPBP, TNF, TYK2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TNXB</italic>, suggesting that the elevated risk of infection in RA patients can be explained by the genetic inherence and pathobiology of the disease itself, independent of immunosuppressive treatment (<xref rid="btab514-B35" ref-type="bibr">Listing <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>).</p>
      <p>We use RA as an example to compare OWAS, TWAS and CAVIAR (<xref rid="btab514-B21" ref-type="bibr">Hormozdiari <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>), a statistical fine-mapping method. Although the three methods differ in principle (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Note</xref> S1.6), there are some overlaps in the significant genes identified (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S6</xref>). We further performed pathway enrichment analysis in the common and exclusive genes to compare the methods (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S7</xref>). We found that five of the eight pathways discussed previously were still significantly enriched after removing the CAVIAR genes or FUSION genes from the OWAS genes. In contrast, no enrichment was found in the common genes, which are defined as genes identified by more than two methods, indicating that OWAS identifies unique association signals compared to CAVIAR and FUSION.</p>
      <p>In parallel to RA studies, we applied OWAS to analyze UKB ATH summary statistics (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Note</xref> S1.7 and <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figs. S8 and S9</xref>). We identified a cluster of genes in 17q21, within which increased expressions of <italic toggle="yes">ORMDL3</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">GSDMB</italic> lead to an increased airway hyper-reactivity, which is the characteristic of ATH and also validated by <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> studies (<xref rid="btab514-B41" ref-type="bibr">Miller <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>). Further, we give a potential biological mechanism between <italic toggle="yes">LRRC32</italic> and ATH, which underscores the capability of OWAS to interpret epigenetic mechanisms of non-coding variants in risk loci.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>3.5 Predicted openness scores</title>
      <p>DNase I hypersensitivity and histone modifications mark regulatory elements and regions of active transcription (<xref rid="btab514-B18" ref-type="bibr">Heintzman <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="btab514-B60" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Here, we show that the predicted openness scores vary significantly among active chromatin regions. The openness was trained on DHSs from GM12878 cell types (<xref rid="btab514-B9" ref-type="bibr">Consortium <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>) by deltaSVM (<xref rid="btab514-B32" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). We collected publicly available data for three histone modifications that have been previously associated with active promoters and enhancers (<xref rid="btab514-B18" ref-type="bibr">Heintzman <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="btab514-B60" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>), including H3K4me1, H3K4me3 and H3K27ac, in HapMap lymphoblastoid cell lines.</p>
      <p>We selected thresholds at 5, 10 and 15, respectively, to define the experimental peak signals and calculated the average of predicted openness scores for variants located in the selected peaks. For comparison, the same number of variants was randomly sampled from the genome and the corresponding openness scores were similarly derived. We ran the sampling process 10 000 times and show the results in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S10</xref>. The averages of predicted openness increased when more stringent thresholds were chosen. For all three histone modifications, the predicted openness in peak regions differed significantly from the background.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>3.6 Type I error control</title>
      <p>In order to evaluate the type I error of our approach, we conducted simulations based on individual-level genotypes from the WTCCC cohort. In particular, we used samples of the type II diabetes study, including 1895 cases and 2872 controls after quality control. Genotype data of chromosome 1 were used for simulation, covering 23 601 SNPs. We split the variants into segments of 5, 20 and 50 SNPs. Openness scores were simulated from a normal distribution. We sampled 100 segments and ran 1000 simulations for each segment. The type I error rates are well controlled, as summarized in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S5</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>3.7 Sensitivity analysis of segment length</title>
      <p>We tested OWAS with segment length fixed at 2.5 KB, 5 KB and 10 KB. Besides, we allowed for variable segment length while fixing the number of SNPs harbored in each segment at 20 (about the median number of SNPs of 5 KB region). The advantages of OWAS in replication rate and heritability enrichment in various traits are retained in all four settings, compared to existing approaches (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figs. S11–14</xref>). Thus, OWAS results are robust to segment length, and we use 5 KB as the default setting.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>4 Discussion</title>
    <p>Recently, there is a growing interest in understanding roles of non-coding variations in complex human diseases, empowered by the huge amount of data generated from epigenomic profiling efforts and the large scale GWAS of various phenotypes. Here, we develop a computational approach, OWAS, which integrates chromatin accessibility information in association tests. Our approach leverages predicted openness scores trained with machine learning methods, overcoming the difficulties in acquiring individual-specific openness measurement in large cohorts. We also derive a mathematical expression to compute OWAS results without individual-level genotype data, which broadens the scope of its application.</p>
    <p>We recognize that recent progress in caQTLs (<xref rid="btab514-B14" ref-type="bibr">Gate <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="btab514-B31" ref-type="bibr">Kumasaka <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>) is closely related to our method, as the overlap of caQTLs and GWAS loci can provide insights into how natural genetic variants modulate cis-regulatory elements, in isolation or in concert, to influence complex traits. However, experimental measurement of chromatin accessibility in large cohort is costly and therefore not common. Thus, the power to identify caQTLs is still limited. A comparison between OWAS and caQTLs in provided in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Note S1.8</xref>.</p>
    <p>Our method has several limitations. First, the results are influenced by the prediction accuracy of the machine learning methods. Nevertheless, with increased sample sizes and improvements in methodologies, we expect the prediction models to be further improved over the time. Second, when used with GWAS summary statistics, the method requires LD information estimated from a reference panel as input. Therefore, a reference cohort that accurately matches the target cohort is of great significance. Third, although incorporating chromatin accessibility information leads to interesting biological interpretations, we emphasize that the method alone cannot infer causality. Fourth, our method relies on pre-trained cell-type-specific sequence models, and its power could be limited by data availability of relevant cell types. A recent study (<xref rid="btab514-B4" ref-type="bibr">Boix <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>) has integrated epigenetic maps from 833 biosamples, containing 733 DNase-seq experiments, showcasing that current epigenome sequencing resources have sufficiently covered many complex traits. Plus, convenient tools [such as openAnnotate (<xref rid="btab514-B6" ref-type="bibr">Chen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>)] can facilitate efficient exploration of openness data across cell types. We expect the power of OWAS to be further enhanced when more data become available.</p>
    <p>In conclusion, we have proposed a new segment-based computational framework, OWAS, which leverages and aggregates the prediction of chromosome accessibility in personal genomes to prioritize GWAS signals. In extensive simulations and real data analyses, OWAS identifies genes/segments that explain more heritability than TWAS methods and have high replication rates in independent cohorts. Our method requires only GWAS summary statistics and a reference LD panel, which guarantees its general applicability without any privacy concerns. As sample sizes of GWAS studies continue to grow, directly using summary statistics also helps maintain the computational burden at a constant level and increases the power of the methods. Furthermore, the significant associations identified by OWAS can lead to interesting biological interpretations, as exemplified in real data analyses of RA and ATH.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
      <label>btab514_Supplementary_Data</label>
      <media xlink:href="btab514_supplementary_data.pdf">
        <caption>
          <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
        </caption>
      </media>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack id="ack1">
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <p>This study made use of data generated by the Wellcome Trust Case Control Consortium (WTCCC) and the Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute. A full list of the investigators who contributed to the generation of the WTCCC data is available at <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.wtccc.org.uk" ext-link-type="uri">www.wtccc.org.uk</ext-link>.</p>
    <sec>
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China [12071243 to L.H.]; Shanghai Municipal Science and Technology Major Project [2017SHZDZX01 to L.H.] and National Science Foundation [DMS-1903139 and DMS-2015411 to J.S.L.].</p>
      <p><italic toggle="yes">Conflict of Interest</italic>: none declared.</p>
    </sec>
  </ack>
  <ref-list id="ref1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="btab514-B1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Arloth</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>DeepWAS: multivariate genotype-phenotype associations by directly integrating regulatory information using deep learning</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput. Biol</source>., <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>e1007616</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32012148</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Astle</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>The allelic landscape of human blood cell trait variation and links to common complex disease</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>167</volume>, <fpage>1415</fpage>–<lpage>1429</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27863252</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</article-title>. <source>J. R. Stat. Soc. Ser. B (Methodological)</source>, <volume>57</volume>, <fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Boix</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Regulatory genomic circuitry of human disease loci by integrative epigenomics</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>590</volume>, <fpage>300</fpage>–<lpage>307</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33536621</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>DIVAN: accurate identification of non-coding disease-specific risk variants using multi-omics profiles</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>., <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26753840</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>OpenAnnotate: a web server to annotate the chromatin accessibility of genomic regions</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>49</volume>, <fpage>W483</fpage>–<lpage>W490</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33999180</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>GPA: a statistical approach to prioritizing GWAS results by integrating pleiotropy and annotation</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>., <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>e1004787</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25393678</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B8">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cobb</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1953</year>) <article-title>Length of life and cause of death in rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>N. Engl. J. Med</source>., <volume>249</volume>, <fpage>553</fpage>–<lpage>556</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13087647</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B9">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Consortium</surname><given-names>E.P.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>An integrated encyclopedia of DNA elements in the human genome</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>489</volume>, <fpage>57</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22955616</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B10">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Consortium</surname><given-names>W.T.C.C.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide association study of 14,000 cases of seven common diseases and 3,000 shared controls</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>447</volume>, <fpage>661</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17554300</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B11">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kellis</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Chromatin-state discovery and genome annotation with ChromHMM</article-title>. <source>Nat. Protocols</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>2478</fpage>–<lpage>2492</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29120462</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B12">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Finucane</surname><given-names>H.K.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal>, RACI Consortium. (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Partitioning heritability by functional annotation using genome-wide association summary statistics</article-title>. <source>Nat. Genet</source>., <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>1228</fpage>–<lpage>1235</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26414678</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B13">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>EAGLE: an algorithm that utilizes a small number of genomic features to predict tissue/cell type-specific enhancer-gene interactions</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput. Biol</source>., <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>e1007436</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31665135</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B14">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gate</surname><given-names>R.E.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Genetic determinants of co-accessible chromatin regions in activated T cells across humans</article-title>. <source>Nat. Genet</source>., <volume>50</volume>, <fpage>1140</fpage>–<lpage>1150</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29988122</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B15">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gorski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>1000 genomes-based meta-analysis identifies 10 novel loci for kidney function</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep</source>., <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>45040</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28452372</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B16">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gusev</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Partitioning heritability of regulatory and cell-type-specific variants across 11 common diseases</article-title>. <source>Am. J. Hum. Genet</source>., <volume>95</volume>, <fpage>535</fpage>–<lpage>552</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25439723</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B17">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gusev</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Integrative approaches for large-scale transcriptome-wide association studies</article-title>. <source>Nat. Genet</source>., <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>245</fpage>–<lpage>252</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26854917</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B18">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Heintzman</surname><given-names>N.D.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Histone modifications at human enhancers reflect global cell-type-specific gene expression</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>459</volume>, <fpage>108</fpage>–<lpage>112</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19295514</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B19">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>G.E.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Functional interpretation of genetic variants using deep learning predicts impact on chromatin accessibility and histone modification</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>10597</fpage>–<lpage>10611</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31544924</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B20">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>A large electronic-health-record-based genome-wide study of serum lipids</article-title>. <source>Nat. Genet</source>., <volume>50</volume>, <fpage>401</fpage>–<lpage>413</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29507422</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B21">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hormozdiari</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Identifying causal variants at loci with multiple signals of association</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>, <volume>198</volume>, <fpage>497</fpage>–<lpage>508</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25104515</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B22">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>A review of post-GWAS prioritization approaches</article-title>. <source>Front. Genet</source>., <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>280</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24367376</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B23">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Inomata</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Robust stability of the embryonic axial pattern requires a secreted scaffold for chordin degradation</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>134</volume>, <fpage>854</fpage>–<lpage>865</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18775317</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B24">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Iotchkova</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal>, UK10K Consortium. (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>GARFIELD classifies disease-relevant genomic features through integration of functional annotations with association signals</article-title>. <source>Nat. Genet</source>., <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>343</fpage>–<lpage>353</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30692680</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B25">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jostins</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Genetic risk prediction in complex disease</article-title>. <source>Hum. Mol. Genet</source>., <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>R182</fpage>–<lpage>R188</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21873261</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B26">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>KEGG for linking genomes to life and the environment</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>D480</fpage>–<lpage>D484</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18077471</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B27">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Klemm</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Chromatin accessibility and the regulatory epigenome</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Genet</source>., <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>220</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30675018</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B28">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Komrokji</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Autoimmune diseases and myelodysplastic syndromes</article-title>. <source>Am. J. Hematol</source>., <volume>91</volume>, <fpage>E280</fpage>–<lpage>E283</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26875020</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B29">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Transcriptional regulation of CD 4+ T cell differentiation in experimentally induced arthritis and rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>Arthr. Rheumatol</source>., <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>653</fpage>–<lpage>661</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29245178</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B30">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Konya</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Treating autoimmune disease by targeting CD8+ T suppressor cells</article-title>. <source>Expert Opin. Biol. Therapy</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>951</fpage>–<lpage>965</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B31">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kumasaka</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Fine-mapping cellular QTLs with RASQUAL and ATAC-seq</article-title>. <source>Nat. Genet</source>., <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>206</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26656845</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B32">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>A method to predict the impact of regulatory variants from DNA sequence</article-title>. <source>Nat. Genet</source>., <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>955</fpage>–<lpage>961</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26075791</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B33">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2020a</year>) <article-title>A method for scoring the cell type-specific impacts of noncoding variants in personal genomes</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>117</volume>, <fpage>21364</fpage>–<lpage>21372</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32817564</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B34">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal>, TOPMed Lipids Working Group. (<year>2020b</year>) <article-title>Dynamic incorporation of multiple in silico functional annotations empowers rare variant association analysis of large whole-genome sequencing studies at scale</article-title>. <source>Nat. Genet</source>., <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>969</fpage>–<lpage>983</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32839606</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B35">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Listing</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The risk of infections associated with rheumatoid arthritis, with its comorbidity and treatment</article-title>. <source>Rheumatology</source>, <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23192911</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B36">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>DeepCAGE: incorporating transcription factors in genome-wide prediction of chromatin accessibility</article-title>. <source>bioRxiv</source>, <fpage>610642</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/610642</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B37">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lories</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luyten</surname><given-names>F.P.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Bone morphogenetic proteins in destructive and remodeling arthritis</article-title>. <source>Arthr. Res. Therapy</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>207</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B38">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Integrative tissue-specific functional annotations in the human genome provide novel insights on many complex traits and improve signal prioritization in genome wide association studies</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>., <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>e1005947</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27058395</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B39">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Maurano</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Systematic localization of common disease-associated variation in regulatory DNA</article-title>. <source>Science</source>, <volume>337</volume>, <fpage>1190</fpage>–<lpage>1195</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22955828</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B40">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>McInnes</surname><given-names>I.B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schett</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Pathogenetic insights from the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>, <volume>389</volume>, <fpage>2328</fpage>–<lpage>2337</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28612747</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B41">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Does reduced zona pellucida binding protein 2 (ZPBP2) expression on chromosome 17q21 protect against asthma?</article-title>  <source>J. Allergy Clin. Immunol</source>., <volume>142</volume>, <fpage>706</fpage>–<lpage>709</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29709669</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B42">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Chromatin accessibility prediction via convolutional long short-term memory networks with k-mer embedding</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>i92</fpage>–<lpage>i101</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28881969</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B43">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nasser</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide enhancer maps link risk variants to disease genes</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>593</volume>, <fpage>238</fpage>–<lpage>243</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33828297</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B44">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Picavet</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hazes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Prevalence of self reported musculoskeletal diseases is high</article-title>. <source>Ann. Rheum. Dis</source>., <volume>62</volume>, <fpage>644</fpage>–<lpage>650</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12810427</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B45">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal>, and the Biologics in Rheumatoid Arthritis Genetics and Genomics Study Syndicate (BRAGGSS). (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Association between anti-tumour necrosis factor treatment response and genetic variants within the TLR and NF<italic toggle="yes">κ</italic>B signalling pathways</article-title>. <source>Ann. Rheum. Dis</source>., <volume>69</volume>, <fpage>1315</fpage>–<lpage>1320</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20448286</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B46">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rentzsch</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>CADD: predicting the deleteriousness of variants throughout the human genome</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>D886</fpage>–<lpage>D894</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30371827</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B47">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ritchie</surname><given-names>G.R.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Functional annotation of noncoding sequence variants</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>294</fpage>–<lpage>296</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24487584</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B48">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Shapira</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Prevalence of anti-toxoplasma antibodies in patients with autoimmune diseases</article-title>. <source>J. Autoimmun</source>., <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>112</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22297145</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B49">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Simmonds</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gough</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The HLA region and autoimmune disease: associations and mechanisms of action</article-title>. <source>Curr. Genom</source>., <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>453</fpage>–<lpage>465</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B50">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Slowikowski</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>SNPsea: an algorithm to identify cell types, tissues and pathways affected by risk loci</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>2496</fpage>–<lpage>2497</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24813542</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B51">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>C.-N.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>The frequency of single nucleotide polymorphisms and their association with uric acid concentration based on data from genome-wide association studies in the Korean population</article-title>. <source>Rheumatol. Int</source>., <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>777</fpage>–<lpage>783</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24408252</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B52">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Soskic</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Chromatin activity at GWAS loci identifies T cell states driving complex immune diseases</article-title>. <source>Nat. Genet</source>., <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>1486</fpage>–<lpage>1493</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31548716</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B53">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>A.I.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A gene atlas of the mouse and human protein-encoding transcriptomes</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci</source>., <volume>101</volume>, <fpage>6062</fpage>–<lpage>6067</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15075390</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B54">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Inhibitory CD8+ T cells in autoimmune disease</article-title>. <source>Hum. Immunol</source>., <volume>69</volume>, <fpage>781</fpage>–<lpage>789</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18812196</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B55">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tedder</surname><given-names>T.F.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>CD19: a promising B cell target for rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Rheumatol</source>., <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>572</fpage>–<lpage>577</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19798033</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B56">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Teslovich</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Biological, clinical and population relevance of 95 loci for blood lipids</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>466</volume>, <fpage>707</fpage>–<lpage>713</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20686565</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B57">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal>; V. A. Million Veteran Program. (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Target genes, variants, tissues and transcriptional pathways influencing human serum urate levels</article-title>. <source>Nat. Genet</source>., <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>1459</fpage>–<lpage>1474</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31578528</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B58">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tomarev</surname><given-names>S.I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nakaya</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Olfactomedin domain-containing proteins: possible mechanisms of action and functions in normal development and pathology</article-title>. <source>Mol. Neurobiol</source>., <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>122</fpage>–<lpage>138</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19554483</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B59">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wainberg</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Opportunities and challenges for transcriptome-wide association studies</article-title>. <source>Nat. Genet</source>., <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>592</fpage>–<lpage>599</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30926968</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B60">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Combinatorial patterns of histone acetylations and methylations in the human genome</article-title>. <source>Nat. Genet</source>., <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>897</fpage>–<lpage>903</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18552846</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B61">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Functional mapping and annotation of genetic associations with FUMA</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun</source>., <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28232747</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B62">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal>; Accelerating Medicines Partnership Rheumatoid Arthritis &amp; Systemic Lupus Erythematosus (AMP RA/SLE) Consortium. (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Notch signalling drives synovial fibroblast identity and arthritis pathology</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>582</volume>, <fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>264</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32499639</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B63">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>GCTA: a tool for genome-wide complex trait analysis</article-title>. <source>Am. J. Hum. Genet</source>., <volume>88</volume>, <fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21167468</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab514-B64">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>clusterProfiler: an R package for comparing biological themes among gene clusters</article-title>. <source>Omics J. Integrative Biol</source>., <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>284</fpage>–<lpage>287</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
