<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">NAR Genom Bioinform</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">NAR Genom Bioinform</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nargab</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>NAR Genomics and Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">2631-9268</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8221386</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34179780</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nargab/lqab058</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">lqab058</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI00030</subject>
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI00980</subject>
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01060</subject>
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01140</subject>
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01180</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Methods Article</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>Kmerator Suite: design of specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer signatures and automatic metadata discovery in large RNA-seq datasets</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Riquier</surname>
          <given-names>Sébastien</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>IRMB, University of Montpellier, INSERM</institution>, 80 rue Augustin Fliche, 34295, Montpellier, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
        <xref rid="FN1" ref-type="author-notes"/>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Bessiere</surname>
          <given-names>Chloé</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>IRMB, University of Montpellier, INSERM</institution>, 80 rue Augustin Fliche, 34295, Montpellier, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
        <xref rid="FN1" ref-type="author-notes"/>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Guibert</surname>
          <given-names>Benoit</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>IRMB, University of Montpellier, INSERM</institution>, 80 rue Augustin Fliche, 34295, Montpellier, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Bouge</surname>
          <given-names>Anne-Laure</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>SeqOne</institution>, 34000, Montpellier, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Boureux</surname>
          <given-names>Anthony</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>IRMB, University of Montpellier, INSERM</institution>, 80 rue Augustin Fliche, 34295, Montpellier, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Ruffle</surname>
          <given-names>Florence</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>IRMB, University of Montpellier, INSERM</institution>, 80 rue Augustin Fliche, 34295, Montpellier, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Audoux</surname>
          <given-names>Jérôme</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>SeqOne</institution>, 34000, Montpellier, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Gilbert</surname>
          <given-names>Nicolas</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>IRMB, University of Montpellier, INSERM</institution>, 80 rue Augustin Fliche, 34295, Montpellier, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Xue</surname>
          <given-names>Haoliang</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Institute for Integrative Biology of the Cell, CEA, CNRS, Université Paris-Saclay</institution>, 91198, Gif sur Yvette, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Gautheret</surname>
          <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Institute for Integrative Biology of the Cell, CEA, CNRS, Université Paris-Saclay</institution>, 91198, Gif sur Yvette, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Commes</surname>
          <given-names>Thérèse</given-names>
        </name>
        <!--therese.commes@inserm.fr-->
        <aff><institution>IRMB, University of Montpellier, INSERM</institution>, 80 rue Augustin Fliche, 34295, Montpellier, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
        <xref rid="COR1" ref-type="corresp"/>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="COR1">To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +33 4 67330190; Email: <email>therese.commes@inserm.fr</email></corresp>
      <fn id="FN1">
        <p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p>
      </fn>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <month>9</month>
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2021-06-23">
      <day>23</day>
      <month>6</month>
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>23</day>
      <month>6</month>
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>3</volume>
    <issue>3</issue>
    <elocation-id>lqab058</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>17</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2020</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>10</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>17</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2021. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of NAR Genomics and Bioinformatics.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact <email>journals.permissions@oup.com</email></license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="lqab058.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <p>The huge body of publicly available RNA-sequencing (RNA-seq) libraries is a treasure of functional information allowing to quantify the expression of known or novel transcripts in tissues. However, transcript quantification commonly relies on alignment methods requiring a lot of computational resources and processing time, which does not scale easily to large datasets. <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>-mer decomposition constitutes a new way to process RNA-seq data for the identification of transcriptional signatures, as <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers can be used to quantify accurately gene expression in a less resource-consuming way. We present the Kmerator Suite, a set of three tools designed to extract specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer signatures, quantify these <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers into RNA-seq datasets and quickly visualize large dataset characteristics. The core tool, Kmerator, produces specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers for 97% of human genes, enabling the measure of gene expression with high accuracy in simulated datasets. KmerExploR, a direct application of Kmerator, uses a set of predictor gene-specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers to infer metadata including library protocol, sample features or contaminations from RNA-seq datasets. KmerExploR results are visualized through a user-friendly interface. Moreover, we demonstrate that the Kmerator Suite can be used for advanced queries targeting known or new biomarkers such as mutations, gene fusions or long non-coding RNAs for human health applications.</p>
    </abstract>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Agence Nationale de la Recherche</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100001665</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>ANR-10-INBS-09</award-id>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Canceropole Grand Ouest</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>2017-EM24</award-id>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Region Occitanie</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>R19073FF</award-id>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="15"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec sec-type="intro" id="SEC1">
    <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
    <p>Publicly available human RNA-sequencing (RNA-seq) datasets are precious resources for biomedical research. RNA-seq data are widely used to identify actively transcribed genes, quantify gene or transcript expression, identify new fusion transcripts or identify alternative splicing or mutation events. The search for specific transcriptional events or RNAs across large-scale data has become essential in precision medicine. Advanced tools such as recount2 (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>) have achieved transcript counts in large datasets, available in an online resource. However, these tools are reference based and only provide counts for precomputed transcripts. An increasing number of studies attempt to analyze in a retrospective fashion the vast repository of RNA-seq data, including normal and pathological conditions, to discover or validate RNA biomarkers for disease diagnosis (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>).</p>
    <p>For this purpose, it is important to select relevant RNA-seq datasets with homogeneous characteristics and sufficient samples among thousands of publicly available files. The reanalysis of RNA-seq datasets poses two major challenges. The first challenge is to filter data series and select the most homogeneous and reliable set of libraries for exploration in the context of incomplete metadata (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). The second challenge is to perform RNA biomarker quantification in reasonable time and with sufficient accuracy to extract biological information in such datasets. Alignment-based methods like STAR (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) and CRAC (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>) require significant computational resources, making them inadequate for querying datasets on the order of 100–1000 files for a specific biomarker. Pseudo-alignment algorithms like Kallisto (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>) and Salmon (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) are much faster but most commonly use a reference transcriptome far from the real complex biological RNA diversity. This highlights the need for tools enabling fast and specific quantification of candidate sequences in a large set of RNA-seq data. Recently, approaches relying on <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers from raw sequence files have emerged and are used for the query of transcriptomic data. These methods require less time and computational resources than common ones and are suited to various biological questions, including the analysis of unannotated and atypical RNA transcriptional events. For instance, Okamura and Kinoshita proposed an ultrafast mRNA quantification method, based on unique <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers, that outperforms conventional approaches (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Yu <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>) investigated gene fusion queries of all tumor samples from The Cancer Genome Atlas project using <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer sets. The DE-kupl pipeline developed by Audoux <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>) finds differential events between two groups of RNA-seq data at the <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer level.</p>
    <p>Moreover, classical methods fail to interrogate the whole transcriptome complexity as each RNA is the result of a complex chain of events that combines genetic variation, transcription regulation and RNA processing combined with pathological alterations (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). The <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer approach we propose is not an equivalent method compared to the above-mentioned ones, but a new way to explore RNA-seq data that could also be used for in-depth exploration outside the reference.</p>
    <p>Although any transcript sequence can be decomposed into <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers, only a subset of these <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers is specific for the transcript. We call this subset the <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer signature. These specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers can then be quantified in RNA-seq raw data, making it quick and easy to measure the candidate transcript expression level in a wide range of RNA-seq datasets.</p>
    <p>In this paper, we present the Kmerator Suite, a set of three tools designed to (i) extract <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer signatures from transcripts, (ii) quantify these <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers into RNA-seq datasets and (iii) visualize large RNA-seq dataset characteristics using precomputed signatures. The core of this suite is Kmerator, which generates <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer signatures specific for genes or transcripts. The second tool, countTags, is used to quantify selected <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers across raw RNA-seq files. We first tested the performance of Kmerator + countTags over the whole transcriptome and showed that <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer signature quantification results were close to simulated count data. The third tool, KmerExploR, demonstrates the capacity of the Kmerator + countTags pipeline combined to a set of predefined <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer signatures, to perform metadata extraction from raw RNA-seq data. KmerExploR extracts sample characteristics related to the sequencing protocol (ribosomal depletion, polyA+, strand-specific protocol, 5′/3′ bias, etc.), tissue origin (sex) and possible contaminations (mycoplasma, virus, other species or cell lines). Such high-level quality control procedures are valuable as a screening tool before analyzing datasets of uncertain quality, such as public datasets. KmerExploR can also be used in advanced applications to look for user-defined transcripts resulting from mutated alleles or gene fusions in RNA-seq datasets.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="SEC2">
    <title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title>
    <sec id="SEC2-1">
      <title>Kmerator: <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer signature identification</title>
      <p>An overview of the Kmerator Suite is provided in Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1A</xref>. Kmerator is a tool designed for the prediction of specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers from input sequences, considering a reference genome and an Ensembl-like fasta transcriptome (see Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1A</xref> and <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S1A</xref>). It is implemented in Julia programming language (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://julialang.org" ext-link-type="uri">https://julialang.org</ext-link>) and distributed with GitHub (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://github.com/Transipedia/kmerator" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/Transipedia/kmerator</ext-link>). Kmerator strictly depends on a reference genome [fasta or Jellyfish (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) index format] and on an Ensembl fasta format transcriptome, to define a <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer as specific or not, depending on the number of occurrences on each reference. The reference genome and transcriptome fasta, used in this paper, have been downloaded here: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ensembl.org/info/data/ftp/index.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ensembl.org/info/data/ftp/index.html</ext-link>. The procedure also needs a list of gene/transcript Ensembl IDs (or gene symbols) or sequences in fasta format from which Kmerator will extract specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers. As shown in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S1A</xref>, Kmerator first uses the Jellyfish software to index and count <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers from the reference genome and transcriptome. For both genome and transcriptome fasta files, Jellyfish produces a hash table including all possible <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers and their number of occurrences. These hash tables are stored for further querying. Second, using Jellyfish query, Kmerator generates, for each input gene/transcript, the list of <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers derived from this sequence and their corresponding genome and transcriptome counts. These <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers are then filtered according to the following criteria: (i) only <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers associated with a biological event (transcript or gene, splice variant, chimeric RNA, circular RNA, etc.) are retained and (ii) <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers must be specific according to Kmerator rules (see Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1C</xref> and <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S1A</xref>). Indeed, Kmerator includes three different levels of specificity (–level option), ‘gene’, ‘transcript’ and ‘chimera’, detailed below:</p>
      <list list-type="bullet">
        <list-item>
          <p>Gene level specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers are found zero (to include <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers containing splicing junctions) or one time in the reference genome. They are also present in the reference transcriptome in at least one isoform transcript sequence. If we want to select only <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers matching at least <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> isoforms on a total of <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>, a threshold can be set to the proportion of isoforms <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> the <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer has to be specific to, using the –threshold option.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>Transcript level specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers are found zero or one time in the reference genome. They also match the reference transcriptome only once (transcript specificity). If the candidate transcript is not annotated, the –unannotated option must be added. In this case, <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers found zero or one time in the reference genome and that do not map to the reference transcriptome are retained.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>Chimera level specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers are found neither in the reference genome nor in the reference transcriptome. This level must be combined to the –unannotated option. Kmerator outputs the list of specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers (also called <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer gene/transcript signature) according to the chosen parameters in fasta format, for each input sequence.</p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
      <fig position="float" id="F1">
        <label>Figure 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Kmerator Suite and Kmerator levels: definitions. <bold>(A)</bold> The Kmerator Suite is a set of three tools: (1) Kmerator extracts gene/transcript <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer signatures. It takes as input a reference genome and a reference transcriptome + a list of gene or transcript sequences to extract specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers from. The output is a set of fasta files (one per input gene/transcript sequence) with the specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers. (2) countTags quantifies input <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers in a set of input sequencing raw files (fastq files) and outputs a count table. (3) KmerExploR is a particular application of Kmerator/countTags to visualize input RNA-seq dataset (set of fastq files) characteristics. The default usage includes characteristics related to the sequencing protocol (ribosomal depletion, polyA+, strand-specific protocol, 5′/3′ bias), tissue origin (sex) and possible contaminations (mycoplasma, virus, other species or HeLa cell line). Users can also visualize their own signatures with the advanced usage. Details are given in the text and <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S1</xref>. <bold>(B)</bold> Kmerator extracts gene/transcript <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer signatures with three possible levels of stringency. This figure describes how the different levels are defined (transcript, gene or chimera) for two example genes A and B. Example gene A has three isoforms: A1, A2 and A3. A1 is the only one with a free interval, i.e. a region not covered by other isoforms, and is defined as the principal transcript (APPRIS database). Therefore, at the transcript level, each transcript has its own specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer set, depending on its coverage with other isoforms. At the gene level, the principal transcript defined with the APPRIS database is used, and specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers can be common to several isoforms. At the chimera level (example of A1–B1 fusion), the <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer is not described in annotations.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="lqab058fig1" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <sec id="SEC2-1-1">
        <title>Kmerator command line options</title>
        <p>The <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer length can be set using the –length option. In the present study, we used the default 31 nt <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer length according to the literature (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). The level of specificity is chosen among ‘gene’, ‘transcript’ and ‘chimera’ with the –level option. When using the gene level, the APPRIS database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://appris.bioinfo.cnio.es" ext-link-type="uri">http://appris.bioinfo.cnio.es</ext-link>) can be queried to identify the ‘PRINCIPAL’ transcript, using the –appris option. APPRIS defines as the ‘PRINCIPAL’ isoform a CDS (coding sequence) variant for each gene, based on the range of protein features. When this option is not used or no principal sequence is given by APPRIS [i.e. for long non-coding RNA (lncRNA)], the isoform with the longest sequence is kept. In this study, we always used the gene level in combination with the –appris option.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="SEC2-1-2">
        <title>Kmerator usage on the entire transcriptome for performance assessment</title>
        <p>Kmerator was tested to extract <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer signatures from the whole human Ensembl transcriptome (combination of cDNA and ncRNA fasta files, version 91). The Ensembl reference transcriptome was filtered to remove any transcript with alternate loci (labels with ‘_alt’) and have been processed by Kmerator at both transcript (i.e. 199 181 transcripts) and gene (54 874 genes) levels with the –appris option previously described. At the transcript level, 62 transcripts have been ignored due to their length inferior to the <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer length (31 nt). The processing to generate the specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers on the whole transcriptome has been completed in &lt;3 days at the gene level (88 003 855 <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers) and 24 h at the transcript level (69 760 957 <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers), using a LINUX server with 30 computing cores and 20 GB hard disk space. This step has to be done only one time for one chosen reference transcriptome. Once we have all the annotated transcript <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer signatures, we can rapidly quantify them in any RNA-seq data.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2-2">
      <title><italic toggle="yes">K</italic>-mer counting and expression quantification</title>
      <sec id="SEC2-2-1">
        <title>Simulated data</title>
        <p>To test the precision of <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer quantification, we created a set of 10 simulated RNA-seq data for which we have the exact counts. We first used the R <italic toggle="yes">compcodeR</italic> package (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) and the ‘generateSyntheticData’ function to simulate a count matrix with two conditions with five samples in each (samples.per.cond = 5). Each line of this matrix corresponds to a transcript of the Ensembl v91 annotation. Counts of transcripts with a length equal or inferior to 200 nt were not simulated. To highlight the quantification process, we increased the number of differentially expressed genes (n.diffexp = 10 000) with balanced over- and underexpressed fractions (fraction.upregulated = 0.5) and with authorized different dispersions between the conditions (between.group.diffdisp = TRUE, fraction.non.overdispersed = 0). Besides, we set the sequencing depth by RNA-seq file to 100 million reads (seq depth = 100 000 000) and we did not filter low counts (filter.threshold.total = 0). Providing this data frame and the Ensembl reference transcriptome, we used the ‘simulate_experiment_countmat’ function, from <italic toggle="yes">polyester</italic> R package (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), to generate paired-end and strand-specific (fr fashion) RNA-seq reads in fasta format. Finally, the fasta files have been converted to fastq.gz format using seqtk (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://github.com/lh3/seqtk" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/lh3/seqtk</ext-link>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="SEC2-2-2">
        <title>countTags</title>
        <p><italic toggle="yes">K</italic>-mers designed by Kmerator on the whole transcriptome were counted into the 10 simulated RNA-seq data. For this purpose, the list of <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers was submitted to countTags (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://github.com/Transipedia/countTags" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/Transipedia/countTags</ext-link>), a tool written in C language (see Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1A</xref>). countTags searches for short sequences (&lt;32 nt) and their reverse complement with an exact match in fastq files and counts their occurrences. We used a <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer length of 31 nt (–<italic toggle="yes">k</italic> 31) and the paired-end option (–paired), and we also used the countTags normalization option to normalize <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer counts per billion of <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers present in the dataset, using the –kbp option. As many specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers are associated with one single transcript/gene, we computed the mean <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer count by transcript/gene.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="SEC2-2-3">
        <title>Comparison with Kallisto</title>
        <p>We compared the Kmerator + countTags pipeline with Kallisto regarding the performances in transcript/gene expression quantification on simulated data detailed above. As our pipeline cannot quantify genes/transcripts without specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers, we limited Kallisto quantification to the genes/transcripts having specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers. Kallisto 0.43.1 (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>) was run using the –fr-stranded option with the Ensembl v91 annotation file. For each pipeline, TPM (transcripts per million) counts were compared to true normalized TPM using the Spearman’s correlation, either at the transcript level or at the gene level. Counts estimated by Kallisto were merged at the gene level by summing normalized transcript counts.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2-3">
      <title>KmerExploR: exploring large RNA-seq datasets</title>
      <p>KmerExploR is a command line tool powered by the back-end pipeline Kmerator + countTags. KmerExploR provides <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer quantification results in RNA-seq samples as a graphical and user-friendly html interface (see Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1A</xref>). To deal with data heterogeneity and the weaknesses of RNA-seq technology, we developed a turnkey application using KmerExploR. Characterization of a requested RNA-seq dataset can be improved with the quantification of selected genes (predictor genes) via the Kmerator + countTags pipeline. Predictor genes and their corresponding specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers are included in KmerExploR and have been selected based on the literature to answer specific biological questions:</p>
      <list list-type="bullet">
        <list-item>
          <p>Are my RNA-seq data based on polyA selection protocol or ribo-depletion?</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>Are my RNA-seq libraries stranded or not?</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>What is/are the sex corresponding to my samples?</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>Is there a read coverage bias from 5′ to 3′ end along my dataset transcripts?</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>Are my RNA-seq data contaminated by HeLa (presence of HeLa-derived human papillomavirus 18), mycoplasmas or other viruses such as hepatitis B virus?</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>What is/are the species present in my samples?</p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
      <sec id="SEC2-3-1">
        <title>Implementation</title>
        <p>KmerExploR is a command line tool written in python 3. It can be installed on a server or on a personal computer from GitHub or with pip command (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://github.com/Transipedia/kmerexplorerexplor" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/Transipedia/kmerexplor</ext-link>). No additional modules are required. KmerExploR does not need a lot of memory and can be launched from a laptop. Indeed, for a common analysis of 36 paired-end samples (80 GB of fastq files), it takes 250 MB of memory (RAM per core) and 24 min. In comparison, the popular useful and complementary QC tool fastQC (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://qubeshub.org/resources/fastqc" ext-link-type="uri">https://qubeshub.org/resources/fastqc</ext-link>) takes 3300 MB of memory (RAM per core) and 15 min. KmerExploR includes countTags, described above. From input fastq files, KmerExploR runs countTags, with a multithreading option, to quantify built-in <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer selection associated with each predictor gene. The detailed diagram is shown in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S1B</xref>. KmerExploR can also directly take countTags output files, as for large datasets it could be useful to separately run countTags on a cluster, for example. KmerExploR outputs an html file with css and javascript in separate files, using the echartsjs library to display user-friendly and graphical information (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://echarts.apache.org/en/index.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://echarts.apache.org/en/index.html</ext-link>). Categories to show are described either in the built-in config file or in the user personal config file. KmerExploR also produces a tabulated text file with mean counts for each predictor gene in each category (rows) and in each sample (columns).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="SEC2-3-2">
        <title>Predictor gene selection</title>
        <p>We selected a subset of housekeeping genes from the list previously published by Eisenberg and Levanon (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) as well as some widely expressed histone genes that produce non-polyadenylated transcripts barely detected in polyA+ RNA-seq (see Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). We also selected specific genes from chromosome Y that have a ubiquitous expression, from Maan <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>’s publication (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). For these different sets of genes, we designed specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers using Kmerator at the gene level and also computed the <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer reversed complementary counterparts for the orientation category. Housekeeping genes’ ubiquitous expression profile in various tissues, chromosome Y genes’ specific expression pattern in male tissues and histone genes’ low expression in polyA+ RNA-seq samples have been validated by exploring the GTEx database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.gtexportal.org" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.gtexportal.org</ext-link>) (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>).</p>
        <p>For the detection of 5′/3′-end biases, we used the specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers from ubiquitous genes (orientation set) and individually attributed them to their corresponding region, 5′ untranslated region (UTR), 3′ UTR or CDS, depending on their position in the principal transcript, according to the APPRIS database. For that purpose, we used Ensembl annotations with the biomaRt R package that gives the information of the UTR and CDS regions for each transcript. We searched the <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers in transcript CDS and UTR sequences to label them by region. For mycoplasma tag selection, we first selected the most frequent mycoplasma found in cell contamination according to Drexler and Uphoff (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). We then downloaded ribosomal RNA (rRNA) sequences of the six selected mycoplasma species from the SILVA database v132 (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>), which provides updated and curated rRNA sequences from Bacteria, Archaea and Eukaryota. Some species have several associated strains and therefore, several rRNA sequences. We have included them all for the <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer design. For HeLa detection, we selected HPV-18 transcripts reported to be expressed in HeLa cells (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Using UGENE software (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>), we manually modified these transcripts to match the mutations reported as HeLa specific in the Cantalupo <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> study (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). We then defined sequences taking 30 nt on both sides of each mutation, before passing them to Kmerator to keep only <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers not present in the human genome and transcriptome. For species identification, we selected those principally found in the SRA database. We then downloaded mitochondrially encoded cytochrome <italic toggle="yes">c</italic> oxidase I (MT-CO1) human gene sequence and its orthologs in each of the selected species, using the corresponding animal reference genome and transcriptome sequences (Ensembl v91 for each). Finally, sequences of virus genomes have been downloaded from RefSeq using the common virus list provided by Uphoff <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). All these potential contamination sequences were used to produce specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers using Kmerator at the chimera level, to select tags that can be found neither in the human reference genome nor in the transcriptome. For the advanced application of KmerExploR, we designed <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers corresponding to new or rare transcriptional events detected in the Leucegene dataset (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://leucegene.ca/" ext-link-type="uri">https://leucegene.ca/</ext-link>). For chimera detection, we used two well-known fusion RNA examples associated with chromosomal translocation and their reciprocal counterparts [RUNX1–RUNXT1 t(<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>,21) RUNXT1–RUNX1, PML–RARA t(15,17) and RARA–PML]. Specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers are designed with Kmerator on 60 bp sequences spanning the junction. For mutation detection, we manually designed 31 bp <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers centered on the mutation for reference and alternative sequences of three genes currently used in acute myeloid leukemia (AML) diagnosis: TET2, KRAS and CEBPA. We finally designed <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers with Kmerator at the transcript level for a new lncRNA previously published in (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>) as NONE ‘chr2-p21’.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="SEC2-3-3">
        <title>RNA-seq dataset</title>
        <p>In this paper, we illustrated KmerExploR output on several datasets, depending on the biological question, all described in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>. Characteristics related to RNA-seq protocol, which we call basic features, are tested on 103 paired-end samples from ENCODE (Dataset-FEATURES). For the contaminations part, we used the 33 single-read samples from the PRJNA153913 study (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) previously described as highly contaminated by mycoplasma (Dataset-MYCO) (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). We also selected three public RNA-seq samples by species to check the relevance of our species-specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers (Dataset-SPECIES). HeLa contamination was tested in three cervical cancer CCLE (Cancer Cell Line Encyclopedia) cell lines: one HeLa and two negative controls (Dataset-HELA-CLE). Finally, for virus detection we used 19 samples from the CCLE dataset reported by Uphoff <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) as contaminated by viruses and three control non-contaminated cell lines also included in the Uphoff <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> study (Dataset-VIRUS-CCLE).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="results" id="SEC3">
    <title>RESULTS</title>
    <sec id="SEC3-1">
      <title>Kmerator performances</title>
      <p>To assess the Kmerator methodology, we first extracted <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer signatures from all the human Ensembl transcriptome (i.e. 199 181 transcripts) and genes (i.e. 54 874 coding and non-coding genes). We were able to identify specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers (<italic toggle="yes">k</italic> = 31 nt) for 83% of human transcripts and 97% of human genes as shown in Figure <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2A</xref> and <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">B</xref>.</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F2">
        <label>Figure 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Kmerator performances on the whole transcriptome. We extracted <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer signatures from all the human Ensembl transcriptome v91 at both gene (54 874 coding and non-coding genes, left) and transcript (i.e. 199 181 transcripts, right) levels. <bold>(A)</bold> The first pie chart represents the proportion of genes having specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers (turquoise) versus those without specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers (red). <bold>(B)</bold> In the same way, we represented the proportion of transcripts having specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers (turquoise) or not (red). For these two classes, we looked at the percentage having free intervals, i.e. regions in the transcript not shared with other isoforms (secondary pie). Most of the transcripts lacking specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers do not have free intervals (91%). We tested Kmerator sensitivity to quantify simulated data, at both gene <bold>(C)</bold> and transcript <bold>(D)</bold> levels. We represented the <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer counts normalized per billion of <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers in the sample (<italic toggle="yes">Y</italic>-axis) as a function of the true expression in TPM (<italic toggle="yes">X</italic>-axis), on the whole simulated dataset. <italic toggle="yes">R</italic> is the Spearman’s correlation coefficient between <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer counts and TPM. Each point on the graph is a transcript and the color scale depends on the transcript density on the graph.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="lqab058fig2" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>This way, the transcriptome information has been almost entirely summarized by 69 760 957 <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers at the transcript level and 88 003 855 <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers at the gene level, corresponding to 23.8% and 30% of the total number of <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers in the reference transcriptome, respectively. The attribution of specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers at the gene and transcript levels is fundamentally different: whereas the gene level (–appris option) accepts specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers shared with other isoforms, the transcript level is more stringent and eliminates each <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer shared by other ones. This explains the higher percentage of transcripts without specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer compared to the gene level. To explain the absence of specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers for some transcripts, we used BiomaRt genomic intervals to calculate the part of each transcript not covered by other isoforms, considering the strand, and named it ‘free interval’ (see Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1B</xref>). As expected, 91% of transcripts without specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer have no ‘free interval’, which means that they are completely covered by other transcripts, thus confirming the validation of the Kmerator process. The set of specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers designed with Kmerator strongly depends on the input sequence and on the level of selection. At the gene level, we observed that the length of the input sequence was correlated with the number of designed specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers (<italic toggle="yes">R</italic> = 0.91, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 2.2e−16; see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S3A</xref>) but not at the transcript level (<italic toggle="yes">R</italic> = 0.22, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 2.2e−16; see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S3B</xref>). On the contrary, the transcript level depends on the overlap between the input transcript and the different isoforms. A high number of isoforms is correlated to a low number of specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers (<italic toggle="yes">R</italic> = 0.79, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 2.2e−16; see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S3C</xref>) and, in addition, the length of free intervals is strongly correlated to the number of specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers (<italic toggle="yes">R</italic> = 0.94, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 2.2e−16; see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S3D</xref>). Finally, <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer design differs between biotypes and selection levels: the biotypes without specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers mainly correspond to small RNAs (miRNAs, rRNA) at the gene level (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S3E</xref>) and to coding and pseudo-genes at the transcript level (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S3F</xref>).</p>
      <p>The Kmerator Suite has been designed as a new way to explore RNA-seq data and rapidly quantify some chosen sequences called predictors. Kmerator, the first key element of this suite, can extract unique <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers from any sequence. In combination with countTags, it is used to generate large <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer count tables. To situate our tool in relation to a widely used, referenced and benchmarked quantification tool, we tested the Kmerator + countTags pipeline accuracy to estimate gene and transcript expression using simulated data (see the ‘Materials and Methods’ section). Indeed, using a simulated dataset, for which we have the exact counts, even if it fails to capture the complexity of real data, is the best way to proceed to illustrate our purpose (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). We have run Kmerator and countTags to search for all human gene and transcript expression levels in a set of 10 simulated data. We assessed Spearman’s correlation between normalized <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer counts and the ground truth. We used countTags <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer mean count per transcript reported to the total of <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers contained in the input fastq. As shown in Figure <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, the Spearman’s correlation factor comparing Kmerator + countTags results to the truth is 0.86 for the gene level (Figure <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2C</xref>) and 0.94 for the transcript level (see Figure <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2D</xref>), indicating a highly positive relationship with normalized counts (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 2e−16).</p>
      <p>Quantification results are comparable when using the Kallisto pseudo-alignment method, despite slightly higher correlation factors (gene and transcript <italic toggle="yes">R</italic> = 0.97; see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S4A and B</xref>). This result is consistent with the recent paper describing Matataki (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>), another quantification tool based on <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers. Our pipeline being not specifically dedicated to gene quantification but for rapid exploration of large datasets is accurate enough to evaluate gene and transcript expression levels in RNA-seq data. Interestingly, the precision of Kallisto quantification decreases strongly with transcripts/genes not covered by Kmerator (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S4C and D</xref>), showing that each protocol using the <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer principle struggles to correctly quantify sequences that do not possess distinctive <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers.</p>
      <p>Finally, we tested speed performance of countTags processing time on random subparts of sample simulated data (10 million, 101 nt paired-end reads), while increasing the number of quantified <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers (1/1000/1 million). It appears that processing time remains low compared to alignment-based protocols (∼1 min for 10 million reads) and depends on the number of <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers quantified (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S4E</xref>). These results support an optimized usage of the Kmerator Suite protocol for its primary usage: the research of a limited number of signatures in large RNA-seq datasets.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC3-2">
      <title>KmerExploR for inspecting large RNA-seq datasets</title>
      <p>We developed KmerExploR to improve the characterization of large RNA-seq datasets using the quantification of selected predictor genes. Predictor genes have been selected based on the literature to answer specific questions (see Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). As described in the ‘Materials and Methods’ section, we first extracted with Kmerator sets of specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers from gene sequences and use KmerExploR to count the <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer occurrences in RNA-seq datasets and visualize the results. Here, we present the results obtained with specific datasets (Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>) selected to highlight the rapid control of biological and technical parameters using KmerExploR. The results of the basic features, including sample sex, polyA or ribo-depletion, orientation and 5′/3′ bias, are presented in Figure <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>.</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F3">
        <label>Figure 3.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>KmerExploR default usage: basic features. All presented bar plots are direct output of KmerExploR and they are generated from the Dataset-FEATURES described in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref> (103 paired-end ENCODE samples) except for the orientation (C), which is a subset of eight RNA-seq from the Dataset-FEATURES. For each bar plot, the legend lists the set of predictor genes for which <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer mean counts are computed (see also Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Samples are on the <italic toggle="yes">X</italic>-axis. Panels (A), (B) and (C) have the mean <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer counts by gene normalized per billion of <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers on the <italic toggle="yes">Y</italic>-axis. <bold>(A)</bold> Sex determination. Samples are sorted by sex in the order female, then male. <bold>(B)</bold> PolyA+ selection versus ribo-depletion by histone detection. Samples are sorted by protocol in this order: polyA, ribo-depletion, unknown. <bold>(C)</bold> Stranded versus unstranded sequencing protocol. For this category, both fastq files by sample are shown. The first four samples are unstranded and the last four samples are stranded. <bold>(D)</bold> Read position biases along 5′ UTR, 3′ UTR and CDS regions. After computing <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer mean counts by gene, they are summed up by 5′ UTR, 3′ UTR or CDS regions and converted in % (<italic toggle="yes">Y</italic>-axis).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="lqab058fig3" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1">
        <label>Table 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>List of predictor genes, by category, included in KmerExploR and associated RNA-seq dataset names used in this paper</p>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Datasets</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predictor genes</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer number</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">References and details</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>PolyA/RiboD</bold>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dataset- FEATURES</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIST2H2AC, HIST2H2AB, HIST1H4J, HIST1H4I, HIST1H4F, HIST1H4D, HIST1H4C, HIST1H4B, HIST1H3I, HIST1H3H, HIST1H3G, HIST1H3F, HIST1H3E, HIST1H3C, HIST1H3B, HIST1H3A, HIST1H2BN, HIST1H2BM, HIST1H2BL, HIST1H2BH, HIST1H2BF, HIST1H2BE, HIST1H2BB, HIST1H2BA, HIST1H2AK, HIST1H2AH, HIST1H2AG, HIST1H2AB, HIST1H1T, HIST1H1E, HIST1H1D, HIST1H1B, HIST1H1A</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 512</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>Orientation</bold>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dataset- FEATURES</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VPS29, SNRPD3, REEP5, RAB7A, PSMB4, PSMB2, GPI, EMC7, CHMP2A, C1orf43, VPS29_rev, SNRPD3_rev, REEP5_rev, RAB7A_rev, PSMB4_rev, PSMB2_rev, GPI_rev, EMC7_rev, CHMP2A_rev, C1orf43_rev</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 638</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S2</xref> (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>Sex</bold>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dataset- FEATURES</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UTY, TMSB4Y, TBL1Y, RPS4Y1, NLGN4Y, EIF1AY, DDX3Y</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 996</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S2</xref> (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>5′/3′ bias</bold>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dataset- FEATURES</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VPS29, SNRPD3, REEP5, RAB7A, PSMB4, PSMB2, GPI, EMC7, CHMP2A, C1orf43</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 705</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S2</xref> (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>Mycoplasma</bold>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dataset-MYCO</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mycoplasma_orale, Mycoplasma_hyorhinis, Acholeplasma_laidlawii, Mycoplasma_hominis, Mycoplasma_arginini, Mycoplasma_fermentans</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">363 025</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>Virus</bold>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dataset-VIRUS-CCLE</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human_gammaherpesvirus_4, Human_herpesvirus_4, Human_herpesvirus_8, Murine_leukemia_virus, Hepatitis_C_virus_genotype, Human_immunodeficiency_virus_1, Human_T_lymphotropic_virus_1, Squirrel_monkey_retrovirus, Human_T_lymphotropic_virus_2, Human_papillomavirus_type_92, Hepatitis_B_virus_strain, Human_immunodeficiency_virus_2, MuLV_related_virus_22Rv1/CWR, Bovine_viral_diarrhea_virus</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">516 882</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>HeLa</bold>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dataset-HELA-CCLE</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">L1_mut7486, L1_mut7258, L1_mut6842, L1_mut6625, L1_mut6460, L1_mut6401, L1_mut5875, E7_mut806, E7_mut751, E6_mut549, E6_mut485, E6_mut287, E6_mut104, E1_mut2269, E1_mut1994, E1_mut1843, E1_mut1807, E1_mut1353, E1_mut1012</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">589</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>Species</bold>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dataset- SPECIES</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo_sapiens_MT_CO1, Danio_rerio_mt_co1, Zea_mays_COX1, Saccharomyces_cerevisiae_COX1, Rattus_norvegicus_Mt_co1, Mus_musculus_mt_Co1, Gallus_gallus_MT_CO1, Drosophila_melanogaster_mt_CoI, Caenorhabditis_elegans_ctc_3_MTCE, Arabidopsis_thaliana_COX1</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 119</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT-CO1 (and orthologs)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>Chimeras</bold>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dataset- LEUCEGENE</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PML–RARA, RARA–PML, RUNX1T1–RUNX1, RUNX1–RUNX1T1</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">724</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>lncRNA</bold>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dataset- LEUCEGENE</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NONE</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>Mutations</bold>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dataset- LEUCEGENE</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TET2, KRAS, CEBPA</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="T1TFN1">
            <p>The samples included in each dataset and some metadata are detailed in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>As previously described, sample sex is determined by searching for <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers corresponding to genes located on the Y chromosome. The <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer signature clearly separates samples depending on the sex. To help the user classify his samples, we defined, in KmerExploR, a threshold of five <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers per billion, above which we expect with confidence that it is a male. Moreover, Y chromosome gene expression variance between the samples can be explained by the variability of cell types and public RNA-seq experiment parameters, including sequencing depth and methods of RNA extraction and selection. For instance, the four male samples with the lowest expression (ENCFF232KGN, ENCFF434EMO, ENCFF831HCD and ENCFF992HBZ) come from a unique study (ENCSR999ZCI). However, the sex classification is more complicated in case of cancerous data. When we are looking at cancerous RNA-seq cell lines, some samples with male metadata show low Y chromosome-specific gene expression (data not shown). This extreme downregulation of chromosome Y gene expression has already been described in previous studies and strongly associated with cancer risk in men (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>).</p>
      <p>Gene abundance can be measured in RNA-seq data through sequencing of mRNA or ribo-depleted total RNA samples. The mRNA protocol relies on polyA selection, when the total RNA method is based on rRNA depletion (Ribozero protocol). However, non-polyadenylated transcripts should only be found in data produced using this procedure, when they should barely be detectable in mRNA samples. As the majority of histone transcripts are known to be non-polyadenylated, we used this characteristic first to detect sample contamination by non-polyadenylated RNA, and second to infer from the result the RNA preparation procedure. We first investigated the expression level of all histone genes and retained the most highly expressed according to the literature. Second, we analyzed their expression pattern using the GTEX resource. As RNA-seq from GTEX are exclusively produced from polyA selected RNA samples, we used this database to select histone genes showing the lowest expression levels (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S2B</xref>). We used this set of histone genes to test a selection of ENCODE samples that metadata indicates either polyA or ribo-depletion protocol (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>). The results clearly demonstrate differences between libraries prepared by ribo-depletion versus polyA selection for most of the chosen histone genes. We observe histone gene expression variability between the samples demonstrating again the disparity of public data. To help users categorize their RNA-seq data, we defined in the KmerExploR tool a threshold of 200 <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer counts per billion for this category, above which we expect to have only the ribo-depleted samples and not the polyA ones.</p>
      <p>Strand-specific and unstranded library preparation are two commonly used preparation protocols that differ by their ability to retain or not RNA strand information. To detect this characteristic from RNA-seq data, we designed <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers, specific for a set of ubiquitous genes (Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) and their reverse complement counterparts. <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>-mers on the forward strand are counted as positive and their reverse complement as negative, permitting to determine the orientation of the library. If forward and reverse tags are found in equivalent proportions in the same fastq file, data are considered as ‘unstranded’. This leads graphically to a balanced distribution between positive and negative counts. As shown in Figure <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, using this property we are able to clearly separate unstranded and stranded libraries. 5′ to 3′-end bias is a difference of reads’ repartition along the transcripts, classically linked to library preparation: incomplete retrotranscription or specific protocols. A comparison between polyA selection and ribo-depletion protocols has previously shown coverage differences across transcripts with a poor 5′-end coverage with the polyA selection method (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Knowing whether an RNA-seq sample possesses a read repartition bias is critical for isoform detection, or simply to give an indication on the library construction protocol used in large-scale analysis of public data. Using previously described housekeeping genes (Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), we have selected different sets of specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers depending on their position in the regions defined as 5′ UTR, 3′ UTR and CDS. Figure <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3C</xref> shows the repartition in percent of these <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers across the Dataset-FEATURES samples. Representing the mean <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer counts as a percentage allows us to evaluate the distribution homogeneity across 5′ UTR, 3′ UTR and CDS regions between the 103 ENCODE samples. This global representation grouping together several genes allows us to identify samples for which one region has a very little coverage. Here, four samples have &lt;10% 5′ UTR coverage (ENCFF734ZAD, ENCFF770NYA, ENCFF419GVS and ENCFF016TGP). We can also notice a better homogeneity of coverage for ribo-depleted samples.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC3-3">
      <title>Detection of potential contamination</title>
      <p>Different microorganisms like mycoplasma and virus can contaminate samples and cell cultures, modifying the metabolism of the cell and therefore biasing the results of ensuing analysis. Moreover, cancer research has shown that viruses are responsible for ∼20% of human cancers (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). To detect contaminants in RNA-seq data, tools relying on alignment like DecontaMiner (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) or viGEN (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>) have been widely used, but the alignment step is time and memory consuming. Exact alignment of <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer-based approaches like Kraken (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>) and Taxonomer (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>) is an alternative for taxonomic classification. However, these tools are complex and involve data cleaning from adaptors (trimming), the use of internal and external databases and/or probabilistic models for contaminant classification. Using a specific and reduced set of <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers, we have seen an advantage to quickly detect principal contaminants of human cells in RNA-seq datasets, free from alignment methods.</p>
      <p>Because mycoplasma is a common source of cell culture sample contamination and could affect host gene expression (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>), we choose to control its presence in RNA-seq data. Mycoplasma contamination is evaluated through the detection of specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers corresponding to 16S rRNA sequences according to the literature. In fact, Olarerin-George and Hogenesch showed that 90% of the specific mycoplasma-mapped reads from human RNA-seq samples mapped to mycoplasma rRNA. We selected six species that have the highest record rate of detection in cell culture samples (i.e. <italic toggle="yes">Acholeplasma laidlawii</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma fermentans</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma hominis</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma hyorhinis</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma orale</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma arginini</italic>) (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) to design our <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers. We used part of an RNA-seq data series previously described as highly contaminated (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) (PRJNA153913 study) to test the relevance of our approach. As shown in Figure <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, we can easily detect the six selected mycoplasma species in some samples, with a prevalence for the <italic toggle="yes">M. hyorhinis</italic> species. Comparing our results with the Olarerin-George and Hogenesch study that used Bowtie 1 alignment and BLAST+ to filter non-specific reads, we were able to confirm mycoplasma rRNA presence for the same samples (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S5A</xref>). Moreover, we observe a high proportionality between our <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer counts and their read counts on the 33 single-read samples (Dataset-MYCO described in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>), for each of the six common <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma</italic> species.</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F4">
        <label>Figure 4.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>KmerExploR default usage: contaminations. All presented bar plots are direct output of KmerExploR and all bar plot datasets are described in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>. For each bar plot, the legend lists the set of predictors for which <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer mean counts are computed (details in Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Samples are on the <italic toggle="yes">X</italic>-axis. Panels (A), (B) and (D) have the mean <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer counts by gene normalized per billion of <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers on the <italic toggle="yes">Y</italic>-axis. <bold>(A)</bold> Mycoplasma contamination on the Dataset-MYCO (33 single-read samples). <bold>(B)</bold> Virus detection on the Dataset-VIRUS-CCLE (22 paired-end samples). <bold>(C)</bold> Species determination on the Dataset-SPECIES (27 paired-end samples). For this category, after computing <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer mean counts by species, they are converted in % (<italic toggle="yes">Y</italic>-axis) to avoid big expression differences between species. <bold>(D)</bold> HeLa determination on the Dataset-HELA-CCLE (three paired-end samples). The sample in the middle is a HeLa cell line and the two others are negative controls (SF767 and SiHa cells).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="lqab058fig4" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Viruses are a significant cause of human cancers. Several studies interrogate for the presence of major viruses known to infect human and other mammalian cells (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Recently, Uphoff <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> screened &gt;300 CCLE RNA-seq data using the Taxonomer interactive tool and compared the results to virus-specific polymerase chain reaction (PCR) analysis, revealing 20 infected cell lines with different viruses (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). To rapidly explore the potential presence of viruses in RNA-seq datasets with our <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer-based approach, we used the same virus reference genomes as described in the Uphoff <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> study. Using Kmerator at the chimera level (absent from human annotations), we designed specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers for each virus and searched them in a subset of contaminated CCLE data according to Uphoff <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (19 CCLE paired-end samples) and in negative controls (3 CCLE paired-end samples), to validate our protocol ability to detect viruses. Among the contaminated samples, we were able to detect the main viruses in the same samples as in the Uphoff <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> study, except for the SRR8615677 sample where we do not detect any virus, as the bovine polyomavirus is not included in our list of common viruses. Our results are shown in Figure <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4B</xref> and Taxonomer results from the Uphoff <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> study are presented in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S5B</xref>. Epstein–Barr virus (EBV) is a very common virus detected in most of the samples; we have therefore analyzed it in more detail in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figures S5C</xref> (our approach) and S5D (Taxonomer quantification). Indeed, our EBV quantification is correlated with the one from Taxonomer (Pearson’s and Spearman’s correlation coefficients are 0.99 and 0.89, respectively).</p>
      <p>HeLa is the first immortal human cell line, coming from Henrietta Lacks’ cancerous tissue samples. Her cancer was triggered by an infection with human papillomavirus type 18 (HPV-18). Nowadays, this cell line is largely used in medical research. Looking for several viruses in public RNA-seq cancer-related databases revealed the presence of HPV-18 sequences in many cancers (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) that closely resemble the HPV-18 viral sequence that is integrated into HeLa cells, suggesting a contamination. Three segments of HPV-18 are integrated into the HeLa genome on chromosome 8 and include the long control region, the E6, E7 and E1 genes, and partial coding regions for the E2 and L1 genes (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). These genes are expressed in HeLa cells, and mutations have been found specifically in HeLa cells. Thus, selecting these mutated HeLa HPV-18 gene-specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers and counting them into three CCLE RNA-seq datasets (one positive sample and two negative controls), we validated the accuracy of our selection as we are able to find our <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer selection specifically in HeLa cells. We also checked the results in other HeLa samples from the PRJNA639358 study (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S5E</xref>).</p>
      <p>As for HeLa cells, cross-species contamination remains a documented ‘danger’ for the interpretation of results in molecular biology (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). The probability of mixed cell lines in sample preparation, usage of PCR that can accidentally amplify the wrong piece of DNA, and an unknown probability of error in metadata assignation motivated us to create a quality check to determine the species of an RNA-seq sample. In (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>), the usage of mitochondrial DNA for phylogenetic and taxonomic inference was discussed and two extreme viewpoints emerged: using exclusively the mitochondrial DNA or fully excluding it. It appears that mitochondrial DNA does not fully answer or impairs the perspectives of advanced phylogenetics. However, the ‘mitochondrial barcode’ approach does show an interesting gene marker, MT-CO1 (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>), that could be sufficient for a quick check of the species of RNA-seq data. Indeed, this gene is highly expressed and reference sequences from many distinct species of animals are available. Thus, we selected specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers with Kmerator, at the gene level, for MT-CO1. We repeated the procedure for MT-CO1 orthologs in different species, principally found in the SRA database, using the appropriate species reference genome and transcriptome. These <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers have been then quantified in three public data by species to check the efficiency of their usage. As shown in Figure <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4C</xref>, the research of MT-CO1 <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers alone can discriminate most of the common Ensembl species and can be usable for a quick quality check. However, without proper experiments we cannot support its usage with phylogenetically close species.</p>
      <p>To conclude, we developed KmerExploR to rapidly control RNA-seq raw data quality and filter samples on unusual profiles or presence of contaminations. KmerExploR is a tool that provides a modular set of analyses like fastQC (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://qubeshub.org/resources/fastqc" ext-link-type="uri">https://qubeshub.org/resources/fastqc</ext-link>). It can be used in a complementary way to fastQC analysis to complete missing metadata in public datasets or to give a quick profile of the RNA-seq contents. The modular analysis is based on a <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer selection from predictor genes, included in KmerExploR. The tool can be used to control any human RNA-seq dataset, and it can also be easily modified adding any other modular function.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC3-4">
      <title>KmerExploR, an advanced usage for the detection of genomic or transcriptomic events</title>
      <p>The above ‘checking application’ of KmerExploR demonstrated all its potential in the rapid exploration of large public RNA-seq datasets before performing any biological query. However, the KmerExploR tool can also be used in a more advanced way such as biomarker search or discovery in human health. This application is a powerful one as it can compensate for the lack of completeness in genomic or transcriptomic references and we currently know that much important information may be missed by ignoring the unreferenced RNA diversity (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). As a proof of concept, we used a set of <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers designed with Kmerator to identify events outside reference annotations including fusion or chimeric RNA, oncogene mutations and new lncRNA expression. We then applied <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer quantification in a tumoral and a non-tumoral dataset to evaluate the specificity and performance of the approach. The results obtained with a part of the Leucegene cohort are presented in Figure <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>.</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F5">
        <label>Figure 5.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>KmerExploR advanced usage: quantification of transcriptomic events outside the annotations. All presented bar plots are direct output of KmerExploR and they are all generated from the Dataset-LEUCEGENE described in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref> (131 paired-end samples). This dataset includes normal CD34<sup>+</sup> cells as control (in green on the <italic toggle="yes">X</italic>-axis) and different AML subtypes (in black on the <italic toggle="yes">X</italic>-axis). For each bar plot, the legend lists the set of predictors for which <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer mean counts normalized per billion (<italic toggle="yes">Y</italic>-axis) are computed. <bold>(A)</bold> Chimera detection. Two well-known fusion RNAs associated with chromosomal translocation and their reciprocal counterparts are presented: RUNX1–RUNXT1 t(<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>,21) and PML–RARA t(15,17). <bold>(B)</bold> Mutation detection. TET2, KRAS and CEBPA genes are used in AML diagnosis. The bar plot shows four different mutations for these genes, detected specifically in some AML samples. The reference allele for each of these mutations is detected in almost all samples. <bold>(C)</bold> New lncRNA detection: NONE ‘chr2-p21’ lncRNA described in (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). This transcript is expressed in the whole dataset but shows different levels of expression depending on AML subtype.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="lqab058fig5" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The selection includes different AML subtypes and normal CD34<sup>+</sup> cells as control (Dataset-LEUCEGENE described in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>). The results obtained with two well-known fusion RNAs associated with chromosomal translocation, RUNX1–RUNXT1 t(<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>,21) and PML–RARA t(15,17), and their reciprocal counterparts RUNXT1–RUNX1 and RARA–PML are presented in Figure <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>. In this case, the <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers, once designed by Kmerator, are restricted to those spanning the fusion junction with at least 10 nucleotides in gene 1 or gene 2 of the fusion. All the normal CD34<sup>+</sup> cells are negative and we only observe an expression in corresponding positive AML subtypes. Figure <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">5B</xref> illustrates the results obtained for mutations in TET2, KRAS and CEBPA genes currently used in AML diagnosis. Once again, we only observe the presence of these mutations in positive samples, demonstrating the high specificity of the approach by <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers. The expression of a new lncRNA was also quickly searched in the Leucegene dataset (see Figure <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">5C</xref>); we observe a homogeneous and low expression in CD34 normal cells compared to a heterogeneous one in AML subtypes. This lncRNA candidate was already described in (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>), using for the first time the ‘<italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer concept’ for checking new biomarker candidates, and we have demonstrated a restricted expression of the NONE ‘chr2-p21’ lncRNA in the hematopoietic lineage using the Leucegene and ENCODE datasets. Hence, for lncRNA candidates, following their discovery in a tissue/disease type, their specificity could be easily evaluated through quantification in a wide range of RNA-seq data including normal and pathological conditions as recently described by Riquier <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>).</p>
      <p>In conclusion, the high specific expression of transcriptional events may lead them to be used as biomarkers for biological and health applications, including cell therapy, diagnosis, prognosis or patient follow-up as it is already done with fusion RNAs and mutations.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="discussion" id="SEC4">
    <title>DISCUSSION</title>
    <p>Considering the growing number of RNA-seq data, the use of raw data sequences is an important step to check with RNA-seq protocols or bioinformatic pipelines bias. Here, we demonstrated that the Kmerator Suite is an efficient and useful set of tools to verify RNA-seq quality and control intrinsic method and biological characteristics that often failed in technical description. We also showed that the Kmerator Suite can be used to quantify gene/transcript-specific expression as well as to explore sequence variations at the transcriptional level. In this first version, the tool is adapted to human data Ensembl entry, as main public data are available for this species (164 000 RNA-seq with &gt;30 million reads for <italic toggle="yes">Homo sapiens</italic> in the SRA database). A new implementation with adapted predictors is necessary for other species.</p>
    <p>The meta-analyses performed in the present study with KmerExploR are a proof of concept of the procedure potential and could be extended to other biological RNA-seq questioning: (i) to extend the application to an enlarged set of microorganisms including new ones like SARS-Cov2 detection and (ii) to search for immunophenotyping profile in cancer datasets as already published by Mangul <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Considering advanced applications, we also demonstrated the potential of <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers to explore gene expression in RNA-seq to reinforce biological questions or biomarker usage and discovery. Moreover, many other requests could be easily considered for annotated gene exploration like gene co-expression, or to compensate the lack of completeness in genomic or transcriptomic references to cover unreferenced RNA diversity and search for new spliced events, intron retention or new transcript categories including circular RNAs. In order to increase the potential of the <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer approach, access to very large-scale datasets like SRA level (164 000 human samples) could be considered with efficient indexing structure development (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>).</p>
    <p>Finally, we showed that the Kmerator Suite can be used to quantify gene/transcript expression as well as to explore sequence variations at the transcriptional level. The simplicity of specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer extraction principle and quantification provide flexibility of usage. Indeed, Kmerator Suite quantification does not use probabilistic methods or expectation–maximization algorithms like in Kallisto (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), Sailfish (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>) or RNA-Skim (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). Therefore, the sets of specific <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers for quantification can be created, merged and updated at will, without consequence on the quantification itself. The principle of user-owned collection of signatures of interest that can be searched broadly among datasets is the core of KmerExploR application.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="SEC5">
    <title>DATA AVAILABILITY</title>
    <p>RNA-seq libraries were downloaded from the European Nucleotide Archive of the European Bioinformatics Institute (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). The reference GRCh38 genome and Ensembl v91 transcripts were downloaded from Ensembl. Kmerator is distributed under the MIT license. The Kmerator, KmerExploR and countTags software, documentation and supplementary material presented herein are available from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://github.com/Transipedia/kmerator" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/Transipedia/kmerator</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://github.com/Transipedia/kmerexplor" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/Transipedia/kmerexplor</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://github.com/Transipedia/countTags" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/Transipedia/countTags,</ext-link> respectively.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
      <label>lqab058_Supplemental_Files</label>
      <media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="lqab058_supplemental_files.zip">
        <caption>
          <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
        </caption>
      </media>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack id="ACK1">
    <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
    <p>The authors are grateful to Henrietta Lacks, now deceased, and to her surviving family members for their contributions to biomedical research. The HeLa cell line that was established from her tumor cells without her knowledge or consent in 1951 has made significant contributions to scientific progress and advances in human health. The authors are also grateful to Rayan Chikhi for his comments and corrections.</p>
    <p><italic toggle="yes">Author contributions</italic>: S.R. and T.C. designed the study. S.R., C.B. and T.C. wrote the manuscript. A.-L.B., N.G. and D.G. were contributors in the design of the study and manuscript corrections. S.R. developed the code of Kmerator, selected and downloaded public datasets, and analyzed data. B.G. and C.B. participated in Kmerator code improvements. C.B. analyzed RNA-seq data and generated figures. B.G. developed KmerExploR code, and generated <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer counting and figures. J.A. and A.B. computed and corrected countTags. F.R. validated the RNA-seq data for mutation and chimeric RNAs, and helped in the interpretation of results. H.X. participated in Kmerator testing and checking. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
  </ack>
  <sec id="SEC6">
    <title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title>
    <p><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://nargab.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nargab/lqab058#supplementary-data" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Data</ext-link> are available at NARGAB Online.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="SEC7">
    <title>FUNDING</title>
    <p>Agence Nationale de la recherche [ANR-10-INBS-09]; Canceropole Grand Ouest [2017-EM24]; Region Occitanie [R19073FF].</p>
    <p><italic toggle="yes">Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p>
  </sec>
  <ref-list id="REF1">
    <title>REFERENCES</title>
    <ref id="B1">
      <label>1.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Collado-Torres</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nellore</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kammers</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taub</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>K.D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jaffe</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leek</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Reproducible RNA-seq analysis using recount2</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><year>2017</year>; <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>319</fpage>–<lpage>321</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28398307</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B2">
      <label>2.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Byron</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Keuren-Jensen</surname><given-names>K.R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Engelthaler</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carpten</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Translating RNA sequencing into clinical diagnostics: opportunities and challenges</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Genet.</source><year>2016</year>; <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>257</fpage>–<lpage>271</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26996076</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B3">
      <label>3.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z.J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>RNA biomarkers: frontier of precision medicine for cancer</article-title>. <source>Non-Coding RNA</source>. <year>2017</year>; <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B4">
      <label>4.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hippen</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Expanding and remixing the metadata landscape</article-title>. <source>Trends Cancer</source>. <year>2020</year>; <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>276</fpage>–<lpage>278</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33229213</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B5">
      <label>5.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dobin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schlesinger</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drenkow</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zaleski</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Batut</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chaisson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gingeras</surname><given-names>T.R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>STAR: ultrafast universal RNA-seq aligner</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23104886</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B6">
      <label>6.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Philippe</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Commes</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rivals</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>CRAC: an integrated approach to the analysis of RNA-seq reads</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2013</year>; <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>R30</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23537109</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B7">
      <label>7.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>N.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pimentel</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Melsted</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pachter</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Near-optimal probabilistic RNA-seq quantification</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><year>2016</year>; <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>525</fpage>–<lpage>527</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27043002</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B8">
      <label>8.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Patro</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duggal</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>M.I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Irizarry</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kingsford</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Salmon provides fast and bias-aware quantification of transcript expression</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>. <year>2017</year>; <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>419</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28263959</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B9">
      <label>9.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Okamura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kinoshita</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Matataki: an ultrafast mRNA quantification method for large-scale reanalysis of RNA-seq data</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2018</year>; <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>266</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30012088</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B10">
      <label>10.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Magner</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>SeqOthello: querying RNA-seq experiments at scale</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2018</year>; <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>167</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30340508</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B11">
      <label>11.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Audoux</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Philippe</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chikhi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gallopin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gabriel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Le Coz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drouineau</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Commes</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gautheret</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>DE-kupl: exhaustive capture of biological variation in RNA-seq data through <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer decomposition</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2017</year>; <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>243</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29284518</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B12">
      <label>12.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Morillon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gautheret</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Bridging the gap between reference and real transcriptomes</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2019</year>; <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>112</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31159855</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B13">
      <label>13.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Marçais</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kingsford</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>A fast, lock-free approach for efficient parallel counting of occurrences of <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>764</fpage>–<lpage>770</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21217122</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B14">
      <label>14.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Soneson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>compcodeR: an R package for benchmarking differential expression methods for RNA-seq data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>2517</fpage>–<lpage>2518</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24813215</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B15">
      <label>15.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Frazee</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jaffe</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leek</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Polyester: simulating RNA-seq datasets with differential transcript expression</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>2778</fpage>–<lpage>2784</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25926345</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B16">
      <label>16.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Levanon</surname><given-names>E.Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Human housekeeping genes, revisited</article-title>. <source>Trends Genet.</source><year>2013</year>; <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>569</fpage>–<lpage>574</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23810203</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B17">
      <label>17.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Maan</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eales</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Akbarov</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rowland</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jobling</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Charchar</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tomaszewski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>The Y chromosome: a blueprint for men’s health?</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Hum. Genet.</source><year>2017</year>; <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>1181</fpage>–<lpage>1188</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28853720</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B18">
      <label>18.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Drexler</surname><given-names>H.G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Uphoff</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Mycoplasma contamination of cell cultures: incidence, sources, effects, detection, elimination, prevention</article-title>. <source>Cytotechnology</source>. <year>2002</year>; <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19003295</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B19">
      <label>19.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parfrey</surname><given-names>L.W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yarza</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gerken</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pruesse</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quast</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schweer</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peplies</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ludwig</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Glöckner</surname><given-names>F.O.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>The SILVA and ‘All-species Living Tree Project (LTP)’ taxonomic frameworks</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2014</year>; <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>D643</fpage>–<lpage>D648</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24293649</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B20">
      <label>20.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cantalupo</surname><given-names>P.G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pipas</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>HeLa nucleic acid contamination in The Cancer Genome Atlas leads to the misidentification of human papillomavirus 18</article-title>. <source>J. Virol.</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>89</volume>:<fpage>4051</fpage>–<lpage>4057</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25631090</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B21">
      <label>21.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Okonechnikov</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Golosova</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fursov</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Unipro UGENE: a unified bioinformatics toolkit</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>1166</fpage>–<lpage>1167</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22368248</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B22">
      <label>22.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Uphoff</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pommerenke</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Denkmann</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drexler</surname><given-names>H.G.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Screening human cell lines for viral infections applying RNA-seq data analysis</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2019</year>; <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>e0210404</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30629668</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B23">
      <label>23.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rufflé</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Audoux</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boureux</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beaumeunier</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gaillard</surname><given-names>J.-B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bou Samra</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Megarbane</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cassinat</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chomienne</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>New chimeric RNAs in acute myeloid leukemia</article-title>. <source>F1000Res.</source><year>2017</year>; <volume>6</volume>:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12688/f1000research.11352.2</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B24">
      <label>24.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Prensner</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Iyer</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Balbin</surname><given-names>O.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dhanasekaran</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laxman</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Asangani</surname><given-names>I.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grasso</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kominsky</surname><given-names>H.D.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Transcriptome sequencing across a prostate cancer cohort identifies PCAT-1, an unannotated lincRNA implicated in disease progression</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><year>2011</year>; <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>742</fpage>–<lpage>749</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21804560</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B25">
      <label>25.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Olarerin-George</surname><given-names>A.O.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hogenesch</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Assessing the prevalence of mycoplasma contamination in cell culture via a survey of NCBI’s RNA-seq archive</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>2535</fpage>–<lpage>2542</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25712092</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B26">
      <label>26.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mangul</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>A.K.-M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Distler</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zelikovsky</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eskin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Systematic benchmarking of omics computational tools</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2019</year>; <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1393</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30918265</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B27">
      <label>27.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cáceres</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jene</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Esko</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pérez-Jurado</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>González</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Extreme downregulation of chromosome Y and cancer risk in men</article-title>. <source>J. Natl Cancer Inst.</source><year>2020</year>; <volume>112</volume>:<fpage>913</fpage>–<lpage>920</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31945786</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B28">
      <label>28.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>A comparison between ribo-minus RNA-sequencing and polyA-selected RNA-sequencing</article-title>. <source>Genomics</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>96</volume>:<fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>265</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20688152</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B29">
      <label>29.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>McLaughlin-Drubin</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Munger</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Viruses associated with human cancer</article-title>. <source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>1782</volume>:<fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18201576</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B30">
      <label>30.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sangiovanni</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Granata</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thind</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guarracino</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>From trash to treasure: detecting unexpected contamination in unmapped NGS data</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2019</year>; <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>168</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30999839</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B31">
      <label>31.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bhuvaneshwar</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Madhavan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gusev</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>viGEN: an open source pipeline for the detection and quantification of viral RNA in human tumors</article-title>. <source>Front. Microbiol.</source><year>2018</year>; <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1172</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29922260</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B32">
      <label>32.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Improved metagenomic analysis with Kraken 2</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2019</year>; <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>257</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31779668</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B33">
      <label>33.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Flygare</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simmon</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Di Sera</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Graf</surname><given-names>E.H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tardif</surname><given-names>K.D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kapusta</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rynearson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Taxonomer: an interactive metagenomics analysis portal for universal pathogen detection and host mRNA expression profiling</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2016</year>; <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27224977</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B34">
      <label>34.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Strong</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>W.N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Concha</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Grady</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baddoo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fewell</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Renne</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>High-throughput RNA sequencing-based virome analysis of 50 lymphoma cell lines from the Cancer Cell Line Encyclopedia Project</article-title>. <source>J. Virol.</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>89</volume>:<fpage>713</fpage>–<lpage>729</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25355872</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B35">
      <label>35.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cantalupo</surname><given-names>P.G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pipas</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Viral sequences in human cancer</article-title>. <source>Virology</source>. <year>2018</year>; <volume>513</volume>:<fpage>208</fpage>–<lpage>216</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29107929</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B36">
      <label>36.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Selitsky</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marron</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hollern</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mose</surname><given-names>L.E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoadley</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dittmer</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perou</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Virus expression detection reveals RNA-sequencing contamination in TCGA</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>. <year>2020</year>; <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31992194</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B37">
      <label>37.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ballenghien</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Faivre</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Galtier</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Patterns of cross-contamination in a multispecies population genomic project: detection, quantification, impact, and solutions</article-title>. <source>BMC Biol.</source><year>2017</year>; <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>25</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28356154</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B38">
      <label>38.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rubinoff</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Between two extremes: mitochondrial DNA is neither the panacea nor the nemesis of phylogenetic and taxonomic inference</article-title>. <source>Syst. Biol.</source><year>2005</year>; <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>952</fpage>–<lpage>961</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16385775</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B39">
      <label>39.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>P. D.N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cywinska</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>deWaard</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Biological identifications through DNA barcodes</article-title>. <source>Proc. R. Soc. Lond. B: Biol. Sci.</source><year>2003</year>; <volume>270</volume>:<fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>321</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B40">
      <label>40.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Riquier</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mathieu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bessiere</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boureux</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruffle</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lemaitre</surname><given-names>J.-M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Djouad</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Commes</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Long non-coding RNA exploration for mesenchymal stem cell characterisation</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>. <year>2021</year>; <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>412</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34088266</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B41">
      <label>41.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mangul</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H.T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Strauli</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gruhl</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Porath</surname><given-names>H.T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Daley</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Christenson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wesolowska-Andersen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>ROP: dumpster diving in RNA-sequencing to find the source of 1 trillion reads across diverse adult human tissues</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2018</year>; <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>36</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29548336</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B42">
      <label>42.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mandric</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rotman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H.T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Strauli</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Montoya</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Der Wey</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ronas</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Statz</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petrova</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Profiling immunoglobulin repertoires across multiple human tissues using RNA sequencing</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2020</year>; <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>3126</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32561710</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B43">
      <label>43.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Marchet</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boucher</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Puglisi</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Medvedev</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chikhi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Data structures based on <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers for querying large collections of sequencing datasets</article-title>. <source>Genome Research</source>. <year>2021</year>; <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33328168</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B44">
      <label>44.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Patro</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mount</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kingsford</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Sailfish enables alignment-free isoform quantification from RNA-seq reads using lightweight algorithms</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><year>2014</year>; <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>462</fpage>–<lpage>464</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24752080</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B45">
      <label>45.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>RNA-Skim: a rapid method for RNA-seq quantification at transcript level</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>i283</fpage>–<lpage>i292</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24931995</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B46">
      <label>46.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Silvester</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alako</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amid</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cerdeño-Tarrága</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cleland</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>P.W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jayathilaka</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Keane</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>The European Nucleotide Archive in 2017</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2018</year>; <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>D36</fpage>–<lpage>D40</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29140475</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
