<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?properties open_access?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1367-4803</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1367-4811</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8826084</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34904625</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btab837</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">btab837</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Applications Notes</subject>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading">
          <subject>Sequence Analysis</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01060</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>PHIST: fast and accurate prediction of prokaryotic hosts from metagenomic viral sequences</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8096-3776</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Zielezinski</surname>
          <given-names>Andrzej</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="btab837-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
        <aff><institution>Department of Computational Biology, Adam Mickiewicz University</institution>, Poznan 61-614, <country country="PL">Poland</country></aff>
        <!--andrzej.zielezinski@amu.edu.pl-->
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9496-733X</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Deorowicz</surname>
          <given-names>Sebastian</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Faculty of Automatic Control, Electronics and Computer Science, Silesian University of Technology</institution>, Gliwice 44-100, <country country="PL">Poland</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5508-0090</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Gudyś</surname>
          <given-names>Adam</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="btab837-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
        <!--adam.gudys@polsl.pl-->
        <aff><institution>Faculty of Automatic Control, Electronics and Computer Science, Silesian University of Technology</institution>, Gliwice 44-100, <country country="PL">Poland</country></aff>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name>
          <surname>Robinson</surname>
          <given-names>Peter</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Associate Editor</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="btab837-cor1">To whom correspondence should be addressed. <email>andrzej.zielezinski@amu.edu.pl</email> or <email>adam.gudys@polsl.pl</email></corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <day>01</day>
      <month>3</month>
      <year>2022</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2021-12-14">
      <day>14</day>
      <month>12</month>
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>14</day>
      <month>12</month>
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>38</volume>
    <issue>5</issue>
    <fpage>1447</fpage>
    <lpage>1449</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>08</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>09</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="editorial-decision">
        <day>08</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>09</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="corrected-typeset">
        <day>18</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2021. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xlink:href="btab837.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <sec id="s1">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <p>Phage–Host Interaction Search Tool (PHIST) predicts prokaryotic hosts of viruses based on exact matches between viral and host genomes. It improves host prediction accuracy at species level over current alignment-based tools (on average by 3 percentage points) as well as alignment-free and CRISPR-based tools (by 14–20 percentage points). PHIST is also two orders of magnitude faster than alignment-based tools making it suitable for metagenomics studies.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2">
        <title>Availability and implementation</title>
        <p>GNU-licensed C++ code wrapped in Python API available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/refresh-bio/phist" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/refresh-bio/phist</ext-link>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4">
        <title>Supplementary information</title>
        <p><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary data</xref> are available at <italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic> online.</p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>National Science Centre</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100004281</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>2018/31/D/NZ2/00108</award-id>
        <award-id>DEC-2016/21/D/ST6/02952</award-id>
        <award-id>DEC-2019/33/B/ST6/02040</award-id>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="7"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec>
    <title>1 Introduction</title>
    <p>Viruses of prokaryotes constitute the vast majority of the global virosphere and play an important role in balancing ecosystems by regulating the composition of bacteria and archaea worldwide. Computational tools allow a routine discovery of previously unknown viruses in metagenomic samples from a wide range of environments (<xref rid="btab837-B7" ref-type="bibr">Nayfach <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>; <xref rid="btab837-B8" ref-type="bibr">Paez-Espino <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="btab837-B9" ref-type="bibr">Ren <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). However, little is known about biology of these novel viruses and the hosts with which they interact since isolation and characterization of viruses is remarkably laborious and time-consuming (<xref rid="btab837-B5" ref-type="bibr">Edwards <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). Computational tools have been developed to predict prokaryotic hosts from metagenome-derived virus sequences based on the molecular signals of virus–host coevolution, including sequence homology (alignment-based tools), sequence composition similarity between viruses and their hosts (alignment-free tools) and matches to host-encoded CRISPR (Clustered Regularly Interspaced Short Palindromic Repeat) spacers (<xref rid="btab837-B3" ref-type="bibr">Coclet and Roux, 2021</xref>).</p>
    <p>Alignment-based tools [e.g. BLASTN (<xref rid="btab837-B2" ref-type="bibr">Altschul <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>), Phirbo (<xref rid="btab837-B12" ref-type="bibr">Zielezinski <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>)] produce the highest host prediction accuracy of 25–44% at the species level (i.e. percentage of viruses with a correctly predicted host species; for details, see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Material</xref>). Nevertheless, these tools have considerable time and memory requirements for large datasets, which hinders their use in metagenomic studies. Alignment-free tools [e.g. WIsH (<xref rid="btab837-B6" ref-type="bibr">Galiez <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>)] compensate for low speed at the cost of reduced prediction accuracy (18–28% at the species level). Finally, CRISPR-based tools [e.g. SpacePHARER (<xref rid="btab837-B11" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>)] can provide direct evidence supporting virus–host interactions, but these methods have low prediction accuracy because not many viruses share CRISPR regions with hosts and not many hosts have CRISPR system (<xref rid="btab837-B5" ref-type="bibr">Edwards et al., 2016</xref>). Here, we introduce Phage–Host Interaction Search Tool (PHIST), a simple tool that allows a fast and accurate host prediction that can be performed on a standard workstation or even a personal laptop computer.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>2 Materials and methods</title>
    <p>PHIST takes as input two directories containing compressed or uncompressed FASTA files of genomic sequences of viruses and candidate hosts, respectively. The tool links viruses to hosts based on the number of <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers shared between their sequences. PHIST is built upon the Kmer-db tool (<xref rid="btab837-B4" ref-type="bibr">Deorowicz <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>) using its recently developed mode of determining numbers of shared <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mers (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Material</xref>). PHIST outputs a CSV file with a matrix of common <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-mer counts between every virus and prokaryote, and a summary CSV file reporting top scoring hosts for each virus. In addition, PHIST provides <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values for the predicted virus–host pairs (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Material</xref>). Information on reference datasets and benchmarking host prediction tools is provided in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Material</xref>.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>3 Results</title>
    <p>We evaluated the performance of PHIST on a reference dataset of 2288 viral genomes and 62 493 complete and draft prokaryotic genomes from (<xref rid="btab837-B10" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). PHIST correctly identified the hosts species for 29.5% of viruses representing an improvement by 4 percentage points over Phirbo and BLASTN (<xref rid="btab837-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig.  1A</xref>). A similar, minor enhancement at the species level (1–2 percentage points) was obtained on two previously published benchmark sets (<xref rid="btab837-B5" ref-type="bibr">Edwards <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="btab837-B6" ref-type="bibr">Galiez <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>) (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Material</xref>). The tool also had the highest host prediction accuracy at the species level when considering the top five predicted host species (i.e. host species with highest similarity to the query virus) (<xref rid="btab837-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig.  1B</xref>). PHIST recovered most of the virus–host interaction pairs that were correctly predicted by other approaches. Specifically, our tool recalled 86% (486 out of 561), 85% (481/563), 93% (353/381), 85% (277/329) and 85% (248/292) virus–host pairs that were correctly predicted by BLASTN, Phirbo, WIsH, SpacePHARER and PILER-CR, respectively (<xref rid="btab837-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig.  1C</xref>).</p>
    <fig position="float" id="btab837-F1">
      <label>Fig. 1.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>(<bold>A</bold>) Host prediction accuracy for 2288 viral genomes against 62 493 candidate hosts, binned by host taxonomic level. (<bold>B</bold>) Host prediction accuracy at the species level across five highest scoring prokaryotic species for each virus sequence (the prediction was scored as correct if the correct host species was among the first five predicted hosts). (<bold>C</bold>) Unique and shared correct virus–host predictions among the tools. The bar chart indicates the intersection size of viruses with correct host prediction at the species level. Connected dots on the bottom panel indicate which pair of tools is considered for each intersection. (<bold>D</bold>) Runtime and memory usage for 2288 viruses and 62 493 prokaryotes. Time and memory measurements of Phirbo also include BLASTN, and SpacePHARER includes PILER-CR analysis. (<bold>E</bold>) Prediction accuracies for contigs subsampled at various lengths from the 2288 virus genomes. The solid line shows the mean prediction accuracy at host taxonomic level and the grey shade indicates the 95% confidence interval. The horizontal dashed line marks the prediction accuracy using the full-length viral genomes. (<bold>F</bold> and <bold>G</bold>) Proportions of congruent predictions for viral contigs between PHIST and those in Paez-Espino <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> and Nayfach <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, respectively. (<bold>H</bold>) Viral assignments to human gut bacteria and archaea. Distribution of host classes reported by Nayfach <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (upper bar chart) and a set of PHIST predictions on viruses that were not assigned to hosts by Nayfach <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (lower bar chart)</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="btab837f1" position="float"/>
    </fig>
    <p>PHIST took an hour to process the dataset (approximately 143 million pairwise comparisons between 2288 viruses and 62 492 candidate hosts) on a 16-core 2.1 GHz Intel Xeon, almost 300 times faster than BLASTN and Phirbo, 16 times faster than WIsH and 2–4 times faster than CRISPR-based tools (<xref rid="btab837-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig.  1D</xref>).</p>
    <p>To evaluate the performance of host prediction for short viral contigs, we randomly subsampled fragments of different lengths (1, 2, 5, 10 and 20 kb) from each of the 2288 viral genomes. The mean host prediction accuracy at the genus and family levels dropped by 9 and 11 percentage points, respectively, for 20–3 kb long contigs (<xref rid="btab837-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig.  1E</xref>). At the species level, however, the prediction accuracy fell by only 3 percentage points (from 26% to 23%) for 20 kb to 3 kb long contigs. We also tested PHIST on a set of 125 842 metagenomic viral contigs (MVCs) of 11 kb median length obtained from various environments (<xref rid="btab837-B8" ref-type="bibr">Paez-Espino <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). The original host prediction used CRISPR-spacer and tRNA sequence matches, and assigned hosts for only 7.9% of the MVCs. PHIST annotated 99% of the MVCs; moreover, the predictions matched the original predictions in 30% at the species level and achieved 80% consistency at the genus level (<xref rid="btab837-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig.  1F</xref>).</p>
    <p>The resulting accuracies can be considered as lower bounds since metagenomic studies restrict the set of candidate host genomes to those present in the sample (<xref rid="btab837-B6" ref-type="bibr">Galiez <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). Thus, we used a set of 189 680 metagenomic viral sequences from human gut provided by <xref rid="btab837-B7" ref-type="bibr">Nayfach <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2021)</xref>, who predicted the hosts among 286 997 genomes of bacteria and archaea from the Unified Human Gastrointestinal Genome collection (<xref rid="btab837-B1" ref-type="bibr">Almeida <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>). The original host prediction used a combination of CRISPR-spacer matches and whole-genome alignments between viruses and candidate hosts (<xref rid="btab837-B7" ref-type="bibr">Nayfach <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>) and assigned hosts to 90% of the viral contigs (<italic toggle="yes">n </italic>=<italic toggle="yes"> </italic>170 072). PHIST annotated 99.95% of the viral contigs (<italic toggle="yes">n </italic>=<italic toggle="yes"> </italic>189 586) and provided an overall 81% agreement on host taxonomy with the original predictions (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Material</xref>). Using the <xref rid="btab837-B7" ref-type="bibr">Nayfach <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2021)</xref> annotation as reference, PHIST obtained 68 and 81% host prediction accuracy at the species and genus levels, respectively (<xref rid="btab837-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig.  1G</xref>). The remaining viral genomes that were not assigned to hosts in Nayfach <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">n </italic>=<italic toggle="yes"> </italic>19 514) were connected by PHIST mostly to Clostridia and Bacteroidia (<xref rid="btab837-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig.  1H</xref>, lower bar chart), which were also two dominant classes of bacteria in Nayfach <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> predictions (<xref rid="btab837-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig.  1H</xref>, upper bar chart). Computing all ∼54 billion pairwise scores between 189 680 viruses and 286 997 prokaryotes required just 3.5 h and 25 GB of RAM (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Material</xref>).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>4 Conclusion</title>
    <p>PHIST predicts hosts species with higher accuracy than alignment-based tools, and allows for rapid analysis of large-scale genomic and metagenomic datasets on non-specialized hardware.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>Funding</title>
    <p>This work was supported by the National Science Centre, Poland [2018/31/D/NZ2/00108 to A.Z., DEC-2016/21/D/ST6/02952 to A.G., DEC-2019/33/B/ST6/02040 to S.D.].</p>
    <p><italic toggle="yes">Conflict of Interest</italic>: none declared. </p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="data-availability">
    <title>Data availability</title>
    <p>All data analysed in this study are available from previously published studies (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Material</xref>).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
      <label>btab837_Supplementary_Data</label>
      <media xlink:href="btab837_supplementary_data.pdf">
        <caption>
          <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
        </caption>
      </media>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ref-list id="ref1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="btab837-B1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>A unified catalog of 204,938 reference genomes from the human gut microbiome</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biotechnol</source>., <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>114</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32690973</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab837-B2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>3389</fpage>–<lpage>3402</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9254694</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab837-B3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Coclet</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roux</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Global overview and major challenges of host prediction methods for uncultivated phages</article-title>. <source>Curr. Opin. Virol</source>., <volume>49</volume>, <fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34126465</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab837-B4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Deorowicz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Kmer-db: instant evolutionary distance estimation</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>136</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29986074</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab837-B5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Computational approaches to predict bacteriophage–host relationships</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol. Rev</source>., <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>258</fpage>–<lpage>272</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26657537</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab837-B6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Galiez</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>WIsH: who is the host? Predicting prokaryotic hosts from metagenomic phage contigs</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>3113</fpage>–<lpage>3114</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28957499</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab837-B7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nayfach</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Metagenomic compendium of 189,680 DNA viruses from the human gut microbiome</article-title>. <source>Nat. Microbiol</source>., <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>960</fpage>–<lpage>970</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34168315</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab837-B8">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Paez-Espino</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Uncovering Earth’s virome</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>536</volume>, <fpage>425</fpage>–<lpage>430</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27533034</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab837-B9">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Identifying viruses from metagenomic data using deep learning</article-title>. <source>Quant. Biol</source>., <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>64</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34084563</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab837-B10">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>A network-based integrated framework for predicting virus–prokaryote interactions</article-title>. <source>NAR Genom. Bioinform</source>., <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab837-B11">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>SpacePHARER: sensitive identification of phages from CRISPR spacers in prokaryotic hosts</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>3364</fpage>–<lpage>3366</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33792634</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btab837-B12">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zielezinski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Taxonomy-aware, sequence similarity ranking reliably predicts phage-host relationships</article-title>. <source>BMC Biol</source>., <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>223</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34625070</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
