<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?properties open_access?>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8262758</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34023905</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkab402</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gkab402</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI00010</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Web Server Issue</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>AnnotSV and knotAnnotSV: a web server for human structural variations annotations, ranking and analysis</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Geoffroy</surname>
          <given-names>Véronique</given-names>
        </name>
        <!--veronique.geoffroy@inserm.fr-->
        <aff><institution>Laboratoire de Génétique Médicale</institution>, U1112, INSERM, IGMA, FMTS, Université de Strasbourg, Strasbourg, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
        <xref rid="FN1" ref-type="author-notes"/>
        <xref rid="COR2" ref-type="corresp"/>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Guignard</surname>
          <given-names>Thomas</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Unité de Génétique Chromosomique</institution>, CHU Montpellier, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
        <xref rid="FN1" ref-type="author-notes"/>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Kress</surname>
          <given-names>Arnaud</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Complex Systems and Translational Bioinformatics</institution>, ICube, UMR 7357, University of Strasbourg, CNRS, FMTS, Strasbourg, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Gaillard</surname>
          <given-names>Jean-Baptiste</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Unité de Génétique Chromosomique</institution>, CHU Montpellier, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Solli-Nowlan</surname>
          <given-names>Tor</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Department of Medical Genetics, Oslo University Hospital</institution>, Oslo, <country country="NO">Norway</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Schalk</surname>
          <given-names>Audrey</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Laboratoires de Diagnostic Génétique</institution>, IGMA, Hôpitaux Universitaires de Strasbourg, Strasbourg, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Gatinois</surname>
          <given-names>Vincent</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Unité de Génétique Chromosomique</institution>, CHU Montpellier, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Dollfus</surname>
          <given-names>Hélène</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Laboratoire de Génétique Médicale</institution>, U1112, INSERM, IGMA, FMTS, Université de Strasbourg, Strasbourg, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>Centre de référence pour les Affections Rares en Génétique Ophtalmologique</institution>, Filière SENSGENE, Hôpitaux Universitaires de Strasbourg, Strasbourg, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Scheidecker</surname>
          <given-names>Sophie</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Laboratoire de Génétique Médicale</institution>, U1112, INSERM, IGMA, FMTS, Université de Strasbourg, Strasbourg, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>Laboratoires de Diagnostic Génétique</institution>, IGMA, Hôpitaux Universitaires de Strasbourg, Strasbourg, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7682-559X</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Muller</surname>
          <given-names>Jean</given-names>
        </name>
        <!--jeanmuller@unistra.fr-->
        <aff><institution>Laboratoire de Génétique Médicale</institution>, U1112, INSERM, IGMA, FMTS, Université de Strasbourg, Strasbourg, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>Laboratoires de Diagnostic Génétique</institution>, IGMA, Hôpitaux Universitaires de Strasbourg, Strasbourg, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
        <aff><institution>Unité Fonctionnelle de Bioinformatique Médicale appliquée au diagnostic (UF7363)</institution>, Hôpitaux Universitaires de Strasbourg, Strasbourg, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
        <xref rid="COR1" ref-type="corresp"/>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="COR1">To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +33 3 69 55 07 77; Fax: +33 3 69 55 18 94; Email: <email>jeanmuller@unistra.fr</email></corresp>
      <corresp id="COR2">Correspondence may also be addressed to Véronique Geoffroy. Email: <email>veronique.geoffroy@inserm.fr</email></corresp>
      <fn id="FN1">
        <p>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors.</p>
      </fn>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <day>02</day>
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2021-05-22">
      <day>22</day>
      <month>5</month>
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>22</day>
      <month>5</month>
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>49</volume>
    <issue>W1</issue>
    <fpage>W21</fpage>
    <lpage>W28</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>29</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>11</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2021. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Nucleic Acids Research.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact <email>journals.permissions@oup.com</email></license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="gkab402.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <p>With the dramatic increase of pangenomic analysis, Human geneticists have generated large amount of genomic data including millions of small variants (SNV/indel) but also thousands of structural variations (SV) mainly from next-generation sequencing and array-based techniques. While the identification of the complete SV repertoire of a patient is getting possible, the interpretation of each SV remains challenging. To help identifying human pathogenic SV, we have developed a web server dedicated to their annotation and ranking (AnnotSV) as well as their visualization and interpretation (knotAnnotSV) freely available at the following address: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.lbgi.fr/AnnotSV/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.lbgi.fr/AnnotSV/</ext-link>. A large amount of annotations from &gt;20 sources is integrated in our web server including among others genes, haploinsufficiency, triplosensitivity, regulatory elements, known pathogenic or benign genomic regions, phenotypic data. An ACMG/ClinGen compliant prioritization module allows the scoring and the ranking of SV into 5 SV classes from pathogenic to benign. Finally, the visualization interface displays the annotated SV in an interactive way including popups, search fields, filtering options, advanced colouring to highlight pathogenic SV and hyperlinks to the UCSC genome browser or other public databases. This web server is designed for diagnostic and research analysis by providing important resources to the user.</p>
    </abstract>
    <abstract abstract-type="graphical">
      <title>Graphical Abstract</title>
      <p>
        <fig position="float" id="ga1">
          <label>Graphical Abstract</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Here we present a web server dedicated to the annotation and ranking of structural variations (AnnotSV) as well as their visualization and interpretation (knotAnnotSV).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="gkab402gra1" position="float"/>
        </fig>
      </p>
    </abstract>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Inserm</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100001677</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>University of Strasbourg</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100003768</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Strasbourg University Hospital</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="8"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec sec-type="intro" id="SEC1">
    <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
    <p>Clinical genetics applications are using more and more high throughput technologies in diagnostic and research settings. Current sequencing techniques encompassing targeted (panel and whole exome) and whole genome sequencing (WGS) but also array technologies are identifying tremendous amount of human variations (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). They include single nucleotide variants (SNV), small insertion/deletions (indel) and structural variations (SV). In particular, WGS generates more and more reliable SV calls in the context of human genetics studies. SV are of specific interest as they play an important role either in genome evolution or as a disease mechanism. Research and clinical communities still face major challenges in annotating and accurately classifying SV. Specific tools for annotation and prioritization are required for helping human geneticists to reliably and quickly interpret clinically relevant SV.</p>
    <p>AnnotSV was developed to fulfil these requirements and was regularly updated since the first release (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>) introducing a prioritization module from the more to the less pathogenic SV (version 2.0) and a phenotype matching module as well as an improved web based visualization service (version 3.0).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="methods" id="SEC2">
    <title>PROGRAM DESCRIPTION AND METHODS</title>
    <sec id="SEC2-1">
      <title>General description of the web server</title>
      <p>There are two major parts in the program workflow (Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), first an annotation engine with AnnotSV and second a visualization and filtering interface with knotAnnotSV. AnnotSV is a fast and efficient tool to annotate and classify the SV identified from the human genome. This tool aims at providing annotations useful (i) to interpret SV potential pathogenicity and (ii) to filter out potential false positive variants from all the identified SV.</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F1">
        <label>Figure 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Schematic overview of the AnnotSV and knotAnnotSV workflow. The web server architecture comprises a two-tiered framework: first an annotation engine with AnnotSV (submitting a query, processing the annotations) and second a visualization and filtering interface with knotAnnotSV (showing results, generating the visualization and filtering system).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="gkab402fig1" position="float"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2-2">
      <title>Inputs/Outputs</title>
      <p>The web server accepts queries in three different ways: chromosomal coordinates and SV type (e.g. chr11:66 286 491–66 289 295 del) for a quick single SV analysis and a VCF (Variant Call Format) (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) or a BED file for multiple SV requests. In order to test the general use of the interface, an input example is available on the web page. Optionally, the user can also submit a VCF file with the SNV/indel calls from any sequencing experiment as input from the same sample. These annotations can be of substantial help to identify possible false positive SV calls (i.e. observing heterozygous SNV/indel at the same position of a large deletion) or report a second variant for a recessive disease. The output contains the overlaps of the SV with relevant genomic features where the genes refer to RefSeq (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) or ENSEMBL (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>) genes (user defined) as well as phenotypic data or a pathogenic scoring of each SV (Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Output can be either visualized in a web browser directly, using a specific link, or downloaded as an html file or a tab separated file (tsv file).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2-3">
      <title>Genomic annotations: categories and data sources</title>
      <p>Genomic annotations can be performed using either the GRCh37 or GRCh38 build of the human genome (user defined). Some of the annotations are linked to the gene name and thus can be provided independently of the genome build. Numerous relevant annotations are provided encompassing the following categories: Gene, Regulatory elements, Pathogenic genomic regions, Benign genomic regions and Breakpoints. As an example, ∼30 000 benign SV (Gain, Loss, Insertion, Inversion) and 20 000 pLI (probability of being Loss-of-function Intolerant) and LOEUF (Loss-of-function Observed/Expected Upper bound Fraction) annotations were retrieved from the gnomAD database (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Around 400 pathogenic regions (Gain, Insertion, Loss), 1100 haploinsufficiency/triplosensitivity genomic regions and 35 benign SV from the ClinGen (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). All the annotations sources and their corresponding version are given in Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and the exhaustive output annotations are listed in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>.</p>
      <table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1">
        <label>Table 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Summary of annotation sources and their versions available in the current version</p>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annotations source</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Version</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                <bold>...<italic toggle="yes">Gene annotations</italic></bold>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene annotations (RefSeq)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/17/2020</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene annotations (ENSEMBL)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/24/2020</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                <bold>...<italic toggle="yes">Regulatory Elements annotations</italic></bold>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Promoter data (RefSeq)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/17/2020</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Promoter data (ENSEMBL)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/24/2020</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EnhancerAtlas 2.0</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/11/2019</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GeneHancer</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Licence required</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                <bold>...<italic toggle="yes">Gene-based annotations</italic></bold>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DDD disease</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/3/2020</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMIM</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/7/2020</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACMG</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACMG SF v2.0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene intolerance (gnomAD)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">V2.1.1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene intolerance (ExAC)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/23/2016</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Haploinsufficiency (DDD)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/13/2020</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Haploinsufficiency and triplosensitivity (ClinGen)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/18/2020</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exomiser</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20/08/2020 (v2007)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCBI gene ID</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/18/2020</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                <bold>...<italic toggle="yes">Annotations with known pathogenic genes or genomic regions</italic></bold>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ClinVar</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/12/2020</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ClinGen</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/18/2020</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMIM</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/7/2020</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">dbVar</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/2/2020</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                <bold>...<italic toggle="yes">Annotations with known pathogenic SNV/indel</italic></bold>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ClinVar</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/12/2020</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                <bold>...<italic toggle="yes">Annotations with known benign genes or genomic regions</italic></bold>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">gnomAD (GRCh37)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">06/03/2019 (v2.1)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ClinVar</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/12/2020</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ClinGen</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/18/2020</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DGV annotations</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/25/2020</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DDD annotations (GRCh37)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/18/2019</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000 genomes annotations (GRCh37)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/19/2017</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000 genomes annotations (GRCh38)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/5/2017</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ira M. Hall's lab annotations</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/31/2018</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                <bold>...<italic toggle="yes">Annotations with features overlapped with the SV</italic></bold>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">COSMIC annotations</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Licence required</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TAD boundaries annotations</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/24/2017</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                <bold>...<italic toggle="yes">Breakpoints annotations</italic></bold>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GRCh37 FASTA genome</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/20/2009</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GRCh38 FASTA genome</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/23/2014</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Repeated sequences annotations</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/16/2020</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Segmental Duplication annotations</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/8/2020</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ENCODE blacklist annotations</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2018 (v2)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAP regions annotations</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/8/2020</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>AnnotSV adjusts the overlapping method between each SV and annotation databases depending on the annotation features. Known pathogenic genes or genomic regions need to be fully overlapped with the SV to annotate, while benign genes or genomic regions need to be fully overlapping with the SV to annotate (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S1</xref>). Genes are reported starting with a single base overlapped.</p>
      <p>In order to make sure AnnotSV remains a prime resource for researchers and geneticists, data annotations are regularly updated (once or twice a year) and novel sources are integrated to meet new needs.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2-4">
      <title>Genomic annotations: full and split visualization modes</title>
      <p>Annotation is provided into 2 modes: one directly related to the full-length SV (Full mode) and one related to each gene within the SV (Split mode). The Full mode integrates the annotations and ranking of the highest scoring elements overlapped while, the Split mode provides detailed annotations for each overlapped gene (ID, OMIM (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>), haploinsufficiency etc.). With the Split mode, users have access to the SV location within each overlapped gene (e.g. ‘exon3-intron11’, 'txStart-intron19’ etc.) and each of these genes is evaluated with respect to individual phenotypic features observed in the patient.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2-5">
      <title>Phenotype-driven prioritization of SV</title>
      <p>Prior biological knowledge and phenotype information may help to identify disease genes from human sequencing and array data. Collecting a full and detailed phenotypic profile of the individuals being investigated will certainly improve the chance of prioritizing the correct causative SV (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10–12</xref>). For this, the patient's phenotype needs to be coded using the Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Using Exomiser (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), AnnotSV scores each SV taking into account the most relevant overlapped gene (i.e. the one having the most similar phenotypes with the phenotypic profile under investigation). Genes overlapped with an SV are scored from the lowest (0.0) to the highest similarity (1.0) so that:</p>
      <list list-type="simple">
        <list-item>
          <p>- Genes previously associated with disease can be easily highlighted,</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>- Genes not previously associated with disease can be highlighted,</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>- Genes associated with diseases that have little or no similarity to the observed phenotypes can be easily removed.</p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2-6">
      <title>New ACMG/ClinGen based ranking</title>
      <p>To assist clinical laboratories in the classification and reporting of SV, the ACMG has developed professional standards in collaboration with the National Institutes of Health (NIH)—funded Clinical Genome Resource (ClinGen) project (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). An automatic SV scoring based on these recommendations (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) has been implemented in AnnotSV which permits each SV to be categorized in one of the following classes: class 1 (benign), class 2 (likely benign), class 3 (variant of unknown significance), class 4 (likely pathogenic) and class 5 (pathogenic). The comprehensive and detailed scoring guidelines are available in the <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S2</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2-7">
      <title>Interface: annotation, visualization and filtering system</title>
      <p>A user-friendly web server interface is freely available online (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://lbgi.fr/AnnotSV/runjob" ext-link-type="uri">https://lbgi.fr/AnnotSV/runjob</ext-link>) to annotate, rank, visualize and filter SV. To help identifying human pathogenic SV, knotAnnotSV displays the annotated SV in an interactive way including popups, search fields, filtering options, advanced colouring to highlight pathogenic SV and hyperlinks to the UCSC genome browser (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) or other public databases (Figure <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The annotation is available for the SV as a whole (Full mode or Compact mode in knotAnnotSV) or divided for each overlapped gene (Split mode or Expanded mode in knotAnnotSV). The Full lines are sorted with the most likely pathogenic SV first. Split lines can be displayed below each corresponding Full line and genes are sorted with the most likely pathogenic first.</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F2">
        <label>Figure 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>knotAnnotSV interface overview. The interface includes multiple annotations columns with detailed popup. Annotation mode includes presentation of annotation for the Full SV (Compact) or the detailed Split by gene view (Expanded). Each annotation column can be easily filtered. External links allows the user see the SV in the UCSC genome browser.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="gkab402fig2" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The SV lines are coloured depending on their SV type (e.g. duplication in blue, deletion in red). Each gene in the split lines is coloured according to their LOEUF score (gradient from the highest haploinsufficiency value in red to the lowest haploinsufficiency value in green). Fully overlapped gene harbour completely coloured cells while partially overlapped genes are partially coloured. This interface includes many functionalities (Table <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) among others hyperlinks to external databases (GeneCards (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>), OMIM etc.) and direct link to the UCSC genome browser with specific highlight to the region of interest.</p>
      <table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2">
        <label>Table 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Summary of knotAnnotSV functions available in the current version</p>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Features</th>
              <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>Display modes</bold>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic toggle="yes">COMPACT</italic>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Display only the “Full” AnnotSV lines, giving a SV view</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic toggle="yes">EXPANDED</italic>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Display both “Full” and “Split” AnnotSV lines, giving a SV + gene view</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic toggle="yes">SINGLE SV FOCUS</italic>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Display only the “Full” and “Split” AnnotSV lines of a single SV (by double-clicking on a full line in compact mode)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>Data knotting</bold>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic toggle="yes">Lines sorting</italic>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lines are sorted according to these priorization rules: ACMG class &gt; Exomiser Score &gt; OMIM morbid &gt; LOEUF bin (this last one is applied on split lines only)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic toggle="yes">Tooltips</italic>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hover annotation with mouse to display related informations</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic toggle="yes">SV type Color coding</italic>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The “Full" lines are highlighted depending on their SV type (e.g. duplication in blue, deletion in red). Split lines have a white background</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic toggle="yes">LOEUF Color coding</italic>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene annotations are red-to-green color-coded depending on the gene LOEUF values. The color is full or truncated depending on the overlapping feature of the SV</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic toggle="yes">Regulatory elements</italic>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulatory elements, whose targets are not overlapped by SV (hence absents from “Gene name" list), are top-listed and ranked according to their Exomiser and morbid features</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>External links</bold>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic toggle="yes">UCSC genome browser</italic>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Click on the “AnnotSV ID" to open the SV in the UCSC Genome browser. The SV region is automatically highlighted in light blue and zoomed out by 1.5x for a better genomic contextualisation</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic toggle="yes">OMIM, GeneCards</italic>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Click on the blue hyperlinks to open the corresponding entry web page</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>Data handling</bold>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic toggle="yes">Values Sorting</italic>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Click on the column headers to sort values. Come back to the original sorting by clicking on the header of the first column (AnnotSV ID)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic toggle="yes">Word Searching</italic>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Search words to extract matching records in the displayed annotations as well as in the OMIM, Pathogenic and Gene Name tooltips</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic toggle="yes">Numerical Filtering</italic>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Filter a range of numerical values by preceding a value with the “&gt;”, “&gt;=”, “&lt;” and “&lt;=” symbols (e.g. to select frequencies less than 1%, type “&lt;0.01”)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic toggle="yes">Filtering Out</italic>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Filter out the numerical values or words respectively preceded with “!=" or “!" (e.g. “! word” or “!= value”)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic toggle="yes">Filter Saving</italic>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At each handling step, all the set-up filters are locally stored</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </table-wrap>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2-8">
      <title>Implementation</title>
      <p>AnnotSV is written in Tcl/Tk and runs on all Unix platforms with a standard Tcl/Tk 8.5 installation including four packages (‘<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://http" ext-link-type="uri">http</ext-link>’, ‘json’, ‘tar’ and ‘csv’). Bedtools (v2.25 and higher) is required. Optionally, bcftools (v1.10 and higher) can be used for VCF handling and a minimal Java 8 installation is required for the Exomiser dependencies. In order to provide a ready to start installation of AnnotSV, each annotation source (that do not require a commercial license) is automatically downloaded during the installation. knotAnnotSv is written in Perl and runs on all Unix platforms with a standard Perl installation (≥5.22) including 2 CPAN libraries (‘YAML::XS’ and ‘Sort::Key::Natural’). knotAnnotSV implements DataTables (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://datatables.net/" ext-link-type="uri">https://datatables.net/</ext-link>) which is a plug-in for the jQuery Javascript library that brings advanced features to HTML tables.</p>
      <p>The web application is based on the PHP Symfony framework and the jQuery library for the frontend. Commands are sent to the compute nodes (Linux servers under Ubuntu 18.04) using the SLURM scheduler (v15.08).</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="results" id="SEC3">
    <title>RESULTS AND USE CASES</title>
    <p>In order to assess the running performance of the web server, datasets from different sources (CGH/SNP arrays, WES, WGS) were annotated (Table <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). In total, from 46 to 3,400 SV ranging in size from 50 bp to 205 Mb were annotated using the GRCh37 build of the human genome taking into account 2 different situations: with or without HPO and with or without sample SNV/indel. As a result, the web server completed the annotation for these SV within a reasonable time frame (∼1–27 min) and with minimal memory (∼100 Mo–1.5 Go) (Table <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The running time depends mainly on the number of overlapped genes (indirectly both on the SV number and the SV size) resulting in as many annotations split lines. Taking into account additional information especially the HPO scoring impacts the running time of the web server.</p>
    <table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3">
      <label>Table 3.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Comparison of computational speeds for the annotation of different datasets</p>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experiment source</th>
            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SV count</th>
            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min SV size (bp)</th>
            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max SV size (bp)</th>
            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean SV size (bp)</th>
            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median SV size (bp)</th>
            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Running time (without HPO* or SNV/indel**)</th>
            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Running time with HPO* (without SNV/indel**)</th>
            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Running time with SNV/indel** (without HPO*)</th>
            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Running time with HPO* and SNV/indel**</th>
            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max memory</th>
            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Split annotations count</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <bold>SNP array</bold>
            </td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 DEL 4 DUP</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 476</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">622 597</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">202 741</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">119 731</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼10 s</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼40 s</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼100 Mo</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <bold>CGH array</bold>
            </td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 DEL 4 DUP</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 000</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 203 230</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">562.208</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">144,753</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼15 s</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼1 min</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼100 Mo</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">301</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <bold>WES</bold>
            </td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 DEL 26 DUP</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">214</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">614.757</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.506</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.178</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼10 s</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼1 min</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼ 40 s</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼1 min 30</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼150 Mo</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <bold>WGS</bold>
            </td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼1400 DEL ∼2000 DUP</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">205 311 845</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 202 342</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼9 min</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼21 min</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼ 14 min</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼27 min</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼1.5 Go</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.003</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The smallest SV from the WGS example</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 DEL</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼10 s</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼30 s</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼ 1 min 10</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼1 min 30</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼380 Mo</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The largest SV from the WGS example</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 DEL</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">205 311 845</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼30 s</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼1 min 50</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼1 min 40</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼3 min</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∼100 Mo</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.472</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn id="T3TFN1">
          <p>SV datasets from different sources (CGH/SNP arrays, WES, WGS) were annotated to evaluate the running time depending on the number of split annotations, the integration of human phenotype and SNV/Indel information from patients next generation sequencing data (vcf).</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="T3TFN2">
          <p>*HPO terms used: HP:0004322; HP:0011314; HP:0011297; HP:0001156; HP:0000556; HP:0012047; HP:0000083.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="T3TFN3">
          <p>**SNV/indel data used: 314 349 variants for the WES study; 5 134 967 variants for the WGS study</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
    </table-wrap>
    <p>Then, we tested the ability of our web server to highlight pathogenic SV in different situations. The challenges in prioritizing functionally and clinically relevant SV has been addressed from array-based techniques and next-generation sequencing datasets (see Supplementary methods).</p>
    <sec id="SEC3-1">
      <title>Case study 1: SNP array (Causal regulatory element overlapped)</title>
      <p>SNP array (Affymetrix 2.7M) in a patient with Rieger anomaly (MIM# 137600) identified 3 losses and 3 gains of one copy. Among those SV, a 950 kb deletion at heterozygous state on 4q25 localized 194 kb before the <italic toggle="yes">PITX2</italic> gene. This deletion without any known gene encompasses <italic toggle="yes">PITX2</italic> regulatory elements (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>). Deletions located in <italic toggle="yes">PITX2</italic> are already known to cause the Axenfeld-Rieger syndrome (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). This illustrates how the annotation of regulatory elements can identify causative SV.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC3-2">
      <title>Case study 2: CGH array (Known pathogenic SV overlapped)</title>
      <p>Prenatal diagnosis using a CGH array (Agilent® 180K) in a foetus with retrognathism and cleft palate revealed among 11 SV (4 gains and 7 losses of one copy ranging from ∼62 kb to 3.2 Mb) a single de novo 3.2 Mb heterozygous deletion close to the <italic toggle="yes">SOX9</italic> gene. Direct submission of the deletion coordinates (chr17:66,426,540–69,629,770) to AnnotSV revealed the existence of known pathogenic Copy Number Variant (CNV) in ClinGen and OMIM (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S3</xref>). Deletions of regulatory elements from the <italic toggle="yes">SOX9</italic> gene have been already described in a Pierre-Robin sequence (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC3-3">
      <title>Case study 3: WGS (Repeated elements highlighted around the breakpoints)</title>
      <p>WGS in two affected siblings with a Mainzer‐Saldino syndrome (MIM# 26692) identified ∼1400 deletions and ∼2000 duplications per patient using SoftSV (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>) and CANOES (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Among those SV, a 6.7 kb tandem duplication in the <italic toggle="yes">IFT140</italic> gene (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) was highlighted. The breakpoints of the duplication of exon 26 to exon 30 (chr16:1 565 629–1 571 297) overlapped two distinct repeated elements from the Alu family (AluJb and AluJr) potentially suggesting a recurrent mechanism (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S4</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC3-4">
      <title>Case study 4: Multiple cases with custom annotations</title>
      <p>In the contexts of cohort analysis or periodic negative cases re-analysis, users can provide SV from multiple samples at once (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S5</xref>). Complementary annotations added in the input file appear as new columns in the output (e.g. Sample Names, associated phenotype etc.).</p>
      <p>Our workflow addresses the need for a user-friendly, integrated annotation and visualization SV tool to help the analysis and biological interpretation of SV derived from small SNP/CGH array to large NGS datasets, and to guide precision medicine.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="discussion" id="SEC4">
    <title>DISCUSSION AND FUTURE UPDATES</title>
    <p>Thanks to the many genomic initiatives around the world, CGH and SNP arrays or sequencing experiments generate a tremendous amount of human structural variations leading to the need of specific annotations tools. There are several online tools available like VEP (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>) or DeAnnCNV (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) (for review see (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>)). Based on these annotations, SV prioritization is gaining interest with a few programs like SVScore (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>) and recently machine learning methods paving the future of SV interpretation (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Among those, AnnotSV has been widely used owing to its large amount of available annotation sources and multiple functionalities including false positive detection and prioritization. Here we propose a web server allowing quick and robust annotation and visualization of SV including phenotype driven and ACMG/ClinGen compliant ranking.</p>
    <p>Since the initial release of the program (v1.0) (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), we have tripled the available data sources in our annotation engine, including current versions of the largest available datasets like gnomAD (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), DGV (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>), DDD (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) but also gene relevant information such as haploinsufficiency and triplosensitivity from the ClinGen (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>), the pLI and LOEUF from ExAC/gnomAD, the OMIM morbid gene list (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). We provide also annotations of regulatory elements from GeneHancer (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>) (upon Licence agreement) and Enhancer Atlas (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>) as well as specific data for breakpoint analysis such GC content and the presence of repeated elements. Users own annotations (e.g. patient's SNV/indel…) can also be added for annotation. The addition of a phenotype driven module powered by Exomiser (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) will help to automatically integrate the phenotypic data using HPO (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) in large scale studies and score the relation between a gene and the patient's phenotype. As described below, the prioritization module has been added in the second version of AnnotSV and a major update is presented in this version (v3.0). Consequently, less annotations columns are displayed and are directly integrated in the ranking. To our knowledge, this makes our web server the most comprehensive online SV annotation, ranking, filtering and interpretation tool (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S3</xref>).</p>
    <p>However, we plan to update on a regular basis the annotations sources already available and provide new ones. Mobile element insertions (MEI) are rare but sometimes recurrent genomic events that can have dramatic impact in pathology (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Identification of known polymorphic MEI can be of high importance, thus implementation of specific databases such as dbRIP (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>) can be very interesting. False positive calls are still a major issue for SV callers (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). Although, we have already implemented the possibility to report SNV/indel genotype of the same sample together with the SV annotations, more can be done. For example, reporting internal occurrence of SV calls may help to remove recurrent technical false positives. At the interface level, knotAnnotSV is optimized for handling CGH to WES scale data. In fact, DataTables processing of the html output is performed on the user browser side, reducing interface fluidity after 1000 lines (Full/Split). The next developments of knotAnnotSV will be focused on performance enhancement through a server-side processing. Along those lines on a more technical point of view, a database backend will be implemented. This will further improve the annotation running time.</p>
    <p>The ACMG/ClinGen recommendations provide a framework to score each SV. AnnotSV is compliant with those recommendations but some of the proposed scoring criteria are not easily accessible and/or requires close evaluation of the clinical context for a given patient. For example, inheritance patterns are not yet included as well as cases from published literature, public databases, and/or internal lab data. However, many ranking improvements are planned. Among the known SV types (i.e. deletions, duplications, insertions, inversions, translocations or even more complex rearrangements), the ACMG-based scoring is only supported for CNV (i.e. gain and loss). As each SV can arbitrary be summarized as a set of novel adjacencies, new SV types will be scored soon using their breakpoints analysis. Indeed, complex forms of SV such as triplications, inverted duplications, insertional translocations, and chromothripsis could be analysed at the breakpoint-level to determine how genes are disrupted, fused, and/or misregulated by breakpoints or to reveal signatures of diverse DNA repair mechanisms (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Currently, even if not scored, each SV is ranked on the interface respectively according to its Exomiser score, number of overlapped genes, OMIM and LOEUF.</p>
    <p>We believe that AnnotSV and knotAnnotSV will be of great interest and use for the audience interested in human genomics including medical geneticists, cytogeneticists, bioinformaticians and genomics scientists.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="SEC5">
    <title>DATA AVAILABILITY</title>
    <p>The web server is available for free public usage at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://lbgi.fr/AnnotSV" ext-link-type="uri">https://lbgi.fr/AnnotSV</ext-link>. Examples are available on the running page. The source code is available from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://github.com/lgmgeo/AnnotSV" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/lgmgeo/AnnotSV</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://github.com/mobidic/knotAnnotSV" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/mobidic/knotAnnotSV</ext-link>.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
      <label>gkab402_Supplemental_Files</label>
      <media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="gkab402_supplemental_files.zip">
        <caption>
          <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
        </caption>
      </media>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack id="ACK1">
    <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
    <p>We would like to thank Julius Jacobsen for his assistance during the phenotype-driven analysis module implementation and Jonathan Mercier for his guidance using the Filesystem Hierarchy Standard. We also wish to thank Vincent Zilliox for testing and users for their constant support suggesting new annotations and features. The work in the Chromosomal Genetics unit is supported by the CHROMOSTEM research platform. The authors would like to thank the BiGEst-ICube Platform for assistance.</p>
  </ack>
  <sec id="SEC6">
    <title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title>
    <p><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/nar/article-lookup/doi/10.1093/nar/gkab402#supplementary-data" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Data</ext-link> are available at NAR Online.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="SEC7">
    <title>FUNDING</title>
    <p>Inserm; University of Strasbourg; Strasbourg University Hospital. Funding for open access charge: Inserm; University of Strasbourg; Strasbourg University Hospital.</p>
    <p><italic toggle="yes">Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p>
  </sec>
  <ref-list id="REF1">
    <title>REFERENCES</title>
    <ref id="B1">
      <label>1.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Farnaes</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>T.Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>White</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dimmock</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kingsmore</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Meta-analysis of the diagnostic and clinical utility of genome and exome sequencing and chromosomal microarray in children with suspected genetic diseases</article-title>. <source>npj Genomic Med.</source><year>2018</year>; <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>16</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B2">
      <label>2.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lionel</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Costain</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monfared</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reuter</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hosseini</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thiruvahindrapuram</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Merico</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jobling</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nalpathamkalam</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Improved diagnostic yield compared with targeted gene sequencing panels suggests a role for whole-genome sequencing as a first-tier genetic test</article-title>. <source>Genet. Med.</source><year>2018</year>; <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>435</fpage>–<lpage>443</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28771251</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B3">
      <label>3.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Geoffroy</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Herenger</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stoetzel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Piton</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dollfus</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>AnnotSV: an integrated tool for structural variations annotation</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2018</year>; <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>3572</fpage>–<lpage>3574</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B4">
      <label>4.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Danecek</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Auton</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abecasis</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Albers</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>DePristo</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Handsaker</surname><given-names>R.E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lunter</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marth</surname><given-names>G.T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sherry</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>The variant call format and VCFtools</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>2156</fpage>–<lpage>2158</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21653522</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B5">
      <label>5.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>O’Leary</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>M.W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brister</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ciufo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haddad</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McVeigh</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rajput</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Robbertse</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith-White</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ako-Adjei</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Reference sequence (RefSeq) database at NCBI: current status, taxonomic expansion, and functional annotation</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>44</volume>:<fpage>D733</fpage>–<lpage>D745</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26553804</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B6">
      <label>6.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zerbino</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Achuthan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Akanni</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amode</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barrell</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bhai</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Billis</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cummins</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gall</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Girón</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Ensembl 2018</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2017</year>; <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>D754</fpage>–<lpage>D761</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B7">
      <label>7.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Karczewski</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alföldi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Francioli</surname><given-names>L.C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khera</surname><given-names>A.V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lowther</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>L.D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>A structural variation reference for medical and population genetics</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2020</year>; <volume>581</volume>:<fpage>444</fpage>–<lpage>451</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32461652</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B8">
      <label>8.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rehm</surname><given-names>H.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>L.D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>C.D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Landrum</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ledbetter</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maglott</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nussbaum</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>ClinGen — the clinical genome resource</article-title>. <source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>372</volume>:<fpage>2235</fpage>–<lpage>2242</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26014595</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B9">
      <label>9.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hamosh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amberger</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Valle</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McKusick</surname><given-names>V.A.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Online Mendelian Inheritance in Man (OMIM)</article-title>. <source>Hum. Mutat.</source><year>2000</year>; <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10612823</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B10">
      <label>10.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zemojtel</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Köhler</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mackenroth</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jäger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hecht</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krawitz</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Graul-Neumann</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Doelken</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ehmke</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spielmann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Effective diagnosis of genetic disease by computational phenotype analysis of the disease-associated genome</article-title>. <source>Sci. Transl. Med.</source><year>2014</year>; <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>252ra123</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B11">
      <label>11.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Javed</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Phen-Gen: combining phenotype and genotype to analyze rare disorders</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>935</fpage>–<lpage>937</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25086502</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B12">
      <label>12.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>P.N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Phenolyzer: phenotype-based prioritization of candidate genes for human diseases</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>841</fpage>–<lpage>843</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26192085</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B13">
      <label>13.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Köhler</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carmody</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vasilevsky</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>J.O.B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Danis</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gourdine</surname><given-names>J.-P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gargano</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>N.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matentzoglu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McMurry</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Expansion of the Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) knowledge base and resources</article-title>. <source>Nucleic. Acids. Res.</source><year>2019</year>; <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>D1018</fpage>–<lpage>D1027</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30476213</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B14">
      <label>14.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Smedley</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>J.O.B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jager</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Köhler</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holtgrewe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schubach</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Siragusa</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zemojtel</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buske</surname><given-names>O.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Washington</surname><given-names>N.L.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Next-generation diagnostics and disease-gene discovery with the Exomiser</article-title>. <source>Nat. Protoc.</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>2004</fpage>–<lpage>2015</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26562621</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B15">
      <label>15.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Riggs</surname><given-names>E.R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>E.F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cherry</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kantarci</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kearney</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raca</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ritter</surname><given-names>D.I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>South</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thorland</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Technical standards for the interpretation and reporting of constitutional copy-number variants: a joint consensus recommendation of the American College of Medical Genetics and Genomics (ACMG) and the Clinical Genome Resource (ClinGen)</article-title>. <source>Genet. Med.</source><year>2020</year>; <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>245</fpage>–<lpage>257</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31690835</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B16">
      <label>16.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>G.P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Casper</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clawson</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Diekhans</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>J.N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hinrichs</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>B.T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nassar</surname><given-names>L.R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>UCSC Genome Browser enters 20th year</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2019</year>; <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>D756</fpage>–<lpage>D761</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B17">
      <label>17.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Safran</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dalah</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Iny Stein</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shmoish</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nativ</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bahir</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Doniger</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krug</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>GeneCards Version 3: the human gene integrator</article-title>. <source>Database</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>2010</volume>:<fpage>baq020</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20689021</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B18">
      <label>18.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Volkmann</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zinkevich</surname><given-names>N.S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mustonen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schilter</surname><given-names>K.F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bosenko</surname><given-names>D.V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Broeckel</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Link</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Semina</surname><given-names>E.V.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Potential novel mechanism for Axenfeld-Rieger Syndrome: deletion of a distant region containing regulatory elements of PITX2</article-title>. <source>Invest. Ophthalmol. Vis. Sci.</source><year>2011</year>; <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>1450</fpage>–<lpage>1459</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20881290</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B19">
      <label>19.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Smyk</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roeder</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Szafranski</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stankiewicz</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>A de novo 1.58 Mb deletion, including MAP2K6 and mapping 1.28 Mb upstream to SOX9, identified in a patient with Pierre Robin sequence and osteopenia with multiple fractures</article-title>. <source>Am. J. Med. Genet. A</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>167</volume>:<fpage>1842</fpage>–<lpage>1850</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B20">
      <label>20.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bartenhagen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dugas</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Robust and exact structural variation detection with paired-end and soft-clipped alignments: SoftSV compared with eight algorithms</article-title>. <source>Brief. Bioinform.</source><year>2016</year>; <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25998133</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B21">
      <label>21.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Backenroth</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Homsy</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Murillo</surname><given-names>L.R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Glessner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brueckner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lifton</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goldmuntz</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>W.K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y.F.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>CANOES: detecting rare copy number variants from whole exome sequencing data</article-title>. <source>NucleicAcids Res.</source><year>2014</year>; <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>e97</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B22">
      <label>22.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Geoffroy</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stoetzel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scheidecker</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perrault</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bär</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kröll</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Delbarre</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Antin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leuvrey</surname><given-names>A.-S.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Whole-genome sequencing in patients with ciliopathies uncovers a novel recurrent tandem duplication in IFT140</article-title>. <source>Hum. Mutat.</source><year>2018</year>; <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>983</fpage>–<lpage>992</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29688594</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B23">
      <label>23.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>McLaren</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rios</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Flicek</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Deriving the consequences of genomic variants with the Ensembl API and SNP Effect Predictor</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>2069</fpage>–<lpage>2070</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20562413</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B24">
      <label>24.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ban</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>DeAnnCNV: a tool for online detection and annotation of copy number variations from whole-exome sequencing data</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>W289</fpage>–<lpage>W294</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26013811</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B25">
      <label>25.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pös</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Radvanszky</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Styk</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pös</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buglyó</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kajsik</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Budis</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Szemes</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Copy number variation: methods and clinical applications</article-title>. <source>Appl. Sci.</source><year>2021</year>; <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>819</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B26">
      <label>26.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ganel</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abel</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></string-name><collab>FinMetSeq Consortium and Hall, I.M.</collab></person-group><article-title>SVScore: an impact prediction tool for structural variation</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2017</year>; <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>1083</fpage>–<lpage>1085</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28031184</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B27">
      <label>27.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sharo</surname><given-names>A.G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>StrVCTVRE: a supervised learning method to predict the pathogenicity of human structural variants</article-title>. <year>2020</year>; <comment>bioRxiv doi:</comment><comment>13 July 2020, preprint: not peer reviewed</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.05.15.097048</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B28">
      <label>28.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Althagafi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alsubaie</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kathiresan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mineta</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aloraini</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Almutairi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alfadhel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gojobori</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alfares</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoehndorf</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>DeepSVP: integration of genotype and phenotype for structural variant prioritization using deep learning</article-title>. <year>2021</year>; <comment>bioRxiv doi:</comment><comment>09 April 2021, preprint: not peer reviewed</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2021.01.28.428557</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B29">
      <label>29.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ziman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yuen</surname><given-names>R.K.C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feuk</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scherer</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>The Database of Genomic Variants: a curated collection of structural variation in the human genome</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2014</year>; <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>D986</fpage>–<lpage>D992</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24174537</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B30">
      <label>30.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Firth</surname><given-names>H.V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>C.F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Study</surname><given-names>D.D.D.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>The Deciphering Developmental Disorders (DDD) study</article-title>. <source>Dev. Med. Child Neurol.</source><year>2011</year>; <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>702</fpage>–<lpage>703</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21679367</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B31">
      <label>31.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Fishilevich</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nudel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rappaport</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hadar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Plaschkes</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Iny Stein</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kohn</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Twik</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Safran</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>GeneHancer: genome-wide integration of enhancers and target genes in GeneCards</article-title>. <source>Database (Oxford)</source>. <year>2017</year>; <volume>2017</volume>:<comment>doi:10.1093/database/bax028</comment>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B32">
      <label>32.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>EnhancerAtlas 2.0: an updated resource with enhancer annotation in 586 tissue/cell types across nine species</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2020</year>; <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>D58</fpage>–<lpage>D64</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31740966</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B33">
      <label>33.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Torene</surname><given-names>R.I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Galens</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arvai</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Borroto</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scuffins</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sroka</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heeley</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Mobile element insertion detection in 89, 874 clinical exomes</article-title>. <source>Genet. Med.</source><year>2020</year>; <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>974</fpage>–<lpage>978</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31965078</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B34">
      <label>34.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Delvallée</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nicaise</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Antin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leuvrey</surname><given-names>A.-S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nourisson</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leitch</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kellaris</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stoetzel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Geoffroy</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scheidecker</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>A BBS1 SVA F retrotransposon insertion is a frequent cause of Bardet-Biedl syndrome</article-title>. <source>Clin. Genet.</source><year>2021</year>; <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>318</fpage>–<lpage>324</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33169370</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B35">
      <label>35.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grover</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Azrak</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Batzer</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>dbRIP: a highly integrated database of retrotransposon insertion polymorphisms in humans</article-title>. <source>Hum. Mutat.</source><year>2006</year>; <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>323</fpage>–<lpage>329</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16511833</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B36">
      <label>36.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Di Stefano</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Papenfuss</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive evaluation and characterisation of short read general-purpose structural variant calling software</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2019</year>; <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>3240</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31324872</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B37">
      <label>37.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Weckselblatt</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rudd</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Human structural variation: mechanisms of chromosome rearrangements</article-title>. <source>Trends Genet.</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>587</fpage>–<lpage>599</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26209074</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
