<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>BMC Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1471-2105</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">9773435</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36544090</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">5113</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-022-05113-y</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Research</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>UGDR: a generic pipeline to detect recombined regions in polyploid and complex hybrid yeast genomes</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <name>
          <surname>Bedrat</surname>
          <given-names>Amina</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>abedrat@mcw.edu</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.418596.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0639 6384</institution-id><institution>Institut Curie, </institution><institution>UPMC University, </institution></institution-wrap>Paris, France </aff>
      <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Meiogenix, 27 Rue du Chemin Vert, Paris, France </aff>
      <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.30760.32</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2111 8460</institution-id><institution>Medical College of Wisconsin, </institution></institution-wrap>8701 W Watertown Plank Rd, Milwaukee, USA </aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>21</day>
      <month>12</month>
      <year>2022</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>21</day>
      <month>12</month>
      <year>2022</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <year>2022</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>23</volume>
    <elocation-id>555</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>3</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>13</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2022</copyright-statement>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract id="Abs1">
      <sec>
        <title>Motivation</title>
        <p id="Par1">In eukaryotes, homologous recombination between the parental genomes frequently occurs during the evolutionary conserved process of meiosis, generating the genetic diversity transmitted by the gametes. The genome-wide determination of the frequency and location of the recombination events can now be efficiently performed by genotyping the offspring’s polymorphic markers. However, genotyping recombination in complex hybrid genomes with existing methods remains challenging because of their strain and ploidy specificity and the degree of diversity and complexity of the parental genomes, especially in <inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$&gt;2n$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2022_5113_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> polyploids.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Results</title>
        <p id="Par2">We present UGDR, a pipeline to genotype the polymorphisms of complex hybrid yeast genomes. It is based on optimal mapping strategies of NGS reads, comparative analyses of the allelic ratio variation and read depth coverage. We tested the UGDR pipeline with sequencing reads from recombined hybrid diploid yeast strains and various clinical strains exhibiting different degrees of ploidy. UGDR allows to plot the markers distribution and recombination profile per chromosome.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <p id="Par3">UGDR detects and plots recombination events in haploids and polyploid yeasts, which facilitates the discovery and understanding of the yeast genetic recombination map and identify new out-performing recombinants.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Supplementary Information</title>
        <p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12859-022-05113-y.</p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
      <title>Keywords</title>
      <kwd>Yeast</kwd>
      <kwd>Polyploid</kwd>
      <kwd>Recombination</kwd>
      <kwd>Alleles frequency</kwd>
      <kwd>Break induced replication (BIR)</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
        <meta-value>© The Author(s) 2022</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec id="Sec1">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <p id="Par4">Recombination between the maternal and paternal homologous chromosomes is a major source of genetic diversity leading to the loss of heterozygosity (LOH) events in somatic cells and meiotic crossing-overs in germline cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. In both cases, the evolutionarily conserved homologous recombination pathways generate novel allelic combinations that, upon Darwinian selection, are beneficial, neutral or detrimental [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Defects in homologous recombination in somatic cells are a source of chromosomal rearrangements [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] and of sterility in sexually reproducing organisms, since meiotic recombination between the homologous chromosomes is essential to ensure their correct segregation at the reductional meiotic division (Meiosis I) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p>
    <p id="Par5">The variable density of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNP) and small insertion/deletion (Indels) along the chromosomes determines the resolution of the recombined sequence extremities. Practically, it can be achieved by the genotyping and/or sequencing of these markers and their phasing in the parental and potentially recombined cells. Previous approaches for detecting recombination events along yeasts chromosomes are based on the analysis of the re-association of parental polymorphic markers and the ploidy of the cell. For example, ssGenotyping [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], a semi-supervised clustering method, used the high-density microarray sequencing data of a parental strain and its meiosis products to determine the genome wide profile of meiotic recombination in yeast tetrads. Another method, ReCombine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] was also developed to genotype yeast meiotic progeny and to arrange recombination events into classes using either microarray or high throughput sequencing data. ReCombine aligns the reads to a merged reference genome (S288C/YJM789) and compares the number of reference versus variant markers using the base alignment quality score. Another generalized framework, RecombineX, has been developed to genotype gametes and draw the recombination profile of tetrads in different organisms including yeasts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. More approaches to precisely track the recombination landscape of diploid yeasts were presented. Indeed, SNP genotyping by sequencing also allowed genotyping and mapping of the recombination events in hybrid diploid cells induced to enter into meiosis prior to returning to mitotic growth (RTG) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Lastly, benefiting from long-read sequencing, MuLoYDH framework [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] was designed to study the genome dynamics and mutational landscapes of yeast diploid hybrids.</p>
    <p id="Par6">All these methods have been successfully used to analyze the recombination events in the experimental setup for which they were designed (specific S288C parent, haploids, and diploids). However, due to their specificity and hard coding, these methods are less fitted to detect and plot the recombination profile of aneuploid/polyploid and/or complex hybrid yeast genomes with different genetic background. Therefore, the need for a user-friendly unbiased method that efficiently investigate recombination in natural hybrids and polyploids with uncharacterized parents remains.</p>
    <p id="Par7">In this study, we propose an Unbiased General Detection of Recombination (UGDR) method that analyzes variations in SNP frequency to detect recombination and foster visualization of recombination tracks in natural and/or constructed hybrid yeast genomes. The detection of recombination in haploid (tetrads), diploid, aneuploidy and polyploid yeasts (limited to 4n) is achieved regardless of the ploidy of the yeast and the parental genome. UGDR also addresses the challenge of the continuous variation of the allele frequencies along with chromosomal loss and gain. We validated the performance of UGDR on published yeast genome data, corresponding to a pair of mother and daughter <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> cells isolated from meiotic return to growth (RTG) and a corresponding tetrad set of four haploid spores isolated from uninterrupted meiosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Furthermore, we assessed the performance of UGDR by comparing its output against that of similar analysis and demonstrated that UGDR achieves the state-of-arts performance for both haploids and diploids and unprecedentedly extended its use to detect potential recombinations in triploid and tetraploid hybrid clinical yeast strains.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec2">
    <title>Methods</title>
    <p id="Par8">For the detection and the visualization of recombination, we employed a three-step method. First, we aligned the raw sequence reads to the reference genome (S288C and/or SK1). Second, we performed variants calling to identify the polymorphic sites and to characterize the normalized allelic frequency of the individual markers in the parental and recombinant samples. Third, we plotted the allelic variation to provide a quick and intuitive way to map the recombination events.</p>
    <sec id="Sec3">
      <title>Dataset</title>
      <p id="Par9">To test UGDR, we downloaded publicly available Illumina paired-end reads sequencing data of recombined and potentially recombined strains from the NCBI Sequence Read Archive (SRA) (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1). The downloaded set includes: four-spore tetrads of haploid strains and two diploid mother and daughter RTG strains (RTG17M &amp; RTG17D,) issued from a SK1/S288C hybrid background [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], and two clinical triploids strains (YJM1138 and YJM114) and two clinical tetraploids strains (YJM958, TJM959) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. It is important to note that the triploids and tetraploids are sequenced by Zhu et al. without sporulation or induced recombination. The S288C fasta sequence was downloaded from the Saccharomyces Genome Database and the novel SK1 fasta assemble was provided by Liti [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4">
      <title>Genome alignment and variants calling (Galocal)</title>
      <p id="Par10">The key steps for studying large-scale dataset are reads mapping and identification of potential polymorphic sites (SNP calling). To manage the alignment of the reads and call the variants, we assembled the necessary open source tools in a custom bash script named Galocal (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). First, we mapped all the reads to the reference using the gapped Burrows-wheeler Aligner (BWA) v.0.7.15 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Next, to achieve an accurate variant detection, we conducted a different post-alignment analysis that included elimination of unmapped reads using SAMtools v.1.3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] and removal of PCR duplicate using Picard tools v.2.4.1 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/broadinstitute/picard">https://github.com/broadinstitute/picard</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. After that, we used the Bayesian algorithms: FreeBayes framework-1.0.2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] to call variants and the DepthOfCoverage tool from the GATK v3.5 framework [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] to determine the depth of coverage (DoC). Finally, the output files (variants files [.vcf] and depth of coverage files [.doc]) were further used to analyze the variations in allelic frequency reflecting the region of recombination.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Workflow of data recombination and coverage analysis. Blue rectangles represent the methods used; yellow squares represent the output files. Lozenges represent name labels for the tools used. <bold>a</bold> Galocal, a pipeline for analyzing sequencing data and calculating depth of coverage. This pipeline encompasses a list of tools to analyze paired-end Illumina sequence. It allows (1) reads’ mapping, (2) filter and remove duplicates, (3) call variant and (4) calculate per base depth of coverage. At the end of this step, three text files are generated (.vcf, .doc and .bam). <bold>b</bold> UGDR, a pipeline to analyze recombination. This pipeline considers two VCF files as an input (one file for the Parental or reference strain P.vcf and a file for the potentially recombined strain R.vcf). (1) The pipeline calculates the ratio from the VCF files and classify them according to their origins: Parental/reference alleles file and Recombined alleles file (2) Compare the allele ratio between parent/reference and the recombined strains, univariate ratios are written in the invariant alleles file and the varying ratios are written in variant alleles file. (3) The last step is to compare the alleles ratios and stock the result in Region of recombination file. Once the files are created, recombination profile is created. <bold>c</bold> NDoC, a pipeline to calculate Depth of Coverage. A depth of coverage is calculated within a 1 kb window from the parental and the recombined DOC files and the results are written in two distinct files. Next, the normalized depth of coverage is calculated, and the data are stoked in xx_normalized1KB file (xx: name of the potentially recombined strains). Lastly the coverage plot per chromosome is plotted</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2022_5113_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec5">
      <title>Analysis of allele frequency variation and identification of recombination region (UGDR)</title>
      <p id="Par11">When describing the allele frequency variation in this study, we use the term “ratio variation”. To analyze ratio variation, we investigated and compared each chromosome’s copy number that supported the alleles in both the potentially recombined strains and reference strain. To start the exploration of the chromosome’s copy involved in the recombination, it must be noted that the allele (SNP) ratios are ploidy dependent (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S2). Indeed, in haploid strains, the heterozygous allele ratio is equal to 1. Meanwhile, in diploid strains, the heterozygous allele ratio is equal to 0.5 and the homozygous allele ratio is equal to 1. In triploid and tetraploid strains, the heterozygous allele ratios are 0.33, 0.67 and 0.25, 0.5, 0.75, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. To calculate the allele ratios from the variants calling files (VCF), we involved two main constants: (1) the observed number of alternative alleles (AO), (2) and the total number of bases sequenced and aligned at a given reference base position (DP). Therefore, the ratio represents the fraction of an alternative allele’s number in the total number of bases at a given position (<inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$Ratio= AO/ DP$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2022_5113_Article_IEq2.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>). Further, the allele ratio is tightly dependent on the quality and counts of the reads at each position; so, the selected alleles for the study are those supported by enough coverage (minimum 20) and an average Phred quality score <inline-formula id="IEq3"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$&gt;200$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>200</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2022_5113_Article_IEq3.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] and AO to <inline-formula id="IEq4"><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$&gt;20$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>20</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2022_5113_Article_IEq4.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> for an 80<inline-formula id="IEq5"><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\times$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mo>×</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2022_5113_Article_IEq5.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> sequencing coverage (cutoffs that the users can adopt to their data). The ratio was calculated, for each allele passing the filters, and summarized with other information such as position and type of the polymorphism in two distinct files called “parental alleles file”, for the data issued from the reference stain, and “recombined alleles file” for the potentially recombined strain (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b).</p>
      <p id="Par12">Next, to detect recombination, we considered the allelic ratio as: (1) invariable if the allele ratio was equal in the parental (P) and potentially recombinant (R) strains (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Fig. S1B), and (2) variable if the P alleles ratio was significantly different and followed the predicted likelihood of ratio variation summarized in (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Fig. S1-A and Table S3). For example, during recombination of a triploid cell, the variants with a parental ratio of 0.33 may vary to 0.66 or 0 (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Fig. S1c-top). If the ratio changes from 0.33 to 0 or 1, with a loss of depth of coverage this indicates a loss of a chromosome (3n to 2n—Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Fig. S1D-top). In contrast, If the ratio changes from 0.33 to 0.5 or 0.25 with a gain of depth of coverage this indicates a gain of a chromosome (3n to 4n—Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Fig. S1D-top). The outcome of this step is stored in two files called “variants alleles file” for information on the alleles with variants and “invariant alleles file” for those with invariant ratios. To robustly call the recombined region, we only retained those delimited by two break points holding at least 4 adjacent alleles that have undergone a variation of their allelic ratio. Nonetheless, regions that contain additional alleles with an invariable ratio were considered when a pair of two variant alleles were separated by a maximum of two invariant ones.</p>
      <p id="Par13">Lastly, the UGDR pipeline creates the “Region of recombination” file that contains all the information about the recombined regions (start and end as well as the number of variable alleles composing the region) and plots the recombination map.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec6">
      <title>Calculate the normalized depth of coverage (NDoC)</title>
      <p id="Par14">To evaluate the recombination region detection analysis, several features like Depth of Coverage (DoC) and mapping quality are important. The analysis of DoC is essential to detect events like insertion, deletion and copy number variation (CNV) between and along the chromosomes during recombination. We used the program DepthOfCoverage of the GATK toolkit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] to obtain the base-level coverage of the genome (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c). After that, to correct the technical DoC variation between parent and recombined cells, we calculated a normalized depth of coverage by dividing the base coverage of the recombinant cell by the base coverage of the parent and averaged the DoC by a one Kb sliding window along the genome (A cutoff that the users can adapt to their data). At the end of this step, the normalized coverage is written to a “Samplename_depthofCove.txt” file and the Depth of coverage plot is generated.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec7">
      <title>Display of recombination and coverage profiles</title>
      <p id="Par15">A genome-wide recombination profile is generated at the end of the process in which the parent and the recombinant genomes are plotted in parallel, and the alleles are represented in different colors according to their allele frequency status. The invariable genotypes (same ratio as the parent) are represented by gray markers (vertical lines), LOHs: ratio = 0, ratio = 1 are represented by red and blue markers, respectively and the heterozygous recombination events s are represented by black markers (e.g. 0.33–0.66 the marker at this location is black). To help identify chromosomal copy changes, the normalized depth of coverage of each chromosome is represented in parallel to the allele frequency where orange circles denote potential chromosomal loss and green dots denote potential chromosomal gain.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec8">
    <title>Results</title>
    <p id="Par16">We developed a computational approach to detect regions of recombination characterized by variation of the allelic ratio. It is based on the likelihood distribution of the alleles (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S3) between a parental cell and its progeny or between two evolved strains regardless of the ploidy of the cells. First, all the Paired-end Illumina Fastq reads data were processed by Galocal.sh. The NGS reads from the 4-spores tetrad, and the diploid RTGs strains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] were mapped to both S288C and SK1 genome reference separately, whereas the triploid and tetraploid clinical strains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] were mapped, to the S288C genome. The alignment outputs (BAM files) are involved to call variants and calculate the per base depth of coverage. Next, the UGDR and NDoC pipelines are implemented to inspect the ratio variation distribution, analyze the normalized depth of coverage for potential chromosomal insertion/deletion and plot the recombination profile.</p>
    <p id="Par17">Interestingly, the study of ratio distribution showed that the ratios are not exact values of 0.33, 0.67 and 1.0 for triploid strains and 0.25, 0.5, 0.75 and 1.0 for tetraploid strains as they likely experience a slight experimental deviation (<inline-formula id="IEq6"><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\theta$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M12"><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2022_5113_Article_IEq6.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Fig. S2). For example, the ratio of the heterozygous alleles in the diploid strains are centered around the value of 0.5, suggesting that the ratio of heterozygous alleles in diploids should fold in [<inline-formula id="IEq7"><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$0.5-\theta$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M14"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2022_5113_Article_IEq7.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, 0.5 + <inline-formula id="IEq8"><alternatives><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\theta$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M16"><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2022_5113_Article_IEq8.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>]. A similar observation has been made for the heterozygous allele ratio values in the triploid and tetraploid strains (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Fig. S2). Moreover, we observed a tight overlapping between the ratio groups of <inline-formula id="IEq9"><alternatives><tex-math id="M17">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$0.25\pm \theta$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M18"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.25</mml:mn><mml:mo>±</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2022_5113_Article_IEq9.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq10"><alternatives><tex-math id="M19">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$0.33\pm \theta$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M20"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.33</mml:mn><mml:mo>±</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2022_5113_Article_IEq10.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and the ratio groups of <inline-formula id="IEq11"><alternatives><tex-math id="M21">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$0.67\pm \theta$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M22"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.67</mml:mn><mml:mo>±</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2022_5113_Article_IEq11.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq12"><alternatives><tex-math id="M23">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$0.75\pm \theta$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M24"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.75</mml:mn><mml:mo>±</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2022_5113_Article_IEq12.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, suggesting that groups of alleles ratios might overlap and errors arise in ratio variation analysis. Therefore, for a better classification of the ratios and to bypass potential ratio variation analysis confounders, we defined the standard deviation (<inline-formula id="IEq13"><alternatives><tex-math id="M25">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\theta$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M26"><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2022_5113_Article_IEq13.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) as half the distance between the two adjacent groups (between 0.25 and 0.33 or 0.67 and 0.75), which is equal to <inline-formula id="IEq14"><alternatives><tex-math id="M27">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\theta$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M28"><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12859_2022_5113_Article_IEq14.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> = 0.04 (<italic>p</italic> value &lt; 0.05).</p>
    <p id="Par18">To examine UGDR’s ability to detect recombination regions, we analyzed three sets of yeast genome sequences: four spore-tetrad (RTG10M-1A, 1B, 1C and 1D), two diploid hybrids RTG cells (RTG17M a mother and RTG17D a daughter) and four clinical euploid strains (triploids: YJM1138 and YJM1140, tetraploids: YJM958 and YJM959—Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1).</p>
    <p id="Par19">The reads of the hybrid S288C/SK1 tetrads, were mapped to S288C (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a) and SK1 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b) haploid references separately (reference genome of only one of the parents). Unsurprisingly, the recombination profile of the tetrads mapped to S288C mirrored the recombination profile of the tetrads mapped to SK1. Indeed, the allele (SNP) genotype is established when the genotype call matches the parental genome mapped against. For example, in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a the red markers are the homozygous markers for S288C alleles (Parent 1) and the blue markers are the parent 2 (in this case it is SK1). On the other hand, in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b the red markers are the homozygous markers for SK1 alleles (Parent 1) and the blue markers are the parent 2 (in this case it is S288C). This indicates that in case of hybrid the reference sequence of only one parent can be used to detect recombination of the progeny. Next, following the ratio variation analysis, the segregation profile of the four-spore tetrads exhibited interstitial and terminal LOH regions of variable length (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The segregation profile of most markers exhibited the expected Mendelian pattern: heterozygous alleles position exhibited 2:2 segregation pattern and the homozygous alleles position exhibited a 4:0 segregation pattern (beginning of chromosome XIII). Additionally, the regions identified previously as masked cross over with (black box) and without (green box) adjacent gene conversion have been identified.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Segregation profile of four wild-type tetrads. The name of each tetrad is indicated on chromosome I. The x-axis represents the chromosome length and the y-axis represents the chromosome name. <bold>a</bold> The genotype of the tetrads when the S288C strain serves as reference, red markers are S288C (parent 1 S288C as a reference), blue markers are SK1 or parent 2 <bold>b</bold> The genotype of the tetrads when the SK1 strain serves as reference, red markers are SK1 (parent 1—SK1 as a reference), blue markers are S288C. Black and green boxes represent crossovers associated with (black boxes) or without (green box) an adjacent gene conversion segregate identified previously by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2022_5113_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
    <p id="Par20">The reads of the RTG17M and RTG17D were also mapped to S288C and SK1 separately. Like the tetrads, the recombination profile of the diploid RTGs mapped to S288C mirrored the recombination profile of the RTGs mapped to SK1 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a, and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Fig. S3), indicating that the likelihood distribution of the allele frequency adopted by UGDR could be detected without a merged reference genome. Besides, the genotype of the diploids RTG17M and RTG17D (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a) showed the expected opposite homozygote genotype supporting the occurrence of LOH regions in a successful return to growth process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. To note, the genotype profile of the RTG17D exhibits an increase of depth of coverage at the end of chromosomes III and a decrease of depth of coverage at the beginning of chromosomes V, indicating the presence of a duplication and deletion at these locations. These terminal chromosomal duplications/deletions were reported as a rearrangement resulting from recombination between dispersed Ty elements, that may result from ectopic Break Induced Replication (BIR) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. In Laureau et al. analysis, the recombination profile of the RTG17D at these locations showed a heterozygous allele profile, but the depth of coverage analysis indicated the presence of chromosomal duplications/deletions. Interestingly, this event clearly detected by UGDR and visualized by the presence of black markers at the end of chromosome III indicating allele frequency changes along with an increase of the Normalized DoC (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a, green dots). The duplication present at the end of chromosome III increases its ploidy from 2n to 3n, and as a result, the ratio of the embedded SNPs varied from 0.5 to 0.33 and/or 0.66 visible by the black bars at the end of chromosome III. However, the deletion observed on chromosome V (ploidy 2n to 1) is unambiguously distinguishable only by the decrease of the normalized DoC, since the SNPs ratio is either 1 (blue) or 0 (red). These results demonstrate the ability of UGDR, by combining the allele frequency variation and depth of coverage, to detect both LOH and structural variations missed by previous methods.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Genotype profile of diploids, triploid and tetraploid cells. <bold>a</bold> Genotype profile of the RTG17M and RTG17D cells mapped to S288C. <bold>b</bold> Genotype profile of polyploid strains: YJM1138 (3n) andYJM958 (4n). The genotype of the two RTGs and the genotype of 3n and 4n strains are shown on the top of each other (names are indicated on chromosome I). The x-axis represents the chromosome length and the y-axis represents the chromosome name. The orange and green dots represent the normalized depth of coverage (NDoC). Orange dots represent whether deletion occurs (NDoC &lt; 0.5) and green dots represent whether insertion occurs (NdoC &gt; 1.5). The genotypes: invariable (same ratio as the parent), LOH (ratio = 0), LOH (ratio = 1) and heterozygous recombination events are represented by the gray, red, blue and black markers (vertical lines), respectively</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12859_2022_5113_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
    <p id="Par21">Lastly, the reads of the phylogenetically close strains (YJM1138, YJM1140, YJM959 and YJM958) were mapped to the S288C strain (close ancestry) and variant calling analysis retained &gt; 68K heterozygous polymorphic positions along the 16 chromosomes for the recombination analysis. Since the parent of those cells is unknown, we selected for the triploids, the YJM1140 strain as a potential parent of the YJM1138 strain, and for the tetraploids, the strain YJM959 as a potential potential parent of the YJM958 strain. Although these strains were not the product of any recombination events, the analysis of ratio variation revealed the presence of several regions of recombination in the stains YJM1138, YJM958 relative to their selected parents. Regions where the recombination event led to large LOHs (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b red markers: 0.33–0 and blue markers 0.66 to 1) and regions where the recombination events occur between two chromosomal copies leading to alleles ratio variation (e.g. 0.3–0.66 or 0.66–0.33) without inducing LOH (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b Black markers—Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Fig. S1).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec9">
    <title>Discussion</title>
    <p id="Par22">In this study, we developed a python-based method called UGDR to detect recombination in different euploid strains and identify new out-performing recombinant yeast. To overcome the limitations of reference specificity and limited ploidy, UGDR is based uniquely on the analysis of allele ratio variation and supported by normalized depth of coverage. The allele ratio is calculated from the data obtained from the variant calling analysis, and the likelihood distribution of the allele frequency is used to detect recombination between two strains (parent and tetrads, mother and daughter or two phylogenetically close strains). The performance of UGDR was evaluated using four meiotic tetrads, two meiotically induced diploids, two triploids and two tetraploids obtained from the literature.</p>
    <p id="Par23">All previous computational approaches succeeded in detecting recombination in tetrads and diploids. Indeed, ReCombine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] was designed to detect recombination in tetrads and requires a merged reference genome containing both parental genomes with some hard coded parameters making it hard to apply for tetrads of unknown reference genome. Recently, RecombineX [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], a general automatic framework for polymorphic markers identification, improved the process of gametes genotyping in yeasts and extended the process to green alga. Clearly, UGDR is more suitable for tetrads with unavailable merged reference parent or a parent different than S288C; nevertheless, RecombineX would be more appropriate to analyze genomes from other organisms. The recombination events reported by Laureau et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] were detected based on  a merged reference. This strategy succeeded in screening the hybrid S288C/SK1 diploid RTGs but missed the direct detection of chromosomal rearrangement. Moreover, this method can’t be applied for other hybrids and ploidies. Meanwhile, UGDR was successful in accurately detecting recombination using separate parent and identifying both the presence of an ectopic recombination event and the change in the depth of coverage that occurred on the chromosomes III and V of the RTG17D. Additionally, UGDR was also able to screen different hybrid RTGs from two different industrial yeasts, different than S288C and SK1 (unpublished data). By extending its usage to polyploid strains, unlike previous methods, UGDR was successful in analyzing and accurately detecting recombination events in triploid and tetraploid yeasts downloaded from the literature. Several industrial triploids RTGs that underwent RTGs to induce recombination were analyzed by UGDR and the tool successfully selected different recombinants (with and without ploidy changes) that were later tested for their fermentation performance (unpublished data).</p>
    <p id="Par24">In conclusion, While UGDR is limited to detecting recombination regions in only yeast genomes with ploidy ≤ 4n, It provides information on the potential recombinations and/or chromosomal rearrangement that occurred between progenies and their parent, a mother and daughter and, unprecedentedly, between two polyploid cells. Such information helped in the identification of original recombinants that might be useful for their industrial application. Moreover, UGDR would be helpful for yeast’s new biotechnological research and applications with great benefits to humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Further developments are aimed at including the analysis of genomes different than yeast and higher ploidies (&gt; 4) in the perspective of expanding its use to other industries and academic research.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Information</title>
    <sec id="Sec10">
      <p>
        <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1">
          <media xlink:href="12859_2022_5113_MOESM1_ESM.pdf">
            <caption>
              <p><bold>Additional file 1.</bold> UGDR-Supplementary.</p>
            </caption>
          </media>
        </supplementary-material>
      </p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <fn-group>
    <fn>
      <p>
        <bold>Publisher's Note</bold>
      </p>
      <p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
    </fn>
  </fn-group>
  <ack>
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <p>The author would like to thank Dr. Alain Nicolas, Donald Halstead and Alexandre Serero for helpful comments on a draft of this manuscript, Sophie Loeillet for the helpful discussions and technical advices and Hector Maldonado Perez for fruitful discussions and critical reading of the manuscript. The author would like to specifically thank Dr. Martin J. Hessner for generously offering the open access fee.</p>
  </ack>
  <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
    <title>Author contributions</title>
    <p>AB implemented the pipeline, wrote the original manuscript, reviewed and edited the final manuscript. The author read and approved the final manuscript</p>
  </notes>
  <notes notes-type="funding-information">
    <title>Funding</title>
    <p>The work was funded by Meiogenix.</p>
  </notes>
  <notes notes-type="data-availability">
    <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
    <p>UGDR is freely distributed under GNU General Public License and available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/AnimaTardeb/Meiogenix-UGDR">https://github.com/AnimaTardeb/Meiogenix-UGDR</ext-link>. UGDR relies on the VCF files obtained by FreeBayes during variant calling and is compatible with Python version 2.7 (or later versions). The plotting programs are written in R and are compatible with R Version 3.2.3 or higher.</p>
  </notes>
  <notes>
    <title>Declarations</title>
    <notes id="FPar1">
      <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
      <p id="Par25">Not applicable.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes id="FPar2" notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p id="Par26">The author declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes id="FPar3">
      <title>Consent for publication</title>
      <p id="Par27">Not applicable.</p>
    </notes>
  </notes>
  <ref-list id="Bib1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="CR1">
      <label>1.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Murray</surname>
            <given-names>AW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Szostak</surname>
            <given-names>JW</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Construction of artificial chromosomes in yeast</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <year>1983</year>
        <volume>305</volume>
        <fpage>189</fpage>
        <lpage>193</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/305189a0</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6350893</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR2">
      <label>2.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Boulton</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Myers</surname>
            <given-names>RS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Redfield</surname>
            <given-names>RJ</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The hotspot conversion paradox and the evolution of meiotic recombination</article-title>
        <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source>
        <year>1997</year>
        <volume>94</volume>
        <fpage>8058</fpage>
        <lpage>8063</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.94.15.8058</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9223314</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR3">
      <label>3.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Doniger</surname>
            <given-names>SW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>HS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Swain</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Corcuera</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Williams</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>S-P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fay</surname>
            <given-names>JC</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A catalog of neutral and deleterious polymorphism in yeast</article-title>
        <source>PLoS Genet</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <fpage>1000183</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000183</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR4">
      <label>4.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sasaki</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lange</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Keeney</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Genome destabilization by homologous recombination in the germ line</article-title>
        <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm2849</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR5">
      <label>5.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yue</surname>
            <given-names>J-X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Aigrain</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hallin</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Persson</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Oliver</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bergström</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Coupland</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Warringer</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lagomarsino</surname>
            <given-names>MC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fischer</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Durbin</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liti</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Contrasting evolutionary genome dynamics between domesticated and wild yeasts</article-title>
        <source>Nat Genet</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>49</volume>
        <issue>6</issue>
        <fpage>913</fpage>
        <lpage>924</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3847</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28416820</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR6">
      <label>6.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lichten</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Goldman</surname>
            <given-names>AS</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Meiotic recombination hotspots</article-title>
        <source>Annu Rev Genet</source>
        <year>1995</year>
        <volume>29</volume>
        <fpage>423</fpage>
        <lpage>44</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.ge.29.120195.002231</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8825482</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR7">
      <label>7.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Grelon</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Meiotic recombination mechanisms</article-title>
        <source>C R Biol</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>339</volume>
        <fpage>247</fpage>
        <lpage>251</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.crvi.2016.04.003</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27180110</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR8">
      <label>8.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mancera</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bourgon</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Brozzi</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huber</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Steinmetz</surname>
            <given-names>LM</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>High-resolution mapping of meiotic crossovers and non-crossovers in yeast</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>454</volume>
        <issue>7203</issue>
        <fpage>479</fpage>
        <lpage>485</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature07135</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18615017</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR9">
      <label>9.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Anderson</surname>
            <given-names>CM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>SY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dimon</surname>
            <given-names>MT</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Oke</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>DeRisi</surname>
            <given-names>JL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fung</surname>
            <given-names>JC</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>ReCombine: a suite of programs for detection and analysis of meiotic recombination in whole-genome datasets</article-title>
        <source>PLoS ONE</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <fpage>25509</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0025509</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR10">
      <label>10.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Llorente</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liti</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yue</surname>
            <given-names>J-X</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Recombinex: a generalized computational framework for automatic high-throughput gamete genotyping and tetrad-based recombination analysis</article-title>
        <source>PLOS Genet</source>
        <year>2022</year>
        <volume>18</volume>
        <fpage>1010047</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1010047</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR11">
      <label>11.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Laureau</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Loeillet</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Salinas</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bergström</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Legoix-Né</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liti</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nicolas</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Extensive recombination of a yeast diploid hybrid through meiotic reversion</article-title>
        <source>PLOS Genet</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <fpage>1005781</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005781</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR12">
      <label>12.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tattini</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tellini</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mozzachiodi</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>D’Angiolo</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Loeillet</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nicolas</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liti</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Accurate tracking of the mutational landscape of diploid hybrid genomes</article-title>
        <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msz177</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR13">
      <label>13.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>YO</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sherlock</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Petrov</surname>
            <given-names>DA</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Whole genome analysis of 132 clinical saccharomyces cerevisiae strains reveals extensive ploidy variation</article-title>
        <source>G3 Genes Genomes Genet</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <issue>8</issue>
        <fpage>2421</fpage>
        <lpage>2434</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.116.029397</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR14">
      <label>14.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Durbin</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Fast and accurate short read alignment with Burrows–Wheeler transform</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics (Oxford, England)</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <issue>14</issue>
        <fpage>1754</fpage>
        <lpage>60</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp324</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19451168</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR15">
      <label>15.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Engel</surname>
            <given-names>SR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dietrich</surname>
            <given-names>FS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fisk</surname>
            <given-names>DG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Binkley</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Balakrishnan</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Costanzo</surname>
            <given-names>MC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dwight</surname>
            <given-names>SS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hitz</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Karra</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nash</surname>
            <given-names>RS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Weng</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wong</surname>
            <given-names>ED</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lloyd</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Skrzypek</surname>
            <given-names>MS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Miyasato</surname>
            <given-names>SR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Simison</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cherry</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The Reference Genome Sequence of Saccharomyces cerevisiae: then and Now</article-title>
        <source>G3 Genes Genomes Genet</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <fpage>89</fpage>
        <lpage>398</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.113.008995</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR16">
      <label>16.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ebbert</surname>
            <given-names>MTW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wadsworth</surname>
            <given-names>ME</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Staley</surname>
            <given-names>LA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hoyt</surname>
            <given-names>KL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pickett</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Miller</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Duce</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kauwe</surname>
            <given-names>JSK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ridge</surname>
            <given-names>PG</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Evaluating the necessity of PCR duplicate removal from next-generation sequencing data and a comparison of approaches</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinform</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>17</volume>
        <issue>S7</issue>
        <fpage>239</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-016-1097-3</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR17">
      <label>17.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Garrison E, Marth G. Haplotype-based variant detection from short-read sequencing (2012). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1207.3907v2">arXiv:1207.3907v2</ext-link></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR18">
      <label>18.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">McKenna A, Hanna M, Banks E, Sivachenko A, Cibulskis K, Kernytsky A, Garimella K, Altshuler D, Gabriel S, Daly M, DePristo MA. The genome analysis toolkit: a MapReduce framework for analyzing next-generation DNA sequencing data. Genome Res. 2010. 10.1101/gr.107524.110. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1011.1669">arXiv:1011.1669</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR19">
      <label>19.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ewing</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Green</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Base-calling of automated sequencer traces using Phred. II. Error probabilities</article-title>
        <source>Genome Res</source>
        <year>1998</year>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <fpage>186</fpage>
        <lpage>194</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.8.3.186</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9521922</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR20">
      <label>20.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Llorente B, Smith CE, Symington LS. Break-induced replication: What is it and what is it for? (2008). 10.4161/cc.7.7.5613</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR21">
      <label>21.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sasaki</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tischfield</surname>
            <given-names>SE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>van Overbeek</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Keeney</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Meiotic recombination initiation in and around retrotransposable elements in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title>
        <source>PLoS Genet</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <issue>8</issue>
        <fpage>1003732</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003732</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR22">
      <label>22.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zymanczyk-Duda</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Brzezińska-Rodak</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Klimek-Ochab</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Duda</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zerka</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <person-group person-group-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Morata</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Loira</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Yeast as a versatile tool in biotechnology</article-title>
        <source>Yeast</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <publisher-loc>Rijeka</publisher-loc>
        <publisher-name>IntechOpen</publisher-name>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR23">
      <label>23.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tullio</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Yeast genomics and its applications in biotechnological processes: What is our present and near future?</article-title>
        <source>J Fungi</source>
        <year>2022</year>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <fpage>752</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jof8070752</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
