<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?properties open_access?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1367-4803</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1367-4811</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">9665871</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36130056</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btac639</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">btac639</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Original Papers</subject>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading">
          <subject>Data and Text Mining</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01060</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>Reproducible acquisition, management and meta-analysis of nucleotide sequence (meta)data using q2-fondue</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6285-8852</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Ziemski</surname>
          <given-names>Michal</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="btac639-FM1" ref-type="author-notes"/>
        <aff><institution>Laboratory of Food Systems Biotechnology, Institute of Food, Nutrition, and Health, ETH Zürich</institution>, Zürich 8092, <country country="CH">Switzerland</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7506-1583</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Adamov</surname>
          <given-names>Anja</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="btac639-FM1" ref-type="author-notes"/>
        <aff><institution>Laboratory of Food Systems Biotechnology, Institute of Food, Nutrition, and Health, ETH Zürich</institution>, Zürich 8092, <country country="CH">Switzerland</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Kim</surname>
          <given-names>Lina</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Laboratory of Food Systems Biotechnology, Institute of Food, Nutrition, and Health, ETH Zürich</institution>, Zürich 8092, <country country="CH">Switzerland</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Flörl</surname>
          <given-names>Lena</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Laboratory of Food Systems Biotechnology, Institute of Food, Nutrition, and Health, ETH Zürich</institution>, Zürich 8092, <country country="CH">Switzerland</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <name>
          <surname>Bokulich</surname>
          <given-names>Nicholas A</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="btac639-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
        <!--nicholas.bokulich@hest.ethz.ch-->
        <aff><institution>Laboratory of Food Systems Biotechnology, Institute of Food, Nutrition, and Health, ETH Zürich</institution>, Zürich 8092, <country country="CH">Switzerland</country></aff>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name>
          <surname>Wren</surname>
          <given-names>Jonathan</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Associate Editor</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <fn id="btac639-FM1">
        <p>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, Michal Ziemski and Anja Adamov should be regarded as Joint First Authors.</p>
      </fn>
      <corresp id="btac639-cor1">To whom correspondence should be addressed. <email>nicholas.bokulich@hest.ethz.ch</email></corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <day>15</day>
      <month>11</month>
      <year>2022</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2022-09-20">
      <day>20</day>
      <month>9</month>
      <year>2022</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>20</day>
      <month>9</month>
      <year>2022</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>38</volume>
    <issue>22</issue>
    <fpage>5081</fpage>
    <lpage>5091</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>04</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>08</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="editorial-decision">
        <day>09</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>19</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="corrected-typeset">
        <day>04</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2022. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xlink:href="btac639.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <sec id="s1">
        <title>Motivation</title>
        <p>The volume of public nucleotide sequence data has blossomed over the past two decades and is ripe for re- and meta-analyses to enable novel discoveries. However, reproducible re-use and management of sequence datasets and associated metadata remain critical challenges. We created the open source Python package <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> to enable user-friendly acquisition, re-use and management of public sequence (meta)data while adhering to open data principles.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2">
        <title>Results</title>
        <p><italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> allows fully provenance-tracked programmatic access to and management of data from the NCBI Sequence Read Archive (SRA). Unlike other packages allowing download of sequence data from the SRA, <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> enables full data provenance tracking from data download to final visualization, integrates with the QIIME 2 ecosystem, prevents data loss upon space exhaustion and allows download of (meta)data given a publication library. To highlight its manifold capabilities, we present executable demonstrations using publicly available amplicon, whole genome and metagenome datasets.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3">
        <title>Availability and implementation</title>
        <p><italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> is available as an open-source BSD-3-licensed Python package at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/bokulich-lab/q2-fondue" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/bokulich-lab/q2-fondue</ext-link>. Usage tutorials are available in the same repository. All Jupyter notebooks used in this article are available under <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/bokulich-lab/q2-fondue-examples" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/bokulich-lab/q2-fondue-examples</ext-link>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s5">
        <title>Supplementary information</title>
        <p><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary data</xref> are available at <italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic> online.</p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <abstract abstract-type="graphical">
      <title>Graphical Abstract</title>
      <p>
        <fig position="float" id="btac639-F8">
          <graphic xlink:href="btac639f8" position="float"/>
        </fig>
      </p>
    </abstract>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Strategic Focus Area ‘Personalized Health and Related Technologies</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>#2021-362</award-id>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Swiss Federal Institutes of Technology</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Swiss National Science Foundation</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100001711</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>310030_204275</award-id>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Swiss Government Excellence</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="11"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec>
    <title>1 Introduction</title>
    <p>The increasing volume of publicly available nucleotide sequence data is driving a revolution in the life sciences, by enabling comparative studies to discover generalizable trends that are often inaccessible or underpowered in an individual study. Individual studies addressing similar biological questions can differ in many technical aspects, including (but not limited to) specific experimental design, employed sequencing technologies, definitions of the examined target variables and selection of potential covariates influencing the target. These inter-study variations can make individual study results biased (<xref rid="btac639-B43" ref-type="bibr">Serghiou <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>) and even contradictory to one another (<xref rid="btac639-B20" ref-type="bibr">Ioannidis and Trikalinos, 2005</xref>). Meta-analysis allows the synthesis of findings from individual studies to reach a more complete understanding: identifying consistent and reproducible signatures across studies and resolving causes of variation among study results (<xref rid="btac639-B14" ref-type="bibr">Gurevitch <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>).</p>
    <p>Meta-analyses of nucleotide sequencing-based studies have intensified within the past decade (see <xref rid="btac639-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>), given the high potential of these data for reuse in comparative analyses. Meta-analyses of genome-wide association data have expanded our knowledge of human polygenic disorders and quantitative traits (<xref rid="btac639-B38" ref-type="bibr">Panagiotou <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Comparative genomics has given insights into vertebrate genome evolution (<xref rid="btac639-B34" ref-type="bibr">Meadows and Lindblad-Toh, 2017</xref>) and the processes of genome function, speciation, selection and adaptation (<xref rid="btac639-B2" ref-type="bibr">Alföldi and Lindblad-Toh, 2013</xref>). Comparative analyses of global microbiome datasets have driven deepening insight into spatiotemporal and biogeographic variation in Earth’s microbial diversity (<xref rid="btac639-B45" ref-type="bibr">Tara Oceans Consortium Coordinators <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="btac639-B47" ref-type="bibr">Thompson <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). Re-analysis of the published genome and metagenome data has enabled the discovery of novel and candidate microbial clades, as in the Genome Taxonomy Database (<xref rid="btac639-B39" ref-type="bibr">Parks <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>), and highlighted the abundance (<xref rid="btac639-B28" ref-type="bibr">Lloyd <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>) and ecosystem-impact (<xref rid="btac639-B53" ref-type="bibr">Zamkovaya <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>) of uncultured microbes, also known as ‘microbial dark matter’. Since meta-analyses can only be conducted if the original study data are publicly available, the recent increase in meta-analyses can be partly attributed to the ongoing open-science efforts of making sequencing data and accompanying metadata standardized and publicly available (<xref rid="btac639-B5" ref-type="bibr">Berman <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="btac639-B33" ref-type="bibr">McNutt <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="btac639-B46" ref-type="bibr">The Path to Open Data, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="btac639-B51" ref-type="bibr">Yilmaz <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). The Sequence Read Archive (SRA), established as part of the International Nucleotide Sequence Database Collaboration (INSDC) by the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI), enables free access to sequence data (<xref rid="btac639-B24" ref-type="bibr">Kodama <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="btac639-B26" ref-type="bibr">Leinonen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011b</xref>), including sequences stored on ENA (<xref rid="btac639-B25" ref-type="bibr">Leinonen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011a</xref>) and DDBJ (<xref rid="btac639-B30" ref-type="bibr">Mashima <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). Since its creation in 2009, the SRA has gathered data at the petabyte scale and continues to scale its infrastructure to ensure efficient data storage and retrieval (Katz <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021).</p>
    <fig position="float" id="btac639-F1">
      <label>Fig. 1.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Increasing trend of sequencing-based meta-analyses over the past 30 years. Displayed article counts were retrieved from PubMed on February 21, 2022 with the search query ‘(meta-analysis) AND ((omics) OR (genom*) OR (microbio*) OR (transcriptom*))’ and a requirement for the article type to be a meta-analysis</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="btac639f1" position="float"/>
    </fig>
    <p>A selection of tools to programmatically access data from the SRA has recently emerged. NCBI offers the <italic toggle="yes">sra-tools</italic> command-line toolkit (<xref rid="btac639-B26" ref-type="bibr">Leinonen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011b</xref>) for downloading and interacting with raw sequence data. The <italic toggle="yes">entrezpy</italic> Python library (<xref rid="btac639-B10" ref-type="bibr">Buchmann and Holmes, 2019</xref>) aids in automating the data download from NCBI’s Entrez databases by providing abstract classes allowing custom implementations. <italic toggle="yes">pysradb</italic> (<xref rid="btac639-B12" ref-type="bibr">Choudhary, 2019</xref>) makes use of the curated metadata database available through the SRAdb project (<xref rid="btac639-B54" ref-type="bibr">Zhu <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>) to download data from the SRA, and <italic toggle="yes">grabseqs</italic> enables fetching of data from not only the SRA but also MG-RAST (<xref rid="btac639-B35" ref-type="bibr">Meyer <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>) and iMicrobe (<xref rid="btac639-B52" ref-type="bibr">Youens-Clark <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>). However, the wider application of these tools in large comparative analyses is hindered by several challenges, including technical complication and a steep learning curve for users with limited programming skills, and the difficulty of tracking data provenance necessary for reproducibility and traceability.</p>
    <p>In order to provide consistent and reliable findings, meta-analyses must follow Findable, Accessible, Interoperable and Reusable (FAIR) Guiding Principles (<xref rid="btac639-B50" ref-type="bibr">Wilkinson <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). To this end, meta-analyses should be performed in a reproducible manner, making use of consistent workflows while keeping track of all the performed data retrieval and analysis steps. Despite increasingly facilitated access to sequencing data, reproducibility and provenance of primary and secondary studies remain challenging (<xref rid="btac639-B3" ref-type="bibr">Amann <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="btac639-B4" ref-type="bibr">Baker, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="btac639-B17" ref-type="bibr">Huang and Gottardo, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="btac639-B23" ref-type="bibr">Kim <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="btac639-B42" ref-type="bibr">Reichman <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Here, we introduce an open-source software package <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> (<bold>F</bold>unctions for reproducibly <bold>O</bold>btaining and <bold>N</bold>ormalizing <bold>D</bold>ata re-<bold>U</bold>sed from <bold>E</bold>lsewhere) to expedite the initial acquisition of data from the SRA, while offering complete provenance tracking. <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> simplifies retrieval of sequencing data and accompanying metadata in a validated and standardized format interoperable with the QIIME 2 ecosystem (<xref rid="btac639-B9" ref-type="bibr">Bolyen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>). By allowing access through multiple QIIME 2 user interfaces, it can be employed by users of different computational capabilities.</p>
    <p>Here, we describe the <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> software package and subsequently demonstrate its use in comparative analyses of marker gene, genome and metagenome sequencing studies. We anticipate <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> will lower existing barriers to comparative analyses of nucleotide sequence data, facilitating more transparent, open and reproducible conduct of meta-analyses.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>2 Implementation</title>
    <sec>
      <title>2.1 Software overview</title>
      <p><italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> is an open source Python 3 package released under the BSD 3-clause license. It can be installed in a conda environment on any UNIX-based system as described in the installation instructions provided on the package website (<ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/bokulich-lab/q2-fondue" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/bokulich-lab/q2-fondue</ext-link>). <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> has been implemented as a QIIME 2 plugin, allowing the use of QIIME 2’s integrated data provenance tracking system, multiple user interfaces and streamlined interoperability with downstream sequence analysis plugins.</p>
      <p>An overview of <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> is shown in <xref rid="btac639-F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>. Two separate <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> actions allow easy access to the SRA database: <italic toggle="yes">get-sequences</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">get-metadata</italic> fetch per-sample sequence data and corresponding metadata (e.g. sample and run information), respectively. The <italic toggle="yes">get-all</italic> pipeline wraps both of these actions to simultaneously retrieve sequences and metadata for a list of SRA accessions. These three actions, <italic toggle="yes">get-sequences</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">get-metadata</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">get-all</italic>, require a single input file containing accession IDs of one type to be fetched. Currently, <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> supports BioProject, study, sample, experiment and run accession IDs. BioProject and study IDs are in a one-to-one relationship, where a study ID denotes the SRA record of the associated BioProject ID. All other IDs are in a one-to-many relationship in the listed order (e.g. one study ID, with its linked BioProject ID, can have many sample IDs associated with it—see <xref rid="btac639-F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> for an overview). Run IDs allow direct interaction with the SRA databases, while the other IDs are first translated into corresponding run IDs using a chain of E-Direct utilities (<xref rid="btac639-B21" ref-type="bibr">Kans, 2013</xref>; <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK179288/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK179288/</ext-link>). An <italic toggle="yes">E-Search</italic> query is executed to look up provided IDs in the BioProject (if BioProject ID was provided as input) or SRA (if study, sample or experiment ID was provided as input) database, followed by an <italic toggle="yes">E-Link</italic> query finalized by an <italic toggle="yes">E-Fetch</italic> query to retrieve the linked run IDs.</p>
      <fig position="float" id="btac639-F2">
        <label>Fig. 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Overview of <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> methods. <italic toggle="yes">get-sequences</italic> method can be used to fetch raw sequencing data (single- and/or paired-end), while <italic toggle="yes">get-metadata</italic> can download corresponding metadata. Both methods can be run simultaneously by using the <italic toggle="yes">get-all</italic> pipeline, which produces all outputs (SampleData, SRAFailedIDs and SRAMetadata). <italic toggle="yes">get-sequences</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">get-metadata</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">get-all</italic> are run with a list of one type of accession IDs (BioProject, study, sample, experiment or run ID). Sequences obtained from multiple fetches can be combined using <italic toggle="yes">combine-seqs</italic> and multiple metadata artifacts can be merged with <italic toggle="yes">merge-metadata</italic>. All accession IDs can be retrieved from Zotero web library collections with the <italic toggle="yes">scrape-collection</italic> action</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="btac639f2" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <fig position="float" id="btac639-F3">
        <label>Fig. 3.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Structure of the SRA metadata data classes used by the <italic toggle="yes">get-metadata</italic> action. Each of the classes represents a different level of metadata organization and can contain other nested metadata objects. As all the objects are linked together, metadata of the entire study and all its children can be retrieved directly from the SRAStudy object</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="btac639f3" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>All data-fetching actions support configurable parallelization to maximally reduce the processing time. The <italic toggle="yes">get-metadata</italic> method employs a multi-threading approach built into the <italic toggle="yes">Entrezpy</italic> modules (see Section 2.2.), while <italic toggle="yes">get-sequences</italic> uses multiple processes and queues to coordinate the data download with its pre- and post-processing steps. Note that parallelization does not improve download speed (for which network bandwidth is the limiting factor), but markedly decreases pre- and post-processing runtime (e.g. data validation steps) (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S1</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>2.2 Sequence retrieval</title>
      <p>The <italic toggle="yes">get-sequences</italic> action makes use of the <italic toggle="yes">sra-tools</italic> command-line toolkit (<xref rid="btac639-B26" ref-type="bibr">Leinonen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011b</xref>; <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/ncbi/sra-tools" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/ncbi/sra-tools</ext-link>) developed by NCBI. The <italic toggle="yes">prefetch</italic> tool is first used to reliably fetch SRA datafiles using the provided run IDs and the <italic toggle="yes">fasterq-dump</italic> utility is then executed to retrieve the corresponding sequences (single- or paired-end) in the FASTQ format. To follow QIIME 2’s naming convention those sequences are then renamed using their accession IDs, compressed and finally validated by QIIME 2’s built-in type validation system. The action keeps track of any errors that occurred while fetching the sequences and performs available storage checks on every iteration to ensure no data are lost when space is exhausted during download. There are three output files generated by the <italic toggle="yes">get-sequences</italic> action: two QIIME artifacts corresponding to single- and paired-end reads, respectively, and one table containing the list of IDs for which the download failed (if any) including the linked error messages.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>2.2 Metadata retrieval</title>
      <p>Retrieval of SRA metadata is possible through the <italic toggle="yes">get-metadata</italic> action. This action uses the <italic toggle="yes">Entrezpy</italic> package (<xref rid="btac639-B10" ref-type="bibr">Buchmann and Holmes, 2019</xref>) to interact with the SRA database by building on top of its built-in modules for different E-Direct utilities. Specifically, we implemented a new <italic toggle="yes">EFetchResult</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">EFetchAnalyzer</italic> that work in tandem to request and parse metadata for the provided run IDs. The result is represented as a table where a single row corresponds to one SRA run and columns reflect all the metadata fields found in the obtained response. In order to keep track of different metadata levels (study, sample, experiment and run), we introduced a set of cascading Python data classes to delineate the hierarchical relationship of the SRA metadata entries (<xref rid="btac639-F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>) and to preserve this structure in the final study metadata. Moreover, tight integration with QIIME 2’s internal type validation system guarantees consistency of metadata generated by <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> by ensuring the presence of all required metadata fields, as specified by NCBI.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>2.2 Metadata retrieval</title>
      <p>The <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> package contains additional functions to simplify sequencing (meta)data retrieval and manipulation, particularly when multiple data fetches are necessary.
</p>
      <list list-type="bullet">
        <list-item>
          <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">get-all</italic></bold> allows the simultaneous download of sequences and related metadata.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">merge-metadata</italic></bold> concatenates metadata tables obtained from several independent <italic toggle="yes">get-metadata</italic> runs and allows the generation of a single, unified metadata artifact.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">combine-seqs</italic></bold> merges sequences obtained from multiple artifacts obtained from several <italic toggle="yes">get-sequences</italic> runs (or from other external sources) into a single sequence artifact.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">scrape-collection</italic></bold> retrieves accession IDs and associated DOI names from a Zotero web library collection (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.zotero.org" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.zotero.org</ext-link>) by using the <italic toggle="yes">pyzotero</italic> package (<xref rid="btac639-B18" ref-type="bibr">Hügel <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>). This enables seamless workflows for collecting IDs of interest from a literature collection, automatically downloading the data, and processing downstream with <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> and QIIME 2.</p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>3 Materials and methods</title>
    <p>The <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> plugin can be used to facilitate comparative analysis of any nucleotide sequence data and metadata available on the SRA. To demonstrate some example use cases, we used <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> and QIIME 2 to analyze publicly available marker gene, whole genome sequence and shotgun metagenome data. All analyses described below are available as fully reproducible and executable Jupyter notebooks (available in the Data Availability section). These examples are provided merely as method demonstrations to showcase seamless integration/interoperation of <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> with downstream analyses and do not represent complete analyses of biological data. Additional steps and larger comparative analyses would be required to derive meaningful conclusions, and to eliminate potential biases from covariates, which were not controlled for in this demonstration analysis.</p>
    <sec>
      <title>3.1 Marker gene amplicon sequence data analysis</title>
      <p>Marker gene amplicon sequencing (e.g. of 16S rRNA genes) is currently the most popular method for high-throughput, untargeted profiling of microbial communities as well as non-microbial diet metabarcoding and environmental DNA applications. To demonstrate the use of <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> for comparative cross-study analysis of marker gene amplicon sequence data, we selected three studies that analyzed the development of the infant gut microbiome in distinct geographical locations: <xref rid="btac639-B27" ref-type="bibr">Lewis <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2017)</xref> with BioProjectID PRJEB16321, <xref rid="btac639-B13" ref-type="bibr">Davis <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2017)</xref> with BioProjectID PRJEB15633 and <xref rid="btac639-B31" ref-type="bibr">McClorry <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2018)</xref> with BioProjectID PRJEB23239. All three studies sequenced 16S rRNA genes in the V4 region with the forward 515F primer and a read length of 251 to 253 nucleotides. <xref rid="btac639-B31" ref-type="bibr">McClorry <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2018)</xref> additionally used the reverse primer R806.</p>
      <p>The <italic toggle="yes">get-all</italic> action of <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> was used to retrieve metadata and sequence data of all three studies from the SRA. To normalize metadata features of interest across studies, namely age and health status, we employed the Python library <italic toggle="yes">pandas</italic> (<xref rid="btac639-B32" ref-type="bibr">McKinney, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="btac639-B41" ref-type="bibr">Reback <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). The downloaded single-read gene sequences were filtered according to the availability of metadata with the <italic toggle="yes">q2-demux</italic> QIIME 2 plugin (<ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/qiime2/q2-demux" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/qiime2/q2-demux</ext-link>), denoised with the <italic toggle="yes">q2-dada2</italic> QIIME 2 plugin (<xref rid="btac639-B11" ref-type="bibr">Callahan <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>), <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/qiime2/q2-dada2" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/qiime2/q2-dada2</ext-link>) and finally features were filtered by frequency, rarefied and summarized with the <italic toggle="yes">q2-feature-table</italic> QIIME 2 plugin (<xref rid="btac639-B7" ref-type="bibr">Bokulich <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018b</xref>) <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/qiime2/q2-feature-table" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/qiime2/q2-feature-table</ext-link>). Finally, the processed metadata and sequence data were used to train two Random Forest classifiers with <italic toggle="yes">q2-sample-classifier</italic> (<xref rid="btac639-B6" ref-type="bibr">Bokulich <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018a</xref>), <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/qiime2/q2-sample-classifier" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/qiime2/q2-sample-classifier</ext-link>) to predict an infant’s age and its health status from its gut microbiome. The infant’s age was reported in four binned age groups: 0–1, 1–4, 4–6 and older than 6 months. For the health status, an infant was identified as healthy if no disease-related features were reported, namely no indication of stunting, wasting, underweight, elevated C-reactive protein status, parasites or anemia. Both classifiers were trained and tested with 10-fold cross-validation using Random Forest classifiers grown with 500 trees. The performance of the trained classifiers was evaluated on the area under the curve (AUC) of the receiver operating characteristics (ROC) curve of the test set of each fold using <italic toggle="yes">scikit-learn</italic> implementations (<xref rid="btac639-B40" ref-type="bibr">Pedregosa <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). The entire analysis can be reproduced by executing the <italic toggle="yes">u1-amplicon.ipynb</italic> Jupyter notebook, available in the Data Availability section.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>3.2 Comparative whole-genome sequence data analysis</title>
      <p>The initial list of SARS-CoV-2 whole genome sequencing data accession IDs was generated based on the metadata obtained from the Nextstrain.org platform (<xref rid="btac639-B15" ref-type="bibr">Hadfield <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>; <ext-link xlink:href="https://data.nextstrain.org/files/ncov/open/metadata.tsv.gz" ext-link-type="uri">https://data.nextstrain.org/files/ncov/open/metadata.tsv.gz</ext-link>, access date: February 08, 2022). Only records with available SRA accession IDs and the least amount of missing data (column <italic toggle="yes">QC_missing_data ==</italic> ‘<italic toggle="yes">good</italic>’) were retained. Furthermore, to limit the scope of this use case only those geographical regions were considered where enough samples were collected (at least 2000 samples per region). The <italic toggle="yes">get-metadata</italic> action of <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> was used to retrieve metadata of 37 500 randomly sampled genomes (12 500 genomes per location) from the SRA. Obtained metadata was then supplemented with the original Nextstrain metadata by merging the two datasets on a common SRA run ID and only samples sequenced using single-end reads on the Illumina NextSeq 500/550 platforms were retained. Finally, sequencing data for 500 randomly sampled genomes (250 genomes per location) was fetched from the SRA using <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue’</italic>s <italic toggle="yes">get-sequences</italic> method. Reads shorter than 35 nt were discarded using the <italic toggle="yes">trim_single</italic> method from the <italic toggle="yes">q2-cutadapt</italic> plugin (<xref rid="btac639-B29" ref-type="bibr">Martin, 2011</xref>; <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/qiime2/q2-cutadapt" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/qiime2/q2-cutadapt</ext-link>) and the quality of the sequences was evaluated using the <italic toggle="yes">summarize</italic> action from the <italic toggle="yes">q2-demux</italic> QIIME 2 plugin (<ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/qiime2/q2-demux" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/qiime2/q2-demux</ext-link>). MinHash signatures were computed for every sample and compared using the <italic toggle="yes">q2-sourmash</italic> plugin (<italic toggle="yes">compute</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">compare</italic> methods, respectively) (<xref rid="btac639-B37" ref-type="bibr">Ondov <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>; <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/dib-lab/q2-sourmash" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/dib-lab/q2-sourmash</ext-link>). A t-SNE plot was generated from the resulting distance matrix using <italic toggle="yes">q2-diversity</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">tsne</italic> method with a learning rate of 125 and perplexity set to 18, <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/qiime2/q2-diversity" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/qiime2/q2-diversity</ext-link>, <xref rid="btac639-B16" ref-type="bibr">Halko <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>) and visualized using <italic toggle="yes">matplotlib</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">seaborn</italic> Python packages (<xref rid="btac639-B19" ref-type="bibr">Hunter, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="btac639-B49" ref-type="bibr">Waskom, 2021</xref>). Finally, to determine whether MinHash signatures are predictive of SARS-CoV-2 geographic origin, k-nearest-neighbors classification with 10-fold cross-validation was applied through the <italic toggle="yes">q2-sample-classifier</italic> plugin (<xref rid="btac639-B6" ref-type="bibr">Bokulich <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018a</xref>; <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/qiime2/q2-sample-classifier" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/qiime2/q2-sample-classifier</ext-link>). The entire analysis can be reproduced by executing the <italic toggle="yes">u2-genome.ipynb</italic> Jupyter notebook, available in the Data Availability section.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>3.3 Shotgun metagenome sequence data analysis</title>
      <p>To fetch metadata for all the shotgun metagenome samples from the Tara Oceans Expedition (<xref rid="btac639-B45" ref-type="bibr">Tara Oceans Consortium Coordinators <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>) we used <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue’</italic>s <italic toggle="yes">get-metadata</italic> action with the following BioProject IDs: PRJEB1787, PRJEB4352, PRJEB4419, PRJEB9691, PRJEB9740 and PRJEB9742. After the removal of missing values, the resulting metadata table was randomly sampled to 100 records and used as input to the <italic toggle="yes">draw-interactive-map</italic> action from the <italic toggle="yes">q2-coordinates</italic> plugin (<xref rid="btac639-B8" ref-type="bibr">Bokulich and Caporaso, 2018</xref>; <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/bokulich-lab/q2-coordinates" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/bokulich-lab/q2-coordinates</ext-link>) to visualize values of the sensors used during the expedition according to their geographical location. Additionally, sequences corresponding to 10 samples at two different locations were fetched using the <italic toggle="yes">get-sequences</italic> action. To reduce the computational time required for this use case demonstration, the reads were subsampled to 20% of the original read count and the resulting artifact (containing single-end reads) was used to calculate and compare MinHash signatures (see the previous section). A PCoA analysis was performed on the resulting distance matrix using the <italic toggle="yes">pcoa</italic> action from the <italic toggle="yes">q2-diversity</italic> plugin (<ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/qiime2/q2-diversity;" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/qiime2/q2-diversity;</ext-link><xref rid="btac639-B16" ref-type="bibr">Halko <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>) and the PCoA plot was visualized using <italic toggle="yes">matplotlib</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">seaborn</italic> Python packages (<xref rid="btac639-B19" ref-type="bibr">Hunter, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="btac639-B49" ref-type="bibr">Waskom, 2021</xref>). The entire analysis can be reproduced by executing the <italic toggle="yes">u3-metagenome.ipynb</italic> Jupyter notebook, available in the Data Availability section.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>4 Results</title>
    <p>Any meta-analysis can be carried out using raw experimental data, its associated metadata or a combination of both. To demonstrate the versatility of <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> in all those scenarios, and seamless integration/interoperability with downstream bioinformatics tools, we performed three example use case data analyses using amplicon, whole genome, and shotgun metagenome sequencing data and related metadata. All three use cases employ QIIME 2 plugins to process received data and illustrate how <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> can immensely increase data analysis reproducibility and transparency by including details on the raw data fetching in the QIIME 2 provenance. These analyses are only meant to demonstrate some example use cases for <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> and should not be interpreted as biologically meaningful results.</p>
    <sec>
      <title>4.1 Use Case 1: amplicon sequence data analysis</title>
      <p>As a demonstration of <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic>’s capacities in enabling the collection and analysis of amplicon sequencing data, we selected three infant gut microbiome development studies from distinct geographical locations: the study by <xref rid="btac639-B27" ref-type="bibr">Lewis <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2017)</xref> from Georgia, <xref rid="btac639-B13" ref-type="bibr">Davis <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2017)</xref>’s study from Gambia and <xref rid="btac639-B31" ref-type="bibr">McClorry <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2018)</xref>’s study from Peru. We used the BioProject IDs reported by those studies to fetch the corresponding raw metadata and sequencing data. This provided us with 350 sequence samples each annotated with 148 metadata features.</p>
      <p>After performing filtering, normalization and denoising steps on the raw 16S rRNA gene sequences (see <xref rid="btac639-F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4A</xref> for an overview of plugins and actions used throughout this use case), a total of 3880 amplicon sequencing variants (ASVs) were identified for 330 samples. The available metadata was used to define binned age groups. The distribution of samples per age group as well as the analyzed age range differ markedly between studies (<xref rid="btac639-F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4B</xref>). We further defined a binary health status which denotes whether the sample stems from a healthy or unhealthy infant (see Methods for more details). Across all studies, 194 unhealthy and 136 healthy infant samples were identified. <xref rid="btac639-F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4C</xref> displays the fraction of healthy infants in each of the three geographic locations covered by the selected studies. It shows that the fraction of healthy infants is very different between studies and geographical locations with <xref rid="btac639-B27" ref-type="bibr">Lewis <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2017)</xref> having analyzed only healthy infants in Georgia and <xref rid="btac639-B13" ref-type="bibr">Davis <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2017)</xref> and <xref rid="btac639-B31" ref-type="bibr">McClorry <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2018)</xref> having analyzed mainly unhealthy infants in Gambia and Peru, respectively.</p>
      <fig position="float" id="btac639-F4">
        <label>Fig. 4.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Analysis of amplicon sequencing data from three infant gut microbiome development studies. (<bold>A</bold>) Overview of QIIME 2 actions used during the amplicon data analysis. (<bold>B</bold>) Counts of samples in the defined age groups per study. (<bold>C</bold>) Fraction of healthy infants in the geographic locations covered by the selected studies. (<bold>D</bold> and <bold>E</bold>) ROC curves of Random Forest classifiers predicting age groups (D) and health status (E), indicating better predictive accuracy for age groups (macro averaged AUC = 0.85) than health status (macro averaged AUC = 0.58) which is not to be trusted as the individual studies differ in many covariates that were not adjusted for in this demonstration</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="btac639f4" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Finally, we trained two Random Forest classifiers with 10-fold cross-validation on the processed microbiome sequence data to predict the age group and health status of each sample, respectively. The classifiers were evaluated on the test set of each fold and revealed a better performance in predicting age groups (macro averaged AUC = 0.85, <xref rid="btac639-F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4D</xref>) than health status (macro averaged AUC = 0.58, <xref rid="btac639-F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4E</xref>). This initial result would, however, require further careful analysis as the individual studies differ in many variables (e.g. age range, health status and geographical location) which we did not account for in this demonstration. Hence, differences in predicted age bins and health status could be artificially inflated by the differences in geolocation or study design. The classifiers trained here might not be capturing age-specific or health-specific features but rather features stemming from the particular study setups.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>4.2 Use Case 2: Whole genome sequence data analysis</title>
      <p>To illustrate how q2-fondue can be used as an entry-point to analysis of whole genome sequencing data we turned to one of the most rapidly growing datasets of the recent years: the SARS-CoV-2 genome dataset. We used all of the pre-processed metadata obtained through the Nextstrain.org platform (<xref rid="btac639-B15" ref-type="bibr">Hadfield <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>) to identify samples that have been deposited in the SRA. We subsampled genomes of SARS-CoV-2 variants from two geographic locations: Europe and North America. We then fetched the corresponding SRA metadata using <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic>, which was used to prepare our final list of genomes. To simplify the analysis and reduce technical variability, we focused only on samples sequenced using single-end reads on the Illumina NextSeq 500/550 platforms. Following the quality control step, we used the sourmash tool to readily compare viral genomes to one another by computing their MinHash signatures (<xref rid="btac639-B37" ref-type="bibr">Ondov <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). The resulting distance matrix was then used to generate a t-SNE plot visualizing how sampled genomes group together. <xref rid="btac639-F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5B</xref> shows that the samples taken at different locations group together to form distinct geographic clusters. Finally, we used k-nearest-neighbors clustering to quantitatively compare genome MinHash signatures to predict SARS-CoV-2 geographic origin (<xref rid="btac639-F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5C</xref>). We found that it was possible to classify the SARS-CoV-2 origin with an accuracy of 92%. This result is intended as a simple demonstration of the capability of <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> in conjunction with other QIIME 2 plugins but should not be considered as final. Additional factors may need to be taken into account to get a complete picture of the relationship between geographic location and viral genome MinHash signatures: other sequencing platforms should be included and more samples from other continents should be added, as well as a careful evaluation of covariates that could bias these results. An overview of plugins and actions applied in this use case can be found in <xref rid="btac639-F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5A</xref>.</p>
      <fig position="float" id="btac639-F5">
        <label>Fig. 5.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Genome MinHash signatures are predictive of SARS-CoV-2 geographic origin. (<bold>A</bold>) Overview of QIIME 2 actions used during the genome data analysis. (<bold>B</bold>) t-SNE analysis of the SARS-CoV-2 genome MinHash distance matrix shows that virus samples can be grouped into distinct geographic clusters based on only genome hash signatures. (<bold>C</bold>) The same distance matrix can be used to reliably predict virus origin from genome hashes. K-nearest-neighbors clustering approach with 10-fold cross-validation was used to classify samples—a confusion matrix constructed from all test sets is shown</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="btac639f5" position="float"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>4.3 Use case 3: shotgun metagenome sequence data analysis</title>
      <p>We used the Tara Ocean expedition dataset (<xref rid="btac639-B45" ref-type="bibr">Tara Oceans Consortium Coordinators <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>) to illustrate how geographic location included in sample metadata deposited in the SRA can be used to display sample properties, using <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> and QIIME 2 (see <xref rid="btac639-F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6A</xref> for an overview of plugins and actions used throughout this use case). We fetched metadata for six BioProjects containing 1049 ocean samples obtained through size fractionation followed by shotgun metagenome sequencing (<xref rid="btac639-F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6B and C</xref>). As geographical coordinates of every sample are included in the SRA metadata, we could directly draw an array of interactive maps visualizing various sample properties using the <italic toggle="yes">q2-coordinates</italic> plugin (<xref rid="btac639-B8" ref-type="bibr">Bokulich and Caporaso, 2018</xref>). As an example, <xref rid="btac639-F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6D</xref> illustrates sample temperatures across the globe. Moreover, we randomly selected 10 samples collected at two distinct locations and used the corresponding sequences to calculate and compare their MinHash signatures. Using PCoA analysis of the resulting distance matrix, we could show that the samples can be separated by location when using only their genome hash signatures (<xref rid="btac639-F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6E</xref>). More interactive visualizations can be found in the Jupyter notebook accompanying this manuscript (see Data Availability section).</p>
      <fig position="float" id="btac639-F6">
        <label>Fig. 6.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Tara Oceans expedition (meta)data analysis. (<bold>A</bold>) Overview of QIIME 2 actions used during the metagenome analysis. (<bold>B</bold>) Counts of samples in the retrieved dataset according to BioProject ID. (<bold>C</bold>) Counts of samples corresponding to different fractions obtained through size fractionation. (<bold>D</bold>) PCoA analysis of the metagenome MinHash signatures of 10 samples taken at two randomly selected locations. Fraction of explained variance is shown for two plotted dimensions. (<bold>E</bold>) Temperature of samples taken at different geographical locations. Only 100 randomly selected samples are shown</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="btac639f6" position="float"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>4.4 Integration with QIIME 2 ecosystem</title>
      <p>Since <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> is a QIIME 2 plugin, it tightly integrates with and benefits from the rest of the QIIME 2 ecosystem. Sequences obtained through the <italic toggle="yes">get-sequences</italic> action can be directly passed into any other QIIME 2 action that accepts this data type (see <xref rid="btac639-F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> for an overview of actions applied in this study). In addition to defining format checks for SRA metadata objects, <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> has implemented transformer functions to allow the metadata downloaded through the use of <italic toggle="yes">get-metadata</italic> action to serve as input to any QIIME 2 action that requires sample metadata. Furthermore, integration with QIIME 2’s built-in provenance tracking system ensures that data fetching from the SRA is also included in the provenance graph (stored directly in all data outputs), enabling researchers to track and completely reproduce the entire analysis pipeline from data download to final visualizations.</p>
      <fig position="float" id="btac639-F7">
        <label>Fig. 7.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Overview of <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> integration with other QIIME 2 plugins and actions as applied in the three use cases presented in this study. This is only a limited demonstration of possible downstream uses for three different nucleotide sequence data types, not an exhaustive list</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="btac639f7" position="float"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>5 Discussion</title>
    <p>Declining costs and increasing throughput of nucleotide sequencing have fueled an exponential increase in published sequence data over the past two decades (<xref rid="btac639-B44" ref-type="bibr">Stephens <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). These data have an immense reuse potential, which has led to a growing trend of sequencing-based meta-analyses (<xref rid="btac639-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>), paving the way to additional discoveries regarding general biological trends (<xref rid="btac639-B1" ref-type="bibr">Abbas <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="btac639-B38" ref-type="bibr">Panagiotou <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="btac639-B47" ref-type="bibr">Thompson <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). However, such studies remain technically challenging and data acquisition and management are significant bottlenecks.</p>
    <p>We developed <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> to lower these hurdles, and to facilitate reproducible acquisition and management of metadata and nucleotide sequence datasets from the SRA (see <xref rid="btac639-T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> for a summary of the most important features). Its integration with the QIIME 2 framework offers complete provenance tracking of the entire process, multiple user interfaces, and thorough input/output data validation, allowing to conduct meta-analyses in a reproducible manner. Furthermore, <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> outputs can be directly used with a wide range of QIIME 2 plugins, offering the user a smooth incorporation with any sequence-based analysis that is (or will become) available within the QIIME 2 ecosystem. Even though the main target of the QIIME 2 framework is microbiome research, <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> itself is intended to be agnostic to the research field and non-microbiome researchers can equally profit from its most important features (see <xref rid="btac639-T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) when performing downstream analyses without QIIME 2 (see tutorials at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/bokulich-lab/q2-fondue" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/bokulich-lab/q2-fondue</ext-link>). Finally, <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue’</italic>s integration with QIIME 2 offers users unparalleled support through the QIIME 2 forum—an exchange platform between users and plugin developers (with a current total of 5700 signed-up members).</p>
    <table-wrap position="float" id="btac639-T1">
      <label>Table 1.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Selection of the most significant issues faced by users when retrieving large amounts of sequencing data, together with their user-friendly solutions offered by <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic></p>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
        <colgroup span="1">
          <col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/>
          <col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/>
        </colgroup>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Problem</th>
            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solution offered by <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic></th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plethora of accession ID types complicates retrieval of sequences/metadata.</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conversion between different accession IDs is performed automatically. All associated parent and child accession IDs are recorded in the final metadata table.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potential data loss on space exhaustion when fetching large amounts of runs.</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> keeps track of available disk space and will abort without data loss when the amount of space is insufficient.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequencing data requires pre-processing/name normalization before it can be used in downstream analyses.</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> takes care of renaming/standardizing all the files after retrieval.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Merged datasets and subsequent data analysis steps are not always reproducible.</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tight integration with QIIME 2 ensures that every data fetching and analysis detail is recorded in provenance stored together with every single output.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diversity of metadata fetched from multiple studies complicates its application in subsequent analyses.</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metadata retrieved by <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> is normalized into a single table with standardized columns.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Network issues and other errors lead to data loss and require cumbersome, repeated data fetches.</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Data retrieval can be automatically repeated in case of encountered errors. In case of repeated failures, all errors are reported and can be investigated by the user once the download is finished. No data loss occurs.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parallelization of custom SRA access scripts is complicated and time-consuming.</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> takes care of data retrieval/processing in a parallel way, making use of multiple threads and CPUs available on the user's system.</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
    <p>Despite its ease of use, <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> does not free the user of their due diligence in checking the details on the extracted datasets in the accompanying publications, where mismatches with obtained run metadata or sequences could be detected. The same holds for following best practices when performing meta-analyses or comparative analyses with data obtained using <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic>. The user must investigate sources of heterogeneity among individual studies included in the analysis (<xref rid="btac639-B48" ref-type="bibr">Thompson, 1994</xref>) and follow statistical procedures to ensure that the detected signals are not an artifact of the different study setups (<xref rid="btac639-B14" ref-type="bibr">Gurevitch <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>).</p>
    <p>The <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> demonstrations shown here represent only a few possible (although simplified) use cases for the software, and we envision many other possible applications for the analysis of diverse nucleotide sequence data types.</p>
    <sec>
      <title>5.1 Future plans</title>
      <p>The <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> package remains under active development, and several additional functionality upgrades are planned in the future. As <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> operates on large amounts of sequencing data we will introduce several performance-enhancing updates that will allow better management of free storage space available during download as well as streamline downloading large numbers of accession IDs to avoid multiple re-fetches.</p>
      <p><italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue’</italic>s metadata retrieval action already greatly simplifies downloading metadata of multiple projects and formatting those as a single result table. Several additional functions are planned to assist with the management and integration of diverse study and sample metadata. Moreover, we acknowledge that additional features may be needed, particularly for accessing non-microbial datasets (as the demonstrations in this publication focus on microbial datasets). We are motivated to further improve <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> to encompass diverse use cases and invite feature requests via <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic>’s GitHub repository or the QIIME 2 forum.</p>
      <p>Finally, to unlock the potential of sequencing data stored in and processed by other repositories we will add support for (meta)data retrieval from various other databases (e.g. MGnify; <xref rid="btac639-B36" ref-type="bibr">Mitchell <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). Altogether, we hope that <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> can become the tool of choice for interacting with the SRA and other similar repositories, while at the same time seamlessly integrating with the whole QIIME 2 ecosystem, hence enabling a wide range of available analysis types.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
      <label>btac639_Supplementary_Data</label>
      <media xlink:href="btac639_supplementary_data.docx">
        <caption>
          <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
        </caption>
      </media>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack id="ack1">
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <p>We thank Evan Bolyen (Northern Arizona University) for insightful discussions on metadata processing and working with the SRA and SRA Toolkit. We also thank Anton Lavrinienko (ETH Zürich) for his valuable comments on the manuscript.</p>
    <sec>
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p>This work was partially supported by the grant [#2021-362] of the Strategic Focus Area ‘Personalized Health and Related Technologies (PHRT)’ of the ETH Domain (Swiss Federal Institutes of Technology) and the Swiss National Science Foundation [310030_204275]. L.F. gratefully acknowledges the support of the Swiss Government Excellence Ph.D. Scholarships for foreign students.</p>
      <p><italic toggle="yes">Conflict of Interest</italic>: none declared.</p>
    </sec>
  </ack>
  <sec sec-type="data-availability">
    <title>Data Availability</title>
    <p>An introductory tutorial with background information and examples for the usage of <italic toggle="yes">q2-fondue</italic> can be accessed at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/bokulich-lab/q2-fondue/blob/main/tutorial/tutorial.md" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/bokulich-lab/q2-fondue/blob/main/tutorial/tutorial.md</ext-link>. All Jupyter notebooks used in this article are available under <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/bokulich-lab/q2-fondue-examples" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/bokulich-lab/q2-fondue-examples</ext-link>.</p>
  </sec>
  <ref-list id="ref1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="btac639-B1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Redondoviridae, a family of small, circular DNA viruses of the human oro-respiratory tract that are associated with periodontitis and critical illness</article-title>. <source>Cell Host Microbe</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>719</fpage>–<lpage>729.e4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31071295</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Alföldi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lindblad-Toh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Comparative genomics as a tool to understand evolution and disease</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>., <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>1063</fpage>–<lpage>1068</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23817047</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Amann</surname><given-names>R.I.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Toward unrestricted use of public genomic data</article-title>. <source>Science</source>, <volume>363</volume>, <fpage>350</fpage>–<lpage>352</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30679363</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>1,500 Scientists lift the lid on reproducibility</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>533</volume>, <fpage>452</fpage>–<lpage>454</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27225100</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Building global infrastructure for data sharing and exchange through the research data alliance</article-title>. <source>D-Lib Mag</source>., <volume>20</volume>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1045/january2014-berman</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bokulich</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>q2-sample-classifier: machine-learning tools for microbiome classification and regression</article-title>. <source>J. Open Source Softw</source>., <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>934</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bokulich</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Optimizing taxonomic classification of marker-gene amplicon sequences with QIIME 2’s q2-feature-classifier plugin</article-title>. <source>Microbiome</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>90</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29773078</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B8">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bokulich</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caporaso</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <source>Nbokulich/q2-Coordinates: 2018.11</source>. <publisher-name>Zenodo</publisher-name>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5281/zenodo.2124295</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B9">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bolyen</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Reproducible, interactive, scalable and extensible microbiome data science using QIIME 2</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biotechnol</source>., <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>852</fpage>–<lpage>857</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31341288</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B10">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Buchmann</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Entrezpy: a python library to dynamically interact with the NCBI entrez databases</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics (Oxford, England)</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>4511</fpage>–<lpage>4514</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B11">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Callahan</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>DADA2: high-resolution sample inference from illumina amplicon data</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>581</fpage>–<lpage>583</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27214047</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B12">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Choudhary</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Pysradb: a python package to query next-generation sequencing metadata and data from NCBI sequence read archive</article-title>. <source>F1000Research</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>532</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31114675</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B13">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>J.C.C.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Growth and morbidity of Gambian infants are influenced by maternal milk oligosaccharides and infant gut microbiota</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep</source>., <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>40466</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28079170</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B14">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gurevitch</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Meta-analysis and the science of research synthesis</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>555</volume>, <fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>182</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29517004</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B15">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hadfield</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Nextstrain: real-time tracking of pathogen evolution</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>4121</fpage>–<lpage>4123</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29790939</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B16">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Halko</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) An algorithm for the principal component analysis of large data sets. <italic toggle="yes">ArXiv:1007.5510 [Cs, Stat]</italic>. <ext-link xlink:href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1007.5510" ext-link-type="uri">http://arxiv.org/abs/1007.5510</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B17">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gottardo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Comparability and reproducibility of biomedical data</article-title>. <source>Brief. Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>391</fpage>–<lpage>401</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23193203</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B18">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hügel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <source>Urschrei/Pyzotero: Zenodo Release</source>. <publisher-name>Zenodo</publisher-name>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5281/zenodo.2917290</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B19">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Matplotlib: a 2D graphics environment</article-title>. <source>Comput. Sci. Eng</source>., <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B20">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ioannidis</surname><given-names>J.P.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trikalinos</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Early extreme contradictory estimates may appear in published research: the Proteus phenomenon in molecular genetics research and randomized trials</article-title>. <source>J. Clin. Epidemiol</source>., <volume>58</volume>, <fpage>543</fpage>–<lpage>549</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15878467</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B21">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kans</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <part-title>Entrez direct: e-utilities on the Unix command line</part-title>. In: <source>Entrez Programming Utilities Help</source><italic toggle="yes">[Internet].</italic><publisher-name>National Center for Biotechnology Information (US)</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Bethesda (MD</publisher-loc>).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B22">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2022</year>) <article-title>The sequence read archive: a decade more of explosive growth</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>50</volume>, <fpage>D387</fpage>–<lpage>D390</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34850094</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B23">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.-M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Experimenting with reproducibility: a case study of robustness in bioinformatics</article-title>. <source>GigaScience</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gigascience/giy077</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B24">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kodama</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group> on behalf of the International Nucleotide Sequence Database Collaboration. <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The sequence read archive: explosive growth of sequencing data</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>D54</fpage>–<lpage>D56</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22009675</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B25">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Leinonen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011a</year>) <article-title>The European nucleotide archive</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>D28</fpage>–<lpage>D31</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20972220</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B26">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Leinonen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal>; <collab>International Nucleotide Sequence Database Collaboration</collab>. (<year>2011b</year>) <article-title>The sequence read archive</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>D19</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21062823</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B27">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>Z.T.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>The fecal microbial community of breast-fed infants from Armenia and Georgia</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep</source>., <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>40932</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28150690</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B28">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>K.G.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Phylogenetically novel uncultured microbial cells dominate earth microbiomes</article-title>. <source>MSystems</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>e00055</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30273414</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B29">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Cutadapt removes adapter sequences from high-throughput sequencing reads</article-title>. <source>EMBnet. J</source>., <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>10</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B30">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mashima</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>DNA data bank of Japan</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>D25</fpage>–<lpage>D31</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27924010</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B31">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>McClorry</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Anemia in infancy is associated with alterations in systemic metabolism and microbial structure and function in a sex-specific manner: an observational study</article-title>. <source>Am. J. Clin. Nutr</source>., <volume>108</volume>, <fpage>1238</fpage>–<lpage>1248</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30351381</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B32">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>McKinney</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <italic toggle="yes">Data Structures for Statistical Computing in Python</italic>. pp. <fpage>56</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.25080/Majora-92bf1922-00a</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B33">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>McNutt</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Liberating field science samples and data</article-title>. <source>Science</source>, <volume>351</volume>, <fpage>1024</fpage>–<lpage>1026</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26941302</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B34">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Meadows</surname><given-names>J.R.S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lindblad-Toh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Dissecting evolution and disease using comparative vertebrate genomics</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Genet</source>., <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>624</fpage>–<lpage>636</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28736437</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B35">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The metagenomics RAST server—a public resource for the automatic phylogenetic and functional analysis of metagenomes</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>386</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18803844</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B36">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>MGnify: the microbiome analysis resource in 2020</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>D570</fpage>–<lpage>D578</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31696235</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B37">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ondov</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Mash: fast genome and metagenome distance estimation using MinHash</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>., <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>132</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27323842</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B38">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Panagiotou</surname><given-names>O.A.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The power of meta-analysis in genome wide association studies</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Genomics Hum. Genet</source>., <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>441</fpage>–<lpage>465</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23724904</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B39">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Parks</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Recovery of nearly 8,000 metagenome-assembled genomes substantially expands the tree of life</article-title>. <source>Nat. Microbiol</source>., <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>1533</fpage>–<lpage>1542</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28894102</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B40">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pedregosa</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) Scikit-learn: machine learning in python. In: <italic toggle="yes">Machine Learning in Python</italic>, Vol. <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>2826</fpage>–<lpage>2830</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.48550/ARXIV.1201.0490</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B41">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Reback</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><collab>MomIsBestFriend</collab> (<year>2020</year>) <source>Pandas-Dev/Pandas: Pandas 1.0.3</source>. <publisher-name>Zenodo</publisher-name>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5281/zenodo.3715232</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B42">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Reichman</surname>,<given-names>O.J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Challenges and opportunities of open data in ecology</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Science </italic></source>, <volume>331</volume>, <fpage>703</fpage>–<lpage>705</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1197962</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21311007</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B43">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Serghiou</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Field-wide Meta-analyses of observational associations can map selective availability of risk factors and the impact of model specifications</article-title>. <source>J. Clin. Epidemiol</source>., <volume>71</volume>, <fpage>58</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26415577</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B44">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>Z.D.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Big data: astronomical or genomical?</article-title><source>PLoS Biol</source>., <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>e1002195</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26151137</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B45">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pesant</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal>; <collab>Tara Oceans Consortium Coordinators</collab>. (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Open science resources for the discovery and analysis of Tara oceans data</article-title>. <source>Sci. Data</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>150023</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26029378</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B46">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">(<year>2019</year>) The path to open data. <source>Nat. Rev. Nephrol</source>., <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>521</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31427809</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B47">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>L.R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal>; <collab>Earth Microbiome Project Consortium</collab>. (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>A communal catalogue reveals earth’s multiscale microbial diversity</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>551</volume>, <fpage>457</fpage>–<lpage>463</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29088705</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B48">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Why sources of heterogeneity in meta-analysis should be investigated</article-title>. <source>BMJ (Clinical Research Ed.)</source>, <volume>309</volume>, <fpage>1351</fpage>–<lpage>1355</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B49">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Waskom</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Seaborn: statistical data visualization</article-title>. <source>J. Open Source Softw</source>., <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>3021</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B50">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>The FAIR guiding principles for scientific data management and stewardship</article-title>. <source>Sci. Data</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>160018</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26978244</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B51">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Minimum information about a marker gene sequence (MIMARKS) and minimum information about any (x) sequence (MIxS) specifications</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biotechnol</source>., <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>415</fpage>–<lpage>420</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21552244</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B52">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Youens-Clark</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>iMicrobe: tools and data-driven discovery platform for the microbiome sciences</article-title>. <source>GigaScience</source>, <volume>8</volume>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gigascience/giz083</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B53">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zamkovaya</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>A network approach to elucidate and prioritize microbial dark matter in microbial communities</article-title>. <source>ISME J</source>., <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>228</fpage>–<lpage>244</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32963345</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac639-B54">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>SRAdb: query and use public next-generation sequencing data from within R</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>19</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23323543</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
