<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?properties open_access?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bioinformatics</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Bioinformatics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1367-4803</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1367-4811</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">9750106</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36287062</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btac710</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">btac710</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Applications Note</subject>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading">
          <subject>Genetics and Population Analysis</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01060</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>EvAM-Tools: tools for evolutionary accumulation and cancer progression models</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6637-9039</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Diaz-Uriarte</surname>
          <given-names>Ramon</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="btac710-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
        <!--r.diaz@uam.es-->
        <aff><institution>Department of Biochemistry, Universidad Autónoma de Madrid, Instituto de Investigaciones Biomédicas “Alberto Sols” (UAM-CSIC)</institution>, Madrid, <country country="ES">Spain</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Herrera-Nieto</surname>
          <given-names>Pablo</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Department of Biochemistry, Universidad Autónoma de Madrid, Instituto de Investigaciones Biomédicas “Alberto Sols” (UAM-CSIC)</institution>, Madrid, <country country="ES">Spain</country></aff>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name>
          <surname>Schwartz</surname>
          <given-names>Russell</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Associate Editor</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="btac710-cor1">To whom correspondence should be addressed. Email: <email>r.diaz@uam.es</email></corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <day>15</day>
      <month>12</month>
      <year>2022</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2022-10-26">
      <day>26</day>
      <month>10</month>
      <year>2022</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>26</day>
      <month>10</month>
      <year>2022</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>38</volume>
    <issue>24</issue>
    <fpage>5457</fpage>
    <lpage>5459</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>03</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>03</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="editorial-decision">
        <day>23</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="corrected-typeset">
        <day>08</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2022. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xlink:href="btac710.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <sec id="s1">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <p>EvAM-Tools is an R package and web application that provides a unified interface to state-of-the-art cancer progression models and, more generally, evolutionary models of event accumulation. The output includes, in addition to the fitted models, the transition (and transition rate) matrices between genotypes and the probabilities of evolutionary paths. Generation of random cancer progression models is also available. Using the GUI in the web application, users can easily construct models (modifying directed acyclic graphs of restrictions, matrices of mutual hazards or specifying genotype composition), generate data from them (with user-specified observational/genotyping error) and analyze the data.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2">
        <title>Availability and implementation</title>
        <p>Implemented in R and C; open source code available under the GNU Affero General Public License v3.0 at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/rdiaz02/EvAM-Tools" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/rdiaz02/EvAM-Tools</ext-link>. Docker images freely available from <ext-link xlink:href="https://hub.docker.com/u/rdiaz02" ext-link-type="uri">https://hub.docker.com/u/rdiaz02</ext-link>. Web app freely accessible at <ext-link xlink:href="https://iib.uam.es/evamtools" ext-link-type="uri">https://iib.uam.es/evamtools</ext-link>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4">
        <title>Supplementary information</title>
        <p><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary data</xref> are available at <italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic> online.</p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Comunidad de Madrid’s</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>PEJ-2019-AI/BMD-13961</award-id>
        <award-id>PID2019-111256RB-I00</award-id>
        <award-id>MCIN/AEI/10.13039/501100011033</award-id>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="3"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec>
    <title>1 Introduction</title>
    <p>Cancer progression models (CPMs) try to identify dependencies between discrete genetic events (e.g. mutations) from cross-sectional data (<xref rid="btac710-B2" ref-type="bibr">Beerenwinkel <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>, <xref rid="btac710-B3" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; <xref rid="btac710-B8" ref-type="bibr">Diaz-Uriarte, 2018</xref>). These dependencies can be deterministic, as in oncogenetic trees (OT) (<xref rid="btac710-B5" ref-type="bibr">Desper <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref rid="btac710-B19" ref-type="bibr">Szabo and Boucher, 2008</xref>), conjunctive Bayesian networks (CBN) (<xref rid="btac710-B10" ref-type="bibr">Gerstung <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="btac710-B16" ref-type="bibr">Montazeri <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>), OncoBN (<xref rid="btac710-B17" ref-type="bibr">Nicol <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>) and Hidden Extended Suppes-Bayes Causal Networks (H-ESBCNs) (<xref rid="btac710-B1" ref-type="bibr">Angaroni <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2022</xref>) or stochastic as in mutual hazard networks (MHN) (<xref rid="btac710-B18" ref-type="bibr">Schill <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). These models also implicitly encode the possible mutational trajectories with predictions about their probability and have been used for predicting cancer evolution, both long-term (<xref rid="btac710-B9" ref-type="bibr">Diaz-Uriarte and Vasallo, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="btac710-B14" ref-type="bibr">Hosseini <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>) and short-term (<xref rid="btac710-B6" ref-type="bibr">Diaz-Colunga and Diaz-Uriarte, 2021</xref>). Although developed in the field of computational oncology, these models are not limited to cancer: they can be applied to other questions involving the irreversible accumulation of discrete items (<xref rid="btac710-B12" ref-type="bibr">Gotovos <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>) and have been used to examine tool use in animal taxa (<xref rid="btac710-B15" ref-type="bibr">Johnston and Røyrvik, 2020</xref>). Their wide utility derives from the assumptions these methods make about the cross-sectional data, which can apply to a broad range of domains. The key assumptions are that (<xref rid="btac710-B2" ref-type="bibr">Beerenwinkel <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>, <xref rid="btac710-B3" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; <xref rid="btac710-B9" ref-type="bibr">Diaz-Uriarte and Vasallo, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="btac710-B11" ref-type="bibr">Gerstung <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>): (i) events are gained one by one; (ii) once gained, events are not lost; and (iii) we can consider the different individuals in the cross-sectional data as replicate evolutionary experiments where all individuals are under the same constraints (e.g. genetic constraints if we are dealing with mutations)—see further details in the additional documentation.</p>
    <p>However, everyday use of these methods, and comparison of output from different ones, is hindered because they are implemented in different languages and with dependencies that make them difficult to install under some operating systems, and they use heterogeneous formats for input and output. In addition, the output is often textual (not graphical) and most implementations do not provide the output users might be interested in, such as probabilities of evolutionary paths and genotypes. Finally, it is difficult to explore how changes in genotype composition affect the fitted models and to analyze with one model data generated under another. Here, we present EvAM-Tools, an R package and web app for evolutionary and event accumulation models, that facilitates the use and comparison of CPMs, and their extension to other problems.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>2 Functionality</title>
    <p><xref rid="btac710-F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> shows an overview of the functionality of EvAM-Tools.</p>
    <fig position="float" id="btac710-F1">
      <label>Fig. 1.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Overview of functionality and workflows with EvAM-Tools (including methods, input and output); emphasis on functionality provided by the Shiny web app</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="btac710f1" position="float"/>
    </fig>
    <sec>
      <title>2.1 Methods available</title>
      <p>EvAM-Tools is available as an R package, <monospace>evamtools</monospace>, that can also launch an interactive GUI as a Shiny (<xref rid="btac710-B4" ref-type="bibr">Chang <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>) web app. A distinctive feature of EvAM-Tools is the unified input and usage of five CPMs, the available state-of-the-art procedures with existing implementations: OT (<xref rid="btac710-B5" ref-type="bibr">Desper <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref rid="btac710-B19" ref-type="bibr">Szabo and Boucher, 2008</xref>), CBN (both H-CBN—<xref rid="btac710-B10" ref-type="bibr">Gerstung <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>—and MC-CBN—<xref rid="btac710-B16" ref-type="bibr">Montazeri <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>), OncoBN (<xref rid="btac710-B17" ref-type="bibr">Nicol <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>), H-ESBCN (<xref rid="btac710-B1" ref-type="bibr">Angaroni <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2022</xref>) and MHN (<xref rid="btac710-B18" ref-type="bibr">Schill <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). OT represents restrictions as a tree (each event can have only one parent); they are untimed models, and weights along the edges are probabilities of transition by the time of observation. CBN represents restrictions with directed acyclic graphs (DAGs) so an event can have multiple parents with an AND relationship (all parent events must have occurred for the child event to appear); in contrast to OT, CBN is a timed model: the parameters of nodes are rates of the exponentially distributed times to event occurrence. OncoBN is untimed like OT but restrictions are represented as DAGs with either AND or OR dependencies (OR dependency: occurrence of one of the parent events is enough for the child to occur). H-ESBCN is timed like CBN but allows for AND, OR and XOR (exactly one of the parents must occur) in the DAG of dependencies. MHN uses a non-deterministic timed model where the rate of acquisition of an event is the product of the baseline hazard of the event and the multiplicative effects (promoting or inhibiting) that other events can have via pairwise interactions; there is no DAG as the model is fully specified by the Θ matrix of hazards and multiplicative effects. (See the additional documentation for a more complete description of the methods, including similarities and differences, assumptions, input and output.)</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>2.2 Input</title>
      <p>EvAM-Tools allows for different types of input (<xref rid="btac710-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). The analyses <italic toggle="yes">sensu stricto</italic> start from cross-sectional data, a matrix of individuals (or patients) by events (or genes, pathways, SNPs, CGH regions, etc.), with a 1 denoting the event (e.g. a mutation in a gene) is present and a 0 denoting the event is not present. This cross-sectional data themselves can be:
</p>
      <list list-type="bullet">
        <list-item>
          <p>Uploaded from a file.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>Entered manually by specifying genotype frequencies.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>Generated from CPM models: users can create/modify the DAGs of restrictions (OT, CBN, OncoBN and H-ESBCN) or the log-Θ matrix (MHN) that define the models, and then generate synthetic data from the models (after specifying the size of the sample and the amount of noise, from both model error and observational noise).</p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
      <p>File uploading and generation of synthetic data from CPM models are available in both the R package and the Shiny web app. The R package also provides a function for the generation of random CPMs/evam models (including OT, OncoBN in conjunctive and disjunctive forms, CBN, H-ESBCN with AND, XOR, OR dependencies and MHN). The Shiny web app provides a GUI that allows to interactively modify: (i) the CPM models, (including the DAG of restrictions, the type of model—OT, OncoBN, CBN and H-ESBCN—and dependencies—AND, OR and XOR—, and their rates or conditional probabilities), and the log-Θ matrix for MHN models; (ii) genotype frequencies, both from uploaded data and from data generated from CPM models. To facilitate the exploration of the methods, the Shiny web app includes preloaded examples of cross-sectional datasets, DAGs and MHN models.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>2.3 Output</title>
      <p>Output includes:
</p>
      <list list-type="bullet">
        <list-item>
          <p>DAGs of restrictions annotated with parameter values (OT, CBN, OncoBN and H-ESBCN) and log-Θ matrix (MHN).</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>Plots and tables of the transition probabilities between genotypes and transition rate matrices from the continuous-time Markov Chain (for models where this exists: CBN, H-ESBCN and MHN). As visualizing the acquisition of mutations in a complex network can be challenging, we use the representation of the hypergraph transition graph from HyperTraPS (<xref rid="btac710-B13" ref-type="bibr">Greenbury <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>); to enhance interpretability, the user can modify the number of paths to show and the type of annotation.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>Plots and tables of the predicted probabilities of genotypes and finite samples from the predicted probabilities with user-specified observational (e.g. genotyping) error levels.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>List of evolutionary paths and their probabilities.</p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
      <p>When using EvAM-Tools from R, the output is available as standard R objects. The web app allows users to download datasets and analysis output.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>2.4 Workflows</title>
      <p>EvAM-Tools encompasses different workflows, including (<xref rid="btac710-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>):</p>
      <list list-type="order">
        <list-item>
          <p>Inference of CPMs from user data uploaded from a file.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>Exploration of the inferences that different CPM methods yield from manually constructed synthetic data.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>Construction of CPM models (DAGs with their rates/probabilities and MHN models) and simulation of synthetic data from them.</p>
          <list list-type="simple">
            <list-item>
              <p>3.1 Examination of the consequences of different CPM models and their parameters on the simulated data.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>3.2 Analysis of data simulated under one model with methods that have different models (e.g. data simulated from CBN analyzed with OT).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>3.3 Analysis of data simulated under one model with manual modification of specific genotype frequencies prior to analyses.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </list-item>
      </list>
      <p>Examples that illustrate these workflows, with both real and simulated data, are available in the additional documentation.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>3 Use cases</title>
    <p>EvAM-Tools can be used, among others, as:
</p>
    <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
        <p>A teaching tool to understand what CPMs imply about observed data and how different inputs affect the fitted models.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>A research tool to analyze cross-sectional data with state-of-the-art CPMs.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>A research tool in methodological work to compare the performance of different methods under data generated by other models or under specific evolutionary scenarios, and to evaluate new methods.</p>
      </list-item>
    </list>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>4 Tests, documentation and availability</title>
    <p>The package includes more than 1400 tests that run at every build/check cycle. These tests provide a code coverage of more than 90%. The Shiny web app includes usage documentation in the landing page, as well as in the application itself using: (i) short documentation strings next to each option; (ii) tooltips; (iii) longer help, via clickable ‘Help’ buttons. The <monospace>evamtools</monospace> R package includes standard R function documentation. The repository README includes installation instructions. The additional documentation includes how to use OncoSimulR (<xref rid="btac710-B7" ref-type="bibr">Diaz-Uriarte, 2017</xref>) to compute transition probabilities between genotypes to provide additional testing and make fitness models explicit; details about CPMs—models, algorithms and assumptions—predicting genotype frequencies and generating random evam models; a FAQ; commented examples, with both real and simulated data, that illustrate the use and utility of EvAM-Tools.</p>
    <p>The web app can be run on our servers or locally. In the latter case, after installing the package from the source or using one of the Docker images, we provide, which include all dependencies and will run both the package and the web app.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>5 Conclusion</title>
    <p>EvAM-Tools provide a unified interface to state-of-the-art CPMs, a user-friendly GUI, output (graphical and tabular) that extends the usual output derived from these methods, and functionality that facilitates methodological work. EvAM-Tools should result in a better understanding and the increased use of these methods and encourage further methodological work and their extension to other scenarios, making it a tool of interest for computational oncologists and more broadly to evolutionary biologists.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
      <label>btac710_Supplementary_Data</label>
      <media xlink:href="btac710_supplementary_data.zip">
        <caption>
          <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
        </caption>
      </media>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack id="ack1">
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <p>C. Lazaro-Perea and two anonymous reviewers for comments that helped improve the article.</p>
    <sec>
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p>This work was supported by grant PID2019-111256RB-I00 funded by MCIN/AEI/10.13039/501100011033 to R.D.U.; P.H.N. supported by Comunidad de Madrid’s [PEJ-2019-AI/BMD-13961 to R.D.U.].</p>
      <p><italic toggle="yes">Conflict of Interest</italic>: none declared.</p>
    </sec>
  </ack>
  <ref-list id="ref1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="btac710-B1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Angaroni</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2022</year>) <article-title>PMCE: efficient inference of expressive models of cancer evolution with high prognostic power</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>754</fpage>–<lpage>762</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac710-B2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Beerenwinkel</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Cancer evolution: mathematical models and computational inference</article-title>. <source>Syst. Biol</source>., <volume>64</volume>, <fpage>e1</fpage>–<lpage>e25</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25293804</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac710-B3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Beerenwinkel</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Computational cancer biology: an evolutionary perspective</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput. Biol</source>., <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>e1004717</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26845763</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac710-B4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2021</year>) <italic toggle="yes">shiny: Web Application Framework for R.</italic> R package version 1.7.1. <ext-link xlink:href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=shiny" ext-link-type="uri">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=shiny</ext-link></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac710-B5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Desper</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Inferring tree models for oncogenesis from comparative genome hybridization data</article-title>. <source>J. Comput. Biol</source>., <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10223663</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac710-B6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Diaz-Colunga</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Diaz-Uriarte</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Conditional prediction of consecutive tumor evolution using cancer progression models: what genotype comes next?</article-title><source>PLoS Comput. Biol</source>., <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>e1009055</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34932572</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac710-B7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Diaz-Uriarte</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>OncoSimulR: genetic simulation with arbitrary epistasis and mutator genes in asexual populations</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>1898</fpage>–<lpage>1899</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28186227</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac710-B8">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Diaz-Uriarte</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Cancer progression models and fitness landscapes: a many-to-many relationship</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>836</fpage>–<lpage>844</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29048486</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac710-B9">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Diaz-Uriarte</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vasallo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Every which way? On predicting tumor evolution using cancer progression models</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput. Biol</source>., <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>e1007246</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31374072</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac710-B10">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gerstung</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Quantifying cancer progression with conjunctive Bayesian networks</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>2809</fpage>–<lpage>2815</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19692554</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac710-B11">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gerstung</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The temporal order of genetic and pathway alterations in tumorigenesis</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>e27136</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22069497</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac710-B12">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gotovos</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2021</year>) Scaling up continuous-time Markov chains helps resolve underspecification. In: Ranzato, M. <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (ed.) <italic toggle="yes">Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems</italic>, Vol. 34. Curran Associates, Inc., New York, USA, pp. 14580–14592.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac710-B13">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Greenbury</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>HyperTraPS: inferring probabilistic patterns of trait acquisition in evolutionary and disease progression pathways</article-title>. <source>Cell Syst</source>., <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>51.e10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31786211</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac710-B14">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hosseini</surname><given-names>S.-R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Estimating the predictability of cancer evolution</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>i389</fpage>–<lpage>i397</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31510665</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac710-B15">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>I.G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Røyrvik</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Data-driven inference reveals distinct and conserved dynamic pathways of tool use emergence across animal taxa</article-title>. <source>iScience</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>101245</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32629611</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac710-B16">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Montazeri</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal>; <collab>Swiss HIV Cohort Study</collab>. (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Large-scale inference of conjunctive Bayesian networks</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>i727</fpage>–<lpage>i735</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27587695</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac710-B17">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nicol</surname><given-names>P.B.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Oncogenetic network estimation with disjunctive Bayesian networks</article-title>. <source>Comput. Syst. Oncol</source>., <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>e1027</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac710-B18">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Schill</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Modelling cancer progression using mutual hazard networks</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>249</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31250881</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="btac710-B19">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Szabo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boucher</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <part-title>Oncogenetic trees</part-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>W.-Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hanin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Handbook of Cancer Models with Applications</source>. <publisher-name>World Scientific, Singapore</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
