<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?properties open_access?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Syst Biol</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Syst Biol</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">sysbio</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Systematic Biology</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1063-5157</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1076-836X</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">9260635</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34387349</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sysbio/syab067</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">syab067</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Special Issue</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01130</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>Assessing Confidence in Root Placement on Phylogenies: An Empirical Study
Using Nonreversible Models for Mammals</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <name>
          <surname>Naser-Khdour</surname>
          <given-names>Suha</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="syab067-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
        <xref rid="AFF1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        <!--suha.naser@anu.edu.au-->
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Quang Minh</surname>
          <given-names>Bui</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="AFF1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        <xref rid="AFF2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Lanfear</surname>
          <given-names>Robert</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref rid="AFF1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <aff id="AFF1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Ecology and Evolution, Research School of Biology</institution>,
Australian National University, Canberra, Australian Capital Territory, Australia</aff>
    <aff id="AFF2"><label>2</label><institution>Research School of Computer Science, Australian National
University</institution>, Canberra, Australian Capital Territory, Australia</aff>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name>
          <surname>Thomson</surname>
          <given-names>Robert</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Associate Editor</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="syab067-cor1">Correspondence to be sent to: Department of Ecology and
Evolution, Research School of Biology, 134 Linnaeus Way, Australian National University,
Canberra, Australian Capital Territory 2601, Australia; E-mail:
<email>suha.naser@anu.edu.au</email>.</corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2022</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2021-08-13">
      <day>13</day>
      <month>8</month>
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>13</day>
      <month>8</month>
      <year>2021</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>71</volume>
    <issue>4</issue>
    <fpage>959</fpage>
    <lpage>972</lpage>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2020</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>03</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>11</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="corrected-typeset">
        <day>11</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2021. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of
the Society of Systematic Biologists.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted
reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is
properly cited.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xlink:href="syab067.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <p>Using time-reversible Markov models is a very common practice in phylogenetic analysis,
because although we expect many of their assumptions to be violated by empirical data,
they provide high computational efficiency. However, these models lack the ability to
infer the root placement of the estimated phylogeny. In order to compensate for the
inability of these models to root the tree, many researchers use external information such
as using outgroup taxa or additional assumptions such as molecular clocks. In this study,
we investigate the utility of nonreversible models to root empirical phylogenies and
introduce a new bootstrap measure, the <italic toggle="yes">rootstrap</italic>, which provides
information on the statistical support for any given root position. [Bootstrap;
nonreversible models; phylogenetic inference; root estimation.]</p>
    </abstract>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Australian Research Council</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100000923</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>DP200103151</award-id>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="14"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <p>The most widely used method for rooting trees in phylogenetics is the outgroup method.
Although the use of an outgroup to root an unrooted phylogeny usually outperforms other
rooting methods (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Huelsenbeck et al. 2002</xref>), the main
challenge with this method is to find an appropriate outgroup (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Watrous and Wheeler 1981</xref>; <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Maddison et al.
1984</xref>; <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Smith 1994</xref>; <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Swofford et al. 1996</xref>; <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Lyons-Weiler et al.
1998</xref>; <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Milinkovitch and Lyons-Weiler 1998</xref>).
Outgroups that are too distantly related to the ingroup may have substantially different
molecular evolution than the ingroup, which can compromise accuracy. And outgroups that are
too closely related to the ingroup may not be valid outgroups at all.</p>
  <p>It is possible to infer the root of a tree without an outgroup using molecular clocks (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Huelsenbeck et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Drummond et al. 2006</xref>). A strict molecular clock assumes that the substitution rate
is constant along all lineages, a problematic assumption especially when the ingroup taxa are
distantly related such that their rates of molecular evolution may vary. Relaxed molecular
clocks are more robust to deviations from the clock-like behavior (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Drummond et al. 2006</xref>), although previous studies have shown that they can
perform poorly in estimating the root of a phylogeny when those deviations are considerable
(<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Tria et al. 2017</xref>).</p>
  <p>Other rooting methods rely on the distribution of branch lengths, including Midpoint Rooting
(<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Farris 1972</xref>), Minimal Ancestor Deviation (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Tria et al. 2017</xref>), and Minimum Variance Rooting (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Mai et al. 2017</xref>). Such methods also assume a clock-like
behavior; however, they are less dependent on this assumption as the unrooted tree is
estimated without it. Similar to inferring a root directly from molecular clock methods, the
accuracy of those rooting methods decreases with higher deviations from the molecular clock
assumption (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Mai et al. 2017</xref>).</p>
  <p>Other less common rooting methods that can be used in the absence of outgroup are: rooting by
gene duplication (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Dayhoff and Schwartz 1980</xref>; <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Gogarten et al. 1989</xref>; <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Iwabe
et al. 1989</xref>), indel-based rooting (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Rivera and Lake
1992</xref>; <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Baldauf and Palmer 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Lake et al. 2007</xref>), rooting the species tree from the
distribution of unrooted gene trees (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Allman et al. 2011</xref>;
Yu et al. 2011), and probabilistic coestimation of gene trees and species tree (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Boussau et al. 2013</xref>).</p>
  <p>All the methods mentioned above, apart from the molecular clock, infer the root position
independently of the ML tree inference. The only existing approach to include root placement
in the ML inference is the application of nonreversible models. Using nonreversible
substitution models relaxes the fundamental assumption of time-reversibility that exists in
the most widely used models in phylogenetic inference (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Jukes
and Cantor 1969</xref>; <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Kimura 1980</xref>; <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Hasegawa et al. 1985</xref>; <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Tavaré 1986</xref>; <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Dayhoff et al. 1978</xref>; <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Jones et al. 1992</xref>; <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Tamura
and Nei 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Whelan and Goldman 2001</xref>; <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Le and Gascuel 2008</xref>). This in itself is a potentially
useful improvement in the fit between models of sequence evolution and empirical data. In
addition, since nonreversible models naturally incorporate a notion of time, the position of
the root on the tree is a parameter that is estimated as part of the ML tree inference. Since
the incorporation of nonreversible models in efficient ML tree inference software is
relatively new (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Minh et al. 2020</xref>), we still understand
relatively little about the ability of nonreversible models to infer the root of a
phylogenetic tree, although a recent simulation study has shown some encouraging results
(<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Bettisworth and Stamatakis 2020</xref>).</p>
  <p>Regardless of the rooting method and the underlying assumptions, it is crucial that we are
able to estimate the statistical confidence we have in any particular placement of the root on
a phylogeny. A number of previous studies have sensibly used ratio likelihood tests such as
the Shimodaira–Hasegawa (SH) test (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Shimodaira and Hasegawa
1999</xref>) and the approximately unbiased (AU) test (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Shimodaira 2002</xref>) to compare a small set of potential root placements, rejecting some
alternative root placements in favor of the ML root placement (e.g., <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Nardi et al. 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Steenkamp et al.
2006</xref>; <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Jansen et al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Moore et al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Williams
et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Kocot et al. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Whelan et
al. 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al. 2018</xref>), these tests are
still somewhat limited in that they do not provide the level of support the data have for a
certain root position.</p>
  <p>There is strong empirical evidence that molecular evolutionary processes are rarely
reversible (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Squartini and Arndt 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Naser-Khdour et al. 2019</xref>), but few studies have explored
the accuracy of nonreversible substitution models to root phylogenetic trees (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Huelsenbeck et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Yap and Speed 2005</xref>; <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al. 2015</xref>;
<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Cherlin et al. 2018</xref>; <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Bettisworth and Stamatakis 2020</xref>). Most studies that have looked at this question in
the past have focused on either simulated data sets (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Huelsenbeck et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Jayaswal et al.
2011</xref>; <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Cherlin et al. 2018</xref>) or relatively small
empirical data sets (<xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Yang and Roberts 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Yap and Speed 2005</xref>; <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Jayaswal et al. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Heaps et al. 2014</xref>;
<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al. 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Cherlin et al. 2018</xref>). In both cases, the addressed substitution models were
nucleotide models, and to our knowledge, no study has yet investigated the potential of amino
acid substitution models in inferring the root placement of phylogenetic trees.</p>
  <p>In this article, we focus on evaluating the utility of nonreversible amino acid and
nucleotide substitution models to root the trees, and we introduce a new metric, the
<italic toggle="yes">rootstrap support value</italic>, which estimates the extent to which the data
support every possible branch as the placement of a root in a phylogenetic tree. Unlike
previous studies that used Bayesian methods with nonreversible substitution models to infer
rooted ML trees (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Heaps et al. 2014</xref>; Cherlin et al.
2018), we will conduct our study in a maximum likelihood (ML) framework using IQ-TREE (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Minh et al. 2020</xref>). A clear advantage of ML over the
Bayesian analysis is that there is no need for a prior on the parameter distributions, which
sometimes can affect tree inference (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Huelsenbeck et al.
2002</xref>; <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Cherlin et al. 2018</xref>). Even though
estimating the nonreversible model’s parameters by maximizing the likelihood function seems
more computationally intensive than calculating posterior probabilities (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Huelsenbeck et al. 2002</xref>), the IQ-TREE algorithm is sufficiently fast to
allow us to estimate root placements, with <italic toggle="yes">rootstrap support</italic> for very large
data sets.</p>
  <p>A recent study investigated the ability of nonreversible nucleotide models to infer the root
placement of phylogenetic trees (Bettisworth and Stamatakis 2020). This study showed that
IQ-TREE performs competitively with a new rooting tool, RootDigger. In most simulated data
sets, IQ-TREE slightly outperformed RootDigger in terms of root placements, but no comparisons
were made between RootDigger and IQ-TREE on empirical data sets. Although RootDigger is
significantly faster than IQ-TREE (Bettisworth and Stamatakis 2020), the former is limited to
nucleotide substitution models. Since we are interested in both nucleotide and amino acid
nonreversible models, we used IQ-TREE for tree and root inference in this study.</p>
  <sec id="SEC1">
    <title>Materials and Methods</title>
    <sec id="SEC1.1">
      <title>The “Rootstrap” Support, and Measurements of Error in Root Placement</title>
      <p>To compute rootstrap supports, we conduct a bootstrap analysis, that is, resampling
alignment sites with replacement, to obtain a number of bootstrap trees. We define the
<italic toggle="yes">rootstrap</italic> support for each branch in the ML tree, as the proportion of
bootstrap trees that have the root on that branch. Since the root can be on any branch in
a rooted tree, the rootstrap support values are computed for all the branches including
external branches. The sum of the rootstrap <!-- edit 1 --><!--<inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX"
              id="ImEquation1"><![CDATA[$\quad$]]></tex-math></inline-formula>  -->support values along
the tree are always smaller than or equal to one. A sum that is smaller than one can occur
when one or more bootstrap replicates are rooted on a branch that does not occur in the ML
tree (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F1">
        <label><sc>Figure</sc> 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Illustration of the rootstrap concept. a) The bootstrap replicates trees. b) The ML
tree with the rootstrap support values for each branch. Note that the sum of the
rootstrap support values is less than 100% due to 100 bootstrap replicates trees
(green box, in the lower-left corner) that have their root at a branch that does not
exist in the ML tree.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="syab067f1" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>By definition, the rootstrap support values for internal branches are bounded by the
bootstrap support values at those branches. On the other hand, the rootstrap support
values for tips (leaf branches) are bounded by 100%, as tips always appear in all the
bootstrap trees.</p>
      <p>If the true position of the root is known (e.g., in simulation studies) or assumed (e.g.,
in the empirical cases we present below), we can calculate additional measurements of the
error of the root placement. We introduce two such measurements here: <italic toggle="yes">root
branchlength error distance</italic> (rBED) and <italic toggle="yes">root split error
distance</italic> (rSED). Since the nonreversible model infers the exact position of the
root on a branch, we define the <italic toggle="yes">root branchlength error distance</italic> (rBED)
as the range between the minimum and maximum distance between the inferred root position
and the “true root” branch. If the true root is on the same branch as the ML tree root,
then rBED will be between 0 and the distance between the ML tree root and the farthest
point on that branch (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). Since rBED is based on
branch lengths only, it ignores the absolute number of splits between the ML tree root and
the true root; and therefore, the rBED for the true root being on the same ML root branch
can be bigger than the rBED for the true root being on a different branch (e.g., Fig. 2).
In order to account for the number of splits (nodes) between the ML tree root and the true
root, we define <italic toggle="yes">root split error distance</italic> (rSED) as the number of splits
between the ML root branch and the branch that is believed to contain the true root (Fig.
2).</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F2">
        <label><sc>Figure</sc> 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>An example to illustrate the root error distance. a) the ML rooted tree, b) the root
branch-length error distance (rBED) if the true root is believed to be on the same ML
root branch (rSED <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation2">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$=$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> 0), c) the rBED if the true root is
believed to be on the branch between D and the clade of C <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$+$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> B
(rSED <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation4">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$=$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> 3).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="syab067f2" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The rootstrap, rBED, and rSED assess different aspects of the root placement. While the
rootstrap offers an indication of the support that the data have for a certain branch to
be the root branch, rBED and rSED provide an estimation to the accuracy of the method in
estimating the exact root position if the root position is known or assumed in advance. In
other words, the rootstrap value is a measure for the robustness of the root placement
given the model and the data and can be used on any data set regardless of whether the
true root position is known, while rBED and rSED are measures of the accuracy of the
nonreversible model to find the root placement given the data, and require the root
position to be known or assumed in advance.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC1.2">
      <title>Empirical Data Sets</title>
      <p>Because nonreversible amino acid models require the estimation of a large number of
parameters, and because we suspected that the information in any such analysis on the
placement of the root branch of a tree might be rather limited, we searched for empirical
data sets that met a number of stringent criteria: </p>
      <list list-type="order">
        <list-item>
          <p>Existence of both DNA and amino acid multiple sequences alignments (MSA) for the same
loci.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>Genome-scale MSAs to ensure that the MSAs have as much information as possible with
which to estimate the nonreversible models’ free parameters and the root position.
Since we do not know the number of sites required to correctly infer the rooted ML
tree, we define 100,000 sites as the minimum number of required sites. This also
allows us to subsample the data set to explore the ability of smaller data sets to
infer root positions.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>Highly curated alignments: since the quality of the inferred phylogeny is highly
dependent on the quality of the MSA (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Philippe et al.
2011</xref>), we focused on data sets that were highly curated for misalignment,
contamination, and paralogy.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>Existence of several clades for which there is a very strong consensus regarding
their root placement. Since we are interested in evaluating the performance of
nonreversible models to infer root placements in an empirical rather than a simulation
context, we need to identify monophyletic subclades for which we can be almost certain
about their root position. This enables us to divide the data set into nonoverlapping
subclades for which we are willing to assume we know the root positions. Furthermore,
we define the minimum number of taxa in each subdata set as five.</p>
          <p>We initially identified a number of genome-scale data sets that contained large
numbers of nucleotide and amino acid MSAs. In many cases, it was difficult to
determine whether these alignments had been rigorously curated, and even more
challenging to find data sets for which the root position of a number of subclades
could be assumed with confidence. The only data set that met all of our criteria was a
data set of placental mammals with 78 ingroup taxa and 3,050,199 amino acids (<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al. 2019</xref>). This data set was originally
published as an MSA (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al. 2017</xref>) based on
very high-quality sequences from Ensembl, NCBI, and GenBank databases. After receiving
detailed critiques for potential alignment errors (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Gatesy and Springer 2017</xref>), the data set was further processed to remove
potential sources of bias and error, and an updated version of the data set was
recently published (<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al. 2018</xref>). The fact
that this alignment comes from one of the most well-studied clades on the planet, has
been independently curated and critiqued by multiple groups of researchers and
includes truly genome-scale data, makes it ideally suited for our study. The curated
alignments can be found on figshare (<ext-link xlink:href="https://figshare.com/s/622e9e0a156e5233944b" ext-link-type="uri">https://figshare.com/s/622e9e0a156e5233944b</ext-link>) under the name “Wu_2018_aa”
and “Wu_2018_dna” for the amino-acid and nucleotide alignments, respectively.</p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC1.3">
      <title>Selecting Clades with a Well-Defined Root</title>
      <p>Since our main objective in this study is to evaluate the effectiveness of nonreversible
models and the rootstrap value in estimating and measuring the support for a given root
placement on empirical data sets, we must identify a collection of subclades of the larger
mammal data set for which it is reasonable to assume a root position. We acknowledge, of
course, that outside a simulation framework it is not possible to be certain of the root
position of a clade. Nevertheless, it is possible to identify clades for which the
position of the root is well supported and noncontroversial, thus minimizing the chances
that the assumption of a particular root position is incorrect. To achieve this, we
analyzed the root position of each order and superorder in the data set, and defined
“<italic toggle="yes">well-defined clades</italic>” that fulfilled <italic toggle="yes">all</italic> of the
following criteria: </p>
      <list list-type="simple">
        <list-item>
          <label>(1)</label>
          <p>It contains at least five taxa. This ensures that the probability of obtaining a
random ML rooted tree to be at most 0.95%. For clades with four taxa, there are 15
different rooted topologies, and therefore a 6.7% probability to get any particular
root position by chance. On the other hand, for clades with at least five taxa, there
are at least 105 different rooted topologies and a maximum probability of 0.95% to
randomly get a particular root position by chance.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <label>(2)</label>
          <p>The bootstrap support for the branch leading to that clade in the phylogenetic tree
calculated from the whole data set is 100%: since the bootstrap value indicates the
support the data have for a certain branch, we also require 100% support for the first
direct descendants in the clade (<ext-link xlink:href="10.5061/dryad.fj6q573rx" ext-link-type="doi">Supplementary Appendix Fig.
SA.1</ext-link> available on Dryad at <ext-link xlink:href="10.5061/dryad.fj6q573rx" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.fj6q573rx</ext-link>). This requirement ensures that
there is strong support in the data set for the root position of the clade when the
entire data set is rooted with an outgroup.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <label>(3)</label>
          <p>The site concordance factor (sCF) for the first direct descendants in the clade is
significantly greater than 33%. The sCF is calculated by comparing the support of each
site in the alignment for the different arrangements of the quartet around a certain
branch. In other words, an sCF of 33% means equal support for any of the possible
arrangements. Therefore, we require that the sCF of the deepest two levels of branches
leading to that clade is significantly greater than 33%. Moreover, we require that the
gene Concordance Factor (gCF) for the first direct descendants in the clade to be
significantly greater than 33% of the sum of the gene concordance factor and the two
Discordance Factors (gDF1 and gDF2). The gCF of a branch is calculated as the
proportion of gene trees containing that branch, and gDFs are calculated as the
proportion of gene trees containing one of the two other resolutions of that branch.
Since for each branch in a bifurcating tree, there are three possible arrangements of
clades around that branch, we ignore all gene trees that do not contain one of these
arrangements (e.g., gene trees that contribute to neither the gCF nor the gDFs).
Although there is no threshold regarding the required proportion of genes concordant
with a certain branch, for convenience, we define branches with gCF significantly
greater than 33% of the sum gCF<inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$+$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>gDF1<inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation6">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$+$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>gCF2
as branches that are concordant with enough genes in the alignment (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Minh et al. 2020</xref>). To test whether the sCF and the
gCF are significantly greater than 33%, we use a simple binomial test with a success
probability of 0.33. The gCF, gDF1, gCF2, and sCF values are based on the tree
estimated from the amino acid data set.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <label>(4)</label>
          <p>At least 95% of the studies that have been published in the last decade support this
clade: we searched google scholar for all published papers since 2009 that determine
the root of the addressed clade. We then checked if at least 95% of those papers agree
that the root position of the clade matches that in the ML tree we estimate from the
whole data set (see <ext-link xlink:href="10.5061/dryad.fj6q573rx" ext-link-type="doi">Supplementary
material</ext-link> available on Dryad).</p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC1.4">
      <title>Estimating Unrooted Phylogenies</title>
      <p>For the whole nucleotide and amino-acid data sets with ingroup and outgroup taxa, we
inferred the unrooted phylogeny using IQ-TREE2 (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Minh et
al. 2020</xref>) with the best-fit fully partitioned model (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Chernomor et al. 2016</xref>) and edge-linked substitution rates (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Duchene et al. 2020</xref>). We then determined the best-fit
reversible model for each partition using ModelFinder (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Kalyaanamoorthy et al. 2017</xref>). See the algorithm for finding well-defined clades
in <ext-link xlink:href="10.5061/dryad.fj6q573rx" ext-link-type="doi">Supplementary Appendix Algorithm SA.1</ext-link> available on Dryad.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC1.5">
      <title>Estimating Rooted Phylogenies</title>
      <p>For each well-defined clade, we first removed all other taxa from the tree and then
sought to infer the root of the well-defined clade using nonreversible models without
outgroups. Using the best partitioning scheme from the reversible analysis, we inferred
the rooted tree for each well-defined clade with the nonreversible models for amino acid
(NR-AA) and nucleotide (NR-DNA) sequences (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Minh et al.
2020</xref>). This approach fits a 12-parameter nonreversible model for DNA sequences,
and a 380-parameter nonreversible model for amino acids. Details of the command lines used
are provided in the Supplementary material section “Algorithm SA.2” available on Dryad.
Each analysis returns a rooted tree. We performed 1000 nonparametric bootstraps of every
analysis to measure the rootstrap support.</p>
      <p>To assess the performance of the rootstrap and the ability of nonreversible models to
estimate the root of the trees on smaller data sets, we also repeated every analysis on
subsamples of the complete data set. For each well-defined clade, we performed analysis on
the complete data set (100%) as well as data sets with 10%, 1%, and 0.1% of randomly
selected loci from the original alignment.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC1.6">
      <title>The Confidence Set of Root Branches using the Approximately Unbiased Test</title>
      <p>In addition to the rootstrap support, we calculate the confidence set of all the branches
that may contain the root of the ML tree using the approximately unbiased (AU) test (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Shimodaira 2002</xref>). To do this, we reroot the ML tree
with all possible placements of the root (one placement for each branch) and calculate the
likelihood of each tree. Using the AU test, we then ask which root placements can be
rejected in favor of the ML root, using an alpha value of 5%. We define the <italic toggle="yes">root
branches confidence set</italic> as the set of root branches that are not rejected in
favor of the ML root placement. An important difference between the AU test and the
rootstrap support is that the AU test is conditioned on a single ML tree topology, but the
rootstrap support is not. Because of this, they provide quite different information about
the position of the root. The AU test assumes that the ML tree topology is true, and then
seeks to determine the confidence set of root placements conditioned on that topology. The
confidence set for the AU test will always therefore contain at least the ML root branch.
The rootstrap does not assume any particular topology and instead asks how many times a
particular root position appears across a set of bootstrap replicates. Because of this, it
is possible for every branch in the ML topology to receive 0% rootstrap support. This can
occur if none of the branches in the ML topology appear as the root branch in any of the
bootstrap topologies.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC1.7">
      <title>Reducing Systematic Bias by Removing Third Codon Positions and Loci that Fail the
MaxSym Test</title>
      <p>As it is common in many phylogenetic analyses to remove third codon positions from the
alignment (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Swofford et al. 1996</xref>), we wanted to
assess the effect of removing third codon positions on the root inference and the
rootstrap values in nucleotide data sets. For that purpose, we remove all the third codon
positions from the nucleotide alignments and reran the analysis using the NR-DNA
model.</p>
      <p>Moreover, although the NR-AA and NR-DNA models relax the reversibility assumption, they
still assume stationarity and homogeneity. To reduce the systematic bias produced by
violating these assumptions, we used the MaxSym test (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Naser-Khdour et al. 2019</xref>) to remove loci that violate those assumptions in the
nucleotide and amino acid data sets and then reran all analyses as above.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC1.8">
      <title>Applying the Methods to Two Clades Whose Root Position is Uncertain</title>
      <p>In addition to the well-defined clades, we used the methods we propose here to infer the
root of two clades of mammals whose root position is controversial; Chiroptera and the
Cetartiodactyla.</p>
      <p>There is a controversy around the root of the Chiroptera (bats) in literature. The two
most popular hypotheses are: 1) the Microchiroptera-Megachiroptera hypothesis; where the
root is placed between the Megachiroptera, which contains the family Pteropodidae, and the
Microchiroptera, which contains all the remaining Chiroptera families. This hypothesis is
well supported in the literature (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Agnarsson et al.
2011</xref>; <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Meredith et al. 2011</xref>). However, more
recent studies seem to provide less support for this hypothesis; 2) the
Yinpterochiroptera-Yangochiroptera hypothesis, in which the Yangochiroptera clade includes
most of Microchiroptera and the Yinpterochiroptera clade includes the rest of
Microchiroptera and all of Megachiroptera. There is growing support for this hypothesis in
the literature (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Meganathan et al. 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Tsagkogeorga et al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Ren et al. 2018</xref>; <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Reyes-Amaya and Flores
2019</xref>).</p>
      <p>Similar to Chiroptera, the root of Cetartiodactyla remains contentious in the literature.
The three main hypotheses regarding the root of Cetartiodactyla are: 1) Tylopoda as the
sister group for all other cetartiodactylans; 2) Suina as the sister group for all other
cetartiodactylans; 3) the monophyletic clade containing Tylopoda and Suina as the sister
group for all other cetartiodactylans.</p>
      <p>To ascertain whether certain sites or loci had very strong effects on the placement of
the root we follow the approach of <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Shen et al.
(2017)</xref> and calculate the difference in site-wise log-likelihood scores
(<inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\Delta $\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>SLS) and gene-wise log-likelihood
scores (<inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation8">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\Delta $\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>GLS) between the supported root
positions for each clade. Moreover, we analyzed subsamples of each data set to test the
limits of using nonreversible models to root trees with smaller data sets.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="SEC2">
    <title>Results</title>
    <sec id="SEC2.1">
      <title>Inference of the Mammal Tree and Selection of Well-defined Clades</title>
      <p>The trees inferred from the whole data sets with the nucleotide-reversible model and the
amino-acid-reversible model (<ext-link xlink:href="10.5061/dryad.fj6q573rx" ext-link-type="doi">Supplementary Appendix Figs. SA.2,
SA.3</ext-link> and <ext-link xlink:href="10.5061/dryad.fj6q573rx" ext-link-type="doi">Table SA.2</ext-link> available on
Dryad) are consistent with the published tree (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al.
2017</xref>). Five clades met all the criteria of well-defined clades, namely,
Afrotheria, Bovidae, Carnivora, Myomorpha, and Primates in both amino acid and nucleotide
data sets (see <ext-link xlink:href="10.5061/dryad.fj6q573rx" ext-link-type="doi">Supplementary Appendix Tables
SA.1</ext-link> and SA.2 available on Dryad). Trees in Newick format can be found on
github: <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/suhanaser/Rootstrap/tree/master/trees" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/suhanaser/Rootstrap/tree/master/trees</ext-link>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2.2">
      <title>High accuracy of the AA Nonreversible Model in Inferring the Root</title>
      <p>Using NR-AA, we inferred the correct root with very high rootstrap support for all five
well-defined clades when all loci were used (<ext-link xlink:href="10.5061/dryad.fj6q573rx" ext-link-type="doi">Supplementary Appendix Table
SA.3</ext-link> available on Dryad). Moreover, for all the five clades, the true root
was the only root placement in the confidence set of the AU test. The average running time
of the NR-AA model (model estimation <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$+$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> tree search
<inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation10">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$+$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> bootstrap <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$+$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> root
inference) is 929 h on one core 2.6 GHz CPU. However, using the optimal number of cores
for each data set reduced the average running time to 43.5 h per data set.</p>
      <p>pt Our results show that using only 10% of the sites in the amino acid alignments (around
300,000 alignment columns) still gave very high rootstrap support values (&gt;98%) for
four of the five well-defined clades (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>) with no
correlation between rSED and rBED and the size of the data set (<ext-link xlink:href="10.5061/dryad.fj6q573rx" ext-link-type="doi">Supplementary
Table SA.3</ext-link> available on Dryad). Moreover, in three of five well-defined
clades, 1% of the sites (around 30,000 alignment columns) was enough to give a very high
rootstrap support value for the assumed correct root placement. Using only 0.1% of the
sites (around 3000 alignment columns) decreased the rootstrap support value noticeably in
all data sets (Supplementary Appendix Table SA.3 available on Dryad). These values are
shown for each data set in Figure 3, where the X-axis is plotted in terms of
parsimony-informative sites to allow for a more direct comparison between data sets, and
to assist those applying these methods in deciding whether to use them on their own data.
Although the rootstrap support for the true root improves as the number of
parsimony-informative sites increase, in some data sets (e.g., Afrotheria nucleotide data
set) this is not the case (Fig. 3).</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F3">
        <label><sc>Figure</sc> 3.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The rootstrap support value for each clade as a function of the number of
parsimony-informative sites.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="syab067f3" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The nonreversible amino acid models were strongly preferred to the reversible models on
the complete data sets (BIC values were 93,943 to 235,958 units better for the
nonreversible models), and for the data sets with 10% of loci subsampled (BIC values were
3577 to 15,082 units better for the nonreversible models), but the opposite was true for
the data sets 1% and 0.1% of the loci subsampled (e.g., BIC values were between 2102 and
2712 units worse for the nonreversible models for the 0.1% subsampled data sets; see
Supplementary Table SA.7 available on Dryad for full results).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2.3">
      <title>Poor Performance of the DNA Nonreversible Model in Inferring the Root</title>
      <p>We correctly inferred the root for four out of the five nucleotide data sets with the
NR-DNA model, when all loci were used. However, the rootstrap support was generally lower
than in the amino-acid data sets (Fig. 3, Supplementary Appendix Tables SA.3 and SA.4
available on Dryad). Similar to amino-acid data sets, there is no correlation between rSED
and rBED and the size of the data set (Supplementary Table SA.4 available on Dryad). The
average running time of the NR-DNA model (model estimation <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation12">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$+$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> tree
search <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$+$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> bootstrap <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation14">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$+$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> root
inference) is 35.7 h on one core 2.6 GHz CPU and 4 h when the optimal number of cores for
each data set were used.</p>
      <p>In contrast to the NR-AA model, there is no conclusive preference for the NR-DNA model
over the reversible DNA model for the data sets we analyzed (Supplementary Table SA.8
available on Dryad). In fact, the BIC values of the NR-DNA models are always worse than
reversible models regardless of the size of the nucleotide data set except for three
clades when all loci were included (Supplementary Table SA.8 available on Dryad). In two
of the data sets (Myomorpha and Primates) where the NR-DNA model was better than the
reversible model, the root placement was inferred correctly with high rootstrap support
(&gt;95%). In fact, the Afrotheria nucleotide data set is the only data set in which the
nonreversible model was better than the reversible model but the root placement was
inferred incorrectly.</p>
      <p>Our results show that removing the third codon positions does not improve the rootstrap
support value. In contrast, in some data sets removing third codon positions decreased the
rootstrap support value and increased the rSED (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table
1</xref>).</p>
      <table-wrap position="float" id="T1">
        <label><sc>Table</sc> 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Rootstrap support and rSED values in whole nucleotide data sets and nucleotide data
sets without third codon positions</p>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
              <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">All loci</th>
              <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Without 3rd</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clades</th>
              <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rootstrap (%)</th>
              <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rSED</th>
              <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rootstrap (%)</th>
              <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rSED</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Afrotheria</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primates</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.7</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.1</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myomorpha</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.2</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carnivora</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bovidae</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.5</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </table-wrap>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2.4">
      <title>Removing Loci that Violate the Stationarity and Homogeneity Assumptions Improves the
rootstrap Support</title>
      <p>As expected, our results show that removing loci that fail the MaxSym test improves the
rootstrap support values when the rootstrap support value was less than 100% and/or the
root placement was inferred incorrectly, as the case in some nucleotide data sets (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p>
      <table-wrap position="float" id="T2">
        <label><sc>Table</sc> 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Rootstrap support values in whole data sets and data sets with loci that passed the
MaxSym test only</p>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
              <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Amino Acid</th>
              <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Nucleotide</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clade</th>
              <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All loci (%)</th>
              <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Passed MaxSym (%)</th>
              <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All loci (%)</th>
              <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Passed MaxSym (%)</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Afrotheria</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primates</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.7</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.9</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myomorpha</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.2</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carnivora</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bovidae</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </table-wrap>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2.5">
      <title>Microchiroptera–Megachiroptera or Yinpterochiroptera–Yangochiroptera?</title>
      <p>Using the whole amino acid data set, our results show 65.5% rootstrap support for the
Yinpterochiroptera–Yangochiroptera hypothesis and 23.2% for the
Microchiroptera–Megachiroptera hypothesis. The remaining11.3% of the rootstrap support
goes to supporting the branch leading to Rhinolophoidea as root branch of the bats (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). Removing amino acid loci that fail the MaxSym
test (110 loci) gives similar results, with 65.9% rootstrap support for the Yinptero-Yango
hypothesis and 25.6% rootstrap support for the Micro-Mega hypothesis. In both cases, the
AU test could not reject any of the three root positions that received nonzero rootstrap
support (Supplementary Appendix Table SA.5 available on Dryad).</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F4">
        <label><sc>Figure</sc> 4.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The ML rooted tree as inferred from the whole Chiroptera amino acid data set. Bold
branches are branches in the AU confidence set. Blue values under each branch are the
rootstrap support values.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="syab067f4" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Using the NR-DNA model gives 100% rootstrap support for the Yinptero-Yango hypothesis,
and we can confidently reject the Micro-Mega hypothesis in favor of the Yinptero-Yango
hypothesis using the AU test (Supplementary Appendix Fig. SA.4 available on Dryad). Yet,
removing nucleotide loci that fail the MaxSym test (<inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\sim$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>25%
of the loci) decreases the support for the Yinptero-Yango hypothesis to 90.1%, although we
can still confidently reject the Micro-Mega hypothesis using the AU test (Supplementary
Appendix Table SA.5 available on Dryad).</p>
      <p>Interestingly, when we randomly subsample 10%, 1%, and 0.1% of the loci in the nucleotide
data set, we consistently get the Yinptero-Yango hypothesis as the ML tree and the solely
rooted topology in the AU confidence set (Supplementary Appendix Table SA.5 available on
Dryad). Moreover, the rootstrap support value for the Yinptero-Yango hypothesis increases
and the rootstrap support value for the Micro-Mega hypothesis decreases as more
parsimony-informative sites are added to the alignment, for both nucleotide and amino acid
data sets (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, Supplementary Appendix Table SA.5
available on Dryad). These results are consistent with previous studies that used smaller
data sets (Supplementary Appendix Fig. SA.10 available on Dryad).</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F5">
        <label><sc>Figure</sc> 5.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Rootstrap support value as a function of the number of parsimony-informative
characters in the Chiroptera nucleotide and amino acid data sets using the
nonreversible DNA model (NR-DNA) and the nonreversible amino acid model (NR-AA).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="syab067f5" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation16">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\Delta $\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>GLS and <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation17">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\Delta $\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>SLS values (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Shen et al. 2017</xref>) reveal that approximately half of the nucleotide and
amino acid loci prefer the Yinptero-Yango hypothesis while the other half prefers
Micro-Mega hypothesis. Furthermore, slightly less than half of the nucleotide sites prefer
the Yinptero-Yango hypothesis. However, more than two-thirds of the amino acid sites
prefer the Yinptero-Yango hypothesis (Supplementary Appendix Fig. SA.5 available on
Dryad). The distributions of <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation18">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\Delta $\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>GLS and <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation19">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\Delta $\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>SLS (Supplementary Appendix Fig. SA.6
available on Dryad) show that a small proportion of the amino acid loci
(<inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation20">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\sim$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>1%) have very strong support for the
Micro-Mega hypothesis, and removing those loci from the alignment increased the rootstrap
support for the Yinptero-Yango hypothesis to 76.6%. Nonetheless, both root placements are
still in the confidence set of the AU test (Supplementary Appendix Table SA.5 available on
Dryad) with the amino acid data set. On the other hand, removing nucleotide loci with the
highest absolute <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation21">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\Delta $\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>GLS value still gives the
Yinptero-Yango hypothesis as the ML tree and the sole topology in the AU confidence set.
Although the nucleotide data show a clear preference to the Yinptero-Yango hypothesis, in
terms of BIC scores, the NR-DNA model performs worse than reversible models in all data
sets except for the data set where we removed loci that failed the MaxSym test
(Supplementary Table SA.5 available on Dryad). On the other hand, the NR-AA performs
better than reversible models in big data sets (Supplementary Table SA.5 available on
Dryad). Yet, the amino acid data do not allow us to distinguish between the two leading
hypotheses for the placement of the root of the Chiroptera based on rooting with
nonreversible models (Supplementary Table SA.5 available on Dryad).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="SEC2.6">
      <title>The Ambiguous Root of Cetartiodactyla</title>
      <p>The ML tree inferred with the whole amino acid data set places the clade containing
Tylopoda (represented by its only extant family; Camelidae) and Suina as the sister group
to all other cetartiodactylans with 71.8% rootstrap support (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>). Yet, The AU test did not reject Tylopoda alone as the sister group to
all other cetartiodactylans. On the other hand, the ML tree inferred with the whole
nucleotide data set places Tylopoda as the only sister group to all other
cetartiodactylans with 71.0% rootstrap support, and we can confidently reject the Tylopoda
<inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation22">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$+$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> Suina hypothesis using the AU test
(Supplementary Appendix Fig. SA.7 available on Dryad).</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F6">
        <label><sc>Figure</sc> 6.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The ML rooted tree of as inferred from the whole Cetartiodactyla amino acid data set.
Bold branches are branches in the AU confidence set. Blue values under each branch are
the rootstrap support values.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="syab067f6" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Removing the amino acid loci that failed the MaxSym test (<inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation23">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\sim$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>1%)
still places Tylopoda <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation24">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$+$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> Suina as the sister group to all other
cetartiodactylans, yet, it decreases the rootstrap support for the Tylopoda
<inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation25">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$+$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> Suina hypothesis to 63.3% and increases
the rootstrap support for the Tylopoda hypothesis to 28.5%. However, we still cannot
reject either of the hypotheses using the AU test (Supplementary Appendix Table SA.6
available on Dryad).</p>
      <p>Removing the nucleotide loci that failed the MaxSym test (<inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation26">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\sim$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>1%)
still places Tylopoda as the only sister group to all other cetartiodactylans and the only
rooted topology in the AU confidence set. However, it decreases the rootstrap support for
the Tylopoda hypothesis to 68.7% and increases the rootstrap support for the Tylopoda
<inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation27">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$+$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> Suina hypothesis to 20.1% (Supplementary
Appendix Table SA.6 available on Dryad).</p>
      <p>The results from the subsample data sets are mixed (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig.
7</xref>). Analyses on smaller data sets show no clear pattern in the placement of the
root (Supplementary Appendix Table SA.6 available on Dryad), leading us to conclude only
that the analyses of the whole data set is likely to provide the most accurate result, but
that it is plausible that adding more data may lead to different conclusions in the
future.</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F7">
        <label><sc>Figure</sc> 7.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>rootstrap support value as a function of the number of parsimony-informative 802
characters in the Cetartiodactyla nucleotide and amino acid datasets using the
Non-Reversible 803 DNA model (NR-DNA) and the Non-Reversible Amino Acid model
(NR-AA).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="syab067f7" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p><inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation28">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\Delta $\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>GLS analyses reveal that approximately, half of the amino acid and
nucleotide loci favor the Tylopoda<inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation29">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$+$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>Suina hypothesis, while
the other half of loci favor the Tylopoda hypothesis (Supplementary Appendix Figs. SA.8
and SA.9 available on Dryad). On the other hand, two-thirds of the amino acid sites and
more than 80% of the nucleotide sites favor the Tylopoda<inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation30">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$+$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>Suina
hypothesis. Removing 1% of the amino acid loci with the highest absolute
<inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation31">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\Delta $\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>GLS values still places Tylopoda
<inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation32">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$+$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> Suina as the sister group to all other
cetartiodactylans. However, the rootstrap support of the Tylopoda
<inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation33">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$+$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> Suina decreased to 63.2% and the
rootstrap support for the Tylopoda hypothesis remains approximately the same
(<inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation34">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\sim$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>14.5%), while the rootstrap support for
the Suina hypothesis increases from 13.7% to 22.4%. Yet, both the Tylopoda
<inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation35">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$+$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> Suina hypothesis and the Tylopoda
hypothesis are in the confidence set of the AU test, while the Suina hypothesis is
rejected by the AU test (Supplementary Appendix Table SA.6 available on Dryad).</p>
      <p>Removing 1% of the nucleotide loci with the highest absolute <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation36">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\Delta $\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>GLS values gives the
Tylopoda<inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation37">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$+$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>Suina as the sister group to all other
cetartiodactylans with 39.7% rootstrap support. However, the sole rooted topology in the
AU confidence set is the topology in which the root is placed on the branch leading to
Suina (Supplementary Appendix Table SA.6 available on Dryad). Similar to Chiroptera and
the well-defined clades, the NR-AA model performs better in terms of the BIC score than
reversible models in big amino-acid data sets, while the NR-DNA performs worse than
reversible models in all data sets (Supplementary Table SA.6 available on Dryad). We
conclude that neither the nucleotide nor the amino acid data are adequate to confidently
infer the root placement of Cetartiodactyla with nonreversible models.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="SEC3">
    <title>Discussion</title>
    <p>In this article, we introduced a new measure of support for the placement of the root in a
phylogenetic tree, the rootstrap support value, and applied it to empirical amino acid and
nucleotide data sets inferred using nonreversible models implemented in IQ-TREE (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Minh et al. 2020</xref>). The rootstrap is a useful measure
because it can be used to assess the statistical support for the placement of the root in
any rooted tree, regardless of the rooting method. In a ML setting, interpretation of the
rootstrap support is similar to the interpretation of the classic nonparametric bootstrap.
In a Bayesian setting, the same procedure could be used to calculate the posterior
probability of the root placement given a posterior distribution of trees. It is noteworthy
that the rootstrap support value is not a measure of the accuracy of the root placement and
therefore should not be interpreted as such. However, it provides information about the
robustness of the root inference with regard to resampling the data. This interpretation is
consistent with the interpretation of the nonparametric bootstrap (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Holmes 2003</xref>) but with regard to the root placement instead of the whole
tree topology.</p>
    <p>In addition to the rootstrap support value, we introduced another two metrics; the root
branch-length error distance (rBED), and the <!-- edit 2 --><!--<inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX"
            id="ImEquation38"><![CDATA[$\quad$]]></tex-math></inline-formula>--> root split error
distance rSED. Similar to the rootstrap metric, these additional metrics can be used in with
any approach that generates rooted phylogenetic trees. We note that both metrics require the
true position of the root to be known (or assumed) and that the rBED requires the rooting
method to be able to accurately place the root in a specific position of the root
branch.</p>
    <p>In this study, we used these and other methods to assess the utility of nonreversible
models to root phylogenetic trees in a ML framework. We focused on applying these methods to
a large and very well curated phylogenomic data set of mammals, as the mammal phylogeny
provides perhaps the best opportunity to find clades for which the root position is known
with some confidence. As expected, our results show an exponential increase in the rootstrap
support for the true root as we add more information to the MSA. Our results suggest that
nonreversible amino-acid models are more useful for inferring root positions than
nonreversible DNA models. One explanation for this difference between the NR-DNA and the
NR-AA models is the bigger character-state space of the NR-AA models. These models have 400
parameters (380 rate parameters and 20 amino acid frequencies) whereas NR-DNA models have
only 16 parameters (12 rate parameters and 4 nucleotide frequencies). This could allow the
NR-AA model to capture the evolutionary process better than the NR-DNA model, potentially
providing more information on the root position of the phylogeny. This hypothesis requires
some further exploration though, and we note that the actual character-space of amino acids
is much smaller than accommodated in NR-DNA models due to functional constraints on protein
structure (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Dayhoff et al. 1978</xref>).</p>
    <p>Another explanation for the difference in performance between the NR-AA and NR-DNA models
is that higher compositional heterogeneity in nucleotide data sets may bias tree inference.
The fact that each amino acid can be specified by more than one codon, and that synonymous
substitutions are more frequent than nonsynonymous substitutions, makes amino acid data sets
less compositionally heterogeneous than nucleotide data sets. In principle, this bias can be
alleviated by removing loci that violate the stationarity and homogeneity assumptions (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Naser-Khdour et al. 2019</xref>). Our results suggest that this
may be the case for the data sets we analyzed: we show that removing loci that violate the
stationarity and homogeneity assumptions improves the accuracy and statistical support for
the placement of the root. This is not surprising since the robustness of the rootstrap,
similar to the bootstrap, relies on the consistency of the inference method, so removing
systematic bias should improve its performance.</p>
    <p>We used the nonreversible approach to rooting trees along with the rootstrap support to
assess the evidence for different root placements in the Chiroptera and Cetartiodactyla.
Using the amino acid data sets we found that in both cases, although there tended to be
higher rootstrap support for one hypothesis, neither of the current hypotheses for either
data set could be rejected. These results emphasize the importance of the rootstrap support
value as a measure of the robustness of the root estimate given the data. In both the
Chiroptera and Cetartiodactyla data sets the root placement varied among subsamples of the
data set, and the rootstrap support reflects this uncertainty. However, checking the
stability of root placement estimate by randomly subsampling from the whole Chiroptera data
set show an obvious trend towards the Yinpterochiroptera–Yangochiroptera hypothesis as the
data set increases in size. This trend is consistent with a small number of influential
sites or loci having their signal progressively drowned out in favor of the
Yinpterochiroptera–Yangochiroptera hypothesis as more data are added to the alignment. In
both the Chiroptera and Cetartiodactyla cases, the amino acid data is inadequate to
distinguish between certain root placements. On the other hand, in both the Chiroptera and
Cetartiodactyla, the nucleotide data sets appear to show stronger support for a single root
placement.</p>
    <p>Comparing BIC scores of reversible and nonreversible models show that in most of the
nucleotide data sets the reversible model was a much better fit to the data than the NR-DNA
model. This is likely due to the limitations of the method we used to infer the NR-DNA
model. Specifically, when inferring the trees with reversible DNA models, we used a
partitioned model such that each partition was able to have an independent DNA substitution
model. On the other hand, when we inferred the NR-DNA model we estimated a single model for
the entire alignment. Thus, the NR-DNA model we inferred was unable to account for
heterogeneity in the evolutionary process among partitions, possibly leading to its worse
fit to the data when assessed using BIC scores. This suggests that using either mixture
models or partitioned models may improve the fit of nonreversible DNA models to the data.
The DNA results are consistent with results from previous study using the NR-DNA model and
RootDigger (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Bettisworth and Stamatakis 2020</xref>), although
that study did not compare the performance of IQ-TREE and RootDigger on empirical data sets.
Its results indicate that the NR-DNA model in IQ-TREE could not infer the correct root
placement for any of the three tested data sets.</p>
    <p>Our results demonstrate that the amino-acid nonreversible model can often be surprisingly
accurate for inferring the root placement of phylogenies in the absence of additional
information (such as outgroups) or assumptions (such as molecular clocks). In all of the
well-defined clades that we examined, the nonreversible amino-acid model successfully
identified the root that we identified a priori as correct, and with very high rootstrap
support. Importantly, the nonreversible amino-acid models also tended to fit the data far
better than their reversible counterparts did. Indeed, we show that root placements appear
to be accurate even with data sets as small as 50 well-curated loci between fairly closely
related taxa such as orders of mammals. Nevertheless, the application of the nonreversible
amino acid models to two clades where the root position has previously been contentious
failed to shed much additional light on the true root placement. Thus, while we show that
the use of nonreversible models certainly has promise, we also show that it is no silver
bullet.</p>
    <p>Where a reliable outgroup taxon can be found, without the issues that can confound the
inference of root placements using outgroups (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Dalevi et al.
2001</xref>; <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Braun and Kimball 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Graham et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Brady
et al. 2006</xref>), we suggest relying on the use of outgroups. Nevertheless, where no
reliable outgroups can be found, or where there is some reason to question the position of a
root inferred using an outgroup (e.g., <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Bergsten 2005</xref>),
our study suggests that using nonreversible models can provide a useful additional line of
evidence for the position of the root of a phylogeny. We note also that the rootstrap value
and the AU test could be used to provide estimates of the uncertainty of root placement
using an outgroup taxon</p>
    <p>Our work suggests a practical approach to inferring the root of a phylogenetic tree using
nonreversible models. First, estimate an unrooted tree topology using the best reversible
models available, excluding outgroup sequences. Next, fix the tree topology and use the best
nonreversible models available to infer the ML root position of that tree. Finally,
determine to what extent the ML root position should be trusted. The degree of trust that
researchers should put in an inferred ML root position should be influenced by three factors
(noting of course that all phylogenetic inferences are susceptible to be misled by model
misspecification). First, the fit of the nonreversible model to the data should be better
than the fit of the reversible model. This can be assessed using common criteria like AICc
or BIC scores. A better fit of the nonreversible model provides some assurance that the data
contain sufficient signal that using a nonreversible model is advisable in the first place.
Our results show that the root placement was inferred correctly with high rootstrap support
in 12 out of the 13 data sets in which the nonreversible model was preferable. In the
absence of a better fit for a nonreversible model, we do not think any inferred ML root
position should be trusted. Second, root positions with higher rootstrap support should be
trusted more, because a higher rootstrap support indicates less variance among sites in the
signal for the placement of the root. Third, ML root positions should be trusted more when
the number of root placements included in the confidence set of an AU test is small, because
a smaller confidence set indicates that there is less uncertainty in the root placement when
the analysis is conditioned on the full alignment and the unrooted ML tree topology. A
conservative approach to inferring root placements with nonreversible models would be to
consider any root placement that has a substantial fraction of the rootstrap support and/or
is included in the set of possible root placements identified by the AU test as a possible
root placement given the assumptions of the model.</p>
    <p>We hope that the combination of nonreversible models, rootstrap support, and AU tests will
add another tool to the phylogeneticist’s arsenal when it comes to inferring rooted
phylogenies.</p>
    <p>Availability and implementation: rootstrap support is implemented in IQ-TREE 2 and a
tutorial is available at the iqtree webpage <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.iqtree.org/doc/Rootstrap" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.iqtree.org/doc/Rootstrap</ext-link>. In addition, a python script is available
at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/suhanaser/Rootstrap" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/suhanaser/Rootstrap</ext-link>.</p>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <sec>
    <title>Supplementary material</title>
    <p>Data available from the Dryad Digital Repository: <ext-link xlink:href="10.5061/dryad.fj6q573rx" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.fj6q573rx</ext-link>.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>Funding</title>
    <p>This work was supported by an Australian Research Council [DP200103151 to R.L. and B.Q.M.]
and by a Chan-Zuckerberg Initiative grant to B.Q.M and R.L.</p>
  </sec>
  <ref-list id="ref1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="B1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Agnarsson</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zambrana-Torrelio</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Flores-Saldana</surname><given-names>N.P.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>May-Collado</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2011</year>. <article-title>A time-calibrated species-level phylogeny of bats
(Chiroptera, Mammalia)</article-title>. <source>PLoS
Curr.</source><volume>3</volume>:<fpage>RRN1212</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21327164</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Allman</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Degnan</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2011</year>. <article-title>Identifying the rooted species tree from the
distribution of unrooted gene trees under the coalescent</article-title>. <source>J.
Math.
Biol.</source><volume>62</volume>:<fpage>833</fpage>–<lpage>862</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20652704</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Baldauf</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>1993</year>. <article-title>Animals and fungi are each other’s closest relatives:
congruent evidence from multiple proteins</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad.
Sci.</source><volume>90</volume>:<fpage>11558</fpage>–<lpage>11562</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8265589</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bergsten</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2005</year>. <article-title>A review of long-branch attraction</article-title>.
<source>Cladistics</source><volume>21</volume>:<fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>193</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34892859</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bettisworth</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stamatakis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2020</year>. <article-title>RootDigger: a root placement program for phylogenetic
trees</article-title>.
<comment>bioRxiv:2020.2002.2013.935304</comment>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Boussau</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Szollosi</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Duret</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gouy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tannier</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Daubin</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2013</year>. <article-title>Genome-scale coestimation of species and gene
trees</article-title>. <source>Genome
Res.</source><volume>23</volume>:<fpage>323</fpage>–<lpage>330</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23132911</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>T.R.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2006</year>. <article-title>Evaluating alternative hypotheses for the early
evolution and diversification of ants</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.
USA</source><volume>103</volume>:<fpage>18172</fpage>–<lpage>18177</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17079492</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B8">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kimball</surname><given-names>R.T.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2002</year>. <article-title>Examining Basal avian divergences with mitochondrial
sequences: model complexity, taxon sampling, and sequence length</article-title>.
<source>Syst.
Biol.</source><volume>51</volume>:<fpage>614</fpage>–<lpage>625</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12228003</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B9">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cherlin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heaps</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nye</surname><given-names>T.M.W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boys</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Embley</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2018</year>. <article-title>The effect of nonreversibility on inferring rooted
phylogenies</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol.
Evol.</source><volume>35</volume>:<fpage>984</fpage>–<lpage>1002</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29149300</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B10">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chernomor</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>von
Haeseler</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Minh</surname><given-names>B.Q.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2016</year>. <article-title>Terrace Aware Data Structure for Phylogenomic Inference
from Supermatrices</article-title>. <source>Syst.
Biol.</source><volume>65</volume>:<fpage>997</fpage>–<lpage>1008</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27121966</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B11">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dalevi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hugenholtz</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Blackall</surname><given-names>L.L.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2001</year>. <article-title>A multiple-outgroup approach to resolving division-level
phylogenetic relationships using 16S rDNA data</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Syst.
Evol.
Microbiol.</source><volume>51</volume>:<fpage>385</fpage>–<lpage>391</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11321083</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B12">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dayhoff</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Orcutt</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>1978</year>. <article-title>A model of evolutionary change in proteins. Atlas of
protein sequence and structure. Vol. 5. Washington, DC: National Biomedical Research
Foundation</article-title>. p. <fpage>345</fpage>–<lpage>352</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B13">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dayhoff</surname><given-names>M.O.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>1980</year>. <article-title>Prokaryote evolution and the symbiotic origin of
eukaryotes</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Hainfried</surname><given-names>E.A.S.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group>,
editors. <source>Endosymbiosis and cell biology</source>.
<publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>De Gruyter</publisher-name>. p.
<fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B14">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2006</year>. <article-title>Relaxed phylogenetics and dating with
confidence</article-title>. <source>PLoS
Biol.</source><volume>4</volume>:<fpage>e88</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16683862</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B15">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Duchene</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>C.S.P.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Duchene</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lanfear</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>S.Y.W.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2020</year>. <article-title>Linking branch lengths across sets of loci provides the
highest statistical support for phylogenetic inference</article-title>. <source>Mol.
Biol.
Evol.</source><volume>37</volume>:<fpage>1202</fpage>–<lpage>1210</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31825512</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B16">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Farris</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>1972</year>. <article-title>Estimating phylogenetic trees from distance
matrices</article-title>. <source>Am.
Nat.</source><volume>106</volume>:<fpage>645</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B17">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gatesy</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2017</year>. <article-title>Phylogenomic red flags: homology errors and zombie
lineages in the evolutionary diversification of placental mammals</article-title>.
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.
USA</source><volume>114</volume>:<fpage>E9431</fpage>-E9432.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29078405</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B18">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gogarten</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kibak</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dittrich</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taiz</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Manolson</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Date</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oshima</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal><year>1989</year>. <article-title>Evolution of the vacuolar
H<inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="ImEquation39">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$+$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>-ATPase: implications for the origin of
eukaryotes</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.
USA</source><volume>86</volume>:<fpage>6661</fpage>–<lpage>6665</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2528146</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B19">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olmstead</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2002</year>. <article-title>Rooting phylogenetic trees with distant outgroups: a
case study from the commelinoid monocots</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol.
Evol.</source><volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1769</fpage>–<lpage>1781</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12270903</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B20">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kishino</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>1985</year>. <article-title>Dating of the human-ape splitting by a molecular clock
of mitochondrial DNA</article-title>. <source>J. Mol.
Evol.</source><volume>22</volume>:<fpage>160</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3934395</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B21">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Heaps</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nye</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boys</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Embley</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2014</year>. <article-title>Bayesian modelling of compositional heterogeneity in
molecular phylogenetics</article-title>. <source>Stat. Appl. Genet. Mol.
Biol.</source><volume>13</volume>:<fpage>589</fpage>–<lpage>609</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25153609</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B22">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2003</year>. <article-title>Bootstrapping phylogenetic trees: theory and
methods</article-title>. <source>Stat.
Sci.</source><volume>18</volume>:<fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>255</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B23">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bollback</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2002</year>. <article-title>Inferring the root of a phylogenetic
tree</article-title>. <source>Syst.
Biol.</source><volume>51</volume>:<fpage>32</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11943091</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B24">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Iwabe</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuma</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Osawa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miyata</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>1989</year>. <article-title>Evolutionary relationship of archaebacteria, eubacteria,
and eukaryotes inferred from phylogenetic trees of duplicated genes</article-title>.
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.
USA</source><volume>86</volume>:<fpage>9355</fpage>–<lpage>9359</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2531898</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B25">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raubeson</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Daniell</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Depamphilis</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Leebens-Mack</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>K.F.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Guisinger-Bellian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Haberle</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></string-name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal><year>2007</year>. <article-title>Analysis of 81 genes from 64 plastid
genomes resolves relationships in angiosperms and identifies genome-scale evolutionary
patterns</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.
USA</source><volume>104</volume>:<fpage>19369</fpage>–<lpage>19374</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18048330</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B26">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jayaswal</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ababneh</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jermiin</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2011</year>. <article-title>Reducing model complexity of the general Markov model of
evolution</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol.
Evol.</source><volume>28</volume>:<fpage>3045</fpage>–<lpage>3059</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21593046</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B27">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>D.T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>W.R.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>1992</year>. <article-title>The rapid generation of mutation data matrices from
protein sequences</article-title>. <source>Comput. Appl.
Biosci.</source><volume>8</volume>:<fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1633570</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B28">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jukes</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cantor</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>1969</year>. <article-title>Evolution of protein molecules</article-title>. In:
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Munro</surname><given-names>H.N.</given-names></string-name></person-group>,
editor. <source>Mammalian protein metabolism</source>. <publisher-loc>New
York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>. p.
<fpage>21</fpage>–-<lpage>132</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B29">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kalyaanamoorthy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Minh</surname><given-names>B.Q.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>T.K.F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>von
Haeseler</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jermiin</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2017</year>. <article-title>ModelFinder: fast model selection for accurate
phylogenetic estimates</article-title>. <source>Nat.
Methods</source><volume>14</volume>:<fpage>587</fpage>–<lpage>589</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28481363</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B30">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>1980</year>. <article-title>A simple method for estimating evolutionary rates of
base substitutions through comparative studies of nucleotide-sequences</article-title>.
<source>J. Mol.
Evol.</source><volume>16</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>120</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7463489</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B31">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kocot</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Todt</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Citarella</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Kohn</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schander</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moroz</surname><given-names>L.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lieb</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal><year>2011</year>. <article-title>Phylogenomics reveals deep molluscan
relationships</article-title>.
<source>Nature</source><volume>477</volume>:<fpage>452</fpage>–<lpage>456</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21892190</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B32">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lake</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Herbold</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Servin</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Skophammer</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2007</year>. <article-title>Rooting the tree of life using nonubiquitous
genes</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol.
Evol.</source><volume>24</volume>:<fpage>130</fpage>–<lpage>136</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17023560</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B33">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>S.Q.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gascuel</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2008</year>. <article-title>An improved general amino acid replacement
matrix</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol.
Evol.</source><volume>25</volume>:<fpage>1307</fpage>–<lpage>1320</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18367465</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B34">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rheindt</surname><given-names>F.E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y,</given-names></string-name><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J,</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal><year>2017</year>. <article-title>Genomic evidence reveals a radiation of placental
mammals uninterrupted by the KPg boundary</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad.
Sci.
USA</source><volume>114</volume>:<fpage>E7282</fpage>-<lpage>E7290</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28808022</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B35">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lyons-Weiler</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoelzer</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Tausch</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>1998</year>. <article-title>Optimal outgroup analysis</article-title>. <source>Biol.
J. Linn.
Soc.</source><volume>64</volume>:<fpage>493</fpage>–<lpage>511</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B36">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Maddison</surname><given-names>W.P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Donoghue</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Maddison</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>1984</year>. <article-title>Outgroup analysis and parsimony</article-title>.
<source>Syst.
Zool.</source><volume>33</volume>:<fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B37">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mai</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sayyari</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mirarab</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2017</year>. <article-title>Minimum variance rooting of phylogenetic trees and
implications for species tree reconstruction</article-title>. <source>PLoS
One</source><volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e0182238</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28800608</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B38">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Meganathan</surname><given-names>P.R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pagan</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCulloch</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>R.D.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2012</year>. <article-title>Complete mitochondrial genome sequences of three bats
species and whole genome mitochondrial analyses reveal patterns of codon bias and lend
support to a basal split in Chiroptera</article-title>.
<source>Gene</source><volume>492</volume>:<fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>129</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22041054</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B39">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Meredith</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Janecka</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Gatesy</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ryder</surname><given-names>O.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Teeling</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goodbla</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eizirik</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simao</surname><given-names>T.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal><year>2011</year>. <article-title>Impacts of the cretaceous
terrestrial revolution and kpg extinction on mammal diversification</article-title>.
<source>Science</source><volume>334</volume>:<fpage>521</fpage>–<lpage>524</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21940861</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B40">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Milinkovitch</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lyons-Weiler</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>1998</year>. <article-title>Finding optimal ingroup topologies and convexities when
the choice of outgroups is not obvious</article-title>. <source>Mol. Phylogenet.
Evol.</source><volume>9</volume>:<fpage>348</fpage>–<lpage>357</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9667982</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B41">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Minh</surname><given-names>B.Q.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>M.W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lanfear</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2020</year>. <article-title>New methods to calculate concordance factors for
phylogenomic datasets</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol.
Evol</source>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B42">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Minh</surname><given-names>B.Q.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Chernomor</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Schrempf</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Woodhams</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>von
Haeseler</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lanfear</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2020</year>. <article-title>IQ-TREE 2: new models and efficient methods for
phylogenetic inference in the genomic era</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol.
Evol.</source><volume>37</volume>:<fpage>1530</fpage>–<lpage>1534</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32011700</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B43">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>C.D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2007</year>. <article-title>Using plastid genome-scale data to resolve enigmatic
relationships among basal angiosperms</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.
USA</source><volume>104</volume>:<fpage>19363</fpage>–<lpage>19368</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18048334</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B44">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nardi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spinsanti</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Boore</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carapelli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dallai</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frati</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2003</year>. <article-title>Hexapod origins: monophyletic or
paraphyletic?</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>299</volume>:<fpage>1887</fpage>–<lpage>1889</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12649480</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B45">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Naser-Khdour</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Minh</surname><given-names>B.Q.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lanfear</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2019</year>. <article-title>The prevalence and impact of model violations in
phylogenetic analysis</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol.
Evol.</source><volume>11</volume>:<fpage>3341</fpage>–<lpage>3352</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31536115</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B46">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Philippe</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brinkmann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Lavrov</surname><given-names>D.V.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Littlewood</surname><given-names>D.T.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Manuel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Worheide</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baurain</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2011</year>. <article-title>Resolving difficult phylogenetic questions: why more
sequences are not enough</article-title>. <source>PLoS
Biol.</source><volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e1000602</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21423652</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B47">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bo</surname><given-names>S.Q.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>P.Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2018</year>. <article-title>Parallel amino acid deletions of prestin protein in two
dramatically divergent bat lineages suggest the complexity of the evolution of
echolocation in bats</article-title>. <source>Acta
Chiropter.</source><volume>20</volume>:<fpage>311</fpage>–<lpage>317</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B48">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Reyes-Amaya</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2019</year>. <article-title>Hypophysis size evolution in Chiroptera</article-title>.
<source>Acta
Chiropterol.</source><volume>21</volume>:<fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B49">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lake</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>1992</year>. <article-title>Evidence that eukaryotes and eocyte prokaryotes are
immediate relatives</article-title>.
<source>Science</source><volume>257</volume>:<fpage>74</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1621096</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B50">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>X.X.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hittinger</surname><given-names>C.T.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Rokas</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2017</year>. <article-title>Contentious relationships in phylogenomic studies can be
driven by a handful of genes</article-title>. <source>Nat. Ecol.
Evol.</source><volume>1</volume>:<fpage>126</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28812701</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B51">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Shimodaira</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2002</year>. <article-title>An approximately unbiased test of phylogenetic tree
selection</article-title>. <source>Syst.
Biol.</source><volume>51</volume>:<fpage>492</fpage>–<lpage>508</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12079646</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B52">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Shimodaira</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>1999</year>. <article-title>Multiple comparisons of log-likelihoods with
applications to phylogenetic inference</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol.
Evol.</source><volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1114</fpage>–<lpage>1116</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B53">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>1994</year>. <article-title>Rooting molecular trees - problems and
strategies</article-title>. <source>Biol. J. Linn.
Soc.</source><volume>51</volume>:<fpage>279</fpage>–<lpage>292</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B54">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Squartini</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arndt</surname><given-names>P.F.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2008</year>. <article-title>Quantifying the stationarity and time reversibility of
the nucleotide substitution process</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol
Evol.</source><volume>25</volume>:<fpage>2525</fpage>–<lpage>2535</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18682605</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B55">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Steenkamp</surname><given-names>E.T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baldauf</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2006</year>. <article-title>The protistan origins of animals and
fungi</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol.
Evol.</source><volume>23</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16151185</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B56">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Swofford</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Waddell</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>1996</year>. <article-title>Phylogenetic inference</article-title>. In:
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Hillis</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mable</surname><given-names>B.K.</given-names></string-name></person-group>,
editor. <source>Molecular systematics</source>. <edition>2nd ed</edition>.
<publisher-loc>Sunderland, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sinauer
Associates</publisher-name>. p. <fpage>407</fpage>–<lpage>513</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B57">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>1993</year>. <article-title>Estimation of the number of nucleotide substitutions in
the control region of mitochondrial DNA in humans and chimpanzees</article-title>.
<source>Mol. Biol.
Evol.</source><volume>10</volume>:<fpage>512</fpage>–<lpage>526</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8336541</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B58">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tavaré</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>1986</year>. <article-title>Some probabilistic and statistical probles in the
analysis of DNA sequences</article-title>. <comment>Lectures on Mathematics in the Life
Sciences 17</comment>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B59">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tria</surname><given-names>F.D.K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Landan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dagan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2017</year>. <article-title>Phylogenetic rooting using minimal ancestor
deviation</article-title>. <source>Nat. Ecol.
Evol.</source><volume>1</volume>:<fpage>193</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29388565</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B60">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tsagkogeorga</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stupka</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cotton</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rossiter</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2013</year>. <article-title>Phylogenomic analyses elucidate the evolutionary
relationships of bats</article-title>. <source>Curr.
Biol.</source><volume>23</volume>:<fpage>2262</fpage>–<lpage>2267</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24184098</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B61">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Watrous</surname><given-names>L.E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>Q.D.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>1981</year>. <article-title>The out-group comparison method of character
analysis</article-title>. <source>Syst.
Zool.</source><volume>30</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B62">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>N.V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kocot</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moroz</surname><given-names>L.L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Halanych</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2015</year>. <article-title>Error, signal, and the placement of Ctenophora sister to
all other animals</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.
USA</source><volume>112</volume>:<fpage>5773</fpage>–<lpage>5778</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25902535</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B63">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2001</year>. <article-title>A general empirical model of protein evolution derived
from multiple protein families using a maximum-likelihood approach</article-title>.
<source>Mol. Biol.
Evol.</source><volume>18</volume>:<fpage>691</fpage>–<lpage>699</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11319253</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B64">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>K.P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Sobral</surname><given-names>B.W.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Nordberg</surname><given-names>E.K.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>E.E.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Shallom</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Dickerman</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2010</year>. <article-title>Phylogeny of gammaproteobacteria</article-title>.
<source>J.
Bacteriol.</source><volume>192</volume>:<fpage>2305</fpage>–<lpage>2314</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20207755</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B65">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heaps</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cherlin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nye</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boys</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Embley</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2015</year>. <article-title>New substitution models for rooting phylogenetic
trees</article-title>. <source>Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond. B Biol.
Sci.</source><volume>370</volume>:<fpage>20140336</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26323766</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B66">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2019</year>. <article-title>Data from: genome-scale DNA sequence data and the
evolutionary history of placental mammals</article-title>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6084/m9.figshare.6031190.v4</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B67">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2018</year>. <article-title>Genome-scale DNA sequence data and the evolutionary
history of placental mammals</article-title>. <source>Data
Brief.</source><volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1972</fpage>–<lpage>1975</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29904704</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B68">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z.H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>1995</year>. <article-title>On the use of nucleic-acid sequences to infer early
branchings in the tree of life</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol.
Evol.</source><volume>12</volume>:
<fpage>451</fpage>–<lpage>458</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7739387</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B69">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yap</surname><given-names>V.B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Speed</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2005</year>. <article-title>Rooting a phylogenetic tree with nonreversible
substitution models</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol.
Biol.</source><volume>5</volume>:<fpage>2</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15629063</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B70">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Warnow</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nakhleh</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2011</year>. <article-title>Algorithms for MDC-based multi-locus phylogeny
inference: beyond rooted binary gene trees on single alleles</article-title>. <source>J.
Comput.
Biol.</source><volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1543</fpage>–<lpage>1559</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22035329</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B71">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.Q.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Che</surname><given-names>L.H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Dan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Slipinski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2018</year>. <article-title>Evolutionary history of Coleoptera revealed by extensive
sampling of genes and species</article-title>. <source>Nat.
Commun.</source><volume>9</volume>:<fpage>205</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29335414</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="B72">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2011</year>. <article-title>Phylogenomic analyses and improved resolution of
Cetartiodactyla</article-title>. <source>Mol. Phylogenet.
Evol.</source><volume>61</volume>:<fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>264</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21315162</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
