<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?properties open_access?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinform Adv</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinform Adv</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bioadv</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Bioinformatics Advances</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">2635-0041</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">9245626</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35785020</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioadv/vbac041</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">vbac041</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Application Note</subject>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading">
          <subject>Data and Text Mining</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>dipm: an R package implementing the Depth Importance in Precision Medicine (DIPM) tree and Forest-based method</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Chen</surname>
          <given-names>Victoria</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Department of Biostatistics, Yale University</institution>, New Haven, CT 06520, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
        <xref rid="vbac041-FM1" ref-type="author-notes"/>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Li</surname>
          <given-names>Cai</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Department of Biostatistics, St. Jude Children’s Research Hospital</institution>, Memphis, TN 38105, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
        <xref rid="vbac041-FM1" ref-type="author-notes"/>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0688-4076</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Zhang</surname>
          <given-names>Heping</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution>Department of Biostatistics, Yale University</institution>, New Haven, CT 06520, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
        <xref rid="vbac041-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
        <!--heping.zhang@yale.edu-->
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name>
          <surname>Lengauer</surname>
          <given-names>Thomas</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Associate Editor</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <fn id="vbac041-FM1">
        <p>Victoria Chen and Cai Li wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as Joint First Authors.</p>
      </fn>
      <corresp id="vbac041-cor1">To whom correspondence should be addressed. <email>heping.zhang@yale.edu</email></corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <year>2022</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2022-06-13">
      <day>13</day>
      <month>6</month>
      <year>2022</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>13</day>
      <month>6</month>
      <year>2022</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>2</volume>
    <issue>1</issue>
    <elocation-id>vbac041</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>21</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>19</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="editorial-decision">
        <day>23</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>09</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="corrected-typeset">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2022. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xlink:href="vbac041.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <sec id="s1">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <p>The Depth Importance in Precision Medicine (DIPM) method is a classification tree designed for the identification of subgroups relevant to the precision medicine setting. In this setting, a relevant subgroup is a subgroup in which subjects perform either especially well or poorly with a particular treatment assignment. Herein, we introduce, dipm, a novel R package that implements the DIPM method using R code that calls a program in C.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2">
        <title>Availability and implementation</title>
        <p>dipm is available under a GPL-3 licence on CRAN <ext-link xlink:href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/dipm/index.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/dipm/index.html</ext-link> and at <ext-link xlink:href="https://ysph.yale.edu/c2s2/software/dipm" ext-link-type="uri">https://ysph.yale.edu/c2s2/software/dipm</ext-link>. It is continuously being developed at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/chenvict/dipm" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/chenvict/dipm</ext-link>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4">
        <title>Supplementary information</title>
        <p><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary data</xref> are available at <italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics Advances</italic> online.</p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>National Institutes of Health</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100000002</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>R01HG010171</award-id>
        <award-id>R01MH116527</award-id>
      </award-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>National Science Foundation</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100000001</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>DMS1722544</award-id>
        <award-id>DMS2112711</award-id>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="4"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec>
    <title>1 Introduction</title>
    <p>In recent years, there has been a shift in medicine toward the more modern approach known as precision medicine (<xref rid="vbac041-B1" ref-type="bibr">Ashley, 2016</xref>). The traditional evidence-based medicine collects data from meta-analyses and randomized controlled trials, from which mean estimates are derived to infer general recommendations, approximating the ‘one size fits all’ scenario (<xref rid="vbac041-B2" ref-type="bibr">Beckmann and Lew, 2016</xref>). Precision medicine diverges from the traditional focus on average treatment effects and instead considers what the optimal treatment is for each individual. Moving toward a more targeted approach takes into greater consideration the heterogeneity that exists in patient populations. Overall, the aim of precision medicine is to better deliver safe and effective treatments to patients by identifying the best treatment for each individual. The Depth Importance in Precision Medicine (DIPM) method is a biostatistical approach to realizing the aims of precision medicine (<xref rid="vbac041-B3" ref-type="bibr">Chen and Zhang, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="vbac041-B4" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). The DIPM method is a classification tree method designed to identify subgroups of patients that perform especially well or especially poorly with a particular treatment assignment. Currently, the DIPM method is built for the analysis of clinical datasets with either a continuous (<xref rid="vbac041-B3" ref-type="bibr">Chen and Zhang, 2020</xref>) or right-censored survival outcome (<xref rid="vbac041-B4" ref-type="bibr">Chen and Zhang, 2022</xref>) and two or more treatment groups. Candidate split variables supplied by the user are mined by the method in search of the most important ones. Motivated by the work done by <xref rid="vbac041-B5" ref-type="bibr">Chen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2007)</xref> and <xref rid="vbac041-B10" ref-type="bibr">Zhu <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2017)</xref>, the DIPM method uses a depth variable importance score to assess the importance of each candidate split variable at each node of the tree. <xref rid="vbac041-B4" ref-type="bibr">Chen and Zhang (2022)</xref> applied the DIPM method to analyze a microarray dataset for breast cancer patients and identified new gene expression subgroups that are statistically meaningful. We have developed the dipm R package, which implements the DIPM method in addition to a method simpler in design with the same research aims. In this application note, we present an overview of the package and illustrate the usage of dipm through real datasets. The <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Material</xref> contains a manual (the vignette for the package).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>2 Methods and implementation</title>
    <p>The DIPM method is designed for the analysis of clinical datasets with either a continuous or right-censored survival outcome variable <italic toggle="yes">Y</italic> and two or more treatment assignments (<xref rid="vbac041-B3" ref-type="bibr">Chen and Zhang, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="vbac041-B4" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). Without loss of generality, higher values of <italic toggle="yes">Y</italic> denote better health outcomes. Note that this is also true for the survival case only when the event of interest is harmful, as longer times to the harmful event are more beneficial. When <italic toggle="yes">Y</italic> is a right-censored survival outcome, the data must also contain a status indicator <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic>. When <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> = 1, this indicates that the event of interest has occurred, while <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> = 0 indicates that an observation is right-censored.</p>
    <p>Candidate split variables are also part of the data and may be binary, ordinal or nominal. All of the learning data are said to be in the first or root node of the classification tree, and nodes may be split into two child nodes. Borrowing the terminology used in <xref rid="vbac041-B10" ref-type="bibr">Zhu <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2017)</xref>, at each node in the tree, a random forest of ‘embedded’ trees is grown to determine the best variable to split the node. Once the best variable is identified, the best split of the best variable is identified based on a calculated score. A flowchart outlining the general steps of the DIPM algorithm is provided in <xref rid="vbac041-F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>.</p>
    <fig position="float" id="vbac041-F1">
      <label>Fig. 1.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Overview of DIPM method classification tree algorithm. A flowchart outlining the general steps of the proposed method’s algorithm is depicted in the figure above</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="vbac041f1" position="float"/>
    </fig>
    <p>In the DIPM method, the depth variable importance score is used to find the best split variable at a node. The score is a relatively simple measure that takes into account solely two components: the depth of a node within a tree and the magnitude of the relevant effect. Using depth information makes use of the observation that more important variables tend to be selected closer to root nodes of trees. Meanwhile, the strength of the split is also taken into account. This second component is a statistic specified depending on the particular analysis and data at hand. Recall that at each node in the overall classification tree, a random forest is constructed to find the best split variable at the node. Once the forest is fit, for each tree <italic toggle="yes">T</italic> in this forest, the following sum is calculated for each covariate <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>:
<disp-formula id="E1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">score</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
    <p><italic toggle="yes">T<sub>j</sub></italic> is the set of nodes in tree <italic toggle="yes">T</italic> split by variable <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">L</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) is the depth of node <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>. For example, the root node has depth 1, the left and right child nodes of the root node have depth 2. <italic toggle="yes">G<sub>t</sub></italic> captures the magnitude of the effect of splitting node <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>. Depending on the type of data available, the test statistic <italic toggle="yes">G<sub>t</sub></italic> will vary. Next, the split criteria used are defined depending on the type of outcome variable and the number of treatment assignments as well. See the <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Material</xref> for more details.</p>
    <p>The dipm package contains two main functions: dipm and spmtree. The dipm function generates classification trees for the precision medicine setting as described above. The spmtree is also designed for the same aim as a simpler tree method. However, this method does not fit a random forest at each node. Instead, the more classical approach of considering all possible splits of all candidate split variables is used, and the single split with the highest split criteria score is selected as the ‘best’ split of the node. For each method, the R code calls a C program to generate each tree. The C backend is used to take advantage of C’s higher computational speed in comparison to R. Furthermore, the R package has been designed to remain consistent with existing R package implementations of tree-based methods such as rpart (<xref rid="vbac041-B8" ref-type="bibr">Therneau and Atkinson, 2018</xref>) and partykit (<xref rid="vbac041-B6" ref-type="bibr">Hothorn and Zeileis, 2015</xref>). Maintaining consistent function arguments across packages is helpful so that users can focus on the analysis at hand instead of spending excessive amounts of time deciphering the intricacies unique to each package. In addition, the package contains a pruning function pmprune that removes terminal sister nodes with the same optimal treatment. This package also contains the function node_dipm, which is specially designed for subgroup analysis and compatible with the plot method defined in the partykit package. It visualizes stratified treatment groups through boxplots for a continuous outcome and survival plots for a survival outcome, respectively.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>3 Example usage</title>
    <p>For both the dipm and spmtree functions, at a minimum, the user must supply a formula and a dataset. For the formula argument, the formula must take format <monospace>Y ∼ treatment | X1 + X2</monospace> for data with a continuous outcome variable <italic toggle="yes">Y</italic> and <monospace>Surv(Y, <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic>) ∼ treatment | X1 + X2</monospace> for data with a survival outcome variable <italic toggle="yes">Y</italic> and a status indicator <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic>. A format such as <monospace>Y ∼ treatment |</monospace>. may be used when all variables in the data, excluding <italic toggle="yes">Y</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> (if applicable), and the treatment variable, are to be used as candidate split variables. For the <monospace>data</monospace> argument, the supplied dataset must contain an outcome variable <italic toggle="yes">Y</italic> and a treatment variable. If <italic toggle="yes">Y</italic> is a right-censored survival time outcome, then there must also be a status indicator <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic>. The <monospace>types</monospace> argument is optional. When the <monospace>types</monospace> argument is missing, the default is to assume all of the candidate split variables are ordinal, which includes numeric variables. If this is not the case, then all of the variables in the data must be specified with a vector of characters in the order that the variables appear. The possible variable types are: ‘binary’, ‘ordinal’, ‘nominal’, ‘response’, ‘status’ and ‘treatment’. Detailed instructions, examples and returned output can be found in the <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Material</xref>.</p>
    <p>The weight change data (<monospace>MASS::anorexia</monospace>) for young female anorexia patients from the MASS package consists of 72 observations and 3 variables (<xref rid="vbac041-B9" ref-type="bibr">Venables and Ripley, 2013</xref>). The data contain three treatment groups: (i) for cognitive behavioral treatment, (ii) for control and (iii) for family treatment. PreWeight is the weight in pounds of the patient before study period. Similarly, PostWeight represents that of the patient after study period. In our analysis, we consider PostWeight as the response of interest and fit a tree based on the DIPM method. <xref rid="vbac041-F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> visualizes the tree using the function node_dipm. For both identified subgroups, family treatment is identified as the optimal treatment. However, the effect of cognitive behavioral treatment versus control is more profound in the subgroup of patients with higher weights before the study than in the subgroup of patients with lower weights before the study.</p>
    <fig position="float" id="vbac041-F2">
      <label>Fig. 2.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Tree visualization of anorexia data using function node_dipm</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="vbac041f2" position="float"/>
    </fig>
    <p>The dataset (<monospace>TH.data::GBSG2</monospace>) from the package TH.data contains the observations of 686 women from the German Breast Cancer Study Group (<xref rid="vbac041-B7" ref-type="bibr">Sauerbrei <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>). The treatment is hormonal therapy (0 for no, 1 for yes). The detailed descriptions of other variables can be seen in the <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Material</xref>. We fit a survival tree based on the DIPM method and visualize the tree using the function node_dipm in <xref rid="vbac041-F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>. Hormonal therapy is most effective except for the patients with progesterone receptor less than 74 fmol and tumor grade I or progesterone receptor more than 74 fmol and tumor size greater than 26 mm and progesterone receptor greater than 320 fmol.</p>
    <fig position="float" id="vbac041-F3">
      <label>Fig. 3.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Tree visualization of breast cancer data using function node_dipm</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="vbac041f3" position="float"/>
    </fig>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>4 Significance and conclusions</title>
    <p>In summary, the dipm R package implements the DIPM classification tree method designed for the analysis of clinical datasets with a continuous or right-censored survival outcome variable and two or more treatment groups. A secondary, additional method is also included in the package that employs a much simpler approach in identifying the best split at a node. Both methods have been carefully evaluated in previous works (<xref rid="vbac041-B3" ref-type="bibr">Chen and Zhang, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="vbac041-B4" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). Furthermore, we develop a plotting function that produces an image of each tree instead of solely a data frame of nodes. Overall, this package delivers a new and handy computational tool that implements the novel DIPM method in the search for subgroups relevant to the precision medicine setting.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec>
    <title>Funding</title>
    <p>This work was supported in part by the National Institutes of Health [R01HG010171 and R01MH116527] and the National Science Foundation [DMS1722544 and DMS2112711].</p>
    <p><italic toggle="yes">Conflict of Interest</italic>: none declared.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
    <supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
      <label>vbac041_Supplementary_Data</label>
      <media xlink:href="vbac041_supplementary_data.pdf">
        <caption>
          <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
        </caption>
      </media>
    </supplementary-material>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ref-list id="ref1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="vbac041-B1">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ashley</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Towards precision medicine</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Genet</source>., <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>507</fpage>–<lpage>522</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27528417</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="vbac041-B2">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Beckmann</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lew</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Reconciling evidence-based medicine and precision medicine in the era of big data: challenges and opportunities</article-title>. <source>Genome Med</source>., <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26750923</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="vbac041-B3">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <part-title>Depth importance in precision medicine (dipm): a tree and forest based method</part-title>. In: Fan, J., Pan, J. (eds) <source>Contemporary Experimental Design, Multivariate Analysis and Data Mining</source>. Cham, Switzerland: <publisher-name>Springer Nature</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>243</fpage>–<lpage>259</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="vbac041-B4">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2022</year>) <article-title>Depth importance in precision medicine (dipm): a tree-and Forest-based method for right-censored survival outcomes</article-title>. <source>Biostatistics</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>172</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32424406</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="vbac041-B5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A Forest-based approach to identifying gene and gene-gene interactions</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>104</volume>, <fpage>19199</fpage>–<lpage>19203</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18048322</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="vbac041-B6">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hothorn</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zeileis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Partykit: a modular toolkit for recursive partytioning in R</article-title>. <source>J. Mach. Learn. Res</source>., <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>3905</fpage>–<lpage>3909</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="vbac041-B7">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sauerbrei</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal>; <collab>for the German Breast Cancer Study Group</collab>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Randomized 2× 2 trial evaluating hormonal treatment and the duration of chemotherapy in node-positive breast cancer patients: an update based on 10 years’ follow-up</article-title>. <source>J. Clin. Oncol</source>., <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>94</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10623698</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="vbac041-B8">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Therneau</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <italic toggle="yes">rpart: Recursive Partitioning and Regression Trees.</italic> R package version 4.1-13.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="vbac041-B9">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Venables</surname><given-names>W.N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ripley</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <source>Modern Applied Statistics with S-PLUS</source>. New York, NY: <publisher-name>Springer Science &amp; Business Media</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="vbac041-B10">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Greedy outcome weighted tree learning of optimal personalized treatment rules</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source>, <volume>73</volume>, <fpage>391</fpage>–<lpage>400</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27704531</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
