<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats2jats3.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<?properties open_access?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Database (Oxford)</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Database (Oxford)</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">databa</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Database: The Journal of Biological Databases and Curation</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1758-0463</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">9290862</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35849014</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/database/baac057</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">baac057</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Original Article</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
        <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI00960</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>GeMo: a web-based platform for the visualization and curation of genome ancestry mosaics</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9308-974X</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Summo</surname>
          <given-names>Marilyne</given-names>
        </name>
        <!--marilyne.summo@cirad.fr-->
        <xref rid="COR0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        <aff><institution content-type="department">CIRAD, UMR AGAP Institut</institution>, Montpellier 34398, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
        <aff><institution content-type="department">UMR AGAP Institut, Univ Montpellier, CIRAD, INRAE, Institut Agro</institution>, Montpellier, 34398, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
        <aff><institution content-type="department">French Institute of Bioinformatics (IFB)—South Green Bioinformatics Platform, Bioversity, CIRAD, INRAE, IRD</institution>, Montpellier 34398, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Comte</surname>
          <given-names>Aurore</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution content-type="department">French Institute of Bioinformatics (IFB)—South Green Bioinformatics Platform, Bioversity, CIRAD, INRAE, IRD</institution>, Montpellier 34398, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
        <aff><institution content-type="department">IRD, CIRAD, INRAE, Institut Agro, PHIM Plant Health Institute, Montpellier University</institution>, Montpellier 34398, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1801-7500</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Martin</surname>
          <given-names>Guillaume</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution content-type="department">CIRAD, UMR AGAP Institut</institution>, Montpellier 34398, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
        <aff><institution content-type="department">UMR AGAP Institut, Univ Montpellier, CIRAD, INRAE, Institut Agro</institution>, Montpellier, 34398, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
        <aff><institution content-type="department">French Institute of Bioinformatics (IFB)—South Green Bioinformatics Platform, Bioversity, CIRAD, INRAE, IRD</institution>, Montpellier 34398, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Perelle</surname>
          <given-names>Pierrick</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution content-type="department">CIRAD, UMR AGAP Institut</institution>, Montpellier 34398, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
        <aff><institution content-type="department">UMR AGAP Institut, Univ Montpellier, CIRAD, INRAE, Institut Agro</institution>, Montpellier, 34398, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Weitz</surname>
          <given-names>Eric M</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution content-type="department">Data Sciences Platform, Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard</institution>, 105 Broadway, Cambridge, MA 02142, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1849-1269</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Droc</surname>
          <given-names>Gaëtan</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff><institution content-type="department">CIRAD, UMR AGAP Institut</institution>, Montpellier 34398, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
        <aff><institution content-type="department">UMR AGAP Institut, Univ Montpellier, CIRAD, INRAE, Institut Agro</institution>, Montpellier, 34398, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
        <aff><institution content-type="department">French Institute of Bioinformatics (IFB)—South Green Bioinformatics Platform, Bioversity, CIRAD, INRAE, IRD</institution>, Montpellier 34398, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0284-1885</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Rouard</surname>
          <given-names>Mathieu</given-names>
        </name>
        <!--m.rouard@cgiar.org-->
        <xref rid="COR0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        <aff><institution content-type="department">French Institute of Bioinformatics (IFB)—South Green Bioinformatics Platform, Bioversity, CIRAD, INRAE, IRD</institution>, Montpellier 34398, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
        <aff><institution content-type="department">Bioversity International, Parc Scientifique Agropolis II</institution>, 34397, Montpellier, <country country="FR">France</country></aff>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
      <corresp id="COR0001">*Corresponding author: Tel: +33 4 67 61 65 65; Fax: +33 4 67 61 56 05; Email: <email xlink:href="marilyne.summo@cirad.fr">marilyne.summo@cirad.fr</email>Correspondence may also be addressed to Mathieu Rouard. Tel: +33 4 67 61 29 08; Fax: +33 04 67 61 03 34; Email: <email xlink:href="m.rouard@cgiar.org">m.rouard@cgiar.org</email></corresp>
    </author-notes>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <year>2022</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2022-07-14">
      <day>14</day>
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2022</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>14</day>
      <month>7</month>
      <year>2022</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>2022</volume>
    <elocation-id>baac057</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>06</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>17</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="editorial-decision">
        <day>23</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="corrected-typeset">
        <day>14</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2022. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <self-uri xlink:href="baac057.pdf"/>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <p><italic toggle="yes">In silico</italic> chromosome painting is a technique by which contributions of distinct genetic groups are represented along chromosomes of hybrid individuals. This type of analysis is used to study the mechanisms by which these individuals were formed. Such techniques are well adapted to identify genetic groups contributing to these individuals as well as hybridization events. It can also be used to follow chromosomal recombinations that occurred naturally or were generated by selective breeding. Here, we present GeMo, a novel interactive web-based and user-oriented interface to visualize in a linear-based fashion results of <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> chromosome painting. To facilitate data input generation, a script to execute analytical commands is provided and an interactive data curation mode is supported to ensure consistency of the automated procedure. GeMo contains preloaded datasets from published studies on crop domestication but can be applied to other purposes, such as breeding programs Although only applied so far on plants, GeMo can handle data from animals as well.</p>
      <p><bold>Database URL</bold>: <ext-link xlink:href="https://gemo.southgreen.fr/" ext-link-type="uri">https://gemo.southgreen.fr/</ext-link></p>
    </abstract>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group award-type="grant">
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution>Agropolis Fondation</institution>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100007599</institution-id>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>1504-006</award-id>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <counts>
      <page-count count="5"/>
    </counts>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <boxed-text id="BX1" position="float">
    <p>
      <bold>Key Points</bold>
    </p>
    <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
        <p>GeMo is a new web resource to carry out ancestry mosaic painting in a linear fashion.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>GeMo enables dynamic and interactive visualization, data sharing online and contains preloaded datasets from published studies.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>GeMo provides access to a script and a well-documented procedure to generate genome ancestry mosaics.</p>
      </list-item>
    </list>
  </boxed-text>
  <sec id="s3">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <p>Hybridizations and introgressions are at the center of multiple scientific questions in biology (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Unraveling their origins and impacts is a key objective to understand the mechanisms by which organisms were formed and evolved, and thus feature in multiple topics such as human ancestries (<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), plant domestication (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), crop improvement (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) and environmental adaptation (<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). At the genome level, the result of these introgression events can be represented as genome ancestry mosaics, defined as a succession of large chromosomal DNA segments, or genomic blocks, of distint origin. These genomic blocks can be associated with genetic groups defined as groups of individuals with a homogenous genetic background resulting from a common ancestor or population (e.g. species, subspecies).</p>
    <p>Over the past decade, our ability to generate genomic data at high throughput for a large sampling has been revolutionized, enabling genome-wide characterization within a particular species (<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). The availability of these genomic data led to the development of new methodologies that use genetic markers to study the genome ancestry mosaics of individuals (<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Such methods, called local ancestry inference methods are based on hidden Markov model, multivariate analysis or ancestral allele ratio approaches. These methods have been applied to various animals and plant organisms (<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11–14</xref>) and will be referred to hereafter as <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> chromosome painting analyses.</p>
    <p>To visualize <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> chromosome painting, packages with linear ideograms or karyotypes such as ChromPlot (<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), ChromDraw (<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), karyoploteR (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>), RIdeogram (<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) can be used, but they require advanced programming skills and generate only static images. A few online applications were developed but are specific to some organisms like DNAPainter for Humans (<ext-link xlink:href="https://dnapainter.com" ext-link-type="uri">https://dnapainter.com</ext-link>) or favor circular-based visualization rather than linear (<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Until now, there were no web-based interfaces handling datasets in an interactive and linear fashion, and none addressing the challenges of polyploidy, which is often encountered in plants.</p>
    <p>Here we present GeMo, a web-based tool for visualization, curation and data sharing of genome ancestry mosaics. It comes with a script and step-by-step instructions, using two local ancestry inference-based methods, TraceAncestor (<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>) and VCFHunter (<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>), which assign alleles to genetic groups and use the allelic ratio observed in individuals to assign an origin to genomic blocks. GeMo can guide users through <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> chromosome painting starting with a Variant Call Format (VCF) file and acts as an online repository for genomics ancestry mosaics.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s4">
    <title>Tool implementation and usage</title>
    <p>GeMo is a lightweight web-based interface implemented in JavaScript. The display of the interactive graph is managed with the JavaScript D3JS library (<ext-link xlink:href="https://d3js.org" ext-link-type="uri">https://d3js.org</ext-link>) and chromosome visual rendering builds on the Ideogram library (<ext-link xlink:href="https://eweitz.github.io/ideogram" ext-link-type="uri">https://eweitz.github.io/ideogram</ext-link>). The web page design uses the Bootstrap library (<ext-link xlink:href="https://getbootstrap.com" ext-link-type="uri">https://getbootstrap.com</ext-link>), which ensures compatibility with modern web browsers. On the back-end, a NodeJS server (<ext-link xlink:href="https://nodejs.org/en/" ext-link-type="uri">https://nodejs.org/en/</ext-link>) ensures data transfer and analysis.</p>
    <sec id="s4-s1">
      <title>Visualization of preloaded ancestry mosaics/datasets</title>
      <p>GeMo contains ancestry mosaics of preloaded individuals resulting from published studies conducted on subsets of plant genotypes (<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20–22</xref>). When selecting a preloaded individual (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>), a form is automatically filled with the genomic coordinates of the genomic blocks and the visualization parameters (e.g. colors, reference sequence coordinates, ploidy). GeMo displays the ancestry mosaic drawing for each chromosome (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>). The chromosomal segments are colored according to their corresponding genetic group.</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F1" fig-type="figure">
        <label>Figure 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Overview of the GeMo visualization interface representing the genome ancestry mosaics of the triploid cultivated banana ‘Grande Naine’ (<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). (A) Menu panel allowing the user to load their own data or to visualize preloaded data (A1). (B) Predicted mosaic structure for the 3 × 11 chromosomes as proposed in (<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Each color on the chromosomes represents a genetic group, except dark gray for undefined genomic block. Symbols on chr01 and chr02 indicate genomic features (such as gene of interest, QTLs, etc.) entered by users based on genomic coordinates of the reference genome used to draw the genome ancestry mosaics in the menu entitled ‘Annotations’ in A2. (C) Automatically exported dataset from GeMo by clicking on a block and imported as a track to the JBrowse configured in the Genome Browser menu in A3.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="baac057f1" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>An interactive legend labels each genetic group with a corresponding color (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>). After modifying the color of a group directly in the legend (free-mode and colorblind mode available), the visualization of the chromosomes is automatically updated. By hovering over each genomic block, a link is displayed for a pre-defined genome browser URL at the observed genomic position.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4-s2">
      <title>Input user datasets</title>
      <p>Users have the possibility to enter their own files using the menu panel (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>). GeMo requires at least two types of datasets to generate the ideogram visualization: (i) a tabulated file for the reference chromosome metadata (names and respective sizes) and (ii) a tabulated file for drawing the genome ancestry mosaic of analyzed individuals. GeMo comes with a list of defined plant chromosomes, but users can enter their own chromosomes as well. The position of the centromeres can be optionally indicated in this file. The file containing genome ancestry mosaics can either be encoded as block position (genomic segment along a chromosome with defined start and stop positions) or normalized curve (observed allelic ratio for each gene pool along the chromosomes).</p>
      <p>Once data is provided, the karyotype diagram is generated dynamically. The resulting visualization depends on the encoding of the ancestry mosaic information. Segments are drawn along chromosomes if block positions are passed (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>) but line plots and chromosome segments are drawn if normalized curves are provided (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref><bold>—</bold>see next section for details about this visualization). Multiple ploidy levels are supported, enabling the representation of haplotypes for polyploid species. Ploidy is auto-detected by the system but needs to be specified when using curves.</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F2" fig-type="figure">
        <label>Figure 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Comparison of genome ancestry mosaic results before (A) and after (B) curation in GeMo. In <bold>A</bold>, the genome ancestry mosaic is not well resolved (dark gray for undefined origin) with default parameters (0.5 for diploid). Once the curve-based mode is activated, an interactive graph facilitates threshold adjustment. In B, the genome ancestry mosaic is better resolved after reducing expected thresholds for the two curves with the main ratios (as indicated in circles).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="baac057f2" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>In addition, a list of genomic coordinates (e.g. genes of interest, Quantitative Trait Loci (QTL)) can be provided as a Browser Extensible Data file to visually spot the corresponding regions on the chromosomes (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>). This can be particularly useful to check co-localization between genomic blocks and genes/regions of interest. As a complement, and to avoid extracting genomic information already available in a JBrowse instance, GeMo allows the user to extract the genomic block information as JBrowse tracks (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1C</xref>).</p>
      <p>To support data import in GeMo, step-by-step tutorials with two possible programs using VCFHunter and TraceAncestor are provided for users starting with a VCF file as well as a single script to facilitate execution (<ext-link xlink:href="https://gemo.readthedocs.io/en/latest/QuickStart.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://gemo.readthedocs.io/en/latest/QuickStart.html</ext-link>). The approach is compatible with genome-wide genotyping methods (e.g. GBS, RADseq, DaRTseq), transcriptomics (i.e. RNAseq) or whole-genome resequencing data, including both individuals to investigate and ancestral genetic groups. The complete data processing of these typically takes less than 1 h per individual. The tutorials describe the creation of either block-position-based mosaics or curve-based mosaics for interactive display, the latter enabling manual curation of the ancestry mosaics via the GeMo Interface. Step-by-step tutorials, compared to the script, allow users to customize parameters and interactively monitor the result of each analytical step.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4-s3">
      <title>Data curation of ancestry mosaic predictions</title>
      <p><italic toggle="yes">In silico</italic> chromosome painting resulting from an automated bioinformatic procedure may not be exact, requiring expert review and adjustment. GeMo proposes a curation mode to edit thresholds for single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) ratios that are by default defined based on expected ploidy (0.5 for heterozygous diploids, 0.33/0.66 for heterozygous triploids, etc.). Indeed, such ratios are expected in the ideal case, but some variations relative to the expected value can exist, either associated with the sequencing and genotyping techniques, errors in the attribution of ancestral alleles or sampling of the individuals used as representatives of a genetic group. For example, if a genetic group is represented by only a few members representing only a small portion of its diversity, identified alleles will under-predict the contribution of this genetic group in individuals descending from it. In this context, the threshold may need to be adapted. As illustrated in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>, the curation mode can be used to significantly improve automated results.</p>
      <p>When normalized curve datasets are available (from preloaded datasets or loaded by users online), GeMo displays interactive graphs that enable the curation of predicted genome ancestry mosaics. These graphs represent the proportion of haplotypes of each genetic group by chromosomes resulting from a normalization of the number of reads supporting each origin on a given window. This allows for visualizing the contribution of each genetic group along the chromosomes and checking the threshold that led to the colored painting of blocks (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>). With GeMo, users can change the threshold on the graph to recalculate the ancestry mosaic block contribution. Once a threshold is changed, the karyotype diagram is dynamically updated, which facilitates threshold adjustment (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4-s4">
      <title>Data and high-resolution image downloads</title>
      <p>Once data is visualized and customized, GeMo offers the possibility to download the latest version of the data sets and export the graphic outputs as SVG for publication purposes. In addition, data can also be stored temporarily online with a unique URL allowing users to share it.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s5">
    <title>Discussion</title>
    <p>GeMo addresses several use cases that are illustrated in <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>. For ancestry inference, once genetic groups are defined and assigned to a putative descendant, <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> chromosome painting reveals their contribution to the genetic makeup of the individual, in particular when a hybridization event is recent (e.g. few meiotic events followed hybridization). This can be observed for example in plants with low fertility (e.g. banana, yam) (<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) or with long generations (e.g. trees) (<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). GeMo provides thus a visual way to analyze and deduce the steps that shaped the genome of a given individual (<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), allowing users to reconstruct simple case pedigrees (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>).</p>
    <fig position="float" id="F3" fig-type="figure">
      <label>Figure 3.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Examples of use cases supported by <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> chromosome painting. (A) Based on defined ancestral genetic groups, a genome ancestry mosaic is painted, allowing identification of the genetic group involved in the hybridization process and deduction of the pedigree. (B) <italic toggle="yes">In silico</italic> chromosome painting in a breeding bi-parental population showing a subset of possible gametic chromosome distribution and possible chromosome recombinations (gray arrows) in progenies. (C) Co-localization of a genomic block with a genomic feature of interest (e.g. QTL) to explore gene content in related JBrowse.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="baac057f3" position="float"/>
    </fig>
    <p>In a breeding context, GeMo provides a visual way to follow chromosome segregations and recombinations (crossing overs during meiosis) in bi-parental populations (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">In silico</italic> chromosome painting visualization can help the user inspect chromosome structures in progenies to select the most desirable individual. Thus, GeMo has the potential to support the visualization of crosses in breeding programs working with molecular approaches (<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>).</p>
    <p>For functional genomics, drawing genome ancestry mosaics in which genomic segments are co-localized with a QTL (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3C</xref>) may reveal traces of adaptative introgressions to be further investigated (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). The recurrent occurrence of a genomic block in natural hybrids, for instance, or co-localization with a given QTL may indicate positive selection. For transcriptomics studies, it provides a way to overlay the chromosomes with genes that display differential expression in a specific haplotype (<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). The software interoperability with genome browsers allows to zoom into specific genes in a genomic block or to export the genome ancestry mosaics as tracks into a JBrowse instance.</p>
    <p>In conclusion, GeMo intends to help users exploit SNP markers and visualize genome ancestry mosaics in an easy and interactive way. GeMo proposes a procedure to conduct <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> chromosome painting with an interactive and online curation mode to improve results from such automatic analyses, enabling parameter adjustment based on organism specificities. GeMo can also act as an online repository, collecting public datasets for which <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> chromosome painting was conducted.</p>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <ack id="ack1">
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <p>This work was supported by the CIRAD—UMR AGAP HPC Data Center of the South Green Bioinformatics platform (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.southgreen.fr/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.southgreen.fr/</ext-link>). We thank colleagues for their careful testing of the software and feedback, in particular Alberto Cenci (Bioversity), Valentin Guignon (Bioversity) and Eloi Durant (IRD) as well as Manuel Ruiz and Angélique Dhont (CIRAD) for their support in the project. We also thank Alexandr Zelenin for committing useful features of the ideogram.js library; Rachel Chase for text editing of the manuscript and the anonymous reviewer for the constructive and comprehensive feedback to improve the manuscript.</p>
  </ack>
  <sec id="s6">
    <title>Funding</title>
    <p>GeMo has been developed in the framework of the Agropolis Fondation (ID 1504–006) ‘GenomeHarvest’ project through the French Investissements d’avenir programme (Labex Agro: ANR-10-LABX-0001-01).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s7">
    <title>Conflict of interest</title>
    <p>None declared.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s8">
    <title>Data availability</title>
    <p>GeMo is available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://gemo.southgreen.fr/" ext-link-type="uri">https://gemo.southgreen.fr/</ext-link>. Data processing instructions, scripts and documentation are available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://gemo.readthedocs.io" ext-link-type="uri">https://gemo.readthedocs.io</ext-link>. GeMo is primarily designed for online access on our servers, but code source is open access on GitHub at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/SouthGreenPlatform/GeMo/" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/SouthGreenPlatform/GeMo/</ext-link> and can be used for local set up.</p>
  </sec>
  <ref-list id="ref1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="R1">
      <label>1.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Hybridization, introgression, and the nature of species boundaries</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J. Hered.</italic></source>, <volume>105</volume>, <fpage>795</fpage>–<lpage>809</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25149255</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R2">
      <label>2.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Edelman</surname><given-names>N.B.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Mallet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Prevalence and adaptive impact of introgression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Annu. Rev. Genet.</italic></source>, <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>265</fpage>–<lpage>283</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34579539</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R3">
      <label>3.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Racimo</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sankararaman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Evidence for archaic adaptive introgression in humans</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat. Rev. Genet.</italic></source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>359</fpage>–<lpage>371</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25963373</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R4">
      <label>4.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Janzen</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Hufford</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>The extent of adaptive wild introgression in crops</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">New Phytol.</italic></source>, <volume>221</volume>, <fpage>1279</fpage>–<lpage>1288</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30368812</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R5">
      <label>5.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Burgarella</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barnaud</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Adaptive introgression: an untapped evolutionary mechanism for crop adaptation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front. Plant Sci.</italic></source>, <volume>10</volume>, <page-range>4</page-range>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R6">
      <label>6.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Castellano</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Andrés</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>The genomics of human local adaptation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Trends Genet.</italic></source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>415</fpage>–<lpage>428</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32396835</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R7">
      <label>7.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sansaloni</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Franco</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Diversity analysis of 80,000 wheat accessions reveals consequences and opportunities of selection footprints</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat. Commun.</italic></source>, <volume>11</volume>, <page-range>4572</page-range>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R8">
      <label>8.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.-Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Zeigler</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>The 3,000 rice genomes project: new opportunities and challenges for future rice research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">GigaScience</italic></source>, <volume>3</volume>, <page-range>8</page-range>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R9">
      <label>9.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Geza</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mugo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mulder</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>A comprehensive survey of models for dissecting local ancestry deconvolution in human genome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brief. Bioinformatics</italic></source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>1709</fpage>–<lpage>1724</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30010715</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R10">
      <label>10.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cottin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Penaud</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Glaszmann</surname><given-names>J.-C.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Simulation-based evaluation of three methods for local ancestry deconvolution of non-model crop species genomes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">G3 (Bethesda)</italic></source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>569</fpage>–<lpage>579</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31862786</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R11">
      <label>11.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chebotarov</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McNally</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Fine scale genomic signals of admixture and alien introgression among asian rice landraces</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Genome Biol. Evol.</italic></source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>1358</fpage>–<lpage>1373</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31002105</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R12">
      <label>12.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dessie</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>The mosaic genome of indigenous African cattle as a unique genetic resource for African pastoralism</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat. Genet.</italic></source>, <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>1099</fpage>–<lpage>1110</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32989325</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R13">
      <label>13.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cardi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sarah</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Genome ancestry mosaics reveal multiple and cryptic contributors to cultivated banana</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Plant J.</italic></source>, <volume>102</volume>, <fpage>1008</fpage>–<lpage>1025</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31930580</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R14">
      <label>14.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al.</etal>  <article-title>Genomic mosaicism due to homoeologous exchange generates extensive phenotypic diversity in nascent allopolyploids</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat. Sci. Rev.</italic></source>, <volume>8</volume>, <page-range>nwaa277</page-range>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R15">
      <label>15.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Oróstica</surname><given-names>K.Y.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Verdugo</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>chromPlot: visualization of genomic data in chromosomal context</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic></source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>2366</fpage>–<lpage>2368</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27153580</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R16">
      <label>16.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Janečka</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Lysak</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>chromDraw: an R package for visualization of linear and circular karyotypes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chromosome Res.</italic></source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>223</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26791998</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R17">
      <label>17.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gel</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Serra</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>karyoploteR: an R/Bioconductor package to plot customizable genomes displaying arbitrary data</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic></source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>3088</fpage>–<lpage>3090</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28575171</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R18">
      <label>18.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>RIdeogram: drawing SVG graphics to visualize and map genome-wide data on the idiograms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PeerJ Comput. Sci.</italic></source>, <volume>6</volume>, <page-range>e251</page-range>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R19">
      <label>19.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>shinyCircos: an R/Shiny application for interactive creation of Circos plot</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic></source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>1229</fpage>–<lpage>1231</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29186362</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R20">
      <label>20.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Comte</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Curk</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Genotyping by sequencing can reveal the complex mosaic genomes in gene pools resulting from reticulate evolution: a case study in diploid and polyploid citrus</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann. Bot.</italic></source>, <volume>123</volume>, <fpage>1231</fpage>–<lpage>1251</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30924905</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R21">
      <label>21.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Baurens</surname><given-names>F.-C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hervouet</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Recombination and large structural variations shape interspecific edible bananas genomes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol. Biol. Evol.</italic></source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>111</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30403808</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R22">
      <label>22.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cenci</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sardos</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hueber</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Unravelling the complex story of intergenomic recombination in ABB allotriploid bananas</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann. Bot.</italic></source>, <volume>127</volume>, <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32104882</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R23">
      <label>23.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chiurugwi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Genomic prediction unifies animal and plant breeding programs to form platforms for biological discovery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat. Genet.</italic></source>, <volume>49</volume>, <fpage>1297</fpage>–<lpage>1303</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28854179</pub-id></mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="R24">
      <label>24.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wesemael</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hueber</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kissel</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Homeolog expression analysis in an allotriploid non-model crop via integration of transcriptomics and proteomics</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci. Rep.</italic></source>, <volume>8</volume>, <page-range>1353</page-range>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
