<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">9206025</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">14218</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-14218-6</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Article</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>scCAN: single-cell clustering using autoencoder and network fusion</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Tran</surname>
          <given-names>Bang</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Tran</surname>
          <given-names>Duc</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Nguyen</surname>
          <given-names>Hung</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Ro</surname>
          <given-names>Seungil</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <name>
          <surname>Nguyen</surname>
          <given-names>Tin</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>tinn@unr.edu</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.266818.3</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 914X</institution-id><institution>Department of Computer Science and Engineering, </institution><institution>University of Nevada, </institution></institution-wrap>Reno, NV 89557 USA </aff>
      <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.266818.3</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 914X</institution-id><institution>Department of Physiology and Cell Biology, </institution><institution>University of Nevada School of Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>Reno, NV 89557 USA </aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>17</day>
      <month>6</month>
      <year>2022</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>17</day>
      <month>6</month>
      <year>2022</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="collection">
      <year>2022</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>12</volume>
    <elocation-id>10267</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>9</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>2</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2022</copyright-statement>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract id="Abs1">
      <p id="Par1">Unsupervised clustering of single-cell RNA sequencing data (scRNA-seq) is important because it allows us to identify putative cell types. However, the large number of cells (up to millions), the high-dimensionality of the data (tens of thousands of genes), and the high dropout rates all present substantial challenges in single-cell analysis. Here we introduce a new method, named single-cell Clustering using Autoencoder and Network fusion (scCAN), that can overcome these challenges to accurately segregate different cell types in large and sparse scRNA-seq data. In an extensive analysis using 28 real scRNA-seq datasets (more than three million cells) and 243 simulated datasets, we validate that scCAN: (1) correctly estimates the number of true cell types, (2) accurately segregates cells of different types, (3) is robust against dropouts, and (4) is fast and memory efficient. We also compare scCAN with CIDR, SEURAT3, Monocle3, SHARP, and SCANPY. scCAN outperforms these state-of-the-art methods in terms of both accuracy and scalability. The scCAN package is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cran.r-project.org/package=scCAN">https://cran.r-project.org/package=scCAN</ext-link>. Data and R scripts are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sccan.tinnguyen-lab.com/">http://sccan.tinnguyen-lab.com/</ext-link></p>
    </abstract>
    <kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject">
      <title>Subject terms</title>
      <kwd>Computational biology and bioinformatics</kwd>
      <kwd>Data mining</kwd>
      <kwd>Data processing</kwd>
      <kwd>Genome informatics</kwd>
      <kwd>Software</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group>
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000001</institution-id>
            <institution>National Science Foundation</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>201385</award-id>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group>
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000002</institution-id>
            <institution>National Institutes of Health</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>GM103440</award-id>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
        <meta-value>© The Author(s) 2022</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec id="Sec1">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <p id="Par2">Advances in microfluidics have enabled the isolation of cells, making it possible to profile individual cells using single-cell sequencing technologies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. This transcriptome profiling of individual cells holds enormous potential for both basic biology and clinical applications, including the identification of new cell types<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>, resolution of the cellular dynamics of developmental processes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>, and identification of gene regulatory mechanisms that vary between cell subtypes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>.</p>
    <p id="Par3">Unsupervised clustering of scRNA-seq data is one of the most important analyses because it allows us to identify putative cell types. However, the large number of cells (up to millions) and the high-dimensionality of the data (tens of thousands of genes or features) present substantial challenges to computational methods<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>.</p>
    <p id="Par4">One prominent strategy is to reduce the dimensionality of the data before performing cluster analysis. Methods in this category include SC3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>, CIDR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>, pcaReduce<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>, SEURAT2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>, SIMLR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>, and SHARP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. These methods typically apply dimension reduction techniques such as PCA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>, t-SNE<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup> and UMAP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup> to obtain a lower-dimensional representation of the data. Deep-learning-based approaches, including scDeepCluster<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>, scAIDE<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>, SCA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, AAE-SC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>, and scGMAI<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>, often use autoencoders to select important features and to project the data onto a low-dimensional latent space. Next, these clustering methods partition the cells using established clustering algorithms (e.g., k-means, spectral clustering, etc.). Since these dimension reduction techniques are sensitive to sequencing platforms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> and dropouts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>, the quality of clustering results also varies accordingly.</p>
    <p id="Par5">Another strategy is to iteratively search for hierarchical structures over both cells and genes. Methods using this strategy include BackSPIN<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>, SAIC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>, and Panoview<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>). These methods attempt to iteratively divide cells and genes into sub-groups to maximize cell similarity within each cluster. These methods, however, require excessive computational power (due to the iteration), and overestimate the number of cell types.</p>
    <p id="Par6">Many single-cell methods also utilize community detection algorithms such as Louvain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup> and Leiden<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. SEURAT3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>, SCANPY<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>, and Monocle3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup> embed community detection algorithms in their analysis pipeline. These methods first convert scRNA-seq data into networks in which cells are nodes and the edges represent similarity among them. Next, they partition the network using community detection algorithms that are known to be fast. The quality of clustering results strongly depends on the construction of the similarity network. Further, although community detection algorithms can produce reasonable results, they often overestimate the number of cell communities (cell types).</p>
    <p id="Par7">Lastly, cluster ensemble is another strategy that aims to aggregate results from multiple clustering models. Methods of this class include SAFE<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>, SAME<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>, and Sc-GPE<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>; these methods selectively combine the results obtained from multiple clustering algorithms, including SC3, CIDR, SEURAT, CIDR, SIMLR, SNN-cliq<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>, SSNN-Louvain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>, and MPGS-Louvain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. One of the main drawbacks of clustering ensemble methods is that they do not scale well for large datasets. Moreover, evaluating the quality of clustering results obtained from each individual method is a difficult task because there is no universally agreed standard on what constitutes good quality clusters in the first place<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>.</p>
    <p id="Par8">Here we introduce scCAN, a single-cell clustering approach that consists of three modules: (1) a non-negative kernel autoencoder to filter out uninformative features, (2) a stacked, variational autoencoder to generate multiple low-dimensional representations of single-cell data, and finally (3) a graph-based technique to determine cell groups from multiple representations. In an extensive analysis using 28 scRNA-seq datasets, we demonstrate that scCAN significantly outperforms state-of-the-art methods in separating cells of different types. We further assess the clustering methods with regards to scalability and robustness against dropouts using simulated datasets. Overall, scCAN is the most robust and accurate method and can analyze most datasets in minutes.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec2">
    <title>Methods</title>
    <p id="Par9">The workflow of scCAN is shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. This workflow consists of three modules. The first module (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A) filters the genes and compresses the input data into a low-dimensional space using two autoencoders. Given the compressed data from module 1, the second module (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B) is used to cluster small data, and the third module (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>C) is used to cluster big data.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The overall analysis pipeline of scCAN consists of three modules. In the first module (<bold>A</bold>), we perform data normalization, gene filtering, and latent variables generation using two autoencoders. In the second module (<bold>B</bold>), we adopt the network fusion-based clustering method to segregate cell types for small data. The third module (<bold>C</bold>) aims at clustering big data using a combination of the network fusion approach and K nearest neighbors (k-NN) algorithm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
    <sec id="Sec3">
      <title>Data compression using autoencoders (Module 1)</title>
      <p id="Par10">Module 1 aims at compressing the original data into a compact representation. This module consists of three main steps: (1) data rescaling, (2) feature selection, and (3) multiple latent variables generation. The first step rescales the data, while the second step removes genes that are not informative. The third step transforms the data obtained from step 2 into a low-dimensional space using a stacked Bayesian autoencoder. The details of each step are presented in the following sections.</p>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Min-max scaling</title>
        <p id="Par11">The input of Module 1 is an already-normalized expression matrix in which rows represent cells while columns represent genes. Given the input matrix, we rescale the data to a range of 0 to 1 as follows:<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} X_{ij} = \dfrac{M_{ij} - min(M_{i.})}{max(M_{i.}) - min(M_{i.})} \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>M</italic> is the input matrix and <italic>X</italic> is the normalized matrix. Note that this min-max scaling is not a scRNA-seq normalization method. This min-max scaling added to our method is used on top of the already normalized data provided by users. Such scaling is frequently used in deep learning models<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup> with the common purpose of reducing standard deviation and suppressing the effect of outliers without altering the transcriptome landscape (see Supplementary Section <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">8</xref> and Figure <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S11</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>Feature selection using non-negative-kernel autoencoder</title>
        <p id="Par12">After the rescaling, we further process the data using an 1-layer autoencoder to filter out genes that do not significantly contribute to differentiating cells. Autoencoder is a self-learning neural network that consists of two core components: an encoder and a decoder. The encoder projects the input onto a lower-dimensional space (compressed data) while the decoder tries to reconstruct the original data from the compressed data. Optimizing this process can theoretically result in a compact representation of the original data. By default, we set the dimension of the compressed data (bottleneck layer) to 50. The low number of dimensions ensures that the data obtained from the bottleneck layer is a compact representation of the original input, high-dimensional data.</p>
        <p id="Par13">We also constrain the weights of the encoder to be non-negative, so that each latent variable in the compressed space is a part-based, additive combination of the input. This technique shrinks the coefficients of less important features to zero while maintaining the non-negative coefficients of the significant features. From the weight distribution of the encoder, scCAN only keeps genes that have non-zero coefficients in the part-based representation. In essence, this set of genes can be considered the <italic>optimal set</italic> (sufficient and necessary) to represent the original data. This set is “necessary” because removing any gene from this set would greatly damage the reconstruction ability of the decoder. Concurrently, the set is “sufficient” because adding any other genes would not improve the quality of the compressed data. By default, scCAN selects the top 5000 genes that have non-zero coefficients with the highest coefficient variances.</p>
        <p id="Par14">After this feature selection step, we obtain a new matrix with the same number of cells (rows), but the columns consist of only the optimal set of genes. This matrix serves as the input of another autoencoder to generate multiple low-dimensional representations of the data.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec6">
        <title>Dimensionality reduction using Stacked Variational Autoencoder</title>
        <p id="Par15">After the feature selection step, we obtain a denoised data matrix that consists of important genes. Although a significant number of genes have been removed, there are still thousands of genes. To reduce the computational resources required for clustering, we further reduce the size of the data by conducting an additional step of dimensional reduction using a modified version of Variational Autoencoder (VAE)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. We call it Stacked Variational Autoencoder because we generate multiple latent spaces instead of generating only one as in the original VAE.</p>
        <p id="Par16">The VAE has the same structure as a standard autoencoder, which consists of an encoder and a decoder. The encoder (<inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$f_E$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4"><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) projects the input to a low-dimensional space while the decoder (<inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$f_D$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6"><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq2.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) reconstructs the original input from the compressed data. Given an expression profile of a cell <italic>x</italic>, we have <inline-formula id="IEq3"><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$e=f_E(x)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq3.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, where <italic>e</italic> is the low-dimensional representation of <italic>x</italic> in the bottleneck layer. Instead of using <italic>e</italic> directly to reconstruct the data, VAE adds two transformations <inline-formula id="IEq4"><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$f_\mu$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10"><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq4.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq5"><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$f_\sigma$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M12"><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq5.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> to generate the parameters <inline-formula id="IEq6"><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\mu$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M14"><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq6.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq7"><alternatives><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\sigma$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M16"><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq7.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. The new vector <italic>z</italic> is now sampled from the distribution <inline-formula id="IEq8"><alternatives><tex-math id="M17">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$N(\mu ,\sigma ^2)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M18"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq8.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. The decoder uses <italic>z</italic> to reconstruct the data: <inline-formula id="IEq9"><alternatives><tex-math id="M19">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\bar{x}=f_D(z)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M20"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq9.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. Adding randomness to <italic>z</italic> will help the VAE model to avoid overfitting without losing the ability of learning a generalized representation of the input.</p>
        <p id="Par17">Here we modify the VAE model to generate multiple compressed spaces with multiple realizations of <italic>z</italic>. The goal is to further diminish overfitting and to increase the robustness of the model. Given a list of latent variables, we use a re-parameterization trick<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup> to obtain multiple realizations of <italic>z</italic> as follows: <inline-formula id="IEq10"><alternatives><tex-math id="M21">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$z = \mu + \sigma *N(0,1)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M22"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq10.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. This strategy ensures the VAE model can be back-propagated. In our model, we limit the size of the latent layer to a low number of dimensions (<italic>d</italic> = 15 by default). We keep <italic>d</italic> small to force the neural network to be as compressed as possible.</p>
        <p id="Par18">After finishing the training stage, the input data is processed through the encoder to generate multiple representative latent variables of the original data. As described in the next section, these compressed representations of the data are used for cell segregation (clustering).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec7">
      <title>Network fusion and spectral clustering for cell segregation (Module 2)</title>
      <p id="Par19">This section describes the workflow for analyzing datasets with a moderate number of cells (<inline-formula id="IEq11"><alternatives><tex-math id="M23">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$n&lt;=5000$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M24"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>5000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq11.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> by default). When the number of samples is large (over 5000 up to millions of cells), we use a different procedure (see Module 3 in “<xref rid="Sec8" ref-type="sec">Big data analysis (Module 3)</xref>” section).</p>
      <p id="Par20">The input of Module 2 is multiple low-dimensional representations (matrices) of the input data. We use a network fusion-based approach to cluster scRNA-seq data via multiple steps: (1) building a cell-similarity network for each of the representations, (2) fusing the networks, and (3) clustering using spectral clustering.</p>
      <p id="Par21">For each latent matrix, we construct a cell-similarity network <inline-formula id="IEq12"><alternatives><tex-math id="M25">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$G = (V,E)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M26"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq12.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> where each vertex <italic>V</italic> corresponds to a cell and each edge <italic>E</italic> represents a link between two cells. Edges are weighted and stored in a <inline-formula id="IEq13"><alternatives><tex-math id="M27">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$m \times m$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M28"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq13.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> matrix <italic>W</italic> with <inline-formula id="IEq14"><alternatives><tex-math id="M29">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$W_{ij}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M30"><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq14.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> represents the weight between cells <inline-formula id="IEq15"><alternatives><tex-math id="M31">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$x_i$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M32"><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq15.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq16"><alternatives><tex-math id="M33">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$x_j$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M34"><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq16.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. To determine the weight for each pair of cells, we first compute the Euclidean distance <inline-formula id="IEq17"><alternatives><tex-math id="M35">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\rho _{ij}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M36"><mml:msub><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq17.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> between the cells <inline-formula id="IEq18"><alternatives><tex-math id="M37">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$x_i$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M38"><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq18.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq19"><alternatives><tex-math id="M39">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$x_j$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M40"><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq19.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. Next, we calculate the average value of the distances between the cell <inline-formula id="IEq20"><alternatives><tex-math id="M41">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$x_i$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M42"><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq20.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and its neighbors <inline-formula id="IEq21"><alternatives><tex-math id="M43">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\rho _{i\_} = \frac{\sum _{j=1...k} (\rho (x_i, n_j))}{k}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M44"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>_</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq21.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> . We repeat this step for the cell <inline-formula id="IEq22"><alternatives><tex-math id="M45">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$x_j$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M46"><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq22.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> to obtain <inline-formula id="IEq23"><alternatives><tex-math id="M47">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\rho _{j\_}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M48"><mml:msub><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>_</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq23.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. We keep the number of neighbors small (<italic>k</italic> = 30 by default) to preserve local cells relationship, but users are free to set their own values. We denote <inline-formula id="IEq24"><alternatives><tex-math id="M49">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\varepsilon _{ij} = \frac{\rho _{ij} + \rho _{i\_} + \rho _{j\_}}{3}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M50"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>_</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>_</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq24.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> as an average distance among cells <inline-formula id="IEq25"><alternatives><tex-math id="M51">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$x_i$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M52"><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq25.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq26"><alternatives><tex-math id="M53">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$x_j$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M54"><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq26.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and neighbour cells to calculate <inline-formula id="IEq27"><alternatives><tex-math id="M55">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$W_{ij}=exp\left( -\frac{\rho ^2(x_{i}x_{j})}{\mu \varepsilon _{ij}}\right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M56"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq27.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> where <inline-formula id="IEq28"><alternatives><tex-math id="M57">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\mu$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M58"><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq28.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is a Gaussian similarity kernel (<inline-formula id="IEq29"><alternatives><tex-math id="M59">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\sigma = 0.5$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M60"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq29.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>). Finally, we repeat this process for every pair of cells to obtain the similarity matrix W for the current latent matrix to obtain a similarity network. Here, each network is a graph representation of a single latent matrix.</p>
      <p id="Par22">Next, we perform network fusion to aggregate multiple similarity networks obtained from their corresponding latent matrices into a consolidated one. The network fusion approach is adapted from SNF method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup> by first calculating the full and sparse kernel for each vertex <italic>V</italic> in the network <italic>G</italic>. The full kernel is the normalized weight matrix <italic>P</italic> obtained from <italic>G</italic>. The sparse kernel <italic>S</italic> is a matrix that contains local affinity of cells and their neighbors. This step maintains the weights for cells in the same group while suppressing the weights of non-neighbouring cells to zero. That means cell similarities in the same community are more trustworthy than the remote ones. We repeatedly calculate the full and sparse kernel for all <italic>n</italic> similarity networks to get the lists of updated weight matrices and encoded neighbour similarity matrices. Then, those matrices are iteratively fused together to obtain the final fused network <italic>P</italic> as follows:<disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M61">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} P^{(v)}= S^{(v)} \times \left( \frac{\sum _{k \ne v} P^{(k)}}{n-1}\right) \times (S^{(v)})^T, \quad v = 1,2,...,n \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M62" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>≠</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>Given the fused network <italic>P</italic>, we use the eigengap method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup> to determine the number of clusters. First, we compute adjacency matrix <italic>A</italic> and degree matrix <italic>D</italic> to get Laplacian matrix <inline-formula id="IEq30"><alternatives><tex-math id="M63">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$L = D-A$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M64"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq30.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. Here, eigen values (<inline-formula id="IEq31"><alternatives><tex-math id="M65">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\lambda$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M66"><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq31.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) and eigen vectors (<italic>x</italic>) are calculated by <inline-formula id="IEq32"><alternatives><tex-math id="M67">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$Lx = \lambda x$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M68"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq32.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. Next, eigengap is defined as <inline-formula id="IEq33"><alternatives><tex-math id="M69">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$eigengap_{i} = \lambda _{i+1} - \lambda _{i}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M70"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq33.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> where <inline-formula id="IEq34"><alternatives><tex-math id="M71">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\lambda _{i}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M72"><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq34.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the <italic>i</italic>-th eigenvalue of the matrix <italic>L</italic>. In our method, <italic>i</italic> is user-control hyperparameter that is set from 2 to 15 by default. From the list of eigengap values, we sort them in ascending order and select the two highest eigengap values. Among those two, we select the eigengap that yields a minimum <italic>i</italic> to prevent overestimating the number of clusters. This <italic>i</italic> value is considered as the optimal number of clusters. Given the number of clusters, we use spectral clustering<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup> to partition the cells in the fused network <italic>P</italic>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec8">
      <title>Big data analysis (Module 3)</title>
      <p id="Par23">When the number of cells is large (<inline-formula id="IEq35"><alternatives><tex-math id="M73">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$n &gt; 5000$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M74"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>5000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq35.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>), we split the cells into two sets: a training set of 5000 randomly selected cells and a testing set that consists of the remaining cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. We then use the same procedure presented in Module 2 to cluster the <italic>training data</italic>. After this step, we obtain a <italic>training cluster assignment</italic>. We annotate the remaining cells in each latent matrix as <italic>testing data</italic>, and we aim to classify them using the cells labels obtained from the <italic>training data</italic>.</p>
      <p id="Par24">We perform the classification process on <italic>testing data</italic> in only one latent matrix among multiple ones obtained from Module 1. In order to do that, we select the best latent matrix that is a closed representation of other matrices. First, we use k-nearest neighbor adaption of spectral clustering algorithm (k-nn SC) to quickly get the clusters assignments for every latent matrix. Given the list of obtained clusters, we use weighted-based meta-clustering (wMetaC) implemented in SHARP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup> to determine the final cluster assignment. The wMetaC algorithm is conducted through 5 steps: (1) calculating cell-cell weighted similarity matrix <italic>W</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq36"><alternatives><tex-math id="M75">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$w_{ij} = s_{ij}(1-s_{ij})$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M76"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq36.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> where <inline-formula id="IEq37"><alternatives><tex-math id="M77">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$s_{ij}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M78"><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq37.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the chance that cell <italic>i</italic> and <italic>j</italic> are in the same cluster, (2) calculating cell weight, which is the sum of all cell-cell weights related to this cell, (3) generating cluster-cluster similarity matrix <inline-formula id="IEq38"><alternatives><tex-math id="M79">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$|C|\times |C|$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M80"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq38.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, where <italic>C</italic> is the union of all the clusters obtained in each replicate, (4) performing hierarchical clustering on cluster-cluster similarity matrix, and (5) determining final clustering result by voting scheme. One note of caution is that the final clustering results obtained from this step are only used to determine the best latent matrix. Then, we measure the adjusted Rand index (ARI) value between the final cluster and the cluster obtained from k-nn SC on each input latent. The latent matrix that yields the highest ARI value will be selected for classification.</p>
      <p id="Par25">Given the final latent matrix, we use k-NN algorithm to classify the remaining cells using cluster’s labels obtained from the <italic>training data</italic>. Lastly, we merge the cluster assignments from the <italic>training data</italic> and the <italic>testing data</italic> to get the final clustering result.</p>
      <p id="Par26">Note that the default value of 5000 allows us to have a sufficiently large sample size to properly determine the cell types which in turns will lead to a proper classification of the remaining cells. At the same time, 5000 is a reasonable small number of samples that allows users to perform the analysis efficiently using personal computers. However, this default value might hinder the process of detecting rare cell types in large datasets. To enhance the method’s capability to detect rare cell types, users can either increase the sample size or perform multi-stage clustering. More details are provided in Supplementary Section <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">9</xref> and Figure <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S12</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec9">
    <title>Results</title>
    <p id="Par27">In this section, we assess the performance of scCAN in the following capabilities: (1) correct estimation of the number of cell types, (2) proper segregation of cells of different types, (3) robustness against dropout events, and (4) scalability against the increasing number of cell types. For this purpose, we analyze 28 real scRNA-seq datasets and simulations in various scenarios. We compare scCAN with five state-of-the-art clustering methods that are widely used for single-cell analysis: CIDR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>, SEURAT3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>, Monocle3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>, SHARP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>, and SCANPY<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>.</p>
    <p id="Par28">Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> shows the number of datasets used in our analysis. Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref> reports more details of the 28 scRNA-seq datasets and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref> reports the download link. The largest dataset, Brain 1.3M, has 1,300,774 cells. The datasets Guo, Kanton, Brann, and Miller were downloaded from the European Bioinformatics Institute (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/gxa/sc/experiments/">https://www.ebi.ac.uk/gxa/sc/experiments/</ext-link>). The datasets Slyper, Zilionis, Orozco, and Kozareva were downloaded from Broad Institute Single Cell Portal (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://singlecell.broadinstitute.org/single_cell">https://singlecell.broadinstitute.org/single_cell</ext-link>). The datasets Montoro, Hrvatin, Darrah, Cao were downloaded from NCBI<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. The Brain 1.3M dataset was downloaded from the 10X Genomics website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://support.10xgenomics.com/single-cell-gene-expression/datasets/1.3.0/1M_neurons">https://support.10xgenomics.com/single-cell-gene-expression/datasets/1.3.0/1M_neurons</ext-link>). The remaining 15 datasets were downloaded from Hemberg Group’s website <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://hemberg-lab.github.io/scRNA.seq.datasets">https://hemberg-lab.github.io/scRNA.seq.datasets</ext-link>. We removed samples with ambiguous labels from these datasets. Specifically, we removed cells with the label “zothers” from Chen,“dropped” from Wang, “not applicable” from Segerstolpe, and “Not available” from Guo, Kanton, and Miller. The only processing step we did was to perform a log transformation (base 2) to rescale the data if the range of the data is larger than 100. All datasets except Brain 1.3M have true cell type information and thus can be used to assess the accuracy of the clustering methods. Each of the Cao and Brain 1.3M datasets has more than a million of cells and thus can be used to assess the scalability of the methods.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Description of the 28 single-cell datasets used in our data analysis.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Name</th><th align="left">Accession ID</th><th align="left">Tissue</th><th align="left">Size</th><th align="left">Class</th><th align="left">Platform</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Brain 1.3M</td><td align="left">GSE93421</td><td align="left">Mouse brain</td><td char="." align="char">1,300,774</td><td char="." align="char">NA</td><td align="left">10X Genomics</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cao</td><td align="left">GSE156793</td><td align="left">Human cerebellum</td><td char="." align="char">1,092,000</td><td char="." align="char">9</td><td align="left">10X Genomics</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Kozareva</td><td align="left">SCP795</td><td align="left">Mouse cerebellum</td><td char="." align="char">611,034</td><td char="." align="char">18</td><td align="left">10X Genomics</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Darrah</td><td align="left">GSE139598</td><td align="left">Human blood</td><td char="." align="char">162,490</td><td char="." align="char">14</td><td align="left">Drop-seq</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Miller</td><td align="left">E-MTAB-8221</td><td align="left">Human lung</td><td char="." align="char">142,523</td><td char="." align="char">11</td><td align="left">10X Genomics</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Orozco</td><td align="left">GSE135133</td><td align="left">Human eye</td><td char="." align="char">100,055</td><td char="." align="char">11</td><td align="left">10X Genomics</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hrvatin</td><td align="left">GSE102827</td><td align="left">Mouse visual cortex</td><td char="." align="char">48,266</td><td char="." align="char">8</td><td align="left">inDrop</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Macosko</td><td align="left">GSE63473</td><td align="left">Mouse retina</td><td char="." align="char">44,808</td><td char="." align="char">12</td><td align="left">Drop-seq</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Zilionis</td><td align="left">GSE127465</td><td align="left">Human lung</td><td char="." align="char">34,558</td><td char="." align="char">9</td><td align="left">inDrop</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Brann</td><td align="left">E-GEOD-151346</td><td align="left">Mouse brain</td><td char="." align="char">26,766</td><td char="." align="char">46</td><td align="left">10X Genomics</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Kanton</td><td align="left">E-HCAD-5</td><td align="left">Human brain</td><td char="." align="char">17,542</td><td char="." align="char">14</td><td align="left">Smart-Seq2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Slyper</td><td align="left">SCP345</td><td align="left">Human blood</td><td char="." align="char">13,316</td><td char="." align="char">8</td><td align="left">10X Genomics</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Chen</td><td align="left">GSE87544</td><td align="left">Mouse brain</td><td char="." align="char">12,089</td><td char="." align="char">46</td><td align="left">Drop-seq</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Baron</td><td align="left">GSE84133</td><td align="left">Human pancreas</td><td char="." align="char">8569</td><td char="." align="char">14</td><td align="left">inDrop</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Guo</td><td align="left">E-GEOD-134144</td><td align="left">Human testis</td><td char="." align="char">7416</td><td char="." align="char">7</td><td align="left">10X Genomics</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Montoro</td><td align="left">GSE103354</td><td align="left">Human pancreas</td><td char="." align="char">7193</td><td char="." align="char">7</td><td align="left">Smart-Seq2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Lake</td><td align="left">phs000833.v3.p1</td><td align="left">Human brain</td><td char="." align="char">3042</td><td char="." align="char">16</td><td align="left">Fluidigm C1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Zeisel</td><td align="left">GSE60361</td><td align="left">Mouse brain</td><td char="." align="char">3005</td><td char="." align="char">9</td><td align="left">STRT-Seq</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Romanov</td><td align="left">GSE74672</td><td align="left">Mouse brain</td><td char="." align="char">2881</td><td char="." align="char">7</td><td align="left">SMARTer</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Segerstolpe</td><td align="left">E-MTAB-5061</td><td align="left">Human pancreas</td><td char="." align="char">2209</td><td char="." align="char">14</td><td align="left">Smart-Seq2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Muraro</td><td align="left">GSE85241</td><td align="left">Human pancreas</td><td char="." align="char">2126</td><td char="." align="char">10</td><td align="left">CEL-Seq2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Xin</td><td align="left">GSE81608</td><td align="left">Human pancreas</td><td char="." align="char">1600</td><td char="." align="char">8</td><td align="left">SMARTer</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Camp</td><td align="left">GSE81252</td><td align="left">Human liver</td><td char="." align="char">777</td><td char="." align="char">7</td><td align="left">SMARTer</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Usoskin</td><td align="left">GSE59739</td><td align="left">Mouse brain</td><td char="." align="char">622</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td align="left">STRT-Seq</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Li</td><td align="left">GSE81861</td><td align="left">Human tissues</td><td char="." align="char">561</td><td char="." align="char">9</td><td align="left">SMARTer</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Wang</td><td align="left">GSE83139</td><td align="left">Human pancreas</td><td char="." align="char">457</td><td char="." align="char">7</td><td align="left">SMARTer</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Patel</td><td align="left">GSE57872</td><td align="left">Human tissues</td><td char="." align="char">430</td><td char="." align="char">5</td><td align="left">Smart-Seq</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pollen</td><td align="left">SRP041736</td><td align="left">Human tissues</td><td char="." align="char">301</td><td char="." align="char">11</td><td align="left">SMARTer</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The table shows the accession ID, tissue, number of cells, true number of cell types, and single-cell platform. All datasets except Brain 1.3M have true cell type information and thus can be used to assess the accuracy of the clustering methods. Each of the Cao and Brain 1.3M datasets has more than a million of cells and thus can be used to assess the scalability of the methods.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
    <p id="Par29">We use CIDR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>, SEURAT3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>, Monocle3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>, SHARP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>, SCANPY<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>, and scCAN to partition each of the 28 real scRNA-seq datasets. CIDR, SEURAT3, Monocle3, and SHARP cannot perform clustering when the dataset has more than 45,000, 30,000, 160,000, and 100,000 cells, respectively. These methods run out of memory in 7, 9, 3, and 5 datasets, respectively (the memory limit is set to 200GB of RAM). Only scCAN and SCANPY can analyze all datasets. Below, we use different metrics to assess the performance of each method.</p>
    <sec id="Sec10">
      <title>Estimating the number of true cell types</title>
      <p id="Par30">We use CIDR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>, SEURAT3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>, Monocle3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>, SHARP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>, SCANPY<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>, and scCAN to partition each of the 27 real scRNA-seq datasets. To evaluate how well each method estimates the number of cell types, we compare the number of clusters produced by each method against the number of true cell types using the absolute log-modulus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>: <inline-formula id="IEq39"><alternatives><tex-math id="M81">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$L(x) = |sign(x)*log10(|x|+1)|$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M82"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq39.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> where <italic>x</italic> is the difference between the number of clusters and the number of cell types. The lower the <italic>L</italic>(<italic>x</italic>) value, the more similar the number of clusters and the true number of cell types. <italic>L</italic>(<italic>x</italic>) equals to zero denotes a perfect estimation.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Absolute log-modulus values obtained from CIDR, SEURAT3, Monocle3, SHARP, SCANPY, and scCAN for 27 real scRNA-seq datasets. This metric measures the difference between the number of clusters and the number of true cell types. The average log modulus of scCAN is 0.59 while those of Monocle3, SCANPY, SHARP, SEURAT3, and CIDR are 1.35, 1, 0.72, 0.64, and 0.63, respectively. scCAN significantly outperforms other methods by having the smallest absolute log-modulus values (Wilcoxon <italic>p</italic>-value of <inline-formula id="IEq40"><alternatives><tex-math id="M83">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$p=8.6\times 10^{-4}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M84"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>8.6</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq40.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>). Note that the dataset Brain 1.3M was excluded from this analysis because it does not have true cell type information.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Fig2_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p>
      <p id="Par31">Figure <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> shows the absolute log-modulus values obtained using the six clustering methods. Each box represents the absolute log-modulus values across 27 scRNA-seq datasets for a method. We observe that Monocle3 and SCANPY frequently overestimate the number of clusters. Both methods have the highest absolute log-modulus values. Overall, scCAN is the best method in estimating the number of true cell types. The average log modulus of scCAN is 0.59 whereas those of Monocle3, SCANPY, SHARP, SEURAT3, and CIDR are 1.35, 1, 0.72, 0.64, and 0.63, respectively. A one-sided Wilcoxon test also confirms that the absolute log-modulus values obtained from scCAN are significantly smaller than other methods with a p-value of <inline-formula id="IEq41"><alternatives><tex-math id="M85">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$9\times 10^{-4}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M86"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>9</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq41.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. We report the absolute log-modulus values for each method and each dataset in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec11">
      <title>Segregating cells of different types</title>
      <p id="Par32">To assess the accuracy of each clustering method, we also compare the clustering results against the true cell labels. For this purpose, we use three evaluation metrics: adjusted Rand index (ARI)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>, adjusted mutual information (AMI)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>, and V-measure<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>. Details of each metric are provided in Supplementary Section <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Accuracy assessment of the six clustering methods using adjusted Rand index (ARI), adjusted mutual information (AMI), and V-measure. scCAN consistently and substantially outperforms other methods in every assessment by having the highest ARI, AMI, and V-measure values across 27 real scRNA-seq datasets.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Fig3_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p>
      <p id="Par33">Figure <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A shows the ARI values obtained from the six clustering methods. Each box represents the ARI values across 27 datasets for a method. The results show that scCAN significantly outperforms other state-of-the-art methods by having the highest ARI values (<inline-formula id="IEq42"><alternatives><tex-math id="M87">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$p=6\times 10^{-12}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M88"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq42.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> using Wilcoxon test). The average ARI value of scCAN is 0.81 which is substantially higher than those of other methods (0.50, 0.55, 0.23, 0.41, and 0.40 for CIDR, Seurat3, Monocle3, SHARP, and SCANPY, respectively). More importantly, scCAN has the highest ARI values in 24 out of 27 datasets (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>).</p>
      <p id="Par34">Figure <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B shows the AMI values of each method. The AMI values of scCAN are significantly higher than those of other methods (<inline-formula id="IEq43"><alternatives><tex-math id="M89">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$p=9 \times 10^{-10}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M90"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>9</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq43.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> using Wilcoxon test). The average AMI value of scCAN is 0.77 while the average AMI values of CIDR, Seurat3, Monocle3, SHARP, and SCANPY are 0.52, 0.64, 0.43, 0.41 and 0.55, respectively. scCAN also has the highest AMI values in 23 out of 27 datasets (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>).</p>
      <p id="Par35">Figure <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>C shows a similar trend using V-measure. The V-measure values of scCAN are significantly higher than those of other methods (<inline-formula id="IEq44"><alternatives><tex-math id="M91">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$p=2\times 10^{-8}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M92"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq44.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>). The average V-measure value of scCAN is 0.81 while the average AMI values of CIDR, Seurat3, Monocle3, SHARP, and SCANPY are 0.57, 0.72, 0.56, 0.50 and 0.66, respectively. scCAN also has the highest V-measure values in 23 out of 27 datasets (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>). The visualizations of cell transcriptomic landscape for 27 datasets using original cell types and cluster assignments generated by scCAN are shown in Supplementary Figures <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>–<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref> and Supplementary Figures <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>–<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S10</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec12">
      <title>Robustness against dropouts</title>
      <p id="Par36">One of the prominent challenges in single-cell data analysis is the prevalence of dropouts. To assess how robust each method is against dropouts, we simulate a number of datasets. There are a number of tools that generate simulated data, including Splatter<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup> and SymSim<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. Though powerful, these tools cannot completely emulate real-world situations. The simulators do not preserve expression levels and gene correlation structure of real genes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. Therefore, instead of generating completely new expression values, we simulate different dropout scenarios using the 27 real datasets listed above. For each dataset, we gradually increase the number of dropouts by randomly replacing non-zero expression values with zeros. The dropout rates are set to 50%, 55%, 60%, 65%, 70%, 75%, 80%, 85% and 90%. In summary, we generate 243 simulated datasets (27 real datasets with 9 different dropout rates per dataset).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Assessment of CIDR, SEURAT3, Monocle3, SHARP, SCANPY and, scCAN against dropouts. Simulations were obtained by varying the number of zeros in each of 27 real biological datasets from 50% to about 90%, respectively. Each box plot shows the ARI values obtained from each method for a specific dropout portion. Wilcoxon test shows that the ARI values obtained from scCAN are significantly higher than CIDR, SEURAT3, Monocle3, SHARP, SCANPY (<inline-formula id="IEq45"><alternatives><tex-math id="M93">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$p&lt;2.2 \times 10^{-16}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M94"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.2</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>16</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq45.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Fig4_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p>
      <p id="Par37">For each dataset, the true cell label of each cell is known and thus can be used <italic>a posteriori</italic> to assess the robustness of each clustering method. We analyze each of the 243 datasets using the six clustering methods and then calculate the ARI values. Figure <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> shows the ARI values for each method across datasets of varying dropout rates. Overall, scCAN consistently outperforms other methods in clustering cell populations regardless of dropout rates. A one-sided Wilcoxon test also confirms that the ARI values obtained from scCAN are significantly higher than those of CIDR, SEURAT3, Monocle3, SHARP, SCANPY (<inline-formula id="IEq46"><alternatives><tex-math id="M95">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$p&lt;2.2 \times 10^{-16}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M96"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.2</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>16</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Article_IEq46.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec13">
      <title>Time and space complexity</title>
      <p id="Par38">In order to assess the scalability of the clustering methods, we record the running time that each method uses to analyze the 28 real datasets. Figure <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> shows the running time of the methods with varying numbers of cells. The time complexity of CIDR increases exponentially with respect to sample size. Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref> shows the detailed running time of each method for all 28 datasets. The cell with “NA” indicates out of memory or error. The memory of our machine is limited to 256 GB. scCAN and SCANPY can cluster all datasets in minutes. The scalability of scCAN and SCANPY for big data analysis is shown at Supplementary Section <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">10</xref> and Supplementary Figures <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S13</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S14</xref>. CIDR, SEURAT3, Monocle3, and SHARP are unable to cluster datasets with more than 48,000, 17,000, 600,000, and 140,000 cells, respectively.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Running time of CIDR, SEURAT3, Monocle3, SHARP, SCANPY, and scCAN for the analysis of 28 real scRNA-seq datasets. The horizontal axis shows the number of cells while the vertical axis shows the running time in the log scale (base 60) of minutes. scCAN and SCANPY are the only two methods that can analyze datasets with more than 200,000 cells.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_Fig5_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec14">
    <title>Conclusion</title>
    <p id="Par39">In this article, we introduce a new clustering method named scCAN that can accurately segregate cells of different types from large-scale scRNA-seq data. The contribution of scCAN is three-fold: (1) effective noise detachment and dimension reduction using a non-negative-kernel and a Stacked Variational Autoencoder, (2) accurate clustering of cells using network fusion and graph-based analysis, and (3) scalable analysis of large number of cells using sampling and k-nearest neighbor. In an extensive analysis using 28 real scRNA-seq datasets and various simulation scenarios, we demonstrate that scCAN outperforms the current state-of-the-art methods, CDIR, SEURAT3, Monocle3, SHARP and SCANPY. The method can: (1) accurate estimate the number of cell types, (2) properly segregate cells of different types, (3) is robust against dropouts, and (4) is able to analyze datasets with more than a million cells in minutes. We also provide a CRAN R package with documentation for users. The tool can be seamlessly embedded into other single-cell analysis pipelines.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Information</title>
    <sec id="Sec15">
      <p>
        <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1">
          <media xlink:href="41598_2022_14218_MOESM1_ESM.pdf">
            <caption>
              <p>Supplementary Information.</p>
            </caption>
          </media>
        </supplementary-material>
      </p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <fn-group>
    <fn>
      <p>
        <bold>Publisher's note</bold>
      </p>
      <p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
    </fn>
  </fn-group>
  <sec>
    <title>Supplementary Information</title>
    <p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41598-022-14218-6.</p>
  </sec>
  <ack>
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <p>This work was partially supported by NIH NIGMS under grant number GM103440, and by NSF under grant numbers 2001385 and 2019609. Any opinions, findings, and conclusions, or recommendations expressed in this material are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the views of any of the funding agencies.</p>
  </ack>
  <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
    <title>Author contributions</title>
    <p>B.T. and T.N. conceived of and designed the approach. B.T. performed the data analysis and all computational experiments. B.T., D.T. implemented the method in R. H.N. and S.R. helped with data preparation and some data analysis. B.T., D.T., H.N., S.R. and T.N. wrote the manuscript. All authors reviewed the manuscript.</p>
  </notes>
  <notes notes-type="data-availability">
    <title>Data availability</title>
    <p>In this manuscript, we analyzed 28 publicly available datasets. The Accession numbers are reported in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>. The link to each dataset is available in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>. The scCAN package is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cran.r-project.org/package=scCAN">https://cran.r-project.org/package=scCAN</ext-link>. Processed data and R scripts are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sccan.tinnguyen-lab.com/">http://sccan.tinnguyen-lab.com/</ext-link></p>
  </notes>
  <notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement">
    <title>Competing interests</title>
    <p id="Par40">The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
  </notes>
  <ref-list id="Bib1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="CR1">
      <label>1.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Saliba</surname>
            <given-names>A-E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Westermann</surname>
            <given-names>AJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gorski</surname>
            <given-names>SA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vogel</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Single-cell RNA-seq: Advances and future challenges</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>42</volume>
        <fpage>8845</fpage>
        <lpage>8860</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gku555</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25053837?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25053837</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR2">
      <label>2.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tran</surname>
            <given-names>Duc</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tran</surname>
            <given-names>Bang</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nguyen</surname>
            <given-names>Hung</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nguyen</surname>
            <given-names>Tin</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A novel method for single-cell data imputation using subspace regression</article-title>
        <source>Scientific Reports</source>
        <year>2022</year>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>2697</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-06500-4</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 35177662?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35177662</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR3">
      <label>3.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Villani</surname>
            <given-names>A-C</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Single-cell RNA-seq reveals new types of human blood dendritic cells, monocytes, and progenitors</article-title>
        <source>Science</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>356</volume>
        <fpage>eaah4573</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aah4573</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 28428369?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28428369</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR4">
      <label>4.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jaitin</surname>
            <given-names>DA</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Massively parallel single-cell RNA-seq for marker-free decomposition of tissues into cell types</article-title>
        <source>Science</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>343</volume>
        <fpage>776</fpage>
        <lpage>779</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1247651</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24531970?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24531970</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR5">
      <label>5.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Single-cell RNA-seq analysis maps development of human germline cells and gonadal niche interactions</article-title>
        <source>Cell Stem Cell</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>20</volume>
        <fpage>858</fpage>
        <lpage>873</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2017.03.007</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 28457750?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28457750</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR6">
      <label>6.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jaitin</surname>
            <given-names>DA</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Dissecting immune circuits by linking CRISPR-pooled screens with single-cell RNA-seq</article-title>
        <source>Cell</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>167</volume>
        <fpage>1883</fpage>
        <lpage>1896</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2016.11.039</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 27984734?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27984734</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR7">
      <label>7.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kiselev</surname>
            <given-names>VY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Andrews</surname>
            <given-names>TS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hemberg</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Challenges in unsupervised clustering of single-cell RNA-seq data</article-title>
        <source>Nat. Rev. Genet.</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>20</volume>
        <fpage>273</fpage>
        <lpage>282</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41576-018-0088-9</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 30617341?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30617341</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR8">
      <label>8.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kiselev</surname>
            <given-names>VY</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>SC3: Consensus clustering of single-cell RNA-seq data</article-title>
        <source>Nat. Methods</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>14</volume>
        <fpage>483</fpage>
        <lpage>486</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.4236</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 28346451?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28346451</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR9">
      <label>9.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Troup</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ho</surname>
            <given-names>JWK</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>CIDR: Ultrafast and accurate clustering through imputation for single-cell RNA-seq data</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol.</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>18</volume>
        <fpage>59</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-017-1188-0</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 28351406?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28351406</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR10">
      <label>10.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>žurauskienė</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yau</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>pcaReduce: Hierarchical clustering of single cell transcriptional profiles</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinform.</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>17</volume>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <lpage>11</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-016-0984-y</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR11">
      <label>11.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Satija</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Farrell</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gennert</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schier</surname>
            <given-names>AF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Regev</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Spatial reconstruction of single-cell gene expression data</article-title>
        <source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>33</volume>
        <fpage>495</fpage>
        <lpage>502</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.3192</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25867923?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25867923</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR12">
      <label>12.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>SIMLR: A tool for large-scale genomic analyses by multi-kernel learning</article-title>
        <source>Proteomics</source>
        <year>2018</year>
        <volume>18</volume>
        <fpage>1700232</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pmic.201700232</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR13">
      <label>13.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wan</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Won</surname>
            <given-names>KJ</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>SHARP: Hyperfast and accurate processing of single-cell RNA-seq data via ensemble random projection</article-title>
        <source>Genome Res.</source>
        <year>2020</year>
        <volume>30</volume>
        <fpage>205</fpage>
        <lpage>213</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.254557.119</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 31992615?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31992615</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR14">
      <label>14.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pearson</surname>
            <given-names>KLIII</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>On lines and planes of closest fit to systems of points in space</article-title>
        <source>Lond. Edinb. Dublin Philos. Mag. J. Sci.</source>
        <year>1901</year>
        <volume>2</volume>
        <fpage>559</fpage>
        <lpage>572</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14786440109462720</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR15">
      <label>15.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Van der Maaten</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hinton</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Visualizing data using t-SNE</article-title>
        <source>J. Mach. Learn. Res.</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <fpage>2579</fpage>
        <lpage>2605</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR16">
      <label>16.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">McInnes, L., Healy, J. &amp; Melville, J. Umap: Uniform manifold approximation and projection for dimension reduction. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1802.03426">arXiv:1802.03426</ext-link> (2018).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR17">
      <label>17.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tian</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wan</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Song</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wei</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Clustering single-cell RNA-seq data with a model-based deep learning approach</article-title>
        <source>Nat. Mach. Intell.</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>1</volume>
        <fpage>191</fpage>
        <lpage>198</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s42256-019-0037-0</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR18">
      <label>18.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xie</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zeng</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>scAIDE: Clustering of large-scale single-cell RNA-seq data reveals putative and rare cell types</article-title>
        <source>NAR Genomics Bioinform.</source>
        <year>2020</year>
        <volume>2</volume>
        <fpage>lqaa082</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nargab/lqaa082</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR19">
      <label>19.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Alessandri</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Sparsely-connected autoencoder (SCA) for single cell RNAseq data mining</article-title>
        <source>NPJ Syst. Biol. Appl.</source>
        <year>2021</year>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <lpage>10</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41540-020-00162-6</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 33402683?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33402683</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR20">
      <label>20.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Guo</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xiao</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lao</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>AAE-SC: A scRNA-seq clustering framework based on adversarial autoencoder</article-title>
        <source>IEEE Access</source>
        <year>2020</year>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <fpage>178962</fpage>
        <lpage>178975</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ACCESS.2020.3027481</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR21">
      <label>21.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>scGMAI: A Gaussian mixture model for clustering single-cell RNA-Seq data based on deep autoencoder</article-title>
        <source>Brief. Bioinform.</source>
        <year>2020</year>
        <volume>22</volume>
        <fpage>bbaa316</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bib/bbaa316</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR22">
      <label>22.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mereu</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Benchmarking single-cell RNA-sequencing protocols for cell atlas projects</article-title>
        <source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source>
        <year>2020</year>
        <volume>38</volume>
        <fpage>747</fpage>
        <lpage>755</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41587-020-0469-4</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 32518403?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32518403</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR23">
      <label>23.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Haque</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Engel</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Teichmann</surname>
            <given-names>SA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lönnberg</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A practical guide to single-cell RNA-sequencing for biomedical research and clinical applications</article-title>
        <source>Genome Med.</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <fpage>75</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13073-017-0467-4</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 28821273?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28821273</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR24">
      <label>24.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zeisel</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Cell types in the mouse cortex and hippocampus revealed by single-cell RNA-seq</article-title>
        <source>Science</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>347</volume>
        <fpage>1138</fpage>
        <lpage>1142</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aaa1934</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25700174?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25700174</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR25">
      <label>25.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Riggs</surname>
            <given-names>AD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>SAIC: An iterative clustering approach for analysis of single cell RNA-seq data</article-title>
        <source>BMC Genomics</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>18</volume>
        <fpage>9</fpage>
        <lpage>17</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-016-3380-0</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28049416</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR26">
      <label>26.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>M-W</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>PanoView: An iterative clustering method for single-cell RNA sequencing data</article-title>
        <source>PLoS Comput. Biol.</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>15</volume>
        <fpage>e1007040</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007040</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 31469823?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31469823</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR27">
      <label>27.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Blondel</surname>
            <given-names>VD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Guillaume</surname>
            <given-names>J-L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lambiotte</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lefebvre</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Fast unfolding of communities in large networks</article-title>
        <source>J. Stat. Mech. Theory Exp.</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>2008</volume>
        <fpage>P10008</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1742-5468/2008/10/P10008</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR28">
      <label>28.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Traag</surname>
            <given-names>VA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Waltman</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>van Eck</surname>
            <given-names>NJ</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>From Louvain to Leiden: Guaranteeing well-connected communities</article-title>
        <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <lpage>12</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-41695-z</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30626917</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR29">
      <label>29.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Stuart</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Comprehensive integration of single-cell data</article-title>
        <source>Cell</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>177</volume>
        <fpage>1888</fpage>
        <lpage>1902</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2019.05.031</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 31178118?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31178118</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR30">
      <label>30.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wolf</surname>
            <given-names>FA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Angerer</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Theis</surname>
            <given-names>FJ</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>SCANPY: Large-scale single-cell gene expression data analysis</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol.</source>
        <year>2018</year>
        <volume>19</volume>
        <fpage>15</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-017-1382-0</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 29409532?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29409532</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR31">
      <label>31.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cao</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The single-cell transcriptional landscape of mammalian organogenesis</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>566</volume>
        <fpage>496</fpage>
        <lpage>502</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-019-0969-x</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 30787437?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30787437</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR32">
      <label>32.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>SAFE-clustering: Single-cell aggregated (from ensemble) clustering for single-cell RNA-seq data</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>35</volume>
        <fpage>1269</fpage>
        <lpage>1277</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bty793</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 30202935?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30202935</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR33">
      <label>33.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Huh</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jiang</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shen</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>SAME-clustering: S ingle-cell A ggregated Clustering via M ixture Model E nsemble</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <year>2020</year>
        <volume>48</volume>
        <fpage>86</fpage>
        <lpage>95</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkz959</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 31777938?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31777938</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR34">
      <label>34.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>H-D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xie</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Sc-GPE: A graph partitioning-based cluster ensemble method for single-cell</article-title>
        <source>Front. Genet.</source>
        <year>2020</year>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <fpage>1606</fpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR35">
      <label>35.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Su</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Identification of cell types from single-cell transcriptomes using a novel clustering method</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2015</year>
        <volume>31</volume>
        <fpage>1974</fpage>
        <lpage>1980</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv088</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 25805722?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25805722</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR36">
      <label>36.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Single-cell clustering based on shared nearest neighbor and graph partitioning</article-title>
        <source>Interdiscip. Sci. Comput. Life Sci.</source>
        <year>2020</year>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <fpage>117</fpage>
        <lpage>130</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12539-019-00357-4</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR37">
      <label>37.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>H-D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Guo</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>F-X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Analysis of single-cell RNA-seq data by clustering approaches</article-title>
        <source>Curr. Bioinform.</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>14</volume>
        <fpage>314</fpage>
        <lpage>322</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1574893614666181120095038</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR38">
      <label>38.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Alqurashi</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Clustering ensemble method</article-title>
        <source>Int. J. Mach. Learn. Cybern.</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <fpage>1227</fpage>
        <lpage>1246</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13042-017-0756-7</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR39">
      <label>39.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">He, K., Zhang, X., Ren, S. &amp; Sun, J. Deep residual learning for image recognition. In <italic>2016 IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)</italic> 770–778 (2016).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR40">
      <label>40.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Huang, G., Liu, Z., Van Der Maaten, L. &amp; Weinberger, K. Q. Densely connected convolutional networks. In <italic>2017 IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)</italic> 4700–4708 (2017).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR41">
      <label>41.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Szegedy, C. <italic>et al.</italic> Going deeper with convolutions. In <italic>2015 IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)</italic> 1–9 (2015).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR42">
      <label>42.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tan, M. &amp; Le, Q. EfficientNet: Rethinking model scaling for convolutional neural networks. In <italic>Proceedings of the 36th International Conference on Machine Learning</italic>, Vol. 97, 6105–6114 (Long Beach, California, USA, 2019).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR43">
      <label>43.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tran</surname>
            <given-names>Duc</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nguyen</surname>
            <given-names>Hung</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tran</surname>
            <given-names>Bang</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>La Vecchia</surname>
            <given-names>Carlo</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Luu</surname>
            <given-names>Hung N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nguyen</surname>
            <given-names>Tin</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Fast and precise single-cell data analysis using a hierarchical autoencoder</article-title>
        <source>Nature Communications</source>
        <year>2021</year>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <lpage>10</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-20314-w</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR44">
      <label>44.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kingma, D. P. &amp; Welling, M. Auto-encoding variational Bayes. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1312.6114">arXiv:1312.6114</ext-link> [cs, stat] (2013).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR45">
      <label>45.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Similarity network fusion for aggregating data types on a genomic scale</article-title>
        <source>Nat. Methods</source>
        <year>2014</year>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <fpage>333</fpage>
        <lpage>337</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2810</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 24464287?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24464287</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR46">
      <label>46.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nguyen</surname>
            <given-names>Tin</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tagett</surname>
            <given-names>Rebecca</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Diaz</surname>
            <given-names>Diana</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Draghici</surname>
            <given-names>Sorin</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A novel approach for data integration and disease subtyping</article-title>
        <source>Genome Research</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>27</volume>
        <issue>12</issue>
        <fpage>2025</fpage>
        <lpage>2039</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.215129.116</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 29066617?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29066617</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR47">
      <label>47.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nguyen</surname>
            <given-names>Hung</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shrestha</surname>
            <given-names>Sangam</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Draghici</surname>
            <given-names>Sorin</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nguyen</surname>
            <given-names>Tin</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>PINSPlus: a tool for tumor subtype discovery in integrated genomic data</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>35</volume>
        <issue>16</issue>
        <fpage>2843</fpage>
        <lpage>2846</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bty1049</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 30590381?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30590381</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR48">
      <label>48.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Von Luxburg</surname>
            <given-names>U</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A tutorial on spectral clustering</article-title>
        <source>Stat. Comput.</source>
        <year>2007</year>
        <volume>17</volume>
        <fpage>395</fpage>
        <lpage>416</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11222-007-9033-z</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR49">
      <label>49.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ng</surname>
            <given-names>AY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jordan</surname>
            <given-names>MI</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Weiss</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>On spectral clustering: Analysis and an algorithm</article-title>
        <source>Adv. Neural. Inf. Process. Syst.</source>
        <year>2002</year>
        <volume>2</volume>
        <fpage>849</fpage>
        <lpage>856</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR50">
      <label>50.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nguyen</surname>
            <given-names>Hung</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tran</surname>
            <given-names>Duc</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tran</surname>
            <given-names>Bang</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Roy</surname>
            <given-names>Monikrishna</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cassell</surname>
            <given-names>Adam</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dascalu</surname>
            <given-names>Sergiu</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Draghici</surname>
            <given-names>Sorin</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nguyen</surname>
            <given-names>Tin</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>SMRT: Randomized Data Transformation for Cancer Subtyping and Big Data Analysis</article-title>
        <source>Front. Oncol.</source>
        <year>2021</year>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <lpage>11</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR51">
      <label>51.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Barrett</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>NCBI GEO: Archive for functional genomics data sets-update</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>41</volume>
        <fpage>D991</fpage>
        <lpage>D995</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gks1193</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 23193258?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23193258</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR52">
      <label>52.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>John</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Draper</surname>
            <given-names>NR</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>An alternative family of transformations</article-title>
        <source>J. R. Stat. Soc.: Ser. C (Appl. Stat.)</source>
        <year>1980</year>
        <volume>29</volume>
        <fpage>190</fpage>
        <lpage>197</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR53">
      <label>53.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hubert</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Arabie</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Comparing partitions</article-title>
        <source>J. Classif.</source>
        <year>1985</year>
        <volume>2</volume>
        <fpage>193</fpage>
        <lpage>218</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01908075</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR54">
      <label>54.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Vinh</surname>
            <given-names>NX</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Epps</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bailey</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Information theoretic measures for clusterings comparison: Variants, properties, normalization and correction for chance</article-title>
        <source>J. Mach. Learn. Res.</source>
        <year>2010</year>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <fpage>2837</fpage>
        <lpage>2854</lpage>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR55">
      <label>55.</label>
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rosenberg, A. &amp; Hirschberg, J. V-measure: A conditional entropy-based external cluster evaluation measure. In <italic>Proceedings of the 2007 Joint Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing and Computational Natural Language Learning (EMNLP-CoNLL)</italic> 410–420 (2007).</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR56">
      <label>56.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zappia</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Phipson</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Oshlack</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Splatter: Simulation of single-cell RNA sequencing data</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol.</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>18</volume>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <lpage>15</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-017-1305-0</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28077169</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR57">
      <label>57.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yosef</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Simulating multiple faceted variability in single cell RNA sequencing</article-title>
        <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <lpage>16</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-07882-8</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30602773</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR58">
      <label>58.</label>
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Song</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>WV</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>JJ</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>scDesign2: A transparent simulator that generates high-fidelity single-cell gene expression count data with gene correlations captured</article-title>
        <source>Genome Biol.</source>
        <year>2021</year>
        <volume>22</volume>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <lpage>37</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-020-02207-9</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33397451</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
