<?properties open_access?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?>
<?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
<?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?>
<?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?>
<?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?>
<?ConverterInfo.Version 1?>
<processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
  <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
</processing-meta>
<front>
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Metabolomics</journal-id>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Metabolomics</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Metabolomics</journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="ppub">1573-3882</issn>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1573-3890</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Springer US</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">9345815</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35917032</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1923</article-id>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11306-022-01923-6</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>Original Article</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>Spectral binning as an approach to post-acquisition processing of high resolution FIE-MS metabolome fingerprinting data</article-title>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
        <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6070-7476</contrib-id>
        <name>
          <surname>Finch</surname>
          <given-names>Jasen P.</given-names>
        </name>
        <address>
          <email>jsf9@aber.ac.uk</email>
        </address>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Wilson</surname>
          <given-names>Thomas</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Lyons</surname>
          <given-names>Laura</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Phillips</surname>
          <given-names>Helen</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Beckmann</surname>
          <given-names>Manfred</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="author">
        <name>
          <surname>Draper</surname>
          <given-names>John</given-names>
        </name>
        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
      </contrib>
      <aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8186.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2168 2483</institution-id><institution>Institute of Biological, Environmental and Rural Sciences, </institution><institution>Aberystwyth University, </institution></institution-wrap>Aberystwyth, SY23 3DA UK </aff>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub">
      <day>2</day>
      <month>8</month>
      <year>2022</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
      <day>2</day>
      <month>8</month>
      <year>2022</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
      <year>2022</year>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>18</volume>
    <issue>8</issue>
    <elocation-id>64</elocation-id>
    <history>
      <date date-type="received">
        <day>10</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="accepted">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2022</copyright-statement>
      <license>
        <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
        <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract id="Abs1">
      <sec>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <p id="Par1">Flow infusion electrospray high resolution mass spectrometry (FIE-HRMS) fingerprinting produces complex, high dimensional data sets which require specialist in-silico software tools to process the data prior to analysis.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Objectives</title>
        <p id="Par2">Present spectral binning as a pragmatic approach to post-acquisition procession of FIE-HRMS metabolome fingerprinting data.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Methods</title>
        <p id="Par3">A spectral binning approach was developed that included the elimination of single scan <italic>m/z</italic> events, the binning of spectra and the averaging of spectra across the infusion profile. The modal accurate <italic>m/z</italic> was then extracted for each bin. This approach was assessed using four different biological matrices and a mix of 31 known chemical standards analysed by FIE-HRMS using an Exactive Orbitrap. Bin purity and centrality metrics were developed to objectively assess the distribution and position of accurate <italic>m/z</italic> within an individual bin respectively.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Results</title>
        <p id="Par4">The optimal spectral binning width was found to be 0.01 amu. 80.8% of the extracted accurate <italic>m/z</italic> matched to predicted ionisation products of the chemical standards mix were found to have an error of below 3 ppm. The open-source R package <italic>binneR</italic> was developed as a user friendly implementation of the approach. This was able to process 100 data files using 4 Central Processing Units (CPU) workers in only 55 seconds with a maximum memory usage of 1.36 GB.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <p id="Par5">Spectral binning is a fast and robust method for the post-acquisition processing of FIE-HRMS data. The open-source R package <italic>binneR</italic> allows users to efficiently process data from FIE-HRMS experiments with the resources available on a standard desktop computer.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Supplementary Information</title>
        <p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 
10.1007/s11306-022-01923-6.</p>
      </sec>
    </abstract>
    <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
      <title>Keywords</title>
      <kwd>Metabolomic fingerprinting</kwd>
      <kwd>Mass spectrometry</kwd>
      <kwd>Post-acquisition processing</kwd>
      <kwd>Software</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group>
        <funding-source>
          <institution>Woodland Heritage</institution>
        </funding-source>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group>
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000265</institution-id>
            <institution>Medical Research Council</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
        <award-id>MR/S010483/1</award-id>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <funding-group>
      <award-group>
        <funding-source>
          <institution-wrap>
            <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000315</institution-id>
            <institution>Aberystwyth University</institution>
          </institution-wrap>
        </funding-source>
      </award-group>
    </funding-group>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
        <meta-value>© Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature 2022</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </article-meta>
</front>
<body>
  <sec id="Sec1">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <p id="Par6">Non-targeted metabolome fingerprinting techniques enable the global metabolite analysis of sample extracts (Dunn et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2005</xref>). Flow infusion electrospray ionisation mass spectrometry (FIE-MS) in particular provides an accessible, robust method for low cost and high throughout metabolite fingerprinting for a wide range of biological matrices (Draper et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2013</xref>).</p>
    <p id="Par7">Comparing metabolome fingerprints across multiple phenotypes has provided a powerful and unbiased approach for discovering potential molecular perturbations (Southam et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2017</xref>). It is often applied to perform initial “first pass” analyses, which rapidly provides the user with a comprehensive overview of a broad range of metabolite chemistry in a biological matrix. Potential perturbation relating to differences in phenotype can then be evaluated, and used to generate hypotheses or guide decision making on the next steps of sample analysis or experimentation before the application of more targeted chromatography based techniques (Beckmann et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2008</xref>). FIE-MS fingerprinting has been used for a wide range of biological applications such as the identification human urinary biomarkers of nutrition and the investigation of plant-fungal pathogen interactions (Lloyd et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2013</xref>; Parker et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2009</xref>).</p>
    <p id="Par8">In the last decade, there has been a proliferation in the use of ultra-high resolution (HR) MS instrumentation with Orbitrap mass analysers becoming the standard for HRMS. These mass analysers have provided extraordinary increases in attainable mass resolution, precision and accuracy. But this has also created new challenges for the post-acquisition spectral processing of mass spectra obtained from these instruments with magnitude increases in the volumes of data that can be acquired per sample.</p>
    <p id="Par9">These magnitude increases in data volume require the development of computationally efficient processing routines, especially for processing large sample sets. Spectral artefacts such as Gibbs oscillations, that are common in Fourier Transform based MS, adds further complexity (Marshall &amp; Hendrickson, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2008</xref>). Similarly, the alignment of mass spectra between samples can also make processing difficult, especially in analytical runs containing many samples (Draper et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2013</xref>). Approaches such as that of Smedsgaard and Nielsen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2005</xref>) and the <italic>proFIA</italic> R package have already attempted to overcome some of these challenges (Delabrière et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2017</xref>).</p>
    <p id="Par10">Here, we present a spectral binning based approach as an efficient and pragmatic solution to the post-acquisition processing of FIE-HRMS metabolome fingerprinting data. This is accompanied by the development of the openly available R package <italic>binneR</italic> as a user-friendly implementation of the approach.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec2">
    <title>Materials and methods</title>
    <sec id="Sec3">
      <title>Biological and chemical standards mix sample preparation</title>
      <p id="Par11">Samples were used from four example biological matrices. These included leaf tissue from the model grass species <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> (Draper et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2001</xref>), human urine, human plasma and horse serum. These were prepared and extracted as described in the supplementary materials and methods.</p>
      <p id="Par12">A diverse mixture of chemical standards from a validated assay was prepared by dissolving in a solvent mixture of methanol, water and formic acid (70%:30%:0.1%), each at a concentration of 2mg/ml (Beckmann et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2020</xref>). This mixture contained a total of 31 standards, for which a list of the names and InChi chemical identifiers can be found in Supplementary Table S1.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4">
      <title>Flow infusion high resolution fingerprinting</title>
      <p id="Par13">Mass spectra were acquired on an Exactive Orbitrap (ThermoFinnigan, San Jose CA) mass spectrometer, which was coupled to an Accela (ThermoFinnigan, San Jose CA) ultra-performance liquid chromatography system. A sample volume of 20 μL was injected and delivered to the electro-spray ionisation (ESI) source via a ‘plug’ flow solvent of pre-mixed HPLC grade MeOH (Fisher Scientific) and ultra-pure H<sub>2</sub>O (18.2 <inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\Omega$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Ω</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq2.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) at a ratio of 7:3. The initial flow rate was 60 μL min<sup>−1</sup> for 0.4 mins and increased to 200 μL min<sup>−1</sup> over 0.8 mins. The flow rate was maintained at 200 μL min<sup>−1</sup> for 0.3 mins then increased to 600 μL min<sup>−1</sup> over 1.5 mins. Then the flow rate was returned to 60 μL min<sup>−1</sup> for 0.5 minutes. The total gradient time was 3.5 mins. The capillary temperature and voltage were set at 270 °C and 37.50 kV respectively.</p>
      <p id="Par14">For the <italic>B. distachyon</italic> leaf and human urine samples, mass spectra were acquired using a single scan filter for each of the positive and negative ionisation modes. Positive ions were acquired between 55.000 and 1000.000 <italic>m/z</italic>, and 63.000 and 1000.000 <italic>m/z</italic> for negative ions. Mass spectra for the horse serum, human plasma and standards mix samples were acquired with two scan events between 55–280 <italic>m/z</italic> and 270–1200 <italic>m/z</italic> for each of the positive and negative acquisition modes. For all scan events, the scan rate was 1 Hz with a mass resolution of 100,000. The automatic gain control (AGC) target was 5 × 10<sup>5</sup> and total ion injection time 250 ms.</p>
      <p id="Par15">Each biological matrix and the chemical standards mix were analysed in separate analytical runs. A total of 10 and two replicate injections were performed for the biological matrices and standards mix respectively. Three blank injections were preformed prior to the analytical replicate injections, with the solvent mixture used in the sample preparation of the particular matrix.</p>
      <p id="Par16">Following data acquisition in profiling mode, raw mass spectra data files (.RAW, ThermoFinnigan) were converted to the universal mass spectrometry open file format, mzML (Martens et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2011</xref>). Conversion and centroiding were performed using msconvert from Proteowizard (Chambers et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2012</xref>). All further processing of mzML files was performed using the R Statistical Programming Language version 4.2.1 (R Core Team, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2020</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec5">
      <title>Spectral binning and accurate <italic>m/z</italic> assignment</title>
      <p id="Par17">
        <fig id="Fig1">
          <label>Fig. 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p>The spectral binning approach for post-acquisition processing of FIE-HRMS metabolomic fingerprinting data. The blue and red arrows denote the actions applied to 0.01 and 0.00001 amu binned data respectively</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/>
        </fig>
      </p>
      <p id="Par18">An overview of the spectral binning approach used here is shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. Firstly, for each set of sample types, the scans within the ‘plug’ flow range of the infusion profile were firstly detected by averaging the chromatographic profiles across the scan ranges and ionisation modes of all the replicate injections. The ‘plug’ flow scans were then identified in the average chromatographic profile as those with a total ion count (TIC) greater than 50% of the scan with the highest TIC (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>An example FIE-HRMS ion chromatogram. The grey area shows plug flow region that is extracted for spectral binning. The red dashed line shows the 50% level of the maximum ion count, above which scans are selected for processing</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
      <p id="Par19">For each individual sample, the <italic>m/z</italic> were binned to 0.00001 amu within each scan by rounding the <italic>m/z</italic> to five decimal places and sum aggregating the ion abundances within each bin. If multiple scan ranges were present, these were combined, with the average abundances calculated for any <italic>m/z</italic> present across scans of overlapping scan range within an ionisation detection mode. The 0.00001 amu bins were then also binned to 0.01 amu using the same method as for the 0.00001 amu bins. Where necessary, alternative bin widths of 1, 0.1, 0.001 and 0.0001 were also used for comparative purposes. See Section <xref rid="Sec12" ref-type="sec">3.1</xref> for a discussion of the optimal amu bin width. The 0.01 amu bins that contained only a single 0.00001 amu <italic>m/z</italic> that appeared in one single scan in one sample from across the sample set were removed. The abundances of both 0.01 and 0.00001 amu bins were then averaged across the ‘plug’ flow scans and each of the 0.01 amu bins were assigned an accurate <italic>m/z</italic> based on the modal 0.00001 amu <italic>m/z</italic> value within the given 0.01 amu range.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec6">
      <title>Bin metrics</title>
      <p id="Par20">Two bin metrics were developed to allow the objective assessment of both the spread and location of <italic>m/z</italic> signals within a given bin window. Bin purity and centrality are defined in the sections below.</p>
      <sec id="Sec7">
        <title>Purity</title>
        <p id="Par21">The bin purity metric provides a measure of the spread of <italic>m/z</italic> across the <italic>m/z</italic> range of a given bin window. For a given bin containing <inline-formula id="IEq9"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$n$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq9.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> mass spectral signals (<italic>m/z</italic>) <inline-formula id="IEq10"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$m = \{m_1,m_2,\ldots ,m_n\}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq10.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> with abundances <inline-formula id="IEq11"><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$a = \{a_1,a_2,\ldots ,a_n\}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq11.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, the bin total ion count <inline-formula id="IEq12"><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$t$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq12.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> can be defined as:<disp-formula id="Equ1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} t = \sum \limits _{i=1}^{n}a_i \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M12" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
        <p id="Par22">The mean <italic>m/z</italic> of the bin:<disp-formula id="Equ2"><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} {\bar{m}} = \frac{\sum \limits _{i=1}^{n}(m_ia_i)}{t} \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M14" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
        <p id="Par23">The mean absolute <italic>m/z</italic> error for a given bin is given by:<disp-formula id="Equ3"><alternatives><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} {\bar{e}} = \frac{\sum \limits _{i=1}^{n}{(a_i|m_i - {\bar{m}}|)}}{t}\end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M16" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_Equ3.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
        <p id="Par24">Finally, bin purity for a bin of width <inline-formula id="IEq13"><alternatives><tex-math id="M17">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$w$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M18"><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq13.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> (amu) can be defined by:<disp-formula id="Equ4"><alternatives><tex-math id="M19">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} p = 1 - \frac{{\bar{e}}}{0.5 \cdot w} \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M20" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_Equ4.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
        <p id="Par25">This gives a score between 0 and 1 with higher bin purity denoting a lower spread of <italic>m/z</italic> values within the bin and therefore a lower likelihood of more than one real mass signal being present within the given bin. Examples of high and low purity bins are shown in Supplementary Fig. S1.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec8">
        <title>Centrality</title>
        <p id="Par26">The bin centrality metric provides a measure of the proximity of the mean <italic>m/z</italic> to <inline-formula id="IEq14"><alternatives><tex-math id="M21">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M22"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq14.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, the centre of a given bin window. This is given by:<disp-formula id="Equ5"><alternatives><tex-math id="M23">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} c = 1 - \frac{|{\bar{m}} - k|}{0.5 \cdot w} \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M24" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_Equ5.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
        <p id="Par27">Similarly to bin purity, this provides a score of between 0 and 1 with higher bin centrality denoting a closer proximity of the <italic>m/z</italic> to the centre of the bin. Examples of high and low centrality bins are shown in Supplementary Fig. S2.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec9">
      <title>Assignment of measured accurate <italic>m/z</italic> to compounds in the chemical standards mix</title>
      <p id="Par28">Using six common negative ionisation mode adducts ([M − H]<sup>1−</sup>, [M + Cl]<sup>1−</sup>, [M + <sup>37</sup>Cl]<sup>1−</sup>, [M + K − 2H]<sup>1−</sup>, [2M − H]<sup>1−</sup>, [M − 2H]<sup>2−</sup>) and six common positive ionisation mode adducts ([M + H]<sup>1+</sup>, [M + K]<sup>1+</sup>, [M + <sup>41</sup>K]<sup>1+</sup>, [M + Na]<sup>1+</sup>, [2M + H]<sup>1+</sup>, [M + 2H]<sup>2+</sup>), possible ionisation products were computed based on the MZedDB ionisation ‘rules’ along with their theoretical <italic>m/z</italic> (Draper et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2009</xref>). The calculated adduct <italic>m/z</italic> were then matched with a search range of 10 ppm to the accurate <italic>m/z</italic> assigned to the 100% fully occupied 0.01 amu bins of the 10 replicate injections of the standards mix.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec10">
      <title>Performance benchmarking of the <italic>binneR</italic> R package</title>
      <p id="Par29">Both processing time and peak random access memory (RAM) usage were tested for the R package <italic>binneR</italic> v2.6.2. These tests were performed on a Dell high performance computing blade with an Intel(R) Xeon(R) Gold 6130 CPU @ 2.10GHz model processor with 128 CPUs, 504GB of RAM and Ubuntu 20.04.4 LTS operating system.</p>
      <p id="Par30">Increments of 1, 10, 100, and 1000 raw data files were used from the <italic>B. distachyon</italic> leaf sample matrix. The data files were duplicated 10 and 100 times for the 100 and 1000 file tests respectively. Processing time and peak memory usage tests were performed separately for each combination of the numbers of files and the numbers of CPU workers in increments of 1, 4, 16 and 64. The R package <italic>rbenchmark</italic> v1.0.0 was used for measuring processing time with a single replication of each file number-CPU workers combination. The R package <italic>profvis</italic> v0.3.7 was used to profile RAM usage with usage sampled at 0.01 second intervals for all combinations except for those with 1 CPU worker and greater than 10 data files that were sampled at 0.5 second intervals. The peak RAM usage was taken as the maximum RAM usage observed during each test.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec11">
    <title>Results and discussion</title>
    <sec id="Sec12">
      <title>Optimal bin width for spectral binning</title>
      <p id="Par31">The optimal width with which to spectral bin FIE-HRMS fingerprinting data is a compromise between the retention of resolution whilst minimising the impacts of instrumental or processing artefacts.</p>
      <p id="Par32">As the amu width of spectral binning decreased, there was an exponential increase in the number of spectral features observed along with an increase in the proportion of missing values across all the example biological matrices (Supplementary Tables S2 and S3). This was a result of the measured deviation in <italic>m/z</italic> signals both between each scan of a sample and between samples. The peak at 133.01416 <italic>m/z</italic> from the <italic>B. distachyon</italic> leaf matrix was found to deviate by a range of up to 0.000244 amu between the infusion scans of a single injection and 0.0000777 amu across the 10 injections (Supplementary Fig. S3). These deviations are due changes in parameters such as temperature and space charge compensation during the Fourier transformation, which is calculated on a scan by scan basis (Hu et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2005</xref>). This means that <italic>m/z</italic> have the potential to freely shift between bins at widths of 0.0001 or less and so contribute to the high proportions of missing data. Due to this, the use of bin widths of 0.0001 amu and below would be unsuitable for spectral binning.</p>
      <p id="Par33">A higher bin width increases the likelihood that one bin will contain peaks from multiple compounds. This can have implication for downstream data analysis as feature trends become convoluted and more difficult to interpret in the context of the biological question. It also makes putative annotation of features more difficult as the correlations between bins become less reflective of the underlying isotopic, adduct and biochemical relationships. This was a major limitation of former nominal mass fingerprinting techniques using low resolution mass analysers (Beckmann et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2008</xref>)<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>The average bin purity at incremental binning width (amu) across the example biological sample matrices for each ionisation mode. Bin purity was averaged across all bins from the 10 technical injections of each matrix. The error bars show the standard error of the mean</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Fig3_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig></p>
      <p id="Par34">The bin purity metric provides a means by which potential co-occurrence can be compared between different binning widths. Bin purity was found to be variable between the example biological matrices however it was consistently highest on average at 0.01 amu (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). At the 0.01 amu binning width, there is the lowest spread of <italic>m/z</italic> relative to the width of the bin.</p>
      <p id="Par35">Imposing discrete bins of any amu width across a mass range where mass deviation can occur could lead to the splitting of peaks between bins where peaks occurs near bin boundaries. At smaller amu bin widths, the chance of this occurring increases as more bin boundaries are present. The result of a split peak would be two negatively correlated, adjacent bins obtained for what in reality is a single peak where the peak falling into one or other of the bins for a given scan (Supplementary Fig. S4). The proliferation of these artificial features could lead to over optimism during downstream modelling where variance is utilised that is unrelated to the biological problem (Enot et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2008</xref>; Worley and Powers, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2013</xref>).</p>
      <p id="Par36">It was found that of the predicted ionisation products for the standards mix, 33 of these were matched to multiple adjacent bins when the data were binned using a width of 0.001 amu, compared to just one ionisation product at 0.01 amu. This shows that there is a magnitude increase in the potential for peaks to be split between bins as binning width decreases. It is likely that this could be further increased in more complex matrices such as those of biological samples that contain hundreds of compounds.</p>
      <p id="Par37">Based on the factors discussed above, the application of the spectral binning approach using a bin width of 0.01 amu provides the best compromise between retaining resolution, while reducing the impacts of missing data and keeping processing artefacts to a minimum.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec13">
      <title>Extracted <italic>m/z</italic> accuracy</title>
      <p id="Par38">It is a requisite that the accurate <italic>m/z</italic> assigned to the 0.01 width amu bins using this approach are able to provide sufficient accuracy to enable the putative assignment of molecular formulas and metabolite annotations.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Extracted accurate <italic>m/z</italic> base peaks for 0.01 amu bins detected for compounds in the mix of chemical standards</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Compound</th><th align="left">Molecular formula</th><th align="left">Adduct</th><th align="left">Theoretical m/z</th><th align="left">Measured m/z</th><th align="left">Abundance</th><th align="left">Purity</th><th align="left">Centrality</th><th align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq15"><alternatives><tex-math id="M25">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\Delta$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M26"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq15.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> ppm</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Carnitine</td><td align="left">C<inline-formula id="IEq16"><alternatives><tex-math id="M27">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{7}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M28"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq16.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>H<inline-formula id="IEq17"><alternatives><tex-math id="M29">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{15}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M30"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>15</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq17.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>NO<inline-formula id="IEq18"><alternatives><tex-math id="M31">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{3}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M32"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq18.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">[M + H]<inline-formula id="IEq19"><alternatives><tex-math id="M33">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^{1+}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M34"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq19.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">162.1125</td><td align="left">162.1121</td><td align="left">1,350,916</td><td align="left">0.996</td><td align="left">0.5720</td><td align="left">2.040</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Creatinine</td><td align="left">C<inline-formula id="IEq20"><alternatives><tex-math id="M35">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{4}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M36"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq20.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>H<inline-formula id="IEq21"><alternatives><tex-math id="M37">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{7}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M38"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq21.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>N<inline-formula id="IEq22"><alternatives><tex-math id="M39">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{3}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M40"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq22.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>O</td><td align="left">[M + H]<inline-formula id="IEq23"><alternatives><tex-math id="M41">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^{1+}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M42"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq23.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">114.0662</td><td align="left">114.0659</td><td align="left">1,053,376</td><td align="left">0.995</td><td align="left">0.1930</td><td align="left">2.280</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hydroxyproline betaine</td><td align="left">C<inline-formula id="IEq24"><alternatives><tex-math id="M43">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{7}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M44"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq24.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>H<inline-formula id="IEq25"><alternatives><tex-math id="M45">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{13}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M46"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>13</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq25.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>NO<inline-formula id="IEq26"><alternatives><tex-math id="M47">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{3}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M48"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq26.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">[M + H]<inline-formula id="IEq27"><alternatives><tex-math id="M49">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^{1+}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M50"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq27.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">160.0968</td><td align="left">160.0966</td><td align="left">1,698,621</td><td align="left">0.994</td><td align="left">0.3060</td><td align="left">1.620</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Indoxyl Sulfate</td><td align="left">C<inline-formula id="IEq28"><alternatives><tex-math id="M51">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{8}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M52"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq28.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>H<inline-formula id="IEq29"><alternatives><tex-math id="M53">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{7}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M54"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq29.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>NO<inline-formula id="IEq30"><alternatives><tex-math id="M55">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{4}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M56"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq30.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>S</td><td align="left">[M − H]<inline-formula id="IEq31"><alternatives><tex-math id="M57">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^{1-}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M58"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq31.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">212.0023</td><td align="left">212.0022</td><td align="left">555,858</td><td align="left">0.995</td><td align="left">0.5610</td><td align="left">0.613</td></tr><tr><td align="left">N-Methyl histidine</td><td align="left">C<inline-formula id="IEq32"><alternatives><tex-math id="M59">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{7}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M60"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq32.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>H<inline-formula id="IEq33"><alternatives><tex-math id="M61">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{11}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M62"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq33.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>N<inline-formula id="IEq34"><alternatives><tex-math id="M63">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{3}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M64"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq34.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>O<inline-formula id="IEq35"><alternatives><tex-math id="M65">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{2}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M66"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq35.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">[M + H]<inline-formula id="IEq36"><alternatives><tex-math id="M67">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^{1+}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M68"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq36.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">170.0924</td><td align="left">170.0920</td><td align="left">464,555</td><td align="left">0.998</td><td align="left">0.5900</td><td align="left">2.180</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Nicotine</td><td align="left">C<inline-formula id="IEq37"><alternatives><tex-math id="M69">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{10}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M70"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq37.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>H<inline-formula id="IEq38"><alternatives><tex-math id="M71">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{14}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M72"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>14</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq38.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>N<inline-formula id="IEq39"><alternatives><tex-math id="M73">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{2}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M74"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq39.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">[M+H]<inline-formula id="IEq40"><alternatives><tex-math id="M75">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^{1+}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M76"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq40.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">163.1230</td><td align="left">163.1225</td><td align="left">1,715,843</td><td align="left">0.870</td><td align="left">0.5480</td><td align="left">2.700</td></tr><tr><td align="left">p-Cresol sulfate</td><td align="left">C<inline-formula id="IEq41"><alternatives><tex-math id="M77">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{7}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M78"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq41.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>H<inline-formula id="IEq42"><alternatives><tex-math id="M79">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{8}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M80"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq42.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>O<inline-formula id="IEq43"><alternatives><tex-math id="M81">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{4}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M82"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq43.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>S</td><td align="left">[M − H]<inline-formula id="IEq44"><alternatives><tex-math id="M83">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^{1-}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M84"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq44.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">187.0070</td><td align="left">187.0069</td><td align="left">2,059,838</td><td align="left">0.996</td><td align="left">0.3870</td><td align="left">0.749</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Proline betaine</td><td align="left">C<inline-formula id="IEq45"><alternatives><tex-math id="M85">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{7}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M86"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq45.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>H<inline-formula id="IEq46"><alternatives><tex-math id="M87">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{13}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M88"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>13</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq46.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>NO<inline-formula id="IEq47"><alternatives><tex-math id="M89">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{2}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M90"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq47.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">[M + H]<inline-formula id="IEq48"><alternatives><tex-math id="M91">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^{1+}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M92"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq48.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">144.1019</td><td align="left">144.1016</td><td align="left">1,681,100</td><td align="left">0.998</td><td align="left">0.6740</td><td align="left">2.010</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Trans-3’-Hydroxycotinine</td><td align="left">C<inline-formula id="IEq49"><alternatives><tex-math id="M93">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{10}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M94"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq49.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>H<inline-formula id="IEq50"><alternatives><tex-math id="M95">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{12}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M96"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq50.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>N<inline-formula id="IEq51"><alternatives><tex-math id="M97">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{2}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M98"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq51.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>O<inline-formula id="IEq52"><alternatives><tex-math id="M99">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{2}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M100"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq52.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">[M + H]<inline-formula id="IEq53"><alternatives><tex-math id="M101">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^{1+}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M102"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq53.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">193.0972</td><td align="left">193.0968</td><td align="left">835,054</td><td align="left">0.997</td><td align="left">0.3550</td><td align="left">2.020</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Trigonelline</td><td align="left">C<inline-formula id="IEq54"><alternatives><tex-math id="M103">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{7}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M104"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq54.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>H<inline-formula id="IEq55"><alternatives><tex-math id="M105">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{7}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M106"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq55.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>NO<inline-formula id="IEq56"><alternatives><tex-math id="M107">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{2}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M108"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq56.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">[M + H]<inline-formula id="IEq57"><alternatives><tex-math id="M109">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^{1+}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M110"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Article_IEq57.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">138.0550</td><td align="left">138.0547</td><td align="left">918,751</td><td align="left">0.999</td><td align="left">0.0551</td><td align="left">1.740</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The top ten most abundant base peaks are shown. For a full list of detected peaks see Supplementary Table S4</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p id="Par39">The accuracy of some of the extracted accurate <italic>m/z</italic> signals from the chemical standards mix are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. A full list of the matched accurate <italic>m/z</italic> can be found in Supplementary Table S4. Out of a total of 347 predicted ionisation products based on the selected common adducts, 151 (43.5%) were matched to accurate <italic>m/z</italic> that had been assigned to 0.01 amu bins. These matches had an average ppm error of 2.35 (SE = ± 0.167) with 122 (80.8%) having an error below 3 ppm. This level of accuracy obtained across the majority of detected features is sufficient to allow for the assignment of putative molecular formulas or metabolite annotations (Kind &amp; Fiehn, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2006</xref>)<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Error of accurate <italic>m/z</italic> matched to the predicted ionisation products in the standards mix plotted against <bold>a</bold> their detected abundance and <bold>b</bold> the calculated 0.01 amu bin purity</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_Fig4_HTML" id="MO9"/></fig></p>
      <p id="Par40">As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, high ppm error was found to be more associated with low abundance as opposed to low purity. This suggests that low accuracy was as a result of instrumental error as opposed to being introduced during processing by the spectral binning approach (Makarov et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2006</xref>).</p>
      <p id="Par41">Of the 195 predicted ionisation products whose accurate <italic>m/z</italic> were unmatched, 26 (13.3%) had 0.01 amu bins that were present in the data set. These present, but unmatched, bins had a high average purity of 0.946 (SE = ± 0.0174) suggesting that these bins were not matched because the predicted ionisation products were not detected. This is opposed to their co-occurrence in a bin with higher abundance <italic>m/z</italic> of alternative ionisation products whose accurate <italic>m/z</italic> were instead selected.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec14">
      <title><italic>binneR</italic>: An R package for spectral binning of FIE-HRMS data</title>
      <p id="Par42">The R package <italic>binneR</italic> was developed as an implementation of this spectral binning approach and is available to install from GitHub (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://aberhrml.github.io/binneR/">https://aberhrml.github.io/binneR/</ext-link>). A usage tutorial is provided within the package for new users.</p>
      <p id="Par43">The package provides utility for the automatic detection of all necessary parameters such as infusion scan detection and scan filters. Parallel processing uses the R package <italic>future</italic>, providing the user with a wide choice of processing strategies (Bengtsson, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2020</xref>). Data files should be provided in common mass spectrometry data formats such as those supported by the mzR package available from Bioconductor (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/sneumann/mzR/">https://github.com/sneumann/mzR/</ext-link>) including mzML and mzXML (Chambers et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2012</xref>; Martens et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2011</xref>; Pedrioli et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2004</xref>). There is an integrated workflow for the spectral binning approach described here including 0.01 amu binning, accurate <italic>m/z</italic> retrieval and bin metric calculation. Also included is functionality for visualising ion chromatograms of infusion profiles and spectral bins.</p>
      <p id="Par44">To show the performance of the package for processing FIE-HRMS data, both the processing time and peak memory usage were measured across a range of data file numbers and CPU workers (Supplementary Fig. S5). It was found that processing 100 files using 4 CPU workers took only 55 seconds and had a peak memory usage of 1.36GB. These required resources show that processing hundreds of data files using this implementation is within the capabilities of a standard modern desktop computer. It should also be noted that there was little gain in processing time using 16 or more CPU workers for 1000 files.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec15">
      <title>The spectral binning approach</title>
      <p id="Par45">Metabolome fingerprinting is not an ultimately comprehensive method for which metabolome profiling techniques utilising chromatographic separation are available and more suited (Theodoridis et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2012</xref>). The basis of this spectral binning approach is for first pass analysis where sample throughput, low cost and efficiency, both in time and computational resources are the most important factors. It can be seen as a pseudo-hierarchical approach were some resolution is conceded for simplicity and efficiency. However, it is an attempt to ensure that the post-acquisition processing step is not the inhibitory factor or bottle neck in biological applications where many thousands of samples may be available such as epidemiological or population studies (Watrous et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2017</xref>).</p>
      <p id="Par46">Binning, used as a form of quantization, is commonly applied in post-acquisition processing approaches for Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) spectroscopy data (Åberg et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2009</xref>). Where adaptive binning is often preferred for NMR, this is made challenging in Fourier transform mass spectrometry due to the deviations in measured <italic>m/z</italic> and the presence of spectral artefacts such as Gibbs occilations (Marshall &amp; Hendrickson, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2008</xref>). Adaptive binning methods can also significantly increase the computational demands and can require manual intervention to ensure that the bin boundaries have been appropriately applied (Anderson et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2011</xref>).</p>
      <p id="Par47">The removal of single scan <italic>m/z</italic> events during spectral binning (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) enables the reduction of random instrumental noise and can greatly reduce the proportion of missing data in an intensity matrix. Removal of these <italic>m/z</italic> reduced the percentage of missing data in the <italic>B. distachyon</italic> matrix by 21.8% and 25.4% in positive and negative ionisation modes respectively. This reduction diminishes as sample numbers increase due to the greater chance that bins will be multiply occupied.</p>
      <p id="Par48">The proposed bin metrics, along with the visualisation of bin spectra, can be used by the investigator as a means to objectively assess the robustness of individual bins where necessary after processing. Spectral bins found to be explanatory for a given biological question by downstream data analyses and suspected to potentially contain <italic>m/z</italic> from multiple compounds, could be investigated further by applying a peak detection routine such as the continuous wavelet transform (Zheng et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2016</xref>). The relative intensities can then be compared to potentially identify the <italic>m/z</italic> responsible for the explanatory bin.</p>
      <p id="Par49">An alternative approach for processing FIE-HRMS data by the <italic>proFIA</italic> R package attempts to detect peaks in the chromatographic dimension using a peak picking approach of the infusion profile as opposed to the spectral dimension (Delabrière et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2017</xref>). This method ensures the detection of the most robust peaks; however, the performance of this approach and peak picking approaches, in general, is that they could be susceptible to information loss. Peaks with poor shape, as a result of short infusion profiles or low abundance, could be missed or incorrectly picked by these routines. The vast majority of <italic>m/z</italic> signals found within FIE-HRMS spectra are of low abundance and close to the baseline. However, these features can often still provide useful information for downstream data mining and it is important that this information is retained.</p>
      <p id="Par50">The poor performance of a peak picking routine could not only affect the precision of an extracted m/z but also the precision of the extracted abundance. Comparatively, a sum aggregated spectral bin with a low bin purity, will only affect the precision of the assigned accurate mass of the bin. While the poor performance of both approaches would affect the potential to assign molecular formulas to accurate <italic>m/z</italic>, the poor performance of peak picking approaches would be more detrimental to downstream data mining.</p>
      <p id="Par51">These peak picking approaches would also be unsuitable for processing direct infusion mass spectrometry (DIMS) data where the ion current is held stable for a period of time (Southam et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2017</xref>). This would also yield peak shapes unsuitable for peak pick routines; however, the spectral binning approach would still be suitable for processing this data.</p>
      <p id="Par52">Spectral binning is also comparatively faster than the <italic>proFIA</italic> approach, with processing taking approximately 1 second per file compared to the reported speed of approximately less than 15 seconds (Delabrière et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2017</xref>). The slower speed of <italic>proFIA</italic> is likely due to the complexity of the extra computational steps involved in the approach.</p>
      <p id="Par53">Due to the simplicity of the spectral binning approach, a number of quality assurance steps should be taken to ensure that robust features can be selected during pre-treatment routines prior to downstream data mining. This includes the block randomisation of sample classes across sample runs, which should be mandatory to avoid the introduction systematic error (Beckmann et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2008</xref>). Accompanying this should be use of quality control (QC) samples, samples that are representative in composition of all the samples to be analysed (Broadhurst et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2018</xref>). The QC samples should be injected at the start of the run and between the randomised class blocks. This allows bins to be filtered based on their relative standard deviation (RSD) across the sample run and only robustly measured bins with RSD values below a threshold value retained for further analysis. Thresholds of below 20% and 30% have been recommended for LC-MS and GC-MS based investigations; however a higher threshold of 50% would be more suitable for FIE-HRMS, given the more complex ionisation environment during sample infusion (Dunn et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2012</xref>).</p>
      <p id="Par54">Bins containing a high percentage of missing values or low occupancy should also be removed as these can represent poorly detected and noisy features. A recommended strategy is that for a bin to be retained, it should be occupied above a threshold of 66% in at least one of the sample classes (Southam et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2017</xref>). Imputation on the remaining missing values can then be performed using approaches such as random forest or k-nearest neighbour imputation (Hrydziuszko &amp; Viant, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2012</xref>; Kokla et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2019</xref>)</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec16">
    <title>Conclusions</title>
    <p id="Par55">The spectral binning approach presented here provides an efficient and pragmatic approach for for post-acquisition processing of FIE-HRMS metabolome fingerprinting data. The optimal <italic>m/z</italic> binning width was found to be 0.01 amu where an initial concession of resolution for processing efficiency is offset by the per bin extraction of modal accurate <italic>m/z</italic>. For the mix of known chemical standards, it was shown that the majority of extracted accurate <italic>m/z</italic> could be matched to the predicted ionisation products with an accuracy below 3 ppm. The purity and centrality metrics also provided an objective means for investigators to assess the robustness of individual bins.</p>
    <p id="Par56">The development the open-source R package <italic>binneR</italic> provides an efficient implementation of the approach that makes the processing of hundreds of FIE-HRMS data files possible on an ordinary desktop PC.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
    <title>Supplementary Information</title>
    <sec id="Sec17">
      <p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary file1 (PDF 92 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_MOESM2_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary file2 (PDF 118 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_MOESM3_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary file3 (PDF 33 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_MOESM4_ESM.csv"><caption><p>Supplementary file4 (CSV 3 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="11306_2022_1923_MOESM5_ESM.csv"><caption><p>Supplementary file5 (CSV 19 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
</body>
<back>
  <fn-group>
    <fn>
      <p>
        <bold>Publisher's Note</bold>
      </p>
      <p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
    </fn>
  </fn-group>
  <ack>
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <p>The authors would like to thank Woodland Heritage for the funding of J.F., Aberystwyth University for the financial support of H.P. and the UK Medical Research Council (MRC) for the funding of T.W. and M.B. (MRC Grant Ref: MR/S010483/1).</p>
  </ack>
  <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
    <title>Author contributions</title>
    <p>JF: conceptualisation, methodology, sample preparation, software development, data analysis and writing-original draft; TW: conceptualisation and manuscript revision; MB: conceptualisation, supervision and manuscript-revision; LL: sample preparation and data collection; HP: data collection; JD: supervision and manuscript revision.</p>
  </notes>
  <notes notes-type="data-availability">
    <title>Data availability</title>
    <p>The metabolomics data reported in this paper are available via the EMBL-EBI MetaboLights database with the study identifier MTBLS4288 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/metabolights/MTBLS4288">https://www.ebi.ac.uk/metabolights/MTBLS4288</ext-link>). The R code used to analyse the data and generate this manuscript is available via GitHub at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/jasenfinch/Spectral_binning_as_an_approach_to_post-acquisition_processing_of_FIE-HRMS_data">https://github.com/jasenfinch/Spectral_binning_as_an_approach_to_post-acquisition_processing_of_FIE-HRMS_data</ext-link>.</p>
  </notes>
  <notes notes-type="data-availability">
    <title>Code availability</title>
    <p>The R package <italic>binneR</italic> is available for download from GitHub at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://aberhrml.github.io/binneR/">https://aberhrml.github.io/binneR/</ext-link>.</p>
  </notes>
  <notes>
    <title>Declarations</title>
    <notes id="FPar2" notes-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflict of interest</title>
      <p id="Par57">The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p>
    </notes>
  </notes>
  <ref-list id="Bib1">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref id="CR1">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Åberg</surname>
            <given-names>KM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Alm</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Torgrip</surname>
            <given-names>RJO</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The correspondence problem for metabonomics datasets</article-title>
        <source>Analytical and Bioanalytical Chemistry</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>394</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>151</fpage>
        <lpage>62</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00216-009-2628-9</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 19198812?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19198812</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR2">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Anderson</surname>
            <given-names>PE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mahle</surname>
            <given-names>DA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Doom</surname>
            <given-names>TE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Reo</surname>
            <given-names>NV</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>DelRaso</surname>
            <given-names>NJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Raymer</surname>
            <given-names>ML</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Dynamic adaptive binning: An improved quantification technique for NMR spectroscopic data</article-title>
        <source>Metabolomics</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <fpage>179</fpage>
        <lpage>90</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11306-010-0242-7</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR3">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Beckmann</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Parker</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Enot</surname>
            <given-names>DP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Duval</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Draper</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>High-throughput, nontargeted metabolite fingerprinting using nominal mass flow injection electrospray mass spectrometry</article-title>
        <source>Nature Protocols</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>3</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <fpage>486</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2007.500</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 18323818?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18323818</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR4">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Beckmann</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wilson</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zubair</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lloyd</surname>
            <given-names>AJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lyons</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Phillips</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tailliart</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A standardized strategy for simultaneous quantification of urine metabolites to validate development of a biomarker panel allowing comprehensive assessment of dietary exposure</article-title>
        <source>Molecular Nutrition &amp; Food Research</source>
        <year>2020</year>
        <volume>64</volume>
        <issue>20</issue>
        <fpage>2000517</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mnfr.202000517</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR5">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bengtsson, H. (2020). <italic>A unifying framework for parallel and distributed processing in r using futures</italic>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.00553">arXiv:2008.00553</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR6">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Broadhurst</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Goodacre</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Reinke</surname>
            <given-names>SN</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kuligowski</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wilson</surname>
            <given-names>ID</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lewis</surname>
            <given-names>MR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dunn</surname>
            <given-names>WB</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Guidelines and considerations for the use of system suitability and quality control samples in mass spectrometry assays applied in untargeted clinical metabolomic studies</article-title>
        <source>Metabolomics</source>
        <year>2018</year>
        <volume>14</volume>
        <issue>6</issue>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <lpage>17</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11306-018-1367-3</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29249916</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR7">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chambers</surname>
            <given-names>MC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Maclean</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Burke</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Amodei</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ruderman</surname>
            <given-names>DL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Neumann</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gatto</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A cross-platform toolkit for mass spectrometry and proteomics</article-title>
        <source>Nature Biotechnology</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>30</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <fpage>918</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.2377</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 23051804?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23051804</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR8">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Delabrière</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hohenester</surname>
            <given-names>UM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Colsch</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Junot</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fenaille</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Thévenot</surname>
            <given-names>EA</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>proFIA: A data preprocessing workflow for flow injection analysis coupled to high-resolution mass spectrometry</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>33</volume>
        <issue>23</issue>
        <fpage>3767</fpage>
        <lpage>75</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btx458</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 29036359?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29036359</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR10">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Draper</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Enot</surname>
            <given-names>DP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Parker</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Beckmann</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Snowdon</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zubair</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Metabolite signal identification in accurate mass metabolomics data with MZedDB, an interactive m/z annotation tool utilising predicted ionisation behaviour’ rules</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <lpage>16</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-10-227</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19118496</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR11">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Draper</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lloyd</surname>
            <given-names>AJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Goodacre</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Beckmann</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Flow infusion electrospray ionisation mass spectrometry for high throughput, non-targeted metabolite fingerprinting: A review</article-title>
        <source>Metabolomics</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>4</fpage>
        <lpage>29</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11306-012-0449-x</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR9">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Draper</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mur</surname>
            <given-names>LAJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jenkins</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ghosh-Biswas</surname>
            <given-names>GC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bablak</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hasterok</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Routledge</surname>
            <given-names>APM</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title><italic>Brachypodium Distachyon</italic>: A new model system for functional genomics in grasses</article-title>
        <source>Plant Physiology</source>
        <year>2001</year>
        <volume>127</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <fpage>1539</fpage>
        <lpage>55</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.010196</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 11743099?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11743099</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR12">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dunn</surname>
            <given-names>WB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bailey</surname>
            <given-names>NJC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Johnson</surname>
            <given-names>HE</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Measuring the metabolome: Current analytical technologies</article-title>
        <source>Analyst</source>
        <year>2005</year>
        <volume>130</volume>
        <issue>5</issue>
        <fpage>606</fpage>
        <lpage>25</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/B418288J</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 15852128?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15852128</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR13">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dunn</surname>
            <given-names>WB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wilson</surname>
            <given-names>ID</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nicholls</surname>
            <given-names>AW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Broadhurst</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The importance of experimental design and QC samples in large-scale and MS-driven untargeted metabolomic studies of humans</article-title>
        <source>Bioanalysis</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <issue>18</issue>
        <fpage>2249</fpage>
        <lpage>64</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4155/bio.12.204</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 23046267?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23046267</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR14">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Enot</surname>
            <given-names>DP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Beckmann</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Parker</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Overy</surname>
            <given-names>DP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Draper</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Preprocessing, classification modeling and feature selection using flow injection electrospray mass spectrometry metabolite fingerprint data</article-title>
        <source>Nature Protocols</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>3</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <fpage>446</fpage>
        <lpage>70</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2007.511</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 18323816?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18323816</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR15">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hrydziuszko</surname>
            <given-names>O</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Viant</surname>
            <given-names>MR</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Missing values in mass spectrometry based metabolomics: An undervalued step in the data processing pipeline</article-title>
        <source>Metabolomics</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>161</fpage>
        <lpage>74</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11306-011-0366-4</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR16">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Noll</surname>
            <given-names>RJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Makarov</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hardman</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cooks</surname>
            <given-names>GR</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The orbitrap: A new mass spectrometer</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Mass Spectrometry</source>
        <year>2005</year>
        <volume>40</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <fpage>430</fpage>
        <lpage>43</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jms.856</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 15838939?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15838939</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR17">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kind</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fiehn</surname>
            <given-names>O</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Metabolomic database annotations via query of elemental compositions: Mass accuracy is insufficient even at less than 1 ppm</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2006</year>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <lpage>10</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-7-234</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16393334</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR18">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kokla</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Virtanen</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kolehmainen</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Paananen</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hanhineva</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Random forest-based imputation outperforms other methods for imputing LC-MS metabolomics data: A comparative study</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
        <year>2019</year>
        <volume>20</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>1</fpage>
        <lpage>11</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-019-3110-0</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30606105</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR19">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lloyd</surname>
            <given-names>AJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Beckmann</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Haldar</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Seal</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Brandt</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Draper</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Data-driven strategy for the discovery of potential urinary biomarkers of habitual dietary exposure</article-title>
        <source>The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>97</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <fpage>377</fpage>
        <lpage>89</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3945/ajcn.112.048033</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 23269817?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23269817</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR20">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Makarov</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Denisov</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lange</surname>
            <given-names>O</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Horning</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Dynamic range of mass accuracy in LTQ orbitrap hybrid mass spectrometer</article-title>
        <source>Journal of the American Society for Mass Spectrometry</source>
        <year>2006</year>
        <volume>17</volume>
        <issue>7</issue>
        <fpage>977</fpage>
        <lpage>82</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jasms.2006.03.006</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 16750636?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16750636</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR21">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Marshall</surname>
            <given-names>AG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hendrickson</surname>
            <given-names>CL</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>High-resolution mass spectrometers</article-title>
        <source>Annual Review of Analytical Chemistry</source>
        <year>2008</year>
        <volume>1</volume>
        <fpage>579</fpage>
        <lpage>99</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.anchem.1.031207.112945</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 20636090?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20636090</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR22">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Martens</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chambers</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sturm</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kessner</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Levander</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shofstahl</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tang</surname>
            <given-names>WH</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>mzML: A community standard for mass spectrometry data</article-title>
        <source>Molecular &amp; Cellular Proteomics</source>
        <year>2011</year>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>R110</fpage>
        <lpage>000133</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/mcp.R110.000133</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR23">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Parker</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Beckmann</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zubair</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Enot</surname>
            <given-names>DP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Caracuel-Rios</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Overy</surname>
            <given-names>DP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Snowdon</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Talbot</surname>
            <given-names>NJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Draper</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Metabolomic analysis reveals a common pattern of metabolic re-programming during invasion of three host plant species by <italic>Magnaporthe grisea</italic></article-title>
        <source>The Plant Journal</source>
        <year>2009</year>
        <volume>59</volume>
        <issue>5</issue>
        <fpage>723</fpage>
        <lpage>37</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2009.03912.x</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 19453445?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19453445</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR24">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pedrioli</surname>
            <given-names>PGA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Eng</surname>
            <given-names>JK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hubley</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vogelzang</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Deutsch</surname>
            <given-names>EW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Raught</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pratt</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A common open representation of mass spectrometry data and its application to proteomics research</article-title>
        <source>Nature Biotechnology</source>
        <year>2004</year>
        <volume>22</volume>
        <issue>11</issue>
        <fpage>1459</fpage>
        <lpage>66</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt1031</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 15529173?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15529173</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR25">
      <mixed-citation publication-type="other">R Core Team. (2020). R: A language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.R-project.org/">https://www.R-project.org/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR26">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Smedsgaard</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nielsen</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Metabolite profiling of fungi and yeast: From phenotype to metabolome by MS and informatics</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
        <year>2005</year>
        <volume>56</volume>
        <issue>410</issue>
        <fpage>273</fpage>
        <lpage>86</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/eri068</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15618299</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR27">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Southam</surname>
            <given-names>AD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Weber</surname>
            <given-names>RJM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Engel</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jones</surname>
            <given-names>MR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Viant</surname>
            <given-names>MR</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A complete workflow for high-resolution spectral-stitching nanoelectrospray direct-infusion mass-spectrometry-based metabolomics and lipidomics</article-title>
        <source>Nature Protocols</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <fpage>310</fpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2016.156</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR28">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Theodoridis</surname>
            <given-names>GA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gika</surname>
            <given-names>HG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Want</surname>
            <given-names>EJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wilson</surname>
            <given-names>ID</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry based global metabolite profiling: A review</article-title>
        <source>Analytica Chimica Acta</source>
        <year>2012</year>
        <volume>711</volume>
        <fpage>7</fpage>
        <lpage>16</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aca.2011.09.042</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 22152789?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22152789</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR29">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Watrous</surname>
            <given-names>JD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Henglin</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Claggett</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lehmann</surname>
            <given-names>KA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Larson</surname>
            <given-names>MG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cheng</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jain</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Visualization, quantification, and alignment of spectral drift in population scale untargeted metabolomics data</article-title>
        <source>Analytical Chemistry</source>
        <year>2017</year>
        <volume>89</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <fpage>1399</fpage>
        <lpage>1404</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.6b04337</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 28208263?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28208263</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR30">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Worley</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Powers</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Multivariate analysis in metabolomics</article-title>
        <source>Current Metabolomics</source>
        <year>2013</year>
        <volume>1</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <fpage>92</fpage>
        <lpage>107</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/2213235X11301010092</pub-id>
        <?supplied-pmid 26078916?>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26078916</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CR31">
      <element-citation publication-type="journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zheng</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fan</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Qiu</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tian</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>An improved algorithm for peak detection in mass spectra based on continuous wavelet transform</article-title>
        <source>International Journal of Mass Spectrometry</source>
        <year>2016</year>
        <volume>409</volume>
        <fpage>53</fpage>
        <lpage>58</lpage>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijms.2016.09.020</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</back>
